<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/politics-news.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 19:06:33 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>DHS official promises election officials that ICE will not be at polling places</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/dhs-ice-polling-places-00799613</link>
      <description>“Any suggestion that ICE is going to be present at polling places is simply disinformation,” said Heather Honey, a DHS official focused on elections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9724-de8a-a1fc-ff6485520000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 19:06:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/f2/6e/028641004eed86c08fc3e1c13dff/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172380707">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photo by AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>A polling station in Arlington, Virginia, on Sept. 20, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f2/6e/028641004eed86c08fc3e1c13dff/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172380707" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard and Erin Doherty</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard and Erin Doherty</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A top Department of Homeland Security official vowed during a private call with election officials Wednesday that immigration officers will not be stationed at polling places in November amid Democratic warnings about interference in the midterms by the federal government.</p> 
<p>Heather Honey, the department’s deputy assistant secretary for election integrity, dismissed as “disinformation” any fears that officers from Immigration Customs and Enforcement would be deployed to the polls as part of President Donald Trump’s ongoing mass deportation campaign.</p> 
<p>“Any suggestion that ICE is going to be present at polling places is simply disinformation,” Honey said, according to four people on the call who were granted anonymity to discuss it. “There will be no ICE presence at polling locations.”</p> 
<p>Honey’s words, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/22/us/politics/trump-election-deniers-voting-security.html?smtyp=cur&amp;smid=fb-nytimes" target="_blank">and her background as a denier of the 2020 election</a>, did not eliminate fears from Democrats, who have been battling with the Trump administration over election issues, especially the Justice Department’s requests for private voter rolls.</p> 
<p>“I can't depend on an election denier like that for the truth under any circumstances,” said Arizona Secretary of State Adrian Fontes, a Democrat who was on the call. “So, they need to get better spokespeople who actually have some integrity.”</p> 
<p>The sparring over ICE officers at polling places reflects Democratic fears that the federal government will insert itself into the midterms and as Trump himself <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/trump-nationalize-elections-2026-midterms-00760015?utm_content=politico/magazine/Politics&amp;utm_source=flipboard" target="_blank">has said his administration</a> “ought to nationalize the voting.”</p> 
<p>Administration officials from four departments — the Election Assistance Commission, Department of Homeland Security, Justice Department and Federal Bureau of Investigation — were on the call, which was organized for a routine discussion of federal assistance ahead of November.</p> 
<p>Fontes said little substance was shared on the call outside of the commitment to not having ICE at polling places.</p> 
<p>“I really don't know exactly what the purpose of this call was other than window dressing,” he said.</p> 
<p>Another person on the call said it was the latest example of “conflicting messages” coming from the Trump administration on election issues.</p> 
<p>“They want both to intimidate and control the states and to try to demonstrate business as usual, so they're sending very conflicting messages to all of us about what they want their role to be in 2026,” the person said.</p> 
<p>“It felt like kind of a cover your butt kind of call, so they have now checked the box that they have met with election officials from across the country,” a third person on the call said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abigail Spanberger gave Democrats’ response to Trump. But she didn’t have the stage to herself.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/state-of-the-union-democrats-response-split-00797336</link>
      <description>Democratic groups staging counterprogramming events offered a snapshot of a party divided over how best to approach the midterms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-930e-d0f8-adde-fb5e1b6e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 00:02:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/1e/92/34e95fa54126a4a317327fa6458b/state-of-the-union-democrats-20486.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Steve Helber/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger delivers the Democratic response to President Donald Trump's State of the Union address, Feb. 24, 2026, in Williamsburg, Virginia.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1e/92/34e95fa54126a4a317327fa6458b/state-of-the-union-democrats-20486.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic leadership's choice to have Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger deliver the State of the Union rebuttal was a strategic move to keep the party's focus on affordability. But she was just one Democrat jockeying to pave the way forward for the party.</p> 
<p>Various Democratic factions hosting numerous competing events Tuesday night diverged on the best way to challenge President Donald Trump. Throughout the speeches, universal calls to bring down costs and crack down on Immigration and Customs Enforcement mixed in with more forceful and sometimes vulgar rebukes of his administration — laying bare the ideological and stylistic divides that are driving the party’s identity crisis.</p> 
<p>Spanberger — a one-time battleground House Democrat who joined Congress during the party’s last wave election — was the headliner, calling from Williamsburg, Virgina, for Trump to focus on the needs of American families while also condemning the president for doing “what he always does: He lied, he scapegoated, and he distracted.” </p> 
<p>But she was far from alone, with a group of Democratic-aligned organizations holding their own State of the Union events in an effort to harness rising furor against Trump.</p> 
<p>Dozens of lawmakers spoke across several counterprogramming events, including a rally hosted by MoveOn and the left-leaning media outlet MeidasTouch <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/trump-state-of-the-union-address-2026/across-dc-a-small-boycott-00797158" target="_blank">on the National Mall</a>, or at another in downtown Washington hosted by the anti-Trump activist networks Defiance and the Portland Frog Brigade along with the Courier Newsroom.</p> 
<p>On the Mall, Rep. Summer Lee (D-Pa.) called to impeach Attorney General Pam Bondi over the Epstein files, and Sen. Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.) accused Trump of “rigging” the midterms by pushing voting restrictions to “save his authoritarian control and turn the presidency into a kingship.” Rep. Becca Balint (D-Vt.) called herself a “bareknuckled brawler with a heart” and declared “that’s what we need right now.”</p> 
<p>The dueling rallies, both timed to overlap with Trump’s speech, were accompanied by a Working Families Party rebuttal also delivered by Lee.</p> 
<p>Some party strategists said the events — which also hosted high-profile Democrats like Robert De Niro, Joy Reid and New York congressional candidate George Conway — splintered the party’s response in a high-profile moment.</p> 
<p>“A uniform response is much better than a cacophony of responses,” said Matt Bennett, an executive with the center-left think tank Third Way. “One narrative is better than many, and Spanberger is very talented at articulating a message that resonates broadly.”</p> 
<p>Dueling State of the Union responses are not a new phenomenon. While the party out of power typically green-lights an English- and Spanish-language rebuttal — Sen. Alex Padilla (D-Calif.) gave Democrats’ response in Spanish this year, vowing his party would lower costs, make voting more accessible and rein in ICE — different wings have long looked to get in on the action, from Tea Party Republicans during Barack Obama’s presidency to the progressive groups on Tuesday night.</p> 
<p>But the lack of a unified response Tuesday comes as the Democratic Party still searches — and fights over — the best way to beat Trump, even as party members agree overall that centering the Trump administration’s struggles to boost the economy gives them the best chance in November.</p> 
<p>Democrats were already divided in their approach to Trump’s address to Congress. Dozens of members across both chambers skipped the speech to protest the president while others said they were attending out of constitutional duty — a schism that stretched <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/katherine-clark-skip-sotu-00796596" target="_blank">all the way up through party leadership</a>.</p> 
<p>Despite calls from Democratic leadership to refrain from protests inside the House chamber, Rep. Al Green (D-Texas) was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/trump-state-of-the-union-address-2026/al-green-escorted-out-00797132" target="_blank">escorted out of the room</a> minutes into Trump’s speech after brandishing a sign reading “Black people aren’t apes,” a likely reference to a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/donald-trump-obamas-monkey-video-00768745" target="_blank">racist video Trump reposted</a> earlier in the month. </p> 
<p>Progressive Reps. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) and Rashida Tlaib (D-Mich.) also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/trump-state-of-the-union-address-2026/democrats-disruption-immigration-00797184" target="_blank">heckled Trump at multiple points</a> during Trump’s speech, including in response to Trump touting his aggressive immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>At multiple moments during his speech, Trump appeared to relish opportunities to draw Democrats in attendance into heated exchanges.</p> 
<p>“You people are crazy,” he said at one point, prompting some Democrats in the room to heckle him in return.</p> 
<p>Spanberger’s aides were cognizant of the volume of competing Democratic rebuttals and built a “war room” team to boost the governor’s response on social media. And while her team insisted that she isn’t competing with other counter-programming events, her aides believed heading into Tuesday evening that Spanberger’s successful affordability-focused campaign last year gave her credibility on how to best respond to Trump.</p> 
<p>Spanberger, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/spanberger-wins-virginia-governors-race-00633606" target="_blank">whose campaign last year</a> is viewed by some party strategists as a blueprint for Democrats to score victories in November, focused on her proposals to lower costs for Virginians, while also criticizing the president for aggressive immigration policies and blaming rising costs on Trump’s tariffs.</p> 
<p>“Americans deserve to know that their leaders are focused on addressing the problems that keep them up at night, problems that dictate where you live, whether you can afford to start a business, or whether you have to skip a prescription in order to buy groceries,” she said in her live rebuttal. “Is the president working to make life more affordable for you and your family? We all know the answer is no.”</p> 
<p>Several of the lawmakers who spoke at competing events echoed that affordability template, including some Democrats with possible presidential ambitions, like Sens. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.) and Chris Murphy (D-Conn.).</p> 
<p>Gallego, who warned in his speech that Trump was making Americans “sicker and poorer,” told POLITICO beforehand that “it’s fine that we have different people talking, provided the message is all the same: [that Democrats] are here to fight for everyday Americans.”</p> 
<p>Some of those behind Democrats’ various response events Tuesday said they aimed to better capture the degree of frustration voters feel towards Trump.</p> 
<p>“These are not the times for an institutionalist to say, ‘Well, let's just give him his moment, and if you want to protest, protest by sitting there silently.’ That's bullshit,” said Miles Taylor, a co-founder of Defiance and former Trump administration official-turned-Trump critic. “And I think that Hakeem Jeffries knows that his caucus feels like that doesn't meet the moment, which is why so many of them are literally just not showing up.”</p> 
<p>Taylor added that the plethora of Democratic responses also reflected the current political media environment, where both voters and candidates can easily find forums that align with their preferences.</p> 
<p>Lee, who railed against Trump’s “authoritarianism” and cast his speech as an “obituary for the country working people built” in her Working Families Party rebuttal, said Democrats are at a “crossroads" and won’t win control of Congress “by electing more of the same” — which she cast as those who “speak boldly but deliver cautiously or sometimes even vote with MAGA.”</p> 
<p>In an interview on Monday, Lee said it was critical for Democrats to promote a bigger tent after progressives scored major wins of their own in recent elections, from <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/zohran-mamdani-wins-mayor-new-york-city-00634476" target="_blank">Zohran Mamdani being elected mayor of New York City</a> to <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-jersey-playbook/2026/02/11/mejia-wins-00775405" target="_blank">Analilia Mejia’s victory this month</a> in the Democratic primary to replace moderate now-Gov. Mikie Sherrill in New Jersey.</p> 
<p>Progressives “are always accepting of moderate places being represented well,” Lee said. But “it feels like there’s a wing of this party fighting back more against us trying to represent our own communities just as hard as somebody who is trying to represent their community in a swing district.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘A really really big decision’: The court cases looming over the midterms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/24/2026-midterms-redistricting-legal-battle-house-majority-00793515</link>
      <description>High-stakes legal cases that could determine the majority loom in nearly a dozen states, with just months to go until the November election.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8c33-de8a-a1fc-fd7317d10001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/71/74/593fe0114c879fcf452603618afc/election-2026-redistricting-what-to-know-04868.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Patrick Aftoora-Orsagos/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>It’s not uncommon for redistricting to end up before judges, but the unusual mid-cycle battle has added fuel to a fire that was already burning.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/71/74/593fe0114c879fcf452603618afc/election-2026-redistricting-what-to-know-04868.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The fight over this year’s House map is barreling through the nation’s courtrooms.</p> 
<p>High-stakes legal cases that could determine the majority loom in nearly a dozen states, with just months to go until the November election. The wave of court cases follows a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/the-redistricting-fight-that-dominated-american-politics-in-2025-00703193" target="_blank">2025 that was marked by fiercely political showdowns</a>, with <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/03/democrats-flee-texas-redistricting-00491487" target="_blank">high-profile walkouts</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/28/the-republicans-thwarting-the-white-houses-redistricting-hopes-00625911" target="_blank">rare Republican defections</a> from President Donald Trump and a hugely <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/prop50-newsom-strategy-00630313" target="_blank">expensive ballot initiative in California</a>. </p> 
<p>And in addition to the state-by-state fights, one case before the Supreme Court — <i>Louisiana v. Callais</i> — has the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/15/supreme-court-voting-rights-act-argument-00608340" target="_blank">ability to blow up the entire map</a>.</p> 
<p>“There was a lot of political action in ’25, and that's turning to the courthouse now, this year,” said Justin Levitt, a former adviser to President Joe Biden on democracy and voting rights and a law professor at Loyola Marymount University. “It's not just the Supreme Court. These are fights about individual state practices all over the place.”</p> 
<p>In Missouri, for example, there are multiple lawsuits — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/missouri-redistricting-gerrymander-fight-00675360" target="_blank">and a ballot measure effort</a> — to try and halt the GOP-led redraw there. In Florida, Democrats are already trying to get ahead of Gov. Ron DeSantis’ planned April redraw with <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/florida-redistricting-draws-lawsuit-00767825" target="_blank">a lawsuit that argues he lacks the authority to call for it</a>. Cases in Utah, New York and Wisconsin that could shift seats are still playing out even as voters gear up for primaries.</p> 
<p>In Maryland, the National Republican Congressional Committee has retained a lawyer to handle any potential redistricting challenges there, according to two people familiar with the hiring granted anonymity to discuss it. In Virginia, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/how-virginias-top-court-might-decide-democrats-gerrymandering-fate-00777364" target="_blank">the state Supreme Court is expected to decide</a> whether the Democratic remapping effort — which still needs to go before voters — is legal, with state Democratic officials vowing to challenge decisions from lower state courts that freeze the gerrymandering push.</p> 
<p>Waiting for the court process to play out means organizations dedicated to redistricting are navigating both political and legal challenges simultaneously — and that voters and election officials have no real idea what district lines they may be asked to use, in some cases, in a manner of weeks.</p> 
<p>“That's something we're used to at this point,” said John Bisognano, president of the National Democratic Redistricting Committee. “Running full steam on the political side or campaign side while waiting for court rulings or engaging court processes has been an ever-present reality for us.”</p> 
<p>That isn’t to say there weren't any major court decisions in 2025, nor that there will be no political fighting this year. Already, Maryland Gov. Wes Moore and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/16/wes-moore-redistricting-maryland-00783292" target="_blank">have been ramping up pressure</a> on <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/bill-ferguson-wes-moore-00664770" target="_blank">state Senate Leader Bill Ferguson</a>, a fellow Democrat who opposes the effort. Florida lawmakers have squabbled over what timing is best to take up the issue, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/virginia-redistricting-legislature-00733644" target="_blank">Virginia may see an expensive ballot measure</a> fight play out over its map.</p> 
<p>By far the biggest legal fight is <i>Louisiana v. Callais</i>, the Supreme Court case which centers around Section 2 of the Voting Rights Act. That case could upend the House map by eliminating a legal interpretation of Section 2 — which broadly outlaws discrimination based on race in elections — that has resulted in states drawing districts where minority voters make up at least half the population.</p> 
<p>The end of Section 2 would give red states, especially in the South, the ability to draw out more than a dozen Democratic-held seats, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/republicans-scotus-vra-00597212" target="_blank">an analysis from liberal groups last year found</a>.</p> 
<p>While many legal scholars, including Levitt, expect the decision to come at the end of the term in June — which could prevent any redraws from taking place before the midterms — the Supreme Court could hand down its ruling whenever it wants, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/28/republican-states-voting-rights-act-redistricting-00623775" target="_blank">some states are prepared to quickly redraw</a>.</p> 
<p>A June decision would likely “radically reshape, not just congressional, but local and state maps for ’27 and ’28,” Levitt said.</p> 
<p>“A really really big decision upends every map across the country,” he said, cautioning that he doesn’t expect a ruling to go there. “I think it's entirely possible that the court here says, ‘you know what, never mind,’ it looks over the edge of the cliff and says, ‘oh, that's really scary.’”</p> 
<p>The court’s next scheduled opinion days are Tuesday and Wednesday of this week.</p> 
<p>There are several other major decisions pending in other courts. In Virginia, Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/virginia-redistricting-blocked-court-ruling-00750060" target="_blank">have won victories</a> in two cases in front of the same Tazewell County judge, although many in the state expect the state Supreme Court to have the final word on if the voter referendum on April 21 will go ahead.</p> 
<p>In Utah, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/utah-redistricting-court-ruling-2026-midterms-00793377" target="_blank">a federal panel ruled on Monday</a> that it would not block the new court-ordered map, which gave one blue-leaning seat to Democrats last year. Republicans may appeal, but the decision — and a <a href="https://apnews.com/article/utah-supreme-court-redistricting-appeal-rejected-52f3aec22e64b8d5f7b470f95ae22599" target="_blank">recent state Supreme Court ruling rejecting</a> another GOP appeal — could lock the lines in place for 2026. And in New York, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/new-york-courts-give-democrats-go-ahead-to-redraw-malliotakis-seat-00788691" target="_blank">two state courts have sided with Democrats</a> hoping to draw one more blue-leaning seat in a surprise win, but Republicans have vowed to <a href="https://apnews.com/article/redistricting-congress-new-york-city-house-gerrymandering-bb8349fb35210ad50d31a41fc8ed5d1c" target="_blank">appeal to the U.S. Supreme Court</a>.</p> 
<p>It’s not uncommon for redistricting to end up before judges, but the unusual mid-cycle battle has added fuel to a fire that was already burning.</p> 
<p>“Redistricting cycles have phases. Map drawing, then litigation, then sometimes more mapdrawing. This mid-decade cycle is no different,” said Adam Kincaid, the president of the National Republican Redistricting Trust, who redrew the Texas map last year that was ultimately upheld by the Supreme Court. “There will be several legal fights in the months ahead.”</p> 
<p>But with the map still uncertain just months away from November — and as primary season begins — the lengthy legal process complicates how election workers can prepare ballots, and can lead to confusion for voters.</p> 
<p>“These things take a real toll on election officials and voters,” David Becker, founder of the Center for Election Innovation and Research, said of mid-decade redistricting. “These things make it very difficult for election officials to manage the workload with less resources than they've ever had.”</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dems refuse to make 2024 mistakes in the wake of tariff ruling</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/democrats-tariffs-affordability-trump-00794017</link>
      <description>The party is betting that a strong economic message will resonate better than emphasizing that the president is violating the law with his trade agenda.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8cd2-d0f8-adde-fedabd210001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 18:39:15 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/31/cc/271f3ec648e7bd9b9973f3a836d0/consumer-prices-10828.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Nam Y. Huh/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Shoppers shop at a grocery store in Schaumburg, Illinois, Feb. 9, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/31/cc/271f3ec648e7bd9b9973f3a836d0/consumer-prices-10828.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson and Alec Hernandez</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson and Alec Hernandez</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Supreme Court’s tariff decision left the door wide open for Democrats to hammer President Donald Trump for violating the law. This time, they’re not taking the bait.</p> 
<p>Instead, Democratic campaigns are leaning into an argument they have been making for months: Trump’s tariffs are coming out of voters’ pockets. Some Democrats can’t help but hit the tariffs as “unlawful,” but they’re pivoting quickly back to affordability.</p> 
<p>“The decision is a significant development, but prices are still high for folks across the country, and the administration is determined to keep them high,” said Rep. Suzan DelBene (D-Wash.,) chair of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. “We are laser focused on affordability and holding Republicans accountable for raising prices on families across the country.”</p> 
<p>She said Democrats’ message would have been the same, regardless of how the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trump-tariffs-supreme-court-ruling-00790687" target="_blank">Supreme Court ruled</a>.</p> 
<p>It’s a striking shift from the party’s strategy in 2024, when candidates took every opportunity to warn voters that a second Trump term would create lawlessness and threaten America’s democracy. Even after the nation’s highest court struck down a key plank in the president’s policy agenda, Democrats are eschewing talk of legal intricacies or executive overreach for a focus on the cost of living.</p> 
<p>In Washington and in battlegrounds around the country, Democratic lawmakers, governors and candidates are folding the Court’s check of Trump’s executive authority into their continued argument that tariffs are raising the price of groceries and household expenses. Congress is newly considering legislation on refunding tariff revenue to American small businesses, though Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/mike-johnson-congress-unlikely-to-find-consensus-to-codify-trumps-tariffs-00793462" target="_blank">threw cold water</a> on its chances of advancing.</p> 
<p>Even Democrats who are pushing a more aggressive message — that Trump “stole” from voters’ pockets — are tying it to affordability for American households, not abuse of power from the White House.</p> 
<p>“Donald Trump stole your money with his illegal tariffs — and you paid higher prices on everything from housing to groceries,” Sen. Elizabeth Warren (D-Mass.) <a href="https://www.facebook.com/senatorelizabethwarren/posts/when-someone-illegally-takes-your-money-thats-called-stealingdonald-trump-stole-/1471220944359765/" target="_blank">said on social media</a>.</p> 
<p>Voters remain overwhelmingly pessimistic about the economy, even as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/solid-inflation-jobs-reports-boost-trump-as-his-polling-on-economy-sinks-00780046" target="_blank">job growth and inflation numbers improve.</a> Democrats targeting vulnerable incumbent Republicans from <a href="https://x.com/MannyRutinel/status/2024876773482045486" target="_blank">Colorado</a> to <a href="http://google.com/url?q=https://mailchi.mp/3bc154f2d5a3/welcome-to-the-jake-johnson-for-congress-campaign-1097089?e%3Db1eb737f83&amp;sa=D&amp;source=docs&amp;ust=1771884130386912&amp;usg=AOvVaw3nzuJsN9yp9V4iGQQSB-cg" target="_blank">Minnesota</a> think they’ve found a winning message: Tariffs are making your life unaffordable, whether they’re legal or not.</p> 
<p>“People aren't going to care whether that's under an IEEPA regulation or Section 122,” said Gabe Horwitz, senior vice president at center-left group Third Way. “The fact is, the Trump administration continues to push tariffs that hurt consumers.”</p> 
<p>Democratic operatives point to a series of off-cycle victories late last year in New Jersey, Virginia and elsewhere, where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/16/economy-voters-new-jersey-virginia-midterms-trump-00693015" target="_blank">candidates made cost-of-living central</a> to their pitch. And a torrent of polling suggests Trump’s tariffs are unpopular with the electorate. In <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/poll-affordability-cost-of-living-00678076?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nrid=0000014e-f100-dd93-ad7f-f905199c0001" target="_blank">a November POLITICO Poll</a>, a 45 percent plurality of Americans said higher tariffs are damaging the U.S. economy — in both the short and long term.</p> 
<p>“Prices are increasing, and any time Trump gives us an opportunity to say something happened in the news today — and that is another point of proof that he's making things more expensive — is a good day for Democrats,” said Andrew Mamo, a Democratic strategist involved in 2026 congressional races, including the Texas Democratic Senate primary. “Every time there is an event that we can bring back to affordability is good.”</p> 
<p>There’s also a growing push to send tariff revenue back to consumers, which Democrats believe plays perfectly into their affordability message.</p> 
<p>Reps. Steven Horsford (D-Nev.) and Janelle Bynum (D-Ore.), who both represent battleground districts, introduced legislation Friday that would require Customs and Border Patrol to refund tariffs collected over the past year to small and independent businesses. A group of Democratic senators — led by Sens. Ron Wyden of Oregon, Ed Markey of Massachusetts and Jeanne Shaheen of New Hampshire — <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/senate-democrats-push-for-trump-tariff-rebates-00793196" target="_blank">introduced a similar bill</a> Monday with the backing of Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer.</p> 
<p>The legislation is likely a nonstarter in the GOP-controlled Congress, but gives Democrats a way to put pressure on Republicans.</p> 
<p>“When someone takes money that wasn't authorized and does it in a way that harms you, they've stolen from you, and that is what the Trump administration has done for the last year,” Horsford said in an interview.</p> 
<p>It follows <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/22/trump-tariffs-midterms-affordability-00792411" target="_blank">calls from several Democratic governors</a> — and 2028 contenders — who quickly seized on the debate about refunds in their responses to last week’s court decision.</p> 
<p>Gov. JB Pritzker of Illinois <a href="https://x.com/JBPritzker/status/2024976736849432935/photo/1" target="_blank">demanded the federal government refund families</a> $1,700 per household. California Gov. Gavin Newsom told reporters that Trump has an “obligation” to return the money to consumers who paid more for goods as a result of the tariffs.</p> 
<p>“He took hundreds of billions of dollars from working folks — from the ag community, from small businesses — for this vanity play, this illegal action,” Newsom said Friday.</p> 
<p>At least one Democrat in a key Senate race is also embracing the demand for a tariff refund. Former Sen. Sherrod Brown, who is trying to unseat Jon Husted, <a href="https://x.com/SherrodBrown/status/2025983249919484263" target="_blank">said on X</a>that he wanted a refund for every Ohio household and that Husted supported the tariffs “at every turn.”</p> 
<p>Providing direct relief to consumers is resonating beyond highly engaged Democratic online circles more so than pointing out the illegality of Trump’s tariffs, said Parker Butler, a Democratic digital strategist and managing partner at Luminary Strategies.</p> 
<p>“Pointing out the fact that, ‘See, look, Trump did something illegal’ — obviously that's worth doing, because he did do something illegal,” said Butler, who ran KamalaHQ in 2024 and now leads digital for James Talarico’s Senate campaign in Texas. “But unfortunately, I don't think that's going to permeate outside these sort of online political bubbles. If you want to actually break through beyond that bubble, which is what Democrats need to be doing, you can say, ‘Trump owes you money. He's been illegally taxing you for nearly a year.’”</p> 
<p>Trump has only doubled down on his tariff plans in the wake of the court decision, saying Friday that he would use Section 122 of the Trade Act of 1974 to impose a 15 percent global tariff. But that would expire after 150 days unless Congress extends it — a vote that could squeeze vulnerable members just months before the November midterm.</p> 
<p>Vulnerable Republicans and GOP strategists <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/tariffs-trump-gop-midterms-00791591" target="_blank">who quietly cheered the Friday court decision</a> are worried that they’re heading into a heated, economy-focused election on their back foot.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Democrats see the president’s insistence on keeping his tariff program alive as fuel for their affordability message.</p> 
<p>“We can't communicate episodically. We need to be communicating constantly,” said Will Robinson, a Democratic consultant and ad-maker. “I think the theoretical thing about the Supreme Court and tariffs is less impactful than what's actually going on in the grocery basket.”</p> 
<p><i>Brakkton Booker and Jordain Carney contributed reporting.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dem AGs plot to thwart Trump election interference</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/democratic-attorneys-general-trump-election-meddling-midterms-00792192</link>
      <description>They’re running war-games as they brace for what Trump could do.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7d5a-d3b5-addf-fddea9800000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b4/fa/be9e6c9c48c6a1e76b2e76e37284/us-pennsylvania-elections-mail-ballots-12158.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Gene J. Puskar/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Democratic attorneys general are preparing for possible interference with midterm voting.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b4/fa/be9e6c9c48c6a1e76b2e76e37284/us-pennsylvania-elections-mail-ballots-12158.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic attorneys general are bracing for President Donald Trump to interfere in the midterm elections — and war-gaming how to stop him.</p> 
<p>The party’s top prosecutors have been strategizing for months about how to counter a series of increasingly extreme scenarios they fear could play out this fall. They have huddled in hotel conference rooms and over Zoom meetings to run tabletop exercises anticipating the president’s moves and choreographing responses.</p> 
<p>They’re preparing for the administration to potentially confiscate ballots and voting machines, strip resources from the postal service to disrupt the delivery of mail ballots, and send military members and immigration agents to polling locations to intimidate voters. They’re readying motions for temporary restraining orders to preserve election materials and remove armed forces from voting sites.</p> 
<p>And, as the president attempts to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/trump-nationalize-elections-2026-midterms-00760015" target="_blank">assert federal control</a> over elections, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/democrats-election-trump-voter-rolls-00758940?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTEAc3J0YwZhcHBfaWQKNjYyODU2ODM3OQABHk1JpI160I09woQ0HmJutQTPV4fO8a3OuvHBTWSJcM1eWT7CuqfdtSgNubUQ_aem_q6736O1YOCiI6BvqFPh5iw" target="_blank">seize voter data</a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/trump-2020-election-prosecutions-00738778" target="_blank">relitigate false claims of fraud from 2020</a>, they’re monitoring Trump and his allies’ every word about elections for clues about what his administration could do next.</p> 
<p>“[Trump] wants to continue to have his party prevail, seemingly by whatever means necessary,” California Attorney General Rob Bonta said. “So we have to be ready for that, sad and tragic as it is.”</p> 
<p>The Democratic attorneys general, some of whom battled Trump’s election-subversion tactics in the courts in 2020, have already challenged the president’s efforts to overhaul election administration and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/25/department-of-justice-voting-rolls-data-00581182" target="_blank">access sensitive voter data</a> ahead of a midterm contest that could turn him into a lame duck.</p> 
<p>Nineteen of them <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/03/ags-sue-trump-over-his-order-overhauling-us-elections-00270102" target="_blank">banded together to sue the administration</a> last spring over Trump’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/25/trump-signs-sweeping-executive-order-targeting-election-rules-00249891" target="_blank">sweeping executive order targeting voting rules</a>, most of which has since been blocked by courts. When the Department of Justice dispatched election monitors to polling locations in New Jersey and California last November, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/27/california-will-dispatch-observers-to-watch-dojs-election-monitors-00624039" target="_blank">Bonta deployed his own observers in his state in response</a>.</p> 
<p>But the president’s more recent moves have prosecutors ratcheting up their preparations for November, five Democratic attorneys general said in interviews.</p> 
<p>Earlier this month, Trump called on Republicans to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/trump-nationalize-elections-2026-midterms-00760015" target="_blank">“nationalize” voting</a> and <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/detroit/news/michigan-leaders-react-trump-nationalize-election-detroit/" target="_blank">suggested the federal government should intervene</a> in election operations in swing-states' predominantly blue cities like Atlanta, Detroit and Philadelphia — places that have been central to his election conspiracy theories for years. House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/17/save-act-election-security-noncitizen-voting-00782470" target="_blank">passed one set of voting restrictions and are teeing up another</a>, though the measures are unlikely to clear the Senate. And Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem raised alarms among Democrats when she said her department is working to ensure “<a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/5739328-noem-voting-midterm-elections/" target="_blank">that we have the right people voting, electing the right leaders.</a>”</p> 
<p>Trump and his allies’ rhetoric is the type of “red-alarm fire that people need to take very seriously,” said Washington Attorney General Nick Brown, who leads the Democratic Attorneys General Association’s election protection working group.</p> 
<p>“He will try anything,” Brown said, so “we have to just sort of think creatively about: If you were the president and you were trying to invalidate an election or undermine an election, what are the oddball, ludicrous, unconstitutional theories that you might advance?”</p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson fired back in a statement accusing Democrats of “plotting to undermine commonsense election integrity efforts supported by a vast majority of Americans” and arguing existing law gives the Department of Justice “full authority to ensure states comply with federal election laws, which mandate accurate state voter rolls.”</p> 
<p>“President Trump is committed to ensuring that Americans have full confidence in the administration of elections, and that includes totally accurate and up-to-date voter rolls free of errors and unlawfully registered non-citizen voters,” Jackson said. “The President has also urged Congress to pass the SAVE Act and other legislative proposals that would establish a uniform standard of photo ID for voting, prohibit no-excuse mail-in voting, and end the practice of ballot harvesting to ensure the safety and security of our elections.”</p> 
<p>Democratic attorneys general have <a href="https://www.facebook.com/DemocraticAGs/posts/the-save-act-wont-protect-elections-it-would-block-eligible-voters-from-the-ball/1333586278813818/" target="_blank">panned the SAVE Act</a> as an attack on the right to vote and urged Congress not to pass it and other measures Trump is pushing.</p> 
<p>They also fear the Trump administration could aim to intimidate legal voters by sending Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents to polling locations.</p> 
<p>ICE chief Todd Lyons said in a congressional hearing earlier this month that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zgE7QZnfBLQ" target="_blank">there’s “no reason” for ICE officials to be deployed to polling facilities</a>. But <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/04/steve-bannon-ice-military-polling-sites-00765331?fbclid=IwY2xjawQEYZFleHRuA2FlbQIxMQBzcnRjBmFwcF9pZAwzNTA2ODU1MzE3MjgAAR6sgdetgAwWCmn65e0P74z1tnJrIOwXmsbEULKhX3h-Ros9AqNVPzc_I8wvdA_aem_2UCbuHMYA42SB1HGA_s-rA" target="_blank">MAGA influencer Steve Bannon</a>, a former White House strategist, is encouraging the president to take that step to prevent noncitizens from voting, despite its <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/07/30/nx-s1-5462836/noncitizen-voting-trump-ceir-review" target="_blank">rare occurrence</a>. He’s also urging Trump to send in troops, further stoking Democrats’ concerns. </p> 
<p>When asked about Bannon’s comments during a briefing earlier this month, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z0XgAtj6tuA" target="_blank">White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said</a> while she “can’t guarantee that an ICE agent won’t be around a polling location in November” she hadn’t “heard the president discuss any formal plans to put ICE outside of polling locations,” calling the question "disingenuous."</p> 
<p>Democrats aren't reassured.</p> 
<p>“If the president said, ‘Look, I want my ICE people to protect American elections … go to all these polling places and stand out in front with guns,’ I think they would do it,” said Attorney General Keith Ellison of Minnesota, where an immigration enforcement surge earlier this year resulted in two deaths. “And I think we all need to be prepared to deal with that problem.”</p> 
<p>Several Democratic attorneys general said they’re particularly alarmed after the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/fulton-county-search-warrant-affidavit-00774751" target="_blank">FBI seized voting records in Fulton County, Georgia</a>, based on a referral from Kurt Olsen, an attorney who worked with Trump to undermine the 2020 election results. They’re now bracing for similar seizures in other places Trump has previously targeted over debunked claims of voter fraud.</p> 
<p>Those concerns are heightened in battleground states with contests that could decide control of Congress.</p> 
<p>“We recognize that what happened in Fulton County could happen in Detroit. Not because there’s any merit to claims that anything wrong happened in Detroit, but because we know that those claims will be made again,” said Democratic Attorney General Dana Nessel of swing-state Michigan.</p> 
<p>“The president and his administration know and understand that Democrats don’t win statewide in Michigan without counting the Detroit vote,” she added. “So of course Trump wants to undermine in people’s minds the integrity of Detroit elections, even though that’s not borne fruit whenever that has been investigated.”</p> 
<p>Democrats in states that rely heavily on mail-in ballots are also girding for an assault on the voting system that Trump is trying to eliminate, but that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/republicans-midterms-mail-in-voting-00693867" target="_blank">GOP operatives</a> and even some <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/trump-mail-voting-congress-00785635" target="_blank">Republicans in Congress</a> support as a way to keep voters engaged in non-presidential years.</p> 
<p>They are worried about Trump weaponizing the postal service, either by <a href="https://apnews.com/article/virus-outbreak-election-2020-ap-top-news-elections-politics-14a2ceda724623604cc8d8e5ab9890ed" target="_blank">again blocking funding for the agency</a> or <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2020/sep/21/usps-post-office-mail-slowdowns-louis-dejoy" target="_blank">installing allies to slow operations</a>. And they cautioned that his push to discount ballots that are postmarked by Election Day but arrive afterward could disenfranchise voters in states with grace periods. The Supreme Court is due to consider a case on ballot deadlines next month.</p> 
<p>Democratic attorneys general, meanwhile, will argue in a lower court next week in a multistate lawsuit seeking to permanently block portions of Trump’s executive order — which includes cutting off mail ballots and requiring documentary proof of citizenship for the national voter registration form — from taking effect.</p> 
<p>Nevada Attorney General Aaron Ford, who is co-leading the lawsuit alongside Bonta, urged his counterparts to “stay nimble.”</p> 
<p>Trump “likes to sow chaos because he thinks it’s going to throw people off their game,” Ford said. “But he has met his match when it comes to the Nevada attorney general’s office; he's met his match when it comes to the Democratic attorneys general.”</p> 
<p><i>Elena Schneider contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nicki Minaj’s social media propped up by thousands of bots, analysis finds</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/the-bots-powering-nicki-minajs-maga-war-00771317</link>
      <description>An analysis shared with POLITICO reveals the rap sensation’s advocacy for conservative causes has been amplified by an army of bots and coordinated activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-434b-de8a-a1fc-fb4b9d800000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/1c/94/24e28ad849538e8f45b6fae80264/main-beeferman-minaj-alt.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Bill Kuchman/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images, AP and iStock)</media:credit>
        <media:title>A new report finds that rap star Nicki Minaj was amplified by thousands of bots as she rose to conservative stardom on social media.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1c/94/24e28ad849538e8f45b6fae80264/main-beeferman-minaj-alt.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jason Beeferman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jason Beeferman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nicki Minaj spent the past year transforming herself from a polarizing rap superstar into a high-profile conservative provocateur, lobbing viral attacks at Democratic leaders, boosting MAGA talking points and earning public praise from President Donald Trump and his allies.</p> 
<p>On social media, Minaj’s pugnacious persona and sharp-edged posts — including repeated broadsides against California Gov. Gavin Newsom — have made her a darling of the Trump administration and the conservative movement, drawing millions of views and steady amplification from far-right influencers.</p> 
<p>But quietly, humming in the background of her varied social media blitzes, a sophisticated army of bots was unconditionally praising and amplifying Minaj’s content, according to <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-7720-de8a-a1fc-ff6079aa0000" target="_blank">a new report</a> shared exclusively with POLITICO.</p> 
<p>The report, compiled by the disinformation detection company Cyabra, identifies a coordinated network of bots — more than 18,000 of them — that drove algorithms to spread Minaj’s posts on X.</p> 
<p>The analysis, which looked at social media activity from Nov. 11 to Dec. 28, provides a window into how the rapper was able to capture millions of views online and position herself as a celebrity the White House found value in partnering with. Last month, Minaj joined the president at the Trump Accounts Summit — where Trump <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fbsKAhAES3k" target="_blank">invited her on stage</a>, showered her with praise and recorded a <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@realdonaldtrump/video/7600543092462112030?is_from_webapp=1&amp;sender_device=pc" target="_blank">chummy TikTok video</a> with her afterward.</p> 
<p>“We don't really see a lot of high volume, high impact orchestration of bad and fake actors within that intersection of the geopolitically driven and music culture,” said Dan Brahmy, the CEO and founder of Cyabra. “It is scarce in our field to see the combination of the bad and the fake online world with the entertainment world.”</p> 
<p>The report found inauthentic accounts repeatedly amplified Minaj’s posts with praise that used “highly similar language,” particularly in response to posts where authentic accounts were criticizing Minaj.</p> 
<p>“Supportive comments generated by fake profiles were predominantly brief, repetitive, and low in semantic complexity, consisting largely of praising keywords and positive hashtags rather than original or substantive engagement,” the report found.</p> 
<p>Other inauthentic activity surrounding Minaj included “longer, more detailed comments designed to appear organic.”</p> 
<p>“Nicki you are brave for living your truth, people might not always agree with what's being played out, but as an artist and watching your growth as a person is inspiring,” read one comment from a purported Minaj fan, @LAX76283656, that was deemed fake by Cyabra.</p> 
<p>“This pattern suggests a deliberate attempt to integrate into genuine conversations, increasing the credibility and visibility of the amplified content,” the report read.</p> 
<p>Cyabra identified one day, Dec. 26, when fake profiles made up 56 percent of all comments on political posts made by Minaj.</p> 
<p>Bot networks have become a familiar feature of modern politics since revelations of Russian interference in the 2016 presidential election, when coordinated inauthentic accounts were used to <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2019/06/05/study-russia-cybersecurity-twitter-1353543" target="_blank">inflame divisions and manipulate online discourse</a>. Such campaigns are now routinely detected around wars, elections and geopolitical flashpoints — but far less often around celebrities or the music industry.</p> 
<p>That backdrop helps explain why Cyabra’s findings seem so peculiar. Rather than a short-lived spike tied to a single event or appearance, the company found sustained and coordinated amplification of Minaj’s posts across a range of political and cultural topics over time.</p> 
<p>When Minaj posted about <a href="https://x.com/NICKIMINAJ/status/1999564153015452068?s=20" target="_blank">her support</a> for Trump, her <a href="https://x.com/NICKIMINAJ/status/1999537761754153280?s=20" target="_blank">concern over the persecution</a> of Christians in Nigeria and Newsom’s <a href="https://x.com/NICKIMINAJ/status/1999471516040503316?s=20" target="_blank">perceived alignment</a> with the transgender community, the bots were there to back her up, Cyabra’s report shows. They also amplified her posts related to the music industry.</p> 
<p>Representatives for Minaj did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>Alex Bruesewitz, a media and political adviser to Trump who considers Minaj a “very close friend,” told POLITICO he is confident there are no bots involved with the rapper’s social media presence.</p> 
<p>“Nicki has never used bot activity to promote herself on social media, because she doesn't need to,” Bruesewitz said. “She has one of the largest fan bases of any musician that's alive today.”</p> 
<p>The Cyabra report was commissioned by a person who was granted anonymity because they fear public retaliation.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/09/8e/e65deb0f4ff0a4efea54f898a7f9/gettyimages-2258679012.jpg" alt="Nicki Minaj joins President Donald Trump on stage as he delivers remarks during the Treasury Department's Trump Accounts Summit on Jan. 28, 2026, in Washington." data-portal-copyright="Win McNamee/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2258679012" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Nicki Minaj joins President Donald Trump on stage as he delivers remarks during the Treasury Department's Trump Accounts Summit on Jan. 28, 2026, in Washington."/><p>Cyabra is about 85 percent confident the more than 18,000 profiles identified are fake. But if the company were to narrow that scope to profiles that exhibit even stronger signs of inauthenticity, the confidence level could easily rise into the 90s, Brahmy said.</p> 
<p>“We always have to make sure that we play at a confidence level that's strong enough for people to rely on it, and doesn't really change the narrative,” he said.</p> 
<p>And when accounts boosting Minaj posted content that researchers identified as “toxic,” the algorithm drove her posts even further. Companies like Cyabra determine toxicity by assessing not just the “positive” or “negative” words used in a post, but the apparent intent behind them, Brahmy said. Personal attacks, slurs, threats or comments that seem designed to deter a reasonable person from engaging in conversation are typically considered toxic.</p> 
<p>“When the conversation is limited to toxic content, a substantially stronger amplification effect emerges,” the report found. “These accounts predominantly amplify content produced by Nicki Minaj and Turning Point USA, indicating a notable overlap between the two within this discourse. Several of the accounts involved had previously been identified as exhibiting fake campaign-like behavior in the context of Minaj’s online activity within and relating to the music industry.”</p> 
<p>Turning Point USA didn’t respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>The analysis also shows how foreign and domestic political narratives can be manipulated by bot networks without broad public awareness — and how influential figures in the hip-hop world are making inroads into the conservative political conversation in America.</p> 
<p>Minaj’s online activity was not only amplified by inauthentic accounts — but also a string of authentic accounts, including those of popular conservative influencers Dom Lucre and Matt Wallace, Cyabra found. The way those accounts parroted Minaj’s talking points suggest strategic coordination behind the scenes, Brahmy said.</p> 
<p>“Real human beings are behaving the exact same way, utilizing the exact same behavioral patterns, as you would expect from a well coordinated campaign,” Brahmy said. “They amplify each other. They are riding the same, similar wave of narrative.”</p> 
<p>Lucre responded with a statement saying, “This is one of the most absurd conspiracy theories I have ever seen in my entire life brother.”</p> 
<p>He then uploaded videos to his <a href="https://x.com/dom_lucre/status/2024224300538941465?s=20" target="_blank">X</a> and <a href="https://youtu.be/GdgJNJYVF8U?si=vjpUuQ7s59uDSus4" target="_blank">YouTube</a> accounts reacting to POLITICO’s questions about whether he was coordinating his posts about Minaj with others or being paid for posts related to the rapper.</p> 
<p>“Nicki Minaj is now pulling so many liberals to the right that they now have to push out a theory that these aren't real organic people, and that she's now manipulating the system with bots,” Lucre said. “If Nicki Minaj was manipulating systems with bots on Instagram, TikTok, X, do you not think there would be a conclusive data that they would have to present this instead of asking influencers to say yes?”</p> 
<p>Wallace did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Minaj’s foray into politics comes after Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/11/07/trump-black-latino-men-working-class-00188185" target="_blank">made inroads with Black and Hispanic voters</a> in the 2024 election. He and his allies have been eager to propel a political realignment around a multiracial, working-class, right-populist coalition, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/latino-voters-powered-trumps-comeback-now-theyre-turning-on-his-economy-00726548" target="_blank">polls show</a> that that 2024 coalition has <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2026/02/18/black-voters-maga-trump/" target="_blank">frayed badly</a> over the last year.</p><img src="https://static.politico.com/44/c0/19224a9f420cbb7a67b76dba914b/ap25355700623331.jpg" alt="Erika Kirk, left, and Nicki Minaj stand on stage during Turning Point USA's AmericaFest 2025, Sunday, Dec. 21, 2025, in Phoenix. (AP Photo/Jon Cherry)" data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25355700623331" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Erika Kirk, left, and Nicki Minaj stand on stage during Turning Point USA's AmericaFest 2025, Sunday, Dec. 21, 2025, in Phoenix. (AP Photo/Jon Cherry)"/><p>Minaj has moved toward embracing the MAGA movement since July of last year. Her rightward shift was cemented in December during her appearance with Erika Kirk, the widow of slain conservative activist Charlie Kirk, at Turning Point USA's AmericaFest convention. In late 2025, before Trump embraced her at last month’s summit, her political views also drew praise from the likes of Vice President JD Vance and Ambassador to the United Nations Mike Waltz.</p> 
<p>On social media, her barrage of GOP-friendly posts garner millions of views, including those taking aim at Newsom.</p> 
<p>“Career politician at the brink of his moment realigns to become nothing more than a Nicki Minaj ANTI. OOF,” Minaj <a href="https://x.com/NICKIMINAJ/status/1999896953124003865?lang=en" target="_blank">wrote</a> in December, with a photo depicting Newsom behind bars in a jail cell. “So now he’s the guy running on ‘wanting to see trans kids’ AND willing to lower himself to becoming just another FEMALE RAPPER to get obliterated by NICKI MINAJ.”</p> 
<p>“Let’s wait…I think Gavvy’s still transitioning,” she said in another <a href="https://x.com/NICKIMINAJ/status/1999914480525037809" target="_blank">post</a> on the same day, which generated over 1 million views.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Newsom — who is named multiple times in the report and was a <a href="https://variety.com/2025/music/news/nicki-minaj-gavin-newsom-feud-tweets-trans-megan-track-1236609232/" target="_blank">frequent target of Minaj</a> during Cyabra’s analysis period — sent a statement ridiculing Minaj when asked for comment on the report’s findings.</p> 
<p>“Like most MAGA mouthpieces, we are not surprised Nicki Minaj needs bots to stay relevant,” Newsom spokesperson Izzy Gardon said. </p> 
<p>Cyabra’s report identifies 18,784 fake profiles that were at the ready to boost Minaj’s content.</p> 
<p>Those accounts represented 33 percent of the total profiles evaluated by Cyabra — a ratio of inauthentic activity similar to those seen during wars and presidential elections, Brahmy said. Inauthentic accounts typically represent between 7 and 10 percent of organic social media discourse, the company said.</p> 
<p>Cyabra works with corporations to identify online bot activity and misinformation campaigns, with the goal of helping them protect their reputation and understand malicious actors online. It uses software to analyze social media activity — and provides its services to PR firms, legal practices, multinational corporations and governments.</p> 
<p>Cyabra gleaned the bot activity by examining the accounts’ temporal synchronization, their linguistic and stylistic uniformity and the similar demographics shared by the fake identities. The company developed a machine learning algorithm to identify fake accounts.</p> 
<p>Jen Golbeck, a computer science professor at the University of Maryland who studies artificial intelligence and social media, told POLITICO the purpose of a “botnet” can go beyond manipulating the narrative in a single comment section. The bots’ interactions signal to social media algorithms that a post draws high-engagement, which drives the algorithm to spread the content further.</p> 
<p>“You can really expand your reach beyond your follower base if you get high levels of interaction, and these interaction bots do that,” said Golbeck, who also writes the <a href="http://magareport.news/" target="_blank">MAGAReport substack</a>.</p> 
<p>Joel Penney, a professor at Montclair State University who studies popular culture and politics, said Trump’s adoption of Minaj into his political project is likely part of a larger strategy to reach younger, more diverse audiences.</p> 
<p>“They've made a lot of efforts to include celebrities who are supportive, including hip-hop figures; Nicki Minaj is probably the biggest name to kind of become a pretty public advocate,” Penney said. “They don't have the power to wave a wand and make all their followers or fans of their music support their political advocacy. But it matters. It contributes to this kind of war for public opinion that we see play out on social media.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noem restricts disaster aid over shutdown that targets ICE</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/22/noem-restricts-disaster-aid-ice-budget-shutdown-00792447</link>
      <description>The Federal Emergency Management Agency will stop paying for nonemergency activities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8724-de8a-a1fc-ff64fc650000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 16:11:21 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ef/a0/fa76ffdf4864a5fd9440f91dd1fa/noem-border-wall-immigration-46470.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ross D. Franklin/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said disaster aid would be distributed at the "bare minimum."</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ef/a0/fa76ffdf4864a5fd9440f91dd1fa/noem-border-wall-immigration-46470.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Thomas Frank</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Thomas Frank</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Trump administration halted disaster aid Sunday to states for long-term rebuilding projects in order to focus on emergency operations as the partial government shutdown enters its second week. </p> 
<p>The Federal Emergency Management Agency “is scaling back to bare-minimum, life-saving operations only,” Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem <a href="https://www.dhs.gov/news/2026/02/22/1-week-democrats-shutdown-dhs-implements-emergency-measures-conserve-resources-and" target="_blank">said in a statement</a>. “All non-emergency recovery work is paused.”</p> 
<p>The funding freeze for projects stemming from past disasters adds a source of uncertainty for states as they navigate the government's shifting system for catastrophe response after President Donald Trump vowed to reduce aid for extreme weather. </p> 
<p>It's also a sign that political acrimony over Trump's immigration crackdown has affected FEMA, which is housed with Immigration and Customs Enforcement under the Department of Homeland Security. Congressional Democrats have blocked a DHS spending bill over ICE's aggressive tactics. </p> 
<p>It's the 11th time since 2003 that FEMA has suspended funding for long-term disaster recovery projects, such as rebuilding public facilities, based on budget constraints. </p> 
<p>The latest restriction was unusual because the agency had <a href="https://www.congress.gov/crs_external_products/IN/PDF/IN12644/IN12644.3.pdf" target="_blank">$7.1 billion available in its disaster fund</a> in late January. Historically, FEMA has waited until the disaster fund drops to about $3 billion before it restricts spending.</p> 
<p>FEMA officials told Congress last week that the fund had $9.6 billion, according to a senior congressional aide who was granted anonymity to discuss internal conversations. The fund's balance increased in February because FEMA recovered aid that had been approved but not spent, the aide said.</p> 
<p>On Sunday, Noem said DHS “must take emergency measures to preserve limited funds and personnel." The announcement came days after FEMA employee travel was restricted by DHS.</p> 
<p>Noem blamed Democrats for the shutdown, which she said forced her to halt the FEMA funding. Noem also suspended two DHS airport programs over the weekend that allowed some travelers to skip long lines at screening checkpoints and at customs entry stations. “These actions reflect the reality of operating without appropriations,” she said.</p> 
<p>Noem, whose department includes the Transportation Security Administration, said she wanted to “refocus Department personnel on the majority of travelers.”</p> 
<p>The TSA contradicted Noem hours after her announcement and said <a href="https://x.com/TSA/status/2025596243762884636" target="_blank">its PreCheck program</a> at passenger screening checkpoints “remains operational with no change for the traveling public.”</p> 
<p>That led some Democrats to criticize the administration for politicizing homeland security programs. </p> 
<p>“These nitwits are at it again,” Rep. Bennie Thompson of Mississippi, the top Democrat on the House Homeland Security Committee, said in a statement, adding that the airport programs “REDUCE airport lines and ease the burden on DHS.”</p> 
<p>Noem’s decision on FEMA funding will not affect operations at 44 active disaster sites, including those in a dozen Southern states that are recovering from a massive winter storm in late January. Nearly 2,800 disaster specialists were working across the country Sunday, and another 4,400 were available to be deployed, <a href="https://content.govdelivery.com/attachments/USDHSFEMA/2026/02/22/file_attachments/3561456/FEMA%20Daily%20Ops%20Briefing%2002-22-2026.pdf" target="_blank">according to a FEMA report</a>.</p> 
<p>But the funding restrictions could delay thousands of long-term disaster rebuilding projects. FEMA pays at least 75 percent of the cost of eligible projects. Many states and localities delay or halt work when FEMA stops its payments.</p> 
<p>“States and communities will be forced to wait for long-term response work to continue,” Gregg Phillips, FEMA’s associate administrator for the Office of Response and Recovery, <a href="https://docs.house.gov/meetings/AP/AP15/20260211/118960/HHRG-119-AP15-Wstate-PhillipsG-20260211.pdf" target="_blank">told a House Appropriations subcommittee</a> on Feb. 11.</p> 
<p>The FEMA disaster fund “has sufficient balances to continue emergency response activities for the foreseeable future,” Phillips said in written testimony submitted to the panel. But if a disaster occurred, the fund “would be seriously strained.”</p> 
<p>The funding restriction also threatens to further delay Trump's decisions on granting 14 requests for disaster aid by governors and tribal leaders since Nov. 26.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ‘gift’ Democrats think Trump just gave them</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/22/trump-tariffs-midterms-affordability-00792411</link>
      <description>For Democrats, it’s not just the tariff ruling that could open a new messaging avenue — it’s also President Donald Trump’s doubling down.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-862b-d647-addc-afef2b150000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 11:40:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/aa/6c/19cc6c0a4019b45c44f148e6dd04/trump-23279.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump speaks during an event to announce new tariffs in the Rose Garden at the White House on Wednesday, April 2, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/aa/6c/19cc6c0a4019b45c44f148e6dd04/trump-23279.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Ali Bianco and Irie Sentner</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Ali Bianco and Irie Sentner</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are frothing at the mouth to center President Donald Trump’s tariff chaos in their affordability messaging as they charge into the midterms.</p> 
<p>The party was already planning to slam Republicans over the economy on the campaign trail, riding the playbook that helped propel New Jersey Gov. Mikie Sherrill, Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger and New York City Mayor Zohran Mamdani to victories last year. Then, on Friday, the Supreme Court in a remarkable rebuke slapped down Trump’s tariffs — declaring illegal his favorite lever to bend the global economy to his will.</p> 
<p>But for Democratic strategists and party officials who spoke with POLITICO, it’s not just the high court’s ruling that could open a new avenue — it’s also Trump’s doubling down, moving to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/21/trump-tariff-supreme-court-00792288" target="_blank">levy 15 percent tariffs worldwide</a> under a different authority. “Now we have a new data point that Trump is not going to relent,” said a person familiar with Democrats’ strategies, granted anonymity to speak candidly.</p> 
<p>Democratic operatives see it as a massive windfall.</p> 
<p>“It’s such a gift,” the person familiar said. “The gift of it is how politically inept it is.”</p> 
<p>Doug Herman, a Democratic strategist based in California, said Trump’s renewed tariff saber-rattling provides “tailor-made” messaging on affordability for Democrats. “Every American has borne the cost of these Trump tariffs,” he said. “It’s the kind of thing that everybody needs to take advantage of in their campaigns.”</p> 
<p>The crop of potential Democratic 2028 presidential candidates leapt into action immediately. Illinois Gov. JB Pritzker <a href="https://x.com/JBPritzker/status/2024976912305496442/photo/1" target="_blank">released an “invoice”</a> demanding that the White House pay more than $8.6 billion in “past due” tariff revenue, which he calculated out to $1,700 per family in his state. “The President owes you an apology — and a refund,” Pete Buttigieg <a href="https://x.com/petebuttigieg/status/2025202239778734254?s=46" target="_blank">said on X</a>. California Gov. Gavin Newsom <a href="https://x.com/allenanalysis/status/2024951108762845350?s=46" target="_blank">told reporters that Trump</a> “should return that money immediately.”</p> 
<p>“They imposed a sales tax on the American people,” veteran Democratic strategist James Carville told POLITICO. “What did you get? Nothing.”</p> 
<p>That messaging — branding the tariffs as illegal taxes that Trump must repatriate to voters (which, he said Friday, he did not intend to do) — is expected to become a core component of Democrats’ strategy as they fight to retake majorities in Congress.</p> 
<p>“I wouldn’t be surprised if tariffs made it in 50 percent of our paid advertising,” said one Democratic strategist working on House campaigns. Another who works on Senate campaigns said they’re preparing to rev up their ads on affordability as well.</p> 
<p>“We have a very clear line that we can draw from [voters] struggling to make ends meet, and things that Trump is doing intentionally,” said Matt Bennett, an executive with Third Way, a center-left think tank. “It is a uniquely easy story for Democrats to tell.”</p> 
<p>It’s also not lost on the party that the states whose economies have been hit hardest by the tariffs are home to some of the most contentious Senate races that could make or break the GOP’s majority. “We’ve not only lost our markets and gotten lower prices selling corn and soybeans, particularly soybeans, but we have also, at the same time right now, we have the misfortune of having very high inputs, a lot of uncertainty,” Iowa Democratic Party Chair Rita Hart told POLITICO. “We’re talking about real hardship where people are going to be really negatively affected financially.”</p> 
<p>Trump, of course, is not on the ballot in November, but multiple Democratic operatives told POLITICO they’re planning to skewer any Republican who has defended his tariffs. “It’s this very, very easy to understand action that the president took, and that congressional Republicans backed,” the Democratic strategist working on Senate races said. So the line for Dem candidates will be cut and dried: “This is where my opponent is not fighting for you,” they said.</p> 
<p>The RNC is fully prepared to defend against any Democratic attacks. “The Supreme Court’s decision does not change the reality: President Trump’s trade agenda is working, and Republicans are united in strengthening the economy for American families,” RNC spokesperson Kiersten Pels said in a statement. “His tariffs have helped lower inflation, raise wages, and drive historic investment into U.S. manufacturing and energy. As we head into the midterms, Republicans are focused on building on these gains and putting workers first — while Democrats oppose the policies bringing jobs back home.”</p> 
<p>The White House, too, is brushing off the idea that Democrats have been handed a messaging victory.</p> 
<p>“President Trump has powerfully used tariffs to renegotiate broken trade deals, lower drug prices, and secure trillions in manufacturing investments for American workers — all things Democrats have promised to do for decades,” White House spokesperson Kush Desai said in a statement. “It’s not surprising Democrats care more about having a phony talking point than these tangible victories for the American people, because talking is all Democrats have ever been able to do.”</p> 
<p>But the economic picture over the last year has soured, with <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trumps-economy-decelerated-as-shutdown-consumer-spending-drag-on-growth-00790640" target="_blank">key indicators released Friday</a> showing slowed growth and rising inflation. Recent polls find that costs and the economy <a href="https://www.reuters.com/data/trumps-approval-rating-2025-01-21/" target="_blank">remain a central concern</a> going into November. And though Trump is visiting battleground states to pitch his economic message, he has thus far struggled to acknowledge voters’ concerns. In Georgia on Thursday, the day before the Supreme Court’s ruling came down, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-sotu-georgia-rally-00790155" target="_blank">Trump claimed he had “won affordability”</a> and told voters his tariffs were “the greatest thing that’s happened in this country.”</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, Trump will stand before Congress for his State of the Union address — one of the largest platforms that the presidential bully pulpit provides. Trump said last week he would focus on the economy in those remarks.</p> 
<p>Democrats have a tsunami of counterprogramming planned — including anti-SOTU rallies. Multiple Democrats, including Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, will bring as their guests some small business owners who’ve been affected by Trump’s tariffs, guaranteeing the issue will be front and center, regardless of the substance of the president’s remarks</p> 
<p>DCCC Chair Suzan DelBene (D-Wash.) previewed what this messaging will sound like on the campaign trail. “House Republicans rubber stamped President Trump’s tariffs and are responsible for the painful affordability crisis they have unleashed on American families,” DelBene said in a statement. “Voters will not soon forget Republicans are the reason everything is more expensive.”</p> 
<p><i>Like this content? Consider signing up for POLITICO's </i><a href="https://www.politico.com/playbook" target="_blank"><i>Playbook newsletter</i></a><i>. </i><br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Graham Platner’s meteoric rise is so unexpected</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/22/maine-senate-graham-platner-janet-mills-susan-collins-00791784</link>
      <description>The progressive oysterman is finding traction in a state that has a long track record of electing senators perceived as moderates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7cd9-de8a-a1fc-fdd976e30001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ef/af/150148144b748146fed5a861d22e/main-piper-mainesenate-override.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photos by Ryan David Brown for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Graham Platner poses for a portrait in Bangor, Maine, on Jan. 29.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ef/af/150148144b748146fed5a861d22e/main-piper-mainesenate-override.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BRUNSWICK, Maine — The fireplace crackled as Democratic Gov. Janet Mills laid out her vision for beating Susan Collins to a room of supporters in late January. Then came the questions about her primary opponent, Graham Platner.</p> 
<p>Platner, one attendee noted, was very successful on social media. A second pointed to his support among young people and asked Mills whether she would support him if he became the party’s nominee.</p> 
<p>“I am a Democrat,” Mills answered, before pivoting to how she sought as governor to make the state more affordable for young Mainers.</p> 
<p>Mills’ Democratic primary opponent isn’t her favorite subject. She would rather talk about how she expanded Medicaid, bolstered protections for reproductive rights, and, most recently, challenged President Donald Trump over the surge of immigration enforcement in the state — issues that conveniently allow the governor to draw contrast with Collins, the five-term Republican who Democrats must unseat in order to take back control of the Senate.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/15/5e/e0a89d2e43af8026b2fbabdca4a7/mills-platner-54-edit.jpg" alt="Maine Gov. Janet Mills speaks to supporters in Brunswick on Jan. 28." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Ryan David Brown" data-title="Maine Gov. Janet Mills speaks to supporters in Brunswick on Jan. 28."/><p>But Platner, a political newcomer, has made himself all but unavoidable in conversations about the Maine Senate race. The 41-year-old oyster farmer and combat veteran is unlike any other recent popular candidate the state has seen: He is brash. He is progressive. He has drawn crowds of hundreds of people, national attention and millions in campaign dollars.</p> 
<p>Platner’s meteoric rise reflects a growing frustration with the Democratic establishment and voters' interest in a new generation of leaders. He is campaigning not just against Collins but against a “billionaire class,” running a campaign in the style of Sen. Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.), <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/30/bernie-sanders-endorsement-maine-graham-platner-00538084" target="_blank">who endorsed him</a>.</p> 
<p>His battle with Mills comes at a moment when the stakes for Democrats could hardly be higher. Though the Maine Democratic Party doesn’t take positions in primaries, some establishment figures like Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/janet-mills-enters-crowded-maine-senate-race-00597876" target="_blank">have backed</a> the moderate governor, who they believe is their best shot at defeating Collins to win back the Senate in 2026.</p> 
<p>The challenge for Platner is that he is running on a vision of disruptive progressivism and generational change in Maine, the oldest state in the nation and one with a long track record electing senators perceived as moderates within their parties. Mills would largely fit that image; Platner would blow it up entirely. But he is betting that voters now want what he is offering — and his early support makes it hard to ignore the possibility.</p> 
<p>“If you look at everyone from Bill Cohen to Angus King to George Mitchell to Susan Collins and Olympia Snowe, there’s a strong, moderate streak there when it hits November,” said Adam Cote, a Maine lawyer and veteran who ran for governor in 2018, coming in second to Mills in the Democratic primary. “In the primary, I don’t know.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ad/43/898c08454ac48fa2917f51096e72/ap26023619583043-edit.jpg" alt="A woman films a Homeland Security Investigations agent at a parking lot in Portland on Jan. 23." data-portal-copyright="Robert F. Bukaty/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26023619583043" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="A woman films a Homeland Security Investigations agent at a parking lot in Portland on Jan. 23."/><p>While public polling in the race has been relatively scarce, an internal poll released by Platner’s campaign last month had him up by double digits over Mills. He has 283,000 followers on Instagram compared to 61,000 for Mills and 25,000 for Collins. His campaign boasts of a 15,000-person strong volunteer network. Through the end of December, he raised $7.8 million to $2.7 million for Mills, enough to begin running TV ads more than four months in advance of the June primary.</p> 
<p>“My wife makes this joke. I've been just saying the same bullshit for years, ranting on about structural inequality, ranting on about, like, American history and how we need to reconnect with things. Nobody cared about me because I was a random dude in Sullivan, Maine,” Platner said in an interview. “I'm now running for United States Senate, and I get to have this conversation at a national level.”</p> 
<p>Both in style and substance, Platner is unlike any candidate who has risen to the highest levels of Maine politics in recent decades. Even before he faced a litany of controversies in the fall — including a series of offensive old Reddit posts <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/17/graham-platner-seeks-to-turn-the-page-on-his-online-comments-00614848" target="_blank">for which he apologized</a> and a tattoo of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/graham-platner-tattoo-nazi-00617686" target="_blank">a Nazi symbol that he had covered up</a> — the Sullivan oysterman was building an operation different from any Maine Democrat.</p> 
<p>Platner does not like the label of progressive, but where he differs with Mills on policy, his positions are largely to her left. He has backed progressive priorities like Medicare for All, described Israel’s military actions in Gaza as a genocide, and favors abolishing Immigration and Customs Enforcement.</p> 
<p>Asked whether progressives can win in Maine, Platner pointed to <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1900&amp;context=survey_center_polls" target="_blank">polling showing Sanders’ popularity</a> despite his finishing narrowly behind Joe Biden in the 2020 presidential primary.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/4d/d6/7bc0f4f845628f8105deffb4e539/politico-graham-platner-106-edit.jpg" alt="Supporters packed a gymnasium during a campaign event for Platner in Damariscotta in October 2025." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Ryan David Brown for POLITICO" data-title="Supporters packed a gymnasium during a campaign event for Platner in Damariscotta in October 2025."/><p>Although more progressive state lawmakers have been elected from southern Maine over the past few election cycles, further-left candidates finished far behind the more moderate ones in statewide primaries for governor in 2018 and Senate in 2020.</p> 
<p>“There's a reason why [Rep. Chellie] Pingree never ran for governor,” said Mark Brewer, a political science professor at the University of Maine. “She recognizes it would be very difficult for someone that’s as far to the left as she is to win statewide in Maine. And when we look at the Democrats who do win statewide, they look like Janet Mills.”</p> 
<p>Some of Platner’s appeal may come less from his specific progressive stances than from his ability to capture the energy of Democratic voters upset about the state of the country — and at their own party for not doing enough to stand up to it. Trump’s second term led even people who were not previously politically active to show up for protests, with many aligned with Platner’s style of economic populism, said Andy O’Brien, a Maine writer and activist supporting Platner.</p> 
<p>“The Trump administration has just been so extreme that I think it’s really radicalized average, ‘normie’ voters,” O’Brien said.</p> 
<p>In an interview, Platner recalled going to a local Democratic party meeting in early 2025 and coming away frustrated that attendees were talking about bylaws, not Trump. In his view, there was pent up grassroots energy to fight the administration — shown, for example, by large No Kings protests in the state — but few organized outlets to turn it into action.</p> 
<p>His campaign proved one outlet for that energy. Following a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/ice-maine-dhs-trump-00740138" target="_blank">surge in ICE activity in Maine</a> in January, Platner led a protest at Collins’ offices in Portland and Bangor, calling on the senator to cut funding to the agency. Dozens of supporters showed up in single-degree temperatures.</p> 
<p>“I’m a supporter of Graham Platner because we need a U.S. senator to represent Maine who will be honest with us, who will be truthful with us, and will work for us,” said Laura Neal, a Bar Harbor resident who attended the protest with a sign reading “My Cat Hates ICE.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/bf/3a/dea2e17145c28bea7a142eda5aaa/img-6348-edit.jpg" alt="Laura Neal stands with her poster during during an anti-ICE protest outside Susan Collins' office in Bangor on Jan. 29." data-portal-copyright="Jessica Piper/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Laura Neal stands with her poster during during an anti-ICE protest outside Susan Collins' office in Bangor on Jan. 29."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/6b/7e/33dc86964a20bab47c46fa3f77d5/ice-in-maine-mills-platner20260129-0068-edit.jpg" alt="Platner speaks with attendees during the protest." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Ryan David Brown" data-title="Platner speaks with attendees during the protest."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/e8/75/d38460fe41dcb2ed9e6c0fee858a/ice-in-maine-mills-platner20260129-0050-edit.jpg" alt="Dozens of protesters showed up in single-degree temperatures, calling on Collins to cut funding to the agency." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Ryan David Brown" data-title="Dozens of protesters showed up in single-degree temperatures, calling on Collins to cut funding to the agency."/><p>Like many Platner backers, Neal doesn’t dislike Mills, but thinks it is time to move on. “I think Governor Mills has done a great job, and it’s time for new energy,” she said.</p> 
<p>In much of the national conversation about the Maine Senate race, Mills has been the less talked about candidate. It’s an odd position for a well-vetted two-term governor.</p> 
<p>Her diagnosis for why Maine Democrats have not been able to knock off Collins is straightforward: Past nominees have been “untested.” The GOP senator has never had to face a Democrat who has won statewide before. If Collins has won in part because of her deep history in the state, Mills matches her.</p> 
<p>“Each of us probably knows everybody in Maine, one way or other,” Mills said in an interview.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/2b/3c/dd1716024ba4a58304be5b7d7bc3/mills-platner-98-edit.jpg" alt="In much of the national conversation about the Maine Senate race, Mills has been the less talked about candidate." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Ryan David Brown" data-title="In much of the national conversation about the Maine Senate race, Mills has been the less talked about candidate."/><p>Mills started as district attorney in rural, more conservative western Maine before being elected to the state legislature, then served as attorney general for much of Republican Paul LePage’s tenure as governor, frequently clashing with him. In 2018, she became the first gubernatorial candidate in Maine in 20 years to win the general election with at least 50 percent of the vote, as well as the state’s first female governor. Four years later, when LePage attempted a comeback, she beat him by 13 percentage points.</p> 
<p>Governing with a Democratic trifecta, Mills expanded Medicaid and enacted a string of other priorities, including free community college, universal school meals and expanded abortion access following the <i>Dobbs</i> decision.</p> 
<p>Since Trump’s return to office, Mills has faced off with him several times. In a White House confrontation last year, the president threatened to withhold funding from Maine over the state’s continued allowance of transgender participation in youth sports, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/21/dem-governor-trump-court-022015" target="_blank">Mills fired back:</a> “See you in court.” The Trump administration paused certain agriculture department funding to Maine; the state sued and the money was restored.</p> 
<p>The episode provided a theme that underlies the governor’s Senate campaign: Collins has not stood up to the president, but Mills will. Her <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/#/viewer/e07b40b9-181e-4849-8463-bcfabdc250c1" target="_blank">latest TV ad</a> describes her as “the one who took on Donald Trump and won.”</p> 
<p>“Susan Collins is formidable,” said Trish Riley, a retired health policy expert who hosted Mills in her Brunswick home last month. “And the only person who can beat a formidable candidate is another formidable candidate, and that’s Janet.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/68/88/608ea7634ed8b4604bb050ebd039/ap051130020186-edit.jpg" alt="Mills, then a state representative, pores over documents with fellow lawmakers during a session at the State House in Augusta in 2005." data-portal-copyright="Pat Wellenbach/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Mills, then a state representative, pores over documents with fellow lawmakers during a session at the State House in Augusta in 2005."/><p>Mills’ tenure as governor has not been free from conflict with other Democrats. She at times disagreed with progressives in the legislature, issuing <a href="https://www.mainepublic.org/politics/2025-06-27/janet-mills-vetoes-laurel-libbys-voice-how-maine-lawmakers-wrapped-up-the-session" target="_blank">more than 50 vetoes</a>, with the most prominent conflicts around labor and tribal sovereignty. That created openings for Platner to hit her record from the left, and his prominent endorsers have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/15/congress/platner-endorsements-00609196" target="_blank">included several labor unions</a>.</p> 
<p>The bigger challenge for her in the primary may be the support from national Democrats like Schumer. Sara Gideon’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/11/04/maine-senate-election-results-2020-434000" target="_blank">2020 loss to Collins</a>, despite strong national Democratic support which helped her far outspend the Republican, led to a sense in the state that the national Democratic actors did not use money wisely and did not understand Maine. For some, that distrust has only compounded since Trump returned to office.</p> 
<p>“There’s a reaction among a lot of Democrats to what they see as the weakness of the establishment leaders in Washington,” said Amy Fried, a retired political science professor from the University of Maine and longtime Collins critic. “The fact that Chuck Schumer is the one who recruited Mills — maybe she would have run anyway, but he’s definitely associated with her. And then you have a lot of people who are on the Left who are really unhappy with what Democratic leadership has done when it comes to pushing back on Trump.”</p> 
<p>Mills maintains that she made no promises to Schumer, and the decision to run was hers. She bristles at the idea that she would be considered part of the political establishment.</p> 
<p>“I got elected to the legislature, not because somebody said, ‘You should be anointed to his job.’ I worked for it, I ran for it, and I won,” she said in an interview. “When I ran for district attorney, I defeated three guys for the primary, and then another guy for the general. Nobody ever gave it to me on a silver platter. Again, when I ran for governor: Seven-way primary. And I won. I’m used to that. Bring it on.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/fa/14/ad4c424349468663a3943596bfac/mills-platner-3-edit.jpg" alt="Mills arrives to a meeting with mayors from across Maine at City Hall in Portland on Jan. 28, to discuss the impact of ICE operations on local communities." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Ryan David Brown" data-title="Mills arrives to a meeting with mayors from across Maine at City Hall in Portland on Jan. 28, to discuss the impact of ICE operations on local communities."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/1e/eb/713a85654b6295bddc6478bbc41b/mills-platner-66-edit.jpg" alt="Mills started as district attorney in rural, more conservative western Maine before being elected to the state legislature, then served as attorney general." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Ryan David Brown" data-title="Mills started as district attorney in rural, more conservative western Maine before being elected to the state legislature, then served as attorney general."/><p>Republicans have been gleeful at the prospect of a grueling primary.</p> 
<p>“Maine Democrats are in a race of extreme vs more extreme — the only question is which of their candidates will run farther to the left to claim victory in this messy primary,” Republican National Committee spokesperson Kristen Cianci said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Whoever prevails in June will have to take on the electorally resilient Collins. If Democrats fail to knock off the GOP senator, there will be recriminations from whichever side loses the primary that their candidate would have been able to defeat her.</p> 
<p>Most supporters of Platner and Mills say they would back the eventual Democratic nominee regardless, with defeating Collins the most important priority. But a nasty primary could still risk alienating some voters, when every vote will count in November.</p> 
<p>“The differences are really pretty big between the two candidates, and I think it’s probably going to get strongly oppositional towards the end,” said Cote, the former gubernatorial candidate. “And how the victor is going to unite the party afterwards is going to be a huge challenge.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voters know what the next big issue is. They don’t know how they feel about it.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/22/poll-data-centers-politics-00791786</link>
      <description>Our new poll reveals the early contours of an evolving political battle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7ce5-de8a-a1fc-fde567d10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/png" url="https://static.politico.com/26/8f/b929c296472daae6ea35ad5d3da6/data-centers-politics.png">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Anna Wiederkehr/POLITICO (source images via Getty)</media:credit>
        <media:title>TPP: Data Center Politics</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/26/8f/b929c296472daae6ea35ad5d3da6/data-centers-politics.png" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Data centers are quickly becoming the next big political issue. And neither party has figured out how to run on them.</p> 
<p>Major political figures on both sides have struggled to figure out their positions, and in-depth <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-43e7-d3b5-addf-e3e7a2900000" target="_blank">results from The POLITICO Poll</a> help explain why: Americans don’t know much about data centers, they don’t really know how to feel about them and they’re not yet sure where the political battle lines lie.</p> 
<p>But they do know they matter. A bipartisan majority of Americans said they expect data centers to become a campaign issue in their area eventually, the poll found, with nearly half saying it would become one within the next five years.</p> 
<p>“If you had asked me about data centers five months ago, I would have said: ‘What’s a data center?’” Republican Oklahoma City Mayor David Holt said in an interview. “Now it’s everywhere. So that’s a short amount of time to fully formulate what you think about it.”</p> 
<p>The survey reveals the early contours of an evolving political battle — and the opportunity and risk for politicians hoping to seize on the nascent power of an issue that touches on AI and tech, infrastructure and development, environmental resources, jobs and energy costs.<br></p><p>Republicans appear to have an early edge on the issue, though public opinion is so largely unformed that it’s unclear how that may change.</p> 
<p>Pluralities — but not majorities — of voters in both parties said they support the construction of data centers, with Americans who say they plan to vote for the GOP in November about 8 points more likely than Democratic voters, according to the survey conducted by independent London-based firm Public First.<br></p><p>Republicans’ appetite for data centers may be driven in part by President Donald Trump, who has been bullish on artificial intelligence and data center expansion and who has been combative against <a href="https://www.eenews.net/articles/trump-goes-to-war-with-states-over-ai/" target="_blank">both blue and red states aiming to restrict that growth</a>. He <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115884759090137876" target="_blank">wrote on social media</a> last month that “Data Centers are key” to ensuring that the U.S. dominates on AI.</p> 
<p>His position is most clearly reflected among his strongest supporters. Asked at the start of the poll for their position, before additional information had been provided, a 55 percent majority of voters who both backed Trump in 2024 and self-identified as “MAGA Republicans” said they support a new data center being built in their local area.</p> 
<p>Support was markedly lower among Trump voters who did not consider themselves MAGA Republicans, at 38 percent, and Kamala Harris voters, at 36 percent.</p> 
<p>Democrats expressed worry about the water supply and electricity bills — concerns that have already emerged in recent elections.</p> 
<p>With public opinion on data centers still fluid, candidates are beginning to experiment with whether — and how — to embrace data centers as a campaign issue.</p> 
<p>Democrats saw early success in highlighting backlash to data centers in the off-year elections, when Mikie Sherrill in New Jersey and Abigail Spanberger in Virginia won their gubernatorial elections by wide margins with pledges to better regulate data centers and their energy consumption. In Georgia, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/democrats-show-early-signs-of-winning-energy-messaging-war-00638942" target="_blank">Democrats beat two Republican incumbent</a> state regulators in part by supporting guardrails around data center growth.</p> 
<p>The issue has only spiraled since. It has fueled intraparty rifts, with <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/democrats-reject-bernie-sanders-data-center-pause-00713664" target="_blank">progressives splitting over whether to temporarily ban new warehouse construction</a> and Republicans who want more guardrails for artificial intelligence <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/14/data-center-boom-creates-political-conundrum-gop-00680635" target="_blank">diverging from a president who’s trying to cut red tape</a>.</p> 
<p>It has also created unusual crossover: Governors in both parties are racing to regulate the booming industry, where regulation has often lagged growth. Conservative Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis rolled <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/we-have-a-right-to-do-this-desantis-wants-florida-to-move-ahead-with-ai-policies-00690680" target="_blank">out a “bill of rights”</a> to protect consumers and residents last year, and moderate Democratic Gov. Josh Shapiro of Pennsylvania <a href="https://www.eenews.net/articles/josh-shapiro-proposes-guardrails-for-ai-data-center-boom-in-pennsylvania/" target="_blank">proposed new safeguards</a> for ratepayers and resources earlier this month.</p> 
<p>The POLITICO Poll found that voters’ top concerns about data centers center around household costs. Asked about the drawbacks to building data centers in the U.S., 29 percent of Americans said it would mean higher electricity bills, 24 percent said an increased risk of blackouts and 23 percent said the projects would cost the taxpayer money.<br></p><p>Data centers are now rocketing to the forefront of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/michigan-senate-mcmorrow-stevens-el-sayed-00758408" target="_blank">Democrats’ messy Senate primary in Michigan</a>. The race in a perennial battleground with some <a href="https://www.datacentermap.com/usa/michigan/" target="_blank">70 data centers</a> will serve as a key test of their potency in swing states heading into 2028.</p> 
<p>Progressive candidate Abdul El-Sayed, in an interview, said voters’ perspectives are “very quickly evolving” and that “it’s unsurprising” that Democratic voters are more skeptical of them — which gives the party an “opportunity to lead” on the issue.</p> 
<p>He has emerged as the most vocal critic of data centers in the three-way race, <a href="https://abdulforsenate.com/2026/01/datacenters/" target="_blank">outlining “terms of engagement” last month</a> that would prevent tech companies from passing energy costs on to ratepayers and protect water resources and jobs.</p> 
<p>State Sen. Mallory McMorrow, who is straddling the line between moderate and progressive, has taken a more measured tone. In public appearances and in statements, <a href="https://x.com/MalloryMcMorrow/status/2018464547376668933" target="_blank">McMorrow has said</a> she opposes any project that “raises residential [electricity] rates, hurts our water, does not use union labor and doesn’t actually create revenue for the state” but also that “done right, data centers are a transformational opportunity.”</p> 
<p>And centrist Democratic Rep. Haley Stevens said “AI and data infrastructure require a clear, responsible policy framework to ensure these technologies are developed safely and securely,” in a statement. She said AI policy should boost productivity and user experience, while protecting taxpayers, strengthening the workforce, and safeguarding “good-paying union jobs.”</p> 
<p>Democratic candidates who find themselves out of step with their voters on data centers could pay a real electoral price, The POLITICO Poll found.</p> 
<p>Just 7 percent of Democrats said they would be less likely to support a Democratic candidate who opposes a data center — but 20 percent said they would be less likely to back one who supports it.</p> 
<p>Divisions over data centers are emerging within the GOP as well, with some Republicans breaking from Trump — a sign of the issue’s rapidly evolving political terrain.</p> 
<p>DeSantis, for instance, has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/27/we-have-to-reject-that-with-every-fiber-of-our-being-desantis-emerges-as-a-chief-ai-skeptic-00704333" target="_blank">become a vocal data center critic</a>, while lawmakers from states experiencing a rise of data centers are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/14/data-center-boom-creates-political-conundrum-gop-00680635" target="_blank">walking a more delicate line</a>, supportive of AI development, but insistent that the states should be the ones regulating data center construction. Most Republicans, however, remain aligned with Trump, bullish on AI development and seeing it as crucial to competing with China.</p> 
<p>Party operatives say data centers could quickly climb up voters’ list of concerns as more of them are proposed and built, but that they’re not yet a dominant electoral issue.</p> 
<p>Americans agree.</p> 
<p>Right now, the construction of data centers ranked last when survey respondents were asked to rank up to three of the top issues facing the U.S. at the moment. But nearly a third of respondents — 30 percent — living within a mile of data centers say the issue will play a role in the November elections, a significantly higher share than the 17 percent who say the same among Americans overall.</p> 
<p>“The only people that are particularly exercised are the ones that are navigating [data centers] in their communities,” said Michigan-based GOP strategist Jason Roe. “I don't think it's yet broadly an issue that people have wrapped their heads around enough to have an opinion.”</p> 
<p>Still, most voters expect the issue to rise, though they’re split on when that will happen. Just one in four Americans said they “don’t think data centers will ever play a role in elections in my area.”</p> 
<p>“This is a political bomb waiting to go off,” said Jared Leopold, a Democratic strategist and co-founder of the clean-energy group Evergreen Action. “You’ve seen data centers go from a third-tier issue to a top-tier issue in politics in the span of a year. … And there are some people who are going to have success riding that wave politically.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans quietly celebrate the demise of tariffs. That relief might not last.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/tariffs-trump-gop-midterms-00791591</link>
      <description>Many in the GOP, especially those in battleground states, are happy to see the blanket tariffs go in a heated election year. Trump has already pledged to bring them back.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7caa-d3b5-addf-fcee977f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 17:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/93/17/609673484812a9817d4c1453e4d6/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2166486293">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>A farmer uses a barn to show support for President Donald Trump in August 2024 near Charles City, Iowa.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/93/17/609673484812a9817d4c1453e4d6/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2166486293" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republicans quietly breathed a collective sigh of relief when the Supreme Court struck down President Donald Trump’s sweeping tariffs on Friday — but that feeling may prove fleeting.</p> 
<p>The court's decision to upend Trump’s global tariffs comes as affordability concerns and the cost of living continue to galvanize voters ahead of the midterms. Many free trade-friendly Republicans spent the past year worrying that the tariffs would drive prices higher, destabilize the economy and hurt their hopes of hanging onto control of Congress this November.</p> 
<p>“It's very possible that the Supreme Court just threw Trump's economy a life preserver, and the president is refusing it and demanding an anchor. These tariffs economically have not played well into the affordability narrative,” said Matthew Bartlett, a Republican strategist and former Trump State Department official. “It just has not been helpful — full stop.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s hard line on tariffs has proven particularly difficult for some GOP candidates to navigate in battleground states where manufacturing and agricultural industries have been hit the hardest by the trade measures. Several of Trump’s allies in farm country and Republicans encouraged him to pump the brakes Friday and reassess his path forward.</p> 
<p>But the president’s announcement of a 10 percent global tariff immediately after the ruling had them back on their guard.</p> 
<p>“We have very powerful alternatives,” Trump said in a press conference Friday afternoon, announcing he will sign the new tariff under Section 122 of the Trade Act of 1974 – and rejecting the possibility of legislating a new measure through Congress. "I don't need to,” he said. “It's already been approved."</p> 
<p>Only minutes earlier, Speaker Mike Johnson (R-La.) had suggested in <a href="https://x.com/SpeakerJohnson/status/2024892242930884617?s=20" target="_blank">a post on X that</a>Congress would work with the administration to find “the best path forward.”</p> 
<p>Polling shows that Trump’s tariffs are broadly unpopular. A 45 percent plurality of Americans said in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/poll-affordability-cost-of-living-00678076?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nrid=0000014e-f100-dd93-ad7f-f905199c0001" target="_blank">a November POLITICO Poll</a> that higher tariffs are damaging the U.S. economy — in both the short and long term. That view falls along partisan lines, with Democrats far more likely to say the levies are damaging the U.S. economy.</p> 
<p>Still, roughly a quarter of Trump’s own 2024 voters agree. Among Republicans who do not identify as “MAGA” — a much more malleable group of voters — opposition to the levies rose. Thirty-two percent of non-MAGA Republicans said the higher tariffs are damaging the economy in both the short and the long term, compared with just 21 percent of self-identifying MAGA Republicans.</p> 
<p>Despite Americans’ overall disapproval of the White House’s tariff agenda, Trump remains bullish on his approach.</p> 
<p>“Without tariffs, this country would be in such trouble right now,” he said in a Thursday speech before a crowd gathered at a factory in northwest Georgia. “I’ve won affordability,” he added.</p> 
<p>But the uncertainty around what comes next on tariffs has some Republicans questioning why the administration didn’t go through Congress from the start, instead choosing a legally riskier route that has left at least a temporary vacuum at the heart of their economic agenda in an election year.</p> 
<p>“Why must we fuck ourselves?” rhetorically asked one GOP official, who, like others in this article, was granted anonymity to speak openly about their concerns with the White House’s economic agenda. “He should’ve gotten congressional approval. Now it’s destabilized the economy.”</p> 
<p>Before the ruling, while Congressional Republicans had occasionally grumbled about the policy, they had largely fallen in line when actually required to vote on it. Now, the Supreme Court’s decision could put more pressure on them to break with the president.</p> 
<p>“You have so much overlap between people who support the president, and people who are hurt worst by the tariffs themselves,” said one longtime GOP strategist in Iowa. “That’s why the criticism has always been somewhat muted.”</p> 
<p>Democratic candidates are quickly taking advantage of that. DCCC spokesperson Courtney Rice said the decision “makes crystal clear the need for Congress to exercise its constitutional authority over trade policy.”</p> 
<p>Abdul El-Sayed, a Democrat running for Senate in Michigan, said “the damage has already been done” by the tariffs. And Rep. Chris Pappas (D-N.H.), running for Senate, released a statement saying his opponents “are running to push Donald Trump’s agenda,” whereas he will work to “rectify the damage that Trump’s tariffs have caused our state.”</p> 
<p>Even historically protectionist-leaning Democrats took shots at Trump. Former Sen. Sherrod Brown (D-Ohio) said in the ruling’s wake that his opponent, Sen. John Husted (R-Ohio), was “once again doubling down on his support for reckless tariffs that are raising costs and sending Ohio farmers into bankruptcy.” (Husted, for his part, <a href="https://x.com/senjonhusted/status/2024903425389924424?s=46" target="_blank">said in a statement</a> that he respects the court’s decision.)</p> 
<p>"Not only do voters hate these tariffs because they've raised costs, but now the Supreme Court has said they're illegal,” said Democratic strategist Jesse Ferguson. “Every Republican in 2026 has a Scarlett ‘T’ on their chest."</p> 
<p>Some Republicans had already publicly questioned the president’s authority to unilaterally impose blanket duties on trading partners without seeking approval from Congress. For them, the ruling proved a win on constitutional grounds.</p> 
<p>“I feel vindicated as I’ve been saying this for the last 12 months,” said Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) <a href="https://x.com/RepDonBacon/status/2024876064216866992?s=20" target="_blank">on X</a>, one of the few House Republicans who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/house-tariff-votes-republicans-affordability-00777567" target="_blank">repeatedly opposed Trump’s tariffs</a>. “In the future, Congress should defend its own authorities and not rely on the Supreme Court.”</p> 
<p>Six House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/house-tariff-votes-republicans-affordability-00777567" target="_blank">voted alongside Democrats last week to condemn</a> Trump’s tariffs on Canada, sending the measure to the Senate, which has already seen <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/senate-republicans-buck-trump-join-dems-in-rejecting-canada-tariffs-00267480" target="_blank">significant GOP defection in other votes</a> on the duty measures. Senior House Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/house-tariff-votes-republicans-affordability-00777567" target="_blank">have vowed to bring up at least three more similar resolutions</a> that will force GOP members to choose between their adherence to free trade principles and their MAGA base.</p> 
<p>“There are a lot of members of Congress excited to see that the tariffs are temporarily not in effect. It has been a pinch at home and it’s been hard to message around,” added one Republican strategist involved with House races. “It gives them some breathing room. It gives them a little bit more leeway in that affordability message.”</p> 
<p>In agriculture-heavy states, the tariffs have been felt acutely in recent months. The Trump administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/white-house-to-announce-farmer-bailout-package-00680633" target="_blank">approved a $12 billion bailout</a> for farmers in December and Hill Republicans are <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2025/12/12/congress-eyes-another-farm-bailout-in-january-ee-00688241" target="_blank">considering a second tranche</a>, though that has yet to pass.</p> 
<p>American Farm Bureau President Zippy Duvall — a frequent ally of Trump’s — released a statement Friday afternoon urging Trump to pump the brakes.</p> 
<p>“With supply costs already at or near record highs, we strongly encourage the president to avoid using any other available authorities to impose tariffs on agricultural inputs that would further increase costs,” Duvall said. “America’s farmers and ranchers need stability to ensure families across America can put food on their tables.”</p> 
<p>It’s a long time until November’s midterms. But in battleground races where tariffs pinched the most, the recent memory of trade adventurism and the ongoing dissatisfaction with the current state of the economy could prove fatal for Republicans, said Wisconsin-based GOP strategist Craig Peterson.</p> 
<p>“In this last year with all the tariffs and increased costs, it's going to take a little while for folks to forget about that,” Peterson said, noting Election Day is less than nine months away. “That's not real long, unfortunately, for the Republicans.”</p> 
<p><i>Erin Doherty, Elena Schneider, Lisa Kashinsky and Adam Wren contributed reporting.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top German soccer team cancels trip to Minneapolis, citing Trump immigration crackdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/werder-bremen-cancel-minneapolis-trip-00790720</link>
      <description>Werder Bremen, one of the founding members of the Bundesliga, said playing in the city “does not fit with our values” in light of two federal law enforcement shootings last month.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7b8e-d647-addc-fbcf61820000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 10:44:12 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/08/f8/481335204104be284a828e1aadca/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2232868200">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Christof Koepsel/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Karim Coulibaly of Werder Bremen celebrates with his teammates after scoring his team's third goal during the Bundesliga match between SV Werder Bremen and Bayer 04 Leverkusen at Weserstadion on Aug. 30, 2025, in Bremen, Germany.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/08/f8/481335204104be284a828e1aadca/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2232868200" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Werder Bremen, a top German soccer team, is canceling its planned trip to Minnesota this summer, after violence and political chaos engulfed Minneapolis amid the Trump administration’s major immigration enforcement push in January.</p> 
<p>“Playing in a city where there’s unrest and people have been shot, that does not fit with our values here at Werder Bremen,” Christoph Pieper, the club’s head of communications, said in a statement. “Furthermore, it was unclear for us which players could be able to enter the United States due to the stricter entry requirements.”</p> 
<p>The administration sent roughly 3,000 federal immigration agents to Minneapolis beginning in December, in a deportation effort <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook-pm/2026/02/12/minnesota-picks-up-the-pieces-after-enforcement-surge-00778461" target="_blank">dubbed Operation Metro Surge</a>. Agents killed two protesters, Renee Good and Alex Pretti, in separate incidents last month as demonstrations spread throughout the city.</p> 
<p>And while White House border czar Tom Homan <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/homan-announces-end-to-minnesota-immigration-enforcement-surge-00777990" target="_blank">announced the White House was ending its surge in Minnesota</a> last week, Werder Bremen’s cancellation is far from the only economic fallout of the surge. Minneapolis city leaders <a href="https://www.minneapolismn.gov/news/2026/february/oms-impact/" target="_blank">announced last Friday that</a> the operation had resulted in a more than $200 million financial impact.</p> 
<p>Werder Bremen, one of the founding members of the Bundesliga <a href="https://www.bremen.eu/life-in-bremen/sport/werder-bremen" target="_blank">and a winner of four German championships</a>, has a reputation as one of the most progressive clubs in Europe. The <a href="https://x.com/werderbremen_en/status/1858602586812936364" target="_blank">club left X for Bluesky in 2024</a> due to "hate speech, hatred towards minorities, right-wing extremist posts and conspiracy theories" that had "been allowed to spread on X at an incredible pace," it said in a statement at the time.</p> 
<p>“We as a club, we have clear values,“ Pieper said Friday. “Our club stands for an open, pluralistic and united society. We are committed to ensuring that all people — regardless of their origin, skin colour, religion, sexual orientation, gender identity, age or disability — are naturally included and have a firm place in our community.”</p> 
<p>The global soccer community has largely been kind to President Donald Trump since his return to the White House last year. The U.S. — alongside Canada and Mexico — is playing host to the quadrennial FIFA World Cup this summer. FIFA President <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/05/the-world-games-washington-problem-00677204" target="_blank">Gianni Infantino has worked to court Trump’s favor</a>, presenting him with a <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/fifa-trump-peace-prize-football-chief-launches-new-award-ahead-world-cup/" target="_blank">new FIFA Peace Prize in December</a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-gets-his-board-of-peace-even-as-bigger-countries-steer-clear-00789617" target="_blank">pledging millions for the White House’s Board of Peace initiative</a> this week.</p> 
<p>Werder Bremen is in the midst of a difficult season in the Bundesliga, languishing in 16th place in the league table with just four wins in the first 22 games of this year’s campaign. But just last year, the team finished in the league’s top 10 — with a 51-point effort keyed by 10 goals from Danish striker Jens Stage.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists on the week in politics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2026/02/20/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00790190</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's an offering of the best of this week's crop, picked fresh off the Toonosphere. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7869-d3b5-addf-f8ed62d70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy and CNN’s Clarissa Ward on the state of the war | The Conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/19/ukrainian-president-volodymyr-zelenskyy-and-cnns-clarissa-ward-on-the-state-of-the-war-in-ukraine-the-conversation-1925912</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-77e3-d3b5-addf-f7e7eee40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 23:59:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy and CNN’s Clarissa Ward on the state of the war | The Conversation</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6389588695112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/070a3ee6-2f52-4d31-aabf-6ae4ea41dba8/1d62c3a1-2bae-483b-9229-1ab5af73091d/main.mp4" src="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/070a3ee6-2f52-4d31-aabf-6ae4ea41dba8/36788966-f01b-4f3a-a462-afeab5debb62/1280x720/match/image.jpg">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-19T17:45:58-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Bowser requests Trump’s help on Potomac sewage spill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/bowser-requests-trumps-help-on-potomac-sewage-spill-00788896</link>
      <description>The request from D.C. Mayor Muriel Bowser comes days after the president blamed the spill on Democrats and said local officials should call and ask for help “politely.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-775c-d0f8-adde-ff5e23f20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c1/ac/e7db13044d7db4014ff2631c409f/potomac-river-sewage-24511.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Cliff Owen/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A warning sign is seen at the sight of a massive pipe rupture, as sewage flows into the Potomac River in Glen Echo, Maryland, on Jan. 23.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c1/ac/e7db13044d7db4014ff2631c409f/potomac-river-sewage-24511.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Miranda Willson and Thomas Frank</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Miranda Willson and Thomas Frank</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Washington, D.C., Mayor Muriel Bowser on Wednesday accepted President Donald Trump’s offer to help fix the massive sewage spill outside the city, making an unusual request for Trump to declare the area a disaster and pay for repairs.</p> 
<p>Bowser’s request came days after Trump tried to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-fixates-on-sewage-a-favored-talking-point-in-fight-with-wes-moore-00786490?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=bluesky" target="_blank">blame the spill</a> on her and other Democrats and said that if they want federal help “they have to call me and ask, politely.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://mayor.dc.gov/sites/default/files/dc/sites/mayormb/page_content/attachments/DC%20Request%20for%20Presidential%20Emergency%20Disaster%20Decleration%202.18.26.pdf" target="_blank">Bowser signed her letter</a> “Respectfully” in asking for the Federal Emergency Management Agency to offset all "costs incurred" by the city and regional sewer authorities following the Jan. 19 collapse of a sewer line in Montgomery County, Maryland. FEMA usually pays 75 percent of disaster repairs unless damage is extreme.</p> 
<p>Bowser told reporters Thursday that she made the request now because Trump expressed interest in helping and to minimize costs to D.C. residents. In addition to seeking assistance, the three-term mayor — who is not seeking reelection — <a href="https://mayor.dc.gov/sites/default/files/dc/sites/mayormb/page_content/attachments/Mayor%27s%20Order%202026-028%20Declaration%20of%20Public%20Emergency%20%E2%80%93%20Potomac%20Interceptor%20Collapse%20and%20Impacts.pdf" target="_blank">declared a local public emergency</a> and asked the federal government to support several other water quality and flood protection projects in the city.</p> 
<p>“I have had outreach from the president's team,” Bowser said during a press conference. “That would indicate to me that they're supportive of the request."</p> 
<p>No president has approved a disaster declaration for a sewage spill, according to an analysis by POLITICO's E&amp;E News of FEMA records dating to 1953.</p> 
<p>President Barack Obama approved <a href="https://www.fema.gov/disaster/3375" target="_blank">an emergency declaration</a> in 2016 for water contamination in Flint, Michigan, that began in 2014. FEMA provides limited aid for emergencies.</p> 
<p>But presidents have authority to approve disasters for a wide range of events. In his first term, Trump approved disaster requests for every state to cover their costs of handling the Covid-19 pandemic. FEMA has given states roughly $140 billion for pandemic costs.</p> 
<p>Bowser’s letter contains no cost estimates — which governors routinely include in their multipage disaster requests — and acknowledges aid would help residents outside her jurisdiction, in Maryland and Virginia.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/COMPS-2977/pdf/COMPS-2977.pdf" target="_blank">Federal law says</a> that disaster requests “shall be made by the Governor of the affected State” — or by a government leader such as a tribal chief, territorial governor or the mayor of Washington, and that a disaster request must be based on a finding that a jurisdiction cannot handle an event by itself. Bowser’s letter to Trump makes no such claim.</p> 
<p>Neither Govs. Wes Moore of Maryland nor Abigail Spanberger of Virginia, both Democrats, have requested disaster aid from Trump. DC Water, the sewer authority, operates the sewer line that extends from as far as Dulles International Airport to a treatment plant in the city and did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>“Maryland will not be seeking an emergency declaration because the responsibility for the repair and subsequent clean up does not fall to Maryland,” said Rhylan Lake, a spokesperson for Moore, in an email. “Since Maryland owns neither the infrastructure nor the land, Maryland does not anticipate needing supplemental resources at this time.”</p> 
<p>Neither the White House nor FEMA responded to questions Thursday about whether they planned to grant D.C.'s assistance request.</p> 
<p>Considered the largest raw sewage spill of its kind in U.S. history, the broken sewer line has released over 250 million gallons of raw sewage in the Potomac River. Environmentalists have been raising concerns for weeks about the spill, which could render the river unsafe for fishing and boating and undermine longstanding efforts to repair the Chesapeake Bay.</p> 
<p>Local environmentalists said they would welcome federal funding to help with the cleanup, but that the priority should be to increase water quality monitoring and better notify the public about whether it’s safe to use the river. </p> 
<p>“Going directly from zero comments on it to an emergency declaration after the fact seems like an unusual pathway,” said Betsy Nicholas, president of Potomac Riverkeeper Network. “We haven’t heard anything from the mayor or the mayor’s office on this for an entire month, which in and of itself was a little surprising and frustrating.”</p> 
<p>Representatives for the utility have previously noted that they are working to accelerate a previously planned rehabilitation project to fix the sewer line. The line dates to the early 1960s. </p> 
<p>Trump administration officials and local authorities have traded jabs in recent days over who is responsible for the spill, with the exact cause still undetermined. </p> 
<p>Trump has primarily cast blame on Moore, with the White House describing the state as responsible for protecting water quality in the Potomac. But both Moore’s office and Bowser say that EPA is the primary regulator of DC Water.</p> 
<p>A FEMA report Thursday morning says DC Water “is engaged with” EPA, FEMA, environmental agencies in the District, Maryland and Virginia, and the National Park Service, which owns the wooded parkland where the spill occurred next to the Potomac.</p> 
<p>“Since the incident was first reported, DC Water has provided daily updates,” <a href="https://content.govdelivery.com/attachments/USDHSFEMA/2026/02/19/file_attachments/3558713/FEMA%20Daily%20Ops%20Briefing%2002-19-2026.pdf" target="_blank">the FEMA report says.</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ohio’s GOP governor sidesteps defending Kristi Noem</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/ohio-mike-dewine-sidesteps-defending-kristi-noem-00788704</link>
      <description>Mike DeWine did, however, say he supported billionaire Les Wexner despite his ties to disgraced financier Jeffrey Epstein.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-76d6-d0f8-adde-fedeb8250000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 12:04:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content medium="video" type="video/mp4" url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/1f87e96f-2dff-4547-bb2d-7cb6eeb0f05f/ed2ff5ca-238a-4c9e-b96c-810e38f652bf/main.mp4">
        <media:description>Gov. DeWine: 'No indication ICE is coming in'</media:description>
        <media:title>Gov. DeWine: 'No indication ICE is coming in'</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/1f87e96f-2dff-4547-bb2d-7cb6eeb0f05f/737d3ee0-5774-4048-9636-1104c7dc9cb7/1280x720/match/image.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Adam Wren</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Adam Wren</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ohio Gov. Mike DeWine would not immediately endorse his fellow Buckeye, Vice President JD Vance, for his party’s 2028 presidential nomination and would not express confidence in Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem amid reports that ICE could target Springfield.</p> 
<p>Asked whether Vance should be the Republican party’s nominee, DeWine said Thursday that “he’s a favorite son of ours, and we’ll see how this whole thing plays out.”</p> 
<p>At POLITICO’s 2026 Governors Summit, the Ohio Republican said he has not heard further news following reports that Springfield could face <a href="https://signalohio.org/springfield-ohio-prepares-for-an-ice-immigration-raid-it-cant-confirm-you-become-powerless-in-a-situation-like-this" target="_blank">an ICE crackdown on its</a> large population of Haitian immigrants: “We've not been told at all if they're going to come in.” And while DeWine said that state and local law enforcement would work to keep the peace if there was a crackdown, he warned that federal officers also need to perform professionally.</p> 
<p>“Frankly, we expect ICE, if they come in, to follow good police protocols. If they do that, we’re going to be able to work our way through it,” he said.</p> 
<p>DeWine sidestepped multiple opportunities to express confidence in Noem’s handling of DHS’ stepped up interior enforcement.</p> 
<p>“Look, I think that what happened in Minnesota was a signal to a lot of people — they didn’t like what they saw,” DeWine said when asked about Noem.</p> 
<p>DeWine did <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/les-wexner-jeffrey-epstein-files-00786674" target="_blank">defend Les Wexner</a>, the billionaire businessman and former client of Jeffrey Epstein whose name is blazoned across many central Ohio institutions, including the The Ohio State Wexner Medical Center. DeWine said Thursday that no evidence has emerged of his wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>“Barring some new information of something that he has done illegal, I don’t see that as a problem,” said DeWine.</p> 
<p>The governor, who has frequently tangled with Trump and Vance — including over their baseless attacks of Haitian immigrants eating pets in Springfield — would not say whether the president has been a “force for good” for the GOP and country.</p> 
<p>Instead, he praised Trump’s actions on border enforcement.</p> 
<p>“He has done something that has not been done before, and that is he has basically sealed the southern border,” DeWine said. “And you can talk to Democrats, talk to Republicans. I think everybody is happy about that.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Pay for your own power’: Shapiro digs in on data center energy costs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/shapiro-tests-democrats-data-center-strategy-00767682</link>
      <description>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro knows how to make data center-friendly policies. He's still trying to make them good politics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7387-d0f8-adde-fbdf2deb0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/64/7f/56a9cb024588b66412ac38821ad7/gov1.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Pennsylvania Senate Democratic Caucus</media:credit>
        <media:title>Gov. Josh Shapiro shakes hands with state Sen. Steve Santarsiero in Falls Township, Pennsylvania, to tout Amazon's new high-tech data center.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/64/7f/56a9cb024588b66412ac38821ad7/gov1.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Peter Behr, Christa Marshall and Joel Kirkland</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Peter Behr, Christa Marshall and Joel Kirkland</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>PHILADELPHIA — Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro, a bellwether Democrat on AI and data centers, is tempering his message ahead of his reelection campaign.</p> 
<p>Shapiro, a swing-state Democrat and a 2028 presidential prospect, has staked his state’s economic fortunes on the tech industry. He wooed a $20 billion investment from Amazon along with major investments by Microsoft and Google. Shapiro has backed President Donald Trump’s call for more nuclear and natural gas plants to power new tech hubs.</p> 
<p>He's now trying to hedge his bet as data centers absorb a nationwide backlash from voters increasingly concerned about their impact on electricity bills.</p> 
<p>“Pay for your own power, so it's not saddling local businesses or homeowners with higher costs,” Shapiro said in an interview with POLITICO earlier this month from a union hall in Philadelphia.</p> 
<p>It’s an unmistakable pivot by a leading practitioner of data center politics who along with other Democratic governors has been trying to bring under control rising electricity prices that could be political kryptonite for both parties. Household electricity bills are rising at <a href="https://www.bls.gov/news.release/cpi.nr0.htm" target="_blank">twice the rate of inflation</a>. In recent weeks, Shapiro has joined Arizona Gov. Katie Hobbs, New York Gov. Kathy Hochul and other Democrats who are sharpening their tone and putting new policies in place to try to claw back taxpayer expenses, increase pressure on utility companies and address local backlash against development.</p> 
<p>“Too many of these projects have been shrouded in secrecy, with local communities left in the dark about who is coming in and what they’re building,” Shapiro said in his annual address to the Pennsylvania General Assembly earlier this month.</p> 
<p>Shapiro, who is riding high in the polls as he launches his reelection campaign, is pitching the AI and data center boom as a source of union jobs during the yearslong construction phase — but also trying to manage the boom's potential to alienate other voters.</p> 
<p>Christopher Borick, a political science professor at Muhlenberg College in Allentown, said Shapiro’s “get stuff done” political brand runs into trouble if voters tie energy affordability concerns to data center projects.</p> 
<p>“People have started to connect the demand for AI and data centers to pricing,” he said.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/05/07/b3237ce4409da660c685961b2367/gutman-amazondatacenter-45.jpg" alt="Construction of the future Amazon data center site in Fairless Hills, Pennsylvania, on Dec. 17, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Caroline Gutman for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Caroline Gutman" data-title="Construction of the future Amazon data center site in Fairless Hills, Pennsylvania, on Dec. 17, 2025."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Jobs and energy</h4> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium"></h5> 
<p>Few Democrats have anticipated the data center zeitgeist as deftly as Shapiro. Shortly after taking office in 2023, he ordered an analysis of where the state and U.S. economies were headed. AI jumped out as a key opportunity, a top adviser said.</p> 
<p>“Not just because we thought it was cool, but because we have strengths,” said Rick Siger, a former Obama staffer who serves as Shapiro’s secretary of community and economic development.</p> 
<p>Carnegie Mellon University, a top engineering and technology school, was a selling point. So was the state’s manufacturing base, which makes hardware for data centers and boasts tech companies that will deploy advanced AI. Shapiro’s team fixated on what major developers were after. “Speed matters, in particular to companies that are competing in AI,” Siger said.</p> 
<p>In June 2025, Shapiro announced Amazon's $20 billion investment in two data center complexes: one in the Philadelphia suburbs of Bucks County and another south of Wilkes-Barre.</p> 
<p>“The employees will be making, in some cases, double the average wage in that county,” Siger said, “to work in a high-tech job and be able to stay home and raise their kids in their hometown.” The data center piece of the AI juggernaut also works well for Shapiro's union-heavy constituency. He toured Steamfitters Local Union 420’s training center in Philadelphia earlier this month, which is training apprentices to install cooling systems for the computer chips packed in wall-to-wall racks inside the cluster of AI factories being developed in Bucks County.</p> 
<p>Rory Carroll, a 42-year-old steamfitter who was among the trainees greeting Shapiro, said he’s “tried everything” to make a living. “I sold cars, delivered pizza, managed a supermarket.” Now, he says he’s on a rising tide.</p> 
<p>Local officials in Bucks County — which Trump flipped red in 2024, for the first time since 1988 — are wary but welcoming.</p> 
<p>“Do I think the trend of technology replacing jobs will continue with the data centers? Of course I do,” said Erin Mullen, vice chair of the Falls Township Board of Supervisors. But she said the temporary construction jobs were worth pursuing. “This is a blue-collar township,” Mullen said. “So even though the jobs are temporary, a lot of families here survive on temporary jobs, and this is huge for the trades.”</p> 
<p>Data centers' demand for energy also works for Shapiro, who's been touting the state's large natural gas reserves in talks with tech companies. Last summer, he joined Trump and the state’s Republican senator, Dave McCormick, in Pittsburgh to announce multibillion-dollar commitments for restarting aging hydropower and expanding electricity generation from nuclear and natural gas.</p> 
<p>Now, after cuts to federal renewable energy tax credits, he's still touting Pennsylvania energy — with a partisan edge.</p> 
<p>"I'm an 'all-of-the-above' energy governor," Shapiro said in the POLITICO interview. "Unfortunately, the president of the United States has cut hundreds of millions of dollars from clean energy development in this commonwealth, which has cost us 26,000 union trade jobs who were set to work on these projects."</p> 
<p>“I don't think it's an either-or — it's a both-and," he continued. "We need to generate more power. Yes, it will rely in part on Pennsylvania natural gas. We also need to generate more power with renewables."</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Power politics</h4> 
<p>Shapiro's call for data center developers to pay for electricity infrastructure that could drive up utility bills echoes the Trump administration's <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/09/trump-administration-eyes-data-center-agreements-amid-energy-price-spikes-00772024" target="_blank">recent rhetoric</a> exhorting them to "pick up the tab" — but Shapiro’s focus on power bills was a long time coming.</p> 
<p>In July 2024, as Shapiro was chasing Amazon, mid-Atlantic ratepayers were hit with a $14.7 billion, one-year charge from PJM Interconnection, the region's electricity grid manager. The double-digit cost increases in utility bills came as a result of projections that electricity supplies could fall short of demand across the 13-state region stretching from northern Virginia to Chicago.</p> 
<p>Shapiro demanded a price cap in December 2024 on the fastest-rising part of PJM customers’ electricity bills — a headline-grabbing event in Pennsylvania. And he’s threatened to pull Pennsylvania out of the PJM market all together, a major uprooting of the way power is delivered in the region. He’s attacked PJM for its byzantine utility-heavy leadership structure that leads to a sclerotic response to rising power prices.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/22/94/fe042a8c43f3a4ceba9879c879ae/secondary7.jpg" alt="Top: Construction of the future Amazon data center site, in Fairless Hills. Bottom: An industrial facility near the same site, in Morrisville." data-portal-copyright="Caroline Gutman for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Top: Construction of the future Amazon data center site, in Fairless Hills. Bottom: An industrial facility near the same site, in Morrisville."/><p>According to federal data, <a href="https://www.eia.gov/electricity/monthly/update/end-use.php#:~:text=Total%20average%20revenues%20per%20kilowatt,with%20three%20sectors%20seeing%20increases." target="_blank">electricity prices in Pennsylvania</a> rose roughly 20 percent between November 2024 and November 2025 — the highest rate in the country. And PJM has warned that states could face power shortages by the end of the decade if the construction of new data centers race ahead of the energy supply.</p> 
<p>“PJM is broken,” Shapiro said in December. “They’re too damned slow. And the needs we have in this country to produce more energy to support everything from data centers to more manufacturing need to be met. And we are being held captive.”</p> 
<p>The enormously complex market rules that affect power prices in Shapiro’s state are outside average Americans’ conversations. But Shapiro and Trump have tied a rising part of their political parties’ credibility to the outcome of their pledges to make data centers pay their own way.</p> 
<p>In January, Shapiro <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/trump-tame-electricity-prices-00733422" target="_blank">went to the White House</a> alongside other East Coast governors of both parties to call for PJM to control power prices — and for data centers to “bring their own power” through long-term contracts with new generation developers.</p> 
<p>Big tech companies are starting to sign on. Trump used a Truth Social post in early January to announce the White House was working with tech companies to get more agreement on containing the public cost of energy infrastructure. Microsoft then pledged to shoulder more of those costs.</p> 
<p>Shapiro's tack could work for him, according to recent polling.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/power-switch/2026/02/13/data-centers-your-new-neighbor-00780829" target="_blank">POLITICO poll</a> released last week showed an electorate still wrestling with the data center question. Respondents' top concerns surrounding data centers were power prices and the risk of blackouts — yet they were generally willing to support a new data center in their area even<a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/02/13/what-do-people-know-about-data-centers-we-explain-in-5-charts-00769974" target="_blank">if it hikes their power bills</a>.</p> 
<p>In his address to lawmakers, Shapiro proposed a three-pronged strike against rising energy costs — proposing new rules for data center developers, electric utilities and the regional grid PJM. He pledged to “hold data center developers accountable to strict standards if they want our full support.”</p> 
<p>Last week, PJM agreed to extend price controls on future electricity production into 2030.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cox pushes back on Trump over gambling and AI regulation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/spencer-cox-utah-trump-ai-unity-gambling-00788583</link>
      <description>The White House recently warned Utah lawmakers against passing a bill regulating artificial intelligence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7692-d647-addc-ffd7e25d0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 11:01:43 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content medium="video" type="video/mp4" url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/2452e6aa-ddc1-434a-9335-679dcd8a16d9/5525a2a0-0952-49ec-b861-44bb2a4d0e8f/main.mp4">
        <media:description>Gov. Spencer Cox criticizes Trump's CTFC head over gambling regulation</media:description>
        <media:title>Gov. Spencer Cox criticizes Trump's CTFC head over gambling regulation</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/2452e6aa-ddc1-434a-9335-679dcd8a16d9/b358bfdb-52b2-4603-8387-ec11d362eb56/1280x720/match/image.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Utah Gov. Spencer Cox criticized the Trump administration’s approaches to prediction markets and artificial intelligence on Thursday — as well as the president’s lack of interest in unifying the country.</p> 
<p>During an interview at POLITICO’s 2026 Governors Summit, the Republican governor and occasional critic of President Donald Trump pushed back on the Trump administration’s recent efforts to limit states’ abilities to regulate gambling and AI, saying the federal government “coming in and trying to tell us” to back off state-level fixes is “preposterous.”</p> 
<p>“Look, this is a joke, and I can’t believe he tried to say this with a straight face,” Cox said, referring to <a href="https://x.com/ChairmanSelig/status/2023744651216240966" target="_blank">CFTC Chair Mike Selig’s</a> announcement earlier this week that the agency has singular authority to regulate prediction markets.</p> 
<p>“I’m concerned about these new technologies, and what they’re doing to our kids,” Cox added. “It's one thing if we're fighting China, and you're developing your model. But once you start selling sexualized chat bots to kids in my state, now I have a problem with that, and I'm going to get involved there, and the Supreme Court is going to back me up.”</p> 
<p>Last week, the White House <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/02/white-house-opposes-utah-gops-ai-transparency-bill-00782634" target="_blank">sent a letter to the Utah Legislature</a> warning lawmakers that a Republican-led AI regulation bill clashes with federal policy. Trump also signed <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/trump-orders-government-to-fight-state-ai-laws-00687948" target="_blank">a December executive order</a> that warned states of consequences for attempting to regulate the fast-growing industry.</p> 
<p>Cox said his approach does not conflict with his belief that the U.S. should win “the AI arms race with China and Russia,” and thus states and municipalities should support construction of data centers across the country.</p> 
<p>“Let's use this technology to benefit humankind, and let's regulate it to make sure they don't destroy humankind,” Cox said.</p> 
<p>He also made it clear he differs with Trump’s approach toward bringing together Americans from different perspectives. Shortly after Trump’s attempted assassination in Butler, Pennsylvania, in 2024, <a href="https://www.deseret.com/politics/2024/07/19/utah-gov-spencer-cox-donald-trump/" target="_blank">Cox endorsed him</a>, saying he hoped Trump could bring the country together.</p> 
<p>Cox said Thursday that hope had been “aspirational.”</p> 
<p>Trump is “someone who, if he put his mind to it, could unify” the country, Cox said. “He's not putting his mind to it. He has said very clearly that he’s not, and that's okay. That's different than me.”</p> 
<p>Cox also critiqued <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/07/31/heritage-american-jd-vance-online-right-phrase-00481724" target="_blank">the growing “Heritage American” movement</a> within his party, saying the nativist message is a recipe for electoral failure.</p> 
<p>“I worry about it because that's a future where we lose a lot of elections in a very ugly way,” Cox said. “I worry about it because that's not where most Americans are. It's certainly not where I am.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wes Moore: 'I don't answer to the Democratic Party’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/wes-moore-redistricting-democrats-2028-00788517</link>
      <description>The Maryland Governor addressed his clashes with state Democrats and said he's not thinking about 2028 at a POLITICO Summit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7690-d647-addc-ffd7efd90001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:48:01 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content medium="video" type="video/mp4" url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/98a943ac-06a3-4adb-9670-8390370ce658/5199c4b2-7a22-4d8c-92a6-fc2349a20e81/main.mp4">
        <media:description>Wes Moore: 'I don't answer to the Democratic Party'</media:description>
        <media:title>Wes Moore: 'I don't answer to the Democratic Party'</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/98a943ac-06a3-4adb-9670-8390370ce658/687353e6-1417-4d4e-9c50-40fc5b3dc862/1280x720/match/image.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore on Thursday defended his recent clashes with state Democrats, denying that he’s in a weak political position with his own legislature that has held up several of his policies and a push to redraw the state’s Congressional maps.</p> 
<p>“There is no political party that made me. In fact, the Democratic Party put millions of dollars to try to stop me from winning. I don’t answer to the Democratic Party. I don’t answer to party bosses,” Moore, a Democrat, said during POLITICO’s 2026 Governors Summit. “I only answer to the people who made me governor of Maryland, which is the people of Maryland.”</p> 
<p>Moore pointed out that he defeated the preferred candidate of many Democratic party bosses when he first ran for governor as a political newcomer in 2022.</p> 
<p><a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/mgawebsite/FloorActions/Agenda/senate-1-?ys=2025S1#Veto2" target="_blank">Maryland Democrats overrode at least 16</a> of the governor’s vetoes in December and the state’s Senate president, Bill Ferguson, is actively blocking Moore’s redistricting effort, saying the bill doesn’t have enough votes to pass on the floor. Moore continues to say Maryland residents are in favor of redistricting in the state, though a poll from December found <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/maryland-residents-bristle-at-wes-moores-redistricting-push-00690336" target="_blank">just 27 percent of residents</a> supported the issue.</p> 
<p>“If Bill Ferguson says, well, the votes aren't there in the Senate, my only point is this: OK, well, you know, the best way to prove that's true? Do a vote,” Moore said.</p> 
<p>Moore — widely considered a 2028 contender though he has repeatedly denied he wants to run — has attempted to position himself as a counterweight to President Donald Trump. But the resistance he’s facing in his own backyard has some national Democrats wondering whether he can successfully mount a White House run.</p> 
<p>On Thursday, Moore again dismissed the idea of running for president, saying he was focused on 2026 and “not even thinking” about 2028. <b>&nbsp;</b></p> 
<p>Oklahoma’s GOP Gov. Kevin Stitt, the current chair of the National Governors Association, defended Moore at the event, saying he had more respect for the Democrat knowing he stood up to lawmakers within his own party.</p> 
<p>“I have more respect for him now, knowing that he vetoed the bills,” Stitt said. “ I have a super majority Republican, and I vetoed 67 bills last year, and I think they overrode probably 45 of them. So it happens to all of us.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pro-Israel group wades into Democratic House primaries</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/pro-israel-dmfi-endorsements-democrats-house-primaries-00787254</link>
      <description>The Democratic Majority for Israel PAC shared its first round of House candidate endorsements in a range of safe-seat and battleground seats exclusively with POLITICO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-72fb-d0f8-adde-fafb72970000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ab/d9/5f73bc234ee6a2571e4b5ec85016/us-israel-hegseth-00814.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>U.S. and Israeli flags are displayed on a table during a meeting at the Pentagon in July 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ab/d9/5f73bc234ee6a2571e4b5ec85016/us-israel-hegseth-00814.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A pro-Israel group is wading into nearly a dozen contentious House primaries as it tries to shape the Democratic Party’s approach to the controversial issue.</p> 
<p>The Democratic Majority for Israel PAC, which backs pro-Israel Democrats, is endorsing 11 House candidates, including several in expensive and crowded primaries the party must win in order to retake the House. The group’s initial endorsement list was shared first with POLITICO.</p> 
<p>DMFI, first launched in 2019, is one of several groups across the political spectrum looking to influence the party’s views on Israel, even as its military operations in Gaza have divided the Democratic Party and become an early litmus test for both 2026 congressional candidates and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/14/2028-democrats-israel-gaza-litmus-test-00508934" target="_blank">2028 presidential hopefuls.</a></p> 
<p>The endorsements include candidates in six battleground races and five more in safe-blue, but crowded, Democratic primaries. They are backing moderate state Rep. Shannon Bird over progressive state Rep. Manny Rutinel for the right to face Rep. Gabe Evans (R-Colo.) in a swingy Colorado district.</p> 
<p>In New York, the group is backing Cait Conley, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2026/02/12/ny-17-primary-poll-cait-conley-beth-davidson-chatzky-drama-00779107" target="_blank">who has entered a crowded primary</a> to take on Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.) in a district which Kamala Harris won by a one-point margin in 2024. In Texas, DMFI has endorsed police officer Johnny Garcia in a wide-open primary for the newly drawn, red-leaning seat.</p> 
<p>DMFI is backing a pair of candidates in two of the four most competitive seats in Pennsylvania — Scranton Mayor Paige Cognetti, who will face off against Rep. Rob Bresnahan (R-Pa.), and former TV anchor Janelle Stelson, who is also on track to run against Rep. Scott Perry (R-Pa.). And in Virginia, former Rep. Elaine Luria picked up the group’s support as she vies to take on her former opponent, Rep. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.).</p> 
<p>The other candidates who are receiving DMFI’s endorsement are all running in crowded primaries in safe blue seats: Maryland state Del. Adrian Boafo, who is running to replace retiring Rep. Steny Hoyer (D-Md.); Michigan state Sen. Jeremy Moss, who is running to replace Rep. Haley Stevens (D-Mich.), who is running for Senate; and former Obama administration official Maura Sullivan, who is running to replace Rep. Chris Pappas (D-N.H.), who is running for the Senate.</p> 
<p>"The vast majority of Americans support the right of Israel to exist as a Jewish state and understand the importance of the U.S.-Israel relationship,” said former Rep. Kathy Manning, who serves on the DMFI PAC board. “If you're running in a competitive district, you need Democrats, you need independents, you need Republicans.”</p> 
<p>Several groups, including DMFI and the American Israel Public Affairs Committee, known as AIPAC, are boosting pro-Israel candidates with significant outside spending. The two groups have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/02/08/dmfi-democratic-primaries-2024-00140267" target="_blank">often</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/05/20/congress/pro-israel-groups-dem-battleground-endorsements-00158859" target="_blank">overlapped</a> in their endorsements, but AIPAC supports Democrats and Republicans — and has drawn the ire of progressives. DMFI, for its part, is focused on regaining a Democratic congressional majority.</p> 
<p>AIPAC’s super PAC, United Democracy Project, dropped more than $38 million on independent expenditures in 2024, while DMFI spent about $4.3 million. DMFI President Brian Romick said the group expects to be spending “comfortably” in the “seven-figures again” in 2026 but declined to elaborate further on the plans.</p> 
<p>In Illinois, among the first primaries next month, DMFI and AIPAC appear aligned in their preferred candidates. DMFI announced it is backing former Rep. Melissa Bean, who is running to replace Rep. Raja Krishnamoorthi (D-Ill.), who is running for the Senate, and Cook County Commissioner Donna Miller, who is vying to replace Rep. Robin Kelly (D-Ill.), another Senate candidate.</p> 
<p>Bean and Miller have also attracted attention for their connections to AIPAC. Their primary opponents in both races <a href="http://washingtonpost.com/politics/2026/02/18/aipac-democrats-midterms-2026-illinois/?utm_campaign=wp_power_up&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=newsletter&amp;carta-url=https%3A%2F%2Fs2.washingtonpost.com%2Fcar-ln-tr%2F46c7a6a%2F6995a0cda424af764b17c096%2F596c2b4bade4e24119c5ca45%2F16%2F64%2F6995a0cda424af764b17c096" target="_blank">have accused them of benefiting from AIPAC’s spending</a>, concealed by shell super PACs that are boosting them with hundreds of thousands of dollars in positive TV spending. But DMFI has not yet endorsed in Illinois’ 9th District, another contentious primary to replace retiring Rep. Jan Schakowsky that AIPAC appears to have waded into.</p> 
<p>Earlier this month, AIPAC <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/centrist-democrats-are-livid-with-aipac-after-primary-meddling-00769461" target="_blank">triggered a wave of criticism and frustration, even from its own allies,</a> for spending $2 million to sink former Rep. Tom Malinowski in a congressional special election in New Jersey. The group’s spending backfired, eliminating Malinowski, but failing to lift up its preferred candidate. Analilia Mejia, a progressive organizer who <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aQCOQ6R5mok&amp;t=2987s" target="_blank">has said Israel committed genocide in Gaza</a>, ultimately won.</p> 
<p>Romick and Manning declined to comment on AIPAC’s strategy, with the former congresswoman noting DMFI is “a distinctly different and separate organization.”</p> 
<p>In 2024, DMFI and AIPAC targeted former Reps. Cori Bush (D-Mo.) and Jamaal Bowman (D-N.Y.) in 2024, both of whom lost their primaries to pro-Israel candidates. Romick demurred on whether DMFI planned to target any Democratic incumbents in 2026, adding that it is going “to take these primaries as they come and see if things develop.”</p> 
<p><i>Jessica Piper contributed reporting.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In feud with Wes Moore, Trump slings feces</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-fixates-on-sewage-a-favored-talking-point-in-fight-with-wes-moore-00786490</link>
      <description>The president returned to his long-running gripes over all things scatological this week in his feud with the rising Democratic star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7271-d647-addc-fbf7e03a0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ba/f2/da3c80a841d4aefd6b49a7f29caa/2026-0217-potomac-francis-1-12.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>The Potomac River is seen near Fletcher's Boathouse in Washington on Tuesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ba/f2/da3c80a841d4aefd6b49a7f29caa/2026-0217-potomac-francis-1-12.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Miranda Willson and Annie Snider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Miranda Willson and Annie Snider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump didn’t just take his feud with Maryland governor and possible 2028 Democratic presidential hopeful Wes Moore into the gutter this week. He turned to the toilet.</p> 
<p><a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116086782319939311" target="_blank">In a series</a> of <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116082091487085093" target="_blank">social media posts</a> Monday and Tuesday, Trump blasted Moore for what he deemed an inept response to a sewage spill that sent hundreds of millions of gallons of raw waste into the Potomac River beginning four weeks ago.</p> 
<p>“There is a massive Ecological Disaster unfolding in the Potomac River as a result of the Gross Mismanagement of Local Democrat Leaders, particularly, Governor Wes Moore, of Maryland,” Trump wrote Tuesday on Truth Social, saying that it’s time <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/02/17/trump-assailed-fema-for-a-year-now-hes-relying-on-it-00784187" target="_blank">for the federal government to step in</a>. “I cannot allow incompetent Local ‘Leadership’ to turn the River in the Heart of Washington into a Disaster Zone.”</p> 
<p>On Wednesday, White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said the president is worried that the Potomac River will carry the stench of excrement during the July 4 celebration of the country’s semiquincentennial that Trump has been planning since returning to office.</p> 
<p>“He is worried about that. Which is why the federal government wants to fix it, and we hope that the local authorities will cooperate with us in doing so,” Leavitt said in response to a reporter’s question during the White House press briefing.</p> 
<p>It’s not the first time Trump has turned poop into a political weapon. In fact, the president who complains regularly about low-flow toilet standards has a long list of scatological gripes that have become one of the few areas where his administration is seeking additional environmental protections as it aggressively rolls back dozens of climate, air and water pollution rules.</p> 
<p>It was on the sewage-fouled beaches of San Diego that EPA Administrator Lee Zeldin marked his first Earth Day as the nation’s top environmental regulator. The administration has put concerted effort into pressuring Mexico to do more to stem the tide of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/20/next-border-fight-stinker-00241886" target="_blank">raw sewage pollution</a> flowing across the border from Tijuana, which for years has dirtied beaches and sickened residents and Navy SEALs who train nearby.</p> 
<p>And during Trump’s first term, it was San Francisco’s long-running sewer overflow problem that EPA targeted for enforcement after the president groused about the city’s large homeless population — a move that <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2019/10/02/us-epa-cites-san-francisco-1-day-after-city-accuses-feds-of-false-statements-1217320" target="_blank">California leaders saw</a> as politically charged.</p> 
<p>Now as Trump feuds with Moore, the nation’s only Black governor, less than two weeks <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/08/wes-moore-race-governors-trump-00770586" target="_blank">after excluding him</a> from a White House dinner for the National Governor’s Association, the image of millions of gallons of raw sewage flowing into the nation’s capital offered another level of political punch altogether. The situation comes as Moore is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/16/trump-fema-coordinating-response-potomac-sewage-spill-00783327" target="_blank">pushing to redraw</a> Maryland’s congressional lines to counter Trump’s red-state redistricting. </p> 
<p>“It’s a great political issue. Nobody wants sewage in the water — that is true of Democrats and Republicans,” said Mae Stevens, a water infrastructure lobbyist who previously served as an environment staffer for Democratic former Maryland Sen. Ben Cardin.</p> 
<p>Asked about the president’s longstanding interest in sewage pollution, White House spokesperson Taylor Rogers said the administration would not allow “the failures of local and state Democrats to diminish the quality of life for millions of Americans.”</p> 
<p>The source of the spill is the Potomac Interceptor sewer line, which partially collapsed Jan. 19 near Cabin John, Maryland, amid frigid winter temperatures, releasing nearly 200 million gallons of untreated wastewater in the first five days. Operating since<i>&nbsp;</i> constructed in 1964, the 54-mile line carries wastewater from D.C. suburbs as far away as Dulles Airport to a treatment plant in southern Washington.</p> 
<p>DC Water, the utility that operates the line, has been making emergency repairs to the broken interceptor, but the effort will take four to six more weeks. After that, crews will need to get to work on an already-planned rehabilitation project, which could take a further nine or 10 months, DC Water spokesperson Sherri Lewis said.</p> 
<p>Though the spill captured the nation’s attention only this week, local environmentalists have been sounding the alarm from the beginning. </p> 
<p>“It’s certainly a big ecological problem and an incredible threat to public health to have raw sewage splashing around and on shorelines,” said Hedrick Belin, president of the Potomac Conservancy, a conservation group. “We don’t need partisan politics getting in the way. This crisis is just too serious.” </p> 
<p>Officials in Maryland, which is technically responsible for the Potomac River, responded “within hours” of the initial spill, said Ammar Moussa, a spokesperson for Moore. But the interceptor falls under EPA’s regulatory purview, according to the governor’s office, accusing the agency that’s <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/01/27/epa-cuts-top-executive-jobs-under-trumps-reorg-00749294" target="_blank">lost thousands of staff</a> under Trump of failing to take action.</p> 
<p>“For the last four weeks, the Trump Administration has failed to act, shirking its responsibility and putting people's health at risk,” Moussa said in a statement. “Notably, the president’s own EPA explicitly refused to participate in the major legislative hearing about the cleanup last Friday.”</p> 
<p>Zeldin shot back at that accusation on Tuesday afternoon. </p> 
<p>“At no point in the lead up to today had DC Water or the state of Maryland requested EPA to take over their responsibilities, and EPA has continued to offer its full support to state and local leaders from the onset,” Zeldin said in a post on X.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Funding woes and ‘really poor infrastructure’</h4> 
<p>Water experts say the sewage spill is a symptom of a larger problem: Aging sewer pipes and water lines nationwide are in desperate need of repairs, but cash-strapped local governments are struggling to pay for them. </p> 
<p>The Trump administration has repeatedly pushed to slash federal funding for water projects. Last year, the White House <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2025/05/02/trump-calls-for-cutting-55-of-epas-budget-00323893" target="_blank">proposed a 90 percent cut</a> to EPA’s State Revolving Funds, the water sector’s largest source of federal dollars. The Senate ultimately rejected the cut in a spending bill that Trump <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/01/16/congress-oks-spending-package-without-protecting-colorado-research-lab-00731555" target="_blank">signed into law</a> last month. </p> 
<p>But extra water funding from the 2021 bipartisan infrastructure law is set to run out this fall, and experts warn of a coming funding cliff at the same time as extreme weather and AI data centers put more pressure on existing pipes, sewers and treatment plants.</p> 
<p>“We’ve got really poor infrastructure. A lot of these pipes, especially on the East Coast, were built decades ago,” said Jon Mueller, a visiting associate law professor at the University of Maryland. “I think it’s unfortunate that it takes a disaster like this to get people to focus on the problem.”</p> 
<p>It’s not yet clear how much the Potomac spill will cost, but the broader rehabilitation project for the interceptor sewer system’s “most vulnerable sections” is $625 million, said DC Water spokesperson Sherri Lewis. The utility has been coordinating with EPA, she added. </p> 
<p>“Just last week, we hosted the Assistant Administrator for Water for a tour of the site and briefing on the project and the progress made to date,” Lewis said in a statement. </p> 
<p>Although officials say the worst of the spill has been contained and that it has not impacted drinking water supplies, 243.5 million gallons of sewage overflows have been reported thus far. </p> 
<p>Environmental advocates are worried about long-term implications for the river, which feeds into the Chesapeake Bay, the nation’s largest estuary and the subject of decades of cleanup efforts. </p> 
<p>Earlier this month, University of Maryland researchers <a href="https://sph.umd.edu/news/umd-team-finds-e-coli-mrsa-potomac-river-after-sewage-spill" target="_blank">recorded extremely high concentrations of bacteria</a>, including a strain that resists antibiotics, tied to the spill. By springtime, that could render parts of the water unsafe for boating, canoeing and fishing. </p> 
<p>Dean Naujoks, who leads the environmental group Potomac Riverkeeper, said he hopes Trump’s involvement could improve what he described as a “botched” cleanup process by DC Water. But he cast blame as well on EPA, describing the agency as essentially missing in action.</p> 
<p>“We can’t get a hold of [EPA]. I have no idea what they’re doing,” Naujoks said. “The squabble between Trump and Gov. Moore has focused more of the attention on accountability, which I think is a good thing.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump looms over Texas attorney general race</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/maga-purity-test-plays-out-in-texas-attorney-general-race-00786750</link>
      <description>Rep. Chip Roy has long sparred with Trump. His breaks with the president have become a flashpoint in his run to be Texas' top lawman.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7246-d3b5-addf-f2c680fc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 16:30:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/97/2c/acf611d84a85b21938197d706eef/u-s-congress-48049.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>It remains unclear whether Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and other fiscal hawks will balk at a new health package with reforms to PBMs and additional community health center funding.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/97/2c/acf611d84a85b21938197d706eef/u-s-congress-48049.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Republican battle to become Texas’ next attorney general has turned into a MAGA purity test, with major implications for the future of the GOP after President Donald Trump leaves office.</p> 
<p>Rep. Chip Roy, a well known Freedom Caucus rabble-rouser and hardline fiscal conservative who has occasionally broken with Trump, is fighting to stay the front-runner for a job that has long been used to aggressively push the conservative agenda and served as a jumping-off point for higher office — like current Attorney General Ken Paxton, who’s running for Senate.</p> 
<p>The next Texas attorney general will help shape the future of the Republican party post-Trump, playing a key role leading the conservative legal movement. But if Roy is going to get there, he’ll first have to get by State Sen. Mayes Middleton and former DOJ attorney Aaron Reitz, who have both carved paths as aggressive foot soldiers for the MAGA movement. The race also includes state Sen. Joan Huffman, who is making a more measured pitch for the job.</p> 
<p>Roy has a lead in the polls, and all three candidates are trying to keep him from earning more than 50 percent of the vote in the March primary to force a runoff in May.</p> 
<p>Their main line of attack: Roy’s past dustups with Trump shows he is inadequately conservative in order to represent Texas in court. Roy, in response, has argued that his reputation as an obstructionist in Congress, deep experience in Washington and independent streak within the party demonstrates he’s well equipped to serve as Texas’ top lawyer.</p> 
<p>The candidates’ eagerness to prove their MAGA credentials were on display in the first few moments of a debate Tuesday night. Middleton bragged that Trump once called him a “MAGA champion.” Reitz said Trump regards him as a “true MAGA attorney.” Huffman said she “led the fight with President Trump on border security” in the state legislature. Roy said he has worked alongside Trump to designate cartels as terrorist organizations.</p> 
<p>But Roy’s rivals have repeatedly hammered him <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/01/24/chip-roy-donald-trump-threats-00200372?fbclid=IwY2xjawP5ifNleHRuA2FlbQIxMQBzcnRjBmFwcF9pZAwzNTA2ODU1MzE3MjgAAR60uqmVC4nhfNyNBfQXXUukkPUOCuIdnJI-gIYsTjGT5vldq-1srH-qcUsZkw_aem_Fd_USs9yKejW3hhPevsP5g" target="_blank"><u>for being at odds</u></a> with Trump and the GOP in the past. The congressman was the first to <a href="https://roy.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-chip-roy-released-following-statement-texas-ag-ken-paxton" target="_blank"><u>call for Paxton to resign</u></a> after he faced charges of bribery and abuse of office in 2020. He bucked Trump to certify the 2020 election and said the president demonstrated “clearly impeachable conduct” on Jan. 6. Roy backed Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis for president in 2024, making him one of just a handful of House Republicans who opposed Trump during that year’s primaries.</p> 
<p>And, his refusal to fall in line with GOP leadership in the House — even holding up numerous funding bills — has <a href="https://rollcall.com/2026/02/05/donald-trump-national-prayer-breakfast-democrats/" target="_blank"><u>occasionally infuriated</u></a> Trump. In late 2024, as Roy led the charge against Trump’s demand that the House raise the debt ceiling without restrictions on future spending, Trump blasted him as “just another ambitious guy, with no talent” and invited primary challengers against him. Roy was a late holdout on Trump’s signature legislative achievement, the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, though he eventually voted for it.</p> 
<p>“This is somebody who has a deep disdain for the MAGA movement … and he's only now singing a different tune now that it's campaign season,” Reitz said of Roy in an interview, while touting his own experience working in the Trump Justice Department’s Office of Legal Policy, a position he held for several months. Reitz has received Paxton’s coveted endorsement and posted strong fundraising numbers.</p> 
<p>Trump has not yet weighed in on who he prefers to take the mantle from Paxton, but his potential endorsement looms over the field. A recent <a href="https://www.uh.edu/news-events/stories/2026/february/02112026-hobby-primary-election-outlook-governor.php" target="_blank"><u>poll</u></a> shows Roy in the lead, with 33 percent of likely Republican voters, followed by Middleton, with 23 percent. Huffman and Reitz trail at 13 percent and 6 percent, respectively. A quarter of voters are undecided.</p> 
<p>Among Texas Republican voters, “the attorney general position is kind of viewed as the police officer of the state,” said Jen French, chair of the Travis County GOP. “Voters like somebody who's going to get in there and what they perceive as ‘fight, fight, fight.’”</p> 
<p>All four GOP candidates are closely aligned on policy, vowing to follow strict interpretations of the Texas and U.S. Constitutions, but Middleton and Reitz have made more bombastic declarations about how they would enforce the law. The differences between the set are mostly stylistic, as they try one to one-up each other on red meat issues like stopping the alleged spread of Sharia law in Texas and halting the flow of abortion pills into the state.</p> 
<p>Middleton has nicknamed himself “MAGA Mayes,” a slogan he’s put on hats his campaign gives away. He’s also leaned into culture war issues that rally the base like banning trans student athletes from competition and allowing the Ten Commandments in schools. The oil and gas businessman from Galveston has largely self-funded his campaign, putting more than $11 million toward the effort.</p> 
<p>Roy, who also leads in fundraising, has been endorsed by well-known conservatives like Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas), who Roy once worked for as his chief of staff, as well as fellow Freedom Caucus Reps. Lauren Boebert of Colorado and Andy Biggs of Arizona. Roy reported $4.2 million in the bank in January, fueled by a $2 million transfer from his congressional campaign account.</p> 
<p>Huffman, one of the longest-serving state senators, highlights her experience prosecuting felony crimes as an assistant district attorney and state district judge in Harris County. In an interview, she said she would treat the job of attorney general as “chief law enforcement officer for Texans,” and work closely with local law enforcement.</p> 
<p>Whoever emerges from the GOP primary will be the heavy favorite in the general election in the Republican-leaning state. On the Democratic side, the race includes State Sen. Nathan Johnson and former Galveston mayor Joe Jaworski, who is making his second shot at the nomination. Jaworski, in an interview, said voters are tired of “a rabid ultra MAGA representation of what government is. It’s all about punishing the vulnerable.”</p> 
<p>The job has long allowed its holder a leading role in the national culture wars — and a springboard to higher office. Republican Gov. Greg Abbott was attorney general before he ran for governor and barraged the Obama administration with lawsuits that made national headlines: He famously quipped in 2013 that his day-to-day was, “I go into the office, I sue the federal government and I go home.” Before he had the job, it was filled by now-Sen. John Cornyn (R-Texas), the man Paxton is currently running against.</p> 
<p>Paxton spent a decade steering the office into the center of the culture wars, pursuing actions in the name of preserving religious liberty and spearheading multistate lawsuits filed by Republican attorneys general against the federal government. The AG role has since become the top destination for young conservative legal talents, a number of whom have gone on to become judges appointed by Trump.</p> 
<p>It is a “choice position,” said Mark Jones, a political science professor at Rice University.</p> 
<p>“There’s this whole playing field within the legal system where the states can have a powerful impact on national policy in a wide range of areas,” he said. “And no state has more successfully – or at least more aggressively – used the power of the courts to try to further a conservative policy agenda than the state of Texas.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Hampshire’s GOP Gov. Kelly Ayotte draws her first major challenger</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/new-hampshire-kelly-ayotte-cinde-warmington-00785878</link>
      <description>Democrat Cinde Warmington launched another bid for the governor’s office after running unsuccessfully in 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7133-d647-addc-fbf7f2170000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 09:58:12 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/65/31/b6124a7c4fc0952443f459d99e75/election-2024-new-hampshire-governor-82581.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Cinde Warmington during a gubernatorial debate in 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/65/31/b6124a7c4fc0952443f459d99e75/election-2024-new-hampshire-governor-82581.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Cinde Warmington launched a repeat bid for governor of New Hampshire on Wednesday, giving Democrats their first major challenger to GOP Gov. Kelly Ayotte in the purple state.</p> 
<p>Warmington, a former state executive councilor, ran unsuccessfully for governor in 2024, losing the Democratic nomination to former Manchester Mayor Joyce Craig who then went on to lose to Ayotte. She now enters a relatively open Democratic field, with just one other declared candidate.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c_7nRuEu0MY" target="_blank">launch video</a> posted to her campaign website, Warmington attacked Ayotte for “making your life more expensive.” She also accused the Republican of not standing up to President Donald Trump’s attempts to open an ICE detention facility in the state.</p> 
<p>“I’ll stand up to Trump when he jacks up health care costs and tariffs. I’ll say ‘no’ to ICE’s warehouse. I’ll work for our small businesses and I’ll make sure we don’t have a sales or income tax,” Warmington said in the video. <a href="https://url4027.email.politico.com/ss/c/u001.6g0Zd3AyneOViJYBXgbV68q315JmMH5kG-tqpKu2qUAoHQyu3STNAgxPcRVy5UDrIoEl2tLNburyB93d6QTITIZSOu-N17Ly2XnbqmiyU6iqi2Esu7eb9rvfl_W9PV1v/4o9/b1KJ9kx2Q8OKd3sZ95FNEg/h3/h001.vFJbE-rQrzow2egjEotMhktd83eGzjYQRc4D1NozcVE" target="_blank">WMUR</a> first reported her launch.</p> 
<p>Ayotte, for her part, has clashed with Trump. She has criticized <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2026-01-28/ayotte-ice-trump-merrimack-immigration-detention-dhs-kristi-noem-warehouse" target="_blank">the lack of transparency</a> around the ICE warehouse and <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2026-02-09/merrimack-ice-detainee-plans-nh-dncr-stewart-resigns" target="_blank">forced the resignation</a> of a state official who had been communicating with the Trump administration without alerting the governor. Her refusal to redistrict last year led the White House to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/30/redistricting-republican-loyalty-test-trump-00584932" target="_blank">weigh putting up a primary challenger against her</a>.</p> 
<p>Ayotte spokesperson John Corbett blasted Warmington in a statement, saying the former health care lobbyist “chose to make money off big pharmaceutical companies who hurt Granite Staters, and she is absolutely disqualified from serving as our Governor.”</p> 
<p>Democrats are bullish they can block Ayotte from a second term, emboldened by their <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/democrats-2025-win-midterms-virginia-new-jersey-00637057" target="_blank">party’s wins in the off-year elections</a>. But they face an uphill battle in a blue-leaning battleground state that routinely elects Republican governors while sending all-Democratic delegations to Congress. </p> 
<p>Recent history is not on Democrats’ side: The party thrice failed to unseat Ayotte’s predecessor, Republican Gov. Chris Sununu. And prognosticators rate the seat as <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/governor-race-ratings" target="_blank">“likely Republican”</a> this year.</p> 
<p>Democrats may also face another messy primary just two years after Warmington and Craig <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2024-election/new-hampshire-primary-governor-race-battleground-state-rcna169406" target="_blank">waged a bruising battle</a> to be their party’s nominee. For now, just Warmington and Democrat Jon Kiper, who finished a distant third in the 2024 race, have declared their candidacies. But Democratic Portsmouth Mayor Deaglan McEachern has been <a href="https://www.seacoastonline.com/story/news/politics/elections/2026/02/11/portsmouth-mayor-deaglan-mceachern-considers-run-nh-governor-election/88606818007/?gnt-cfr=1&amp;gca-cat=p&amp;gca-uir=true&amp;gca-epti=z11xx11p119550c119550v11xx11d--49--b--49--&amp;gca-ft=262&amp;gca-ds=sophi" target="_blank">publicly weighing a bid for governor</a> as recently as this month.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/survey_center_polls/922/" target="_blank">University of New Hampshire survey from January</a> showed Ayotte leading both men in hypothetical general-election matchups; it did not test her against Warmington. Ayotte notched a 50-percent approval rating in the poll, though 44 percent of likely voters said she did not deserve to be reelected compared to 42 percent who did.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This emerging Democratic star is embroiled in a primary fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/texas-house-primary-rio-grande-valley-00784771</link>
      <description>The primary in the Rio Grande Valley mirrors the battle in the state's Senate race.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-6d72-d647-addc-eff78a600001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/86/91/6906c535433d90d55b2c3b6e144c/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2246570182">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Greg Doherty/Getty Images for The Latin Recording Academy</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tejano music star Bobby Pulido, shown last November in Las Vegas, is in a contentious primary that has turned increasingly personal.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/86/91/6906c535433d90d55b2c3b6e144c/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2246570182" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tejano music star Bobby Pulido is a favorite of national Democrats this cycle, as he mounts an uphill battle to flip a deep-red Rio Grande Valley House seat that President Donald Trump won by 18 points in 2024.</p> 
<p>But before he can take on Rep. Monica De La Cruz (R-Texas) in the state's 15th District, he must navigate the politics of a messy primary with emergency room doctor Ada Cuellar in a race that has turned increasingly personal — and mirrors the fight up the ticket for one of the state’s Senate seats.</p> 
<p>The primary has emerged as somewhat of a proxy war in the high-profile Senate primary between Rep. Jasmine Crockett, who has backed Cuellar, and state Rep. James Talarico, who supports Pulido. Both contests have become emblematic of larger divides facing a party that is still going through growing pains after across-the-board losses to Republicans in 2024.</p> 
<p>Pulido is running a race geared toward a general election with a Republican-leaning electorate. In an interview, he said he is “not trying to run a primary race,” but rather a “general campaign.” Cuellar, meanwhile, argues Pulido’s vision for the future of the party is out of touch with what’s on the ground.</p> 
<p>Cuellar herself is facing a tough path to even reach November. Pulido’s name ID alone may be enough to get him through to the general. Even still, she has mounted repeated attacks on Pulido across the airwaves, arguing he is too conservative of a Democrat.</p> 
<p>A few of them have landed. Pulido’s campaign has apologized for a past <a href="https://www.mediaite.com/media/news/exclusive-texas-democrat-bobby-pulido-has-long-history-of-explicit-misogynistic-commentary/" target="_blank">misogynistic comment directed toward Hillary Clinton</a>. His opponents have also focused on past remarks in which <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yAurcCq3vMU&amp;feature=youtu.be" target="_blank">he said he doesn’t live in Texas full time</a> and used his <a href="https://x.com/drcuellartx15/status/2020898021249048773?s=20" target="_blank">friendship with a local judge</a> to get out of a speeding ticket.</p> 
<p>Cuellar said the strategy became necessary because party leaders in both Texas and Washington were putting their thumb on the scale for Pulido.</p> 
<p>“The establishment has been misreading the moment,” she said in an interview. “This district wasn't looking for a conservative Dem. They were looking for someone who is willing to fight someone with experience and someone who can actually solve problems.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Pulido’s campaign says it’s focused on the ground game, pointing to dozens of events Pulido has hosted in the district in recent weeks at taquerias and community centers. They have so far insisted that they don’t want to go negative in the campaign.</p> 
<p>“It’s become personal one way only,” Pulido said. “I haven’t responded. We’ve been really focused on talking to voters.”</p> 
<p>Pulido’s campaign insists he’ll cruise through the primary. An internal poll conducted by GBAO from Jan. 24-27 and shared with POLITICO showed Pulido leading Cuellar by nearly 50 points — 68 percent to 19 percent. Thirteen percent of the 500 likely voters surveyed were undecided, and the poll has a margin of error of plus or minus 4.4 percent.</p> 
<p>While he says he’s not interested in responding publicly, there are still clear signs Pulido is trying to push back on Cuellar’s attacks. In <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/927cd4f8-2806-4115-afba-4dc5546d76be" target="_blank">his first campaign ad of the primary</a> released late last week, Cuellar’s face is shown on the screen while Pulido says American politics has become focused on “lies that don’t lower grocery prices.”</p> 
<p>Cuellar has navigated controversy of her own. She fired a consultant who <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2026/02/09/the-big-ads-from-the-big-game-00770981" target="_blank">was previously involved in Republican races</a> as she worked to cast Pulido as too conservative for the district.</p> 
<p>“Would I like for a primary to not be as contentious as it’s been? Yes, I wish it wasn’t,” Pulido said. “But it’s OK. It’s politics. I’m a big boy. But we're trying to advance to face Monica De La Cruz.”</p> 
<p>The sharp-elbowed campaign from Cuellar has worried some Pulido allies who are fearful these same types of attacks could prove potent in a general election. But Cuellar said her tactics are doing national Democrats a favor.</p> 
<p>“We’re actually vetting the candidate,” Cuellar said. “The DCCC clearly didn’t vet him at all.”</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Trump is Remaking America’s Nuclear Regulator</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/18/how-trump-is-remaking-americas-nuclear-regulator-1921561</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-6e89-de8a-a1fc-ffc9dc7c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">How Trump is Remaking America’s Nuclear Regulator</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6389499348112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/35ebde5d-9fff-4792-8adb-527ce18ae726/fb4da6e2-bc9a-4314-8530-7d644f54b739/main.mp4" src="28/92/d6aab046490194242e0c188b5315/ep-5-thumbnail-horizontal-w-title-1.png">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Maryland Democrats are thwarting Wes Moore’s political ambitions</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/16/wes-moore-redistricting-maryland-00783292</link>
      <description>"The operations of his political tentacles are weak," says one Democratic strategist. "His inside political network is weak.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-67fa-de8a-a1fc-fffa27700000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 15:40:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/1c/dd/7260ed4549bdadf8f61d2b115c51/trump-baltimore-19131.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Nick Wass/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore speaks during a news conference, Sept. 5, 2025, in Baltimore.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1c/dd/7260ed4549bdadf8f61d2b115c51/trump-baltimore-19131.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore's national political ambitions could be stymied by Democrats in his own backyard.</p> 
<p>The governor’s power play to redraw the state’s congressional lines and snare Democrats a single House seat has earned him accolades from progressive activists and party leaders in Washington, raising his profile as he weighs a 2028 presidential run. But Moore also has been outmaneuvered at times by members of own party, particularly those in the Maryland Senate where his gerrymander blitz is facing an unceremonious death.</p> 
<p>The redistricting gambit is one of the first big political tests Moore has faced that has national implications and could elevate him further within the party — or expose weaknesses as he positions himself as a counterweight to President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Critics say Moore hasn’t been aggressive enough in using bare-knuckle tactics to push through his agenda. Supporters say the first-term governor is focused on redistricting because he sees it as vital to his future national ambitions. Some national Democrats question whether Moore can lead the nation if he fails to bend lawmakers in a solidly blue state with a Democratic-controlled Legislature to enact his policy priorities. POLITICO spoke to almost two dozen state and federal lawmakers and Democratic strategists for this story.</p> 
<p>David Turner, Moore’s senior adviser and communications director, said the governor spearheading Maryland’s redistricting effort is not about furthering his political career.</p> 
<p>“Anyone who thinks this is about national ambitions isn’t paying enough attention to the damage being done in 2026,” he said. “The Governor has been clear: at a time when other states are discussing mid-decade redistricting, Maryland needs to as well.”</p> 
<p>Moore’s inability to convince enough Maryland Democratic senators to go along with redrawing maps has drawn unfavorable comparisons to California Gov. Gavin Newsom, another likely 2028 White House contender who successfully pushed through a major redistricting effort in his state. After California voters approved the state’s redistricting proposal, Newsom urged other states, including Maryland, to “contribute a verse” in the party’s gerrymandering push.</p> 
<p>“If he did kind of match Gavin in terms of that effectiveness, being able to take this issue, win on it and kind of help build his image, I think that would [have been] a great opportunity for him,” said Paul Mitchell of Moore. Mitchell is a redistricting expert and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/15/california-gerrymander-paul-mitchell-00510786" target="_blank">architect of the newly adopted California congressional maps</a>.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/4e/56/3e4b398e4ffabb01c336e4d29d4a/maryland-affordability-26319.jpg" alt="Maryland Gov. Wes Moore speaks during a press conference announcing the Protection from Predatory Pricing Act, in Severna Park, Maryland, Jan. 20, 2026." data-portal-copyright="Stephanie Scarbrough/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26020744326319" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Maryland Gov. Wes Moore speaks during a press conference announcing the Protection from Predatory Pricing Act, in Severna Park, Maryland, Jan. 20, 2026."/><p>While Moore championed bills to raise the state’s minimum wage, worked to reduce <a href="https://www.wbaltv.com/article/2025-crime-data-baltimore-lowest-homicide-rate-decades/69898283" target="_blank">Baltimore's homicide rate</a> to near 50-year lows and helped Marylanders cover soaring energy costs, in December, <a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/mgawebsite/FloorActions/Agenda/senate-1-?ys=2025S1#Veto2" target="_blank">Maryland Democrats overrode at least 16</a> of the governor’s vetoes — tying his predecessor, GOP Gov. Larry Hogan, for the most he had in a single year during his two terms. That included one override veto over an issue that peeved many Black lawmakers months earlier: Moore’s blockage of the formation of a commission to study reparations in the state.</p> 
<p>Weeks after his reparations veto, Moore traveled to an early presidential primary state to deliver the keynote remarks at the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/30/wes-moore-dives-into-2028-race-in-south-carolina-00378647" target="_blank">South Carolina Democrats Blue Palmetto Dinner</a>, where he said: “Gone are the days when we are the party of bureaucracy, multi-year studies, panels and college debate club rules.”</p> 
<p>It is a stark illustration of the criticism that’s followed Moore since he cruised to victory in his first-ever election four years ago: that he’s using the governor’s mansion as a springboard to Washington instead of doing the work of building relationships in Annapolis to get his bills across the finish line.</p> 
<p>“Truly, Wes Moore is a great candidate…He has the pizzazz and the swagger that some folks wish they could have,” a Democratic strategist who has worked on state, local and presidential campaigns said and granted anonymity to offer an unvarnished assessment of Moore. “But the operations of his political tentacles are weak. His inside political network is weak.”</p> 
<p>Moore addressed some of this criticism head on last week, where the tension was palpable during a joint address of the General Assembly.</p> 
<p>“I will not stand here and tell you that I have gotten it all right,” Moore said in his State of the State address Wednesday. “It's taken time to build relationships. It's taken time to learn Annapolis. I am an outsider at heart, and I don't see that changing,” he said before ramping up to a central theme of his remarks – and pressuring Senate Democrats to take up a congressional redistricting bill.</p> 
<p>He characterized his months-long public tussle with Maryland Senate President Bill Ferguson as “a very principled disagreement.”</p> 
<p>Though the Maryland House of Delegates approved legislation Moore backed to redraw the seat of the state’s lone Republican, House Freedom Caucus chair Rep. Andy Harris, Maryland’s gerrymandering effort is still being blocked in the state Senate.</p> 
<p>Ferguson has maintained he will not bring the bill up for a vote, saying there is not enough support for it in his chamber, it’s legally risky and adopting the new maps would jeopardize Maryland’s current 7-1 advantage.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/90/6d/939f90ec49f1a1cf168e845222db/election-2024-maryland-senate-tax-debate-84416.jpg" alt="Maryland State Senate President Bill Ferguson addresses the senate chamber during the opening session of the Maryland General Assembly, at the State Capitol in Annapolis, Maryland, Jan. 10, 2024." data-portal-copyright="Bryan Woolston/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="24093757684416" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Maryland State Senate President Bill Ferguson addresses the senate chamber during the opening session of the Maryland General Assembly, at the State Capitol in Annapolis, Maryland, Jan. 10, 2024."/><p>Many national Democrats have pressured Ferguson and other holdouts, including former Speaker Nancy Pelosi and Democratic Leader Hakeem Jeffries, who in an <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/02/15/politics/jeffries-midterms-gerrymandering-redistricting" target="_blank">interview with CNN on Sunday</a> suggested he would travel to Annapolis to meet with Ferguson.</p> 
<p>Two Moore aides, granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy, also point out that top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, Jamie Raskin (D-Md.), who previously served in the Maryland Senate, <a href="https://jamieraskin.com/md-general-assembly-letter/" target="_blank">penned a letter</a> to state lawmakers this week calling it a “clear and present danger” not to act. Raskin also sought to undercut Ferguson’s legal justification for not acting, pointing to recent decisions by the U.S. Supreme Court allowing both Texas and California to use their redrawn maps ahead of the midterms. But the Senate leader appears unswayed.</p> 
<p>“I think the miscalculation is that a lot of people are being led to believe that it's only Bill who doesn't want the map,” said one Maryland Legislative Black Caucus member granted anonymity to discuss internal party dynamics. </p> 
<p>Maryland’s Feb. 24 <a href="https://elections.maryland.gov/elections/2026/2026_Election_Calendar.pdf" target="_blank">candidate filing deadline</a> is quickly approaching — the date Ferguson and supporters say any changes beyond that date will be too late and overly disruptive to the state elections calendar.</p> 
<p>The two Moore aides argued that it is an arbitrary deadline and pointed to legislation <a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/mgawebsite/Legislation/Details/HB0689?ys=2026rs" target="_blank">working its way through the Maryland House</a> pushing the filing deadline to late March.</p> 
<p>A December poll by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/maryland-residents-bristle-at-wes-moores-redistricting-push-00690336" target="_blank">University of Maryland, Baltimore County</a> found just 27 percent of Maryland residents said redrawing maps was a top issue, signaling affordability and quality education were top of mind.</p> 
<p>Maryland-based Democratic strategist Len Foxwell said Moore’s attempts so far to win over voters in the state have been too focused on cable television and podcast appearances, adding the governor’s redistricting push never gained steam because he and his team “botched the rollout so badly.”</p> 
<p>Instead of engaging in the kind of aggressive public relations campaign that Newsom launched to sell voters on the need to gerrymander, Moore created an advisory commission to solicit public input. Its meetings were held virtually and typically at odd hours, with most proceedings taking place late on Friday afternoons. The outcome of whether the commission was going to recommend new maps was never in doubt.</p> 
<p>“The work of the commission was a rather dreary exercise in muscle-flexing,” Foxwell said. “The clear message was that we are doing this because we can do it. And I don't think that was a message that was satisfying.”</p> 
<p>Moore hasn’t deployed scorched-earth tactics against Ferguson, unlike the kind Trump encouraged where he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/trump-indiana-redistricting-republicans-rodric-bray-00686257" target="_blank">threatened to primary Indiana Republicans</a>who wouldn’t support his attempt to gerrymander in the Hoosier state. Indiana Senate Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/trump-indiana-redistricting-republicans-rodric-bray-00686257" target="_blank">ultimately blocked Trump’s push</a>.</p> 
<p>Jeffries, who could become the nation’s first Black speaker should Democrats take back the U.S. House this fall, said during a hastily arranged press conference in the U.S. Capitol in late January that Marylanders “deserve an up or down vote.” Moore, standing shoulder-to-shoulder with Jeffries, looked on as the Democratic congressional leader directed his disdain toward Ferguson, though he never named him.</p> 
<p>Behind the scenes, Jeffries and other top Democrats backing Moore are working around Ferguson by leaning on the Black Caucus to force a rarely-used state Senate procedure to discharge the redistricting bill out of the chamber’s Rules Committee. If it’s successful it will force a floor vote on the House-passed bill. But <a href="https://www.thebanner.com/politics-power/state-government/arthur-ellis-senate-redistricting-protest-7BHVDQD5JRFJVPGHWVDZXZH3LQ/" target="_blank">just one member</a> of the Black Caucus is openly supporting that tactic and the prevailing thought is the legislation will sit in purgatory until the General Assembly session ends in April.</p> 
<p>The Maryland Legislative Black Caucus member added that while Moore is seen as a rising Democratic star on the national stage, there is work to be done by the governor in Annapolis.</p> 
<p>“I think it's that his folks are trying to insulate him from some things,” the lawmaker continued. “Because if he starts to have those relationships, then he's going to start to hear that some of these ideas that he has are not necessarily the best, and that becomes a problem for some of his national aspirations.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DHS watchdog warns shutdown could imperil immigration enforcement oversight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/15/dhs-watchdog-shutdown-immigration-enforcement-00782758</link>
      <description>The lapse in funding is forcing the department’s inspector general to suspend the majority of its audits and probes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-6353-d647-addc-ebd72ab50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:52:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b6/c9/625d6f82417f83004cff90b43180/gettyimages-2258531337.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Patrick T. Fallon/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Protestors clash with police during a protest against Immigration and Customs Enforcement in Los Angeles on January 30, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b6/c9/625d6f82417f83004cff90b43180/gettyimages-2258531337.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The partial government shutdown that went into effect Saturday is throwing the fate of oversight at the Department of Homeland Security into peril, with the department’s independent watchdog warning a lapse in funding could jeopardize several ongoing investigations.</p> 
<p>DHS’s inspector general currently has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/dhs-watchdog-probe-trump-immigration-00768311" target="_blank">eight active probes</a> into the Trump administration’s nationwide immigration crackdown, including reviews of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/dhs-inspector-general-investigates-ice-surveillance-00768778" target="_blank">use of facial recognition</a> and allegations of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents using <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-investigation-use-of-force-ice-00761953" target="_blank">excessive force</a>.</p> 
<p>But with a lapse in funding for DHS, the Office of the Inspector General has been forced to suspend approximately 85 percent of its audits, evaluations and inspections, according to the OIG.</p> 
<p>Congressional Democrats are demanding sweeping reforms to ICE and Customs and Border Patrol before they’ll vote to fund DHS, including requirements that immigration enforcement agents wear body cameras and display their ID numbers and last names. With Senate Republicans and the White House refusing to budge on several key demands — including a proposed prohibition on federal agents wearing masks — the department is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/congress-shutdown-dhs-ice-00779881" target="_blank">likely to remain unfunded</a> for at least 10 days.</p> 
<p>Democrats in Congress first asked Joseph Cuffari, the DHS inspector general President Donald Trump appointed during his first term, to investigate the use of force by ICE agents last June. The lawmakers, including Sens. Elizabeth Warren and Ed Markey of Massachusetts, wrote to Cuffari earlier this month <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-240c-df17-afbf-7d3f17b40000" target="_blank">asking him to expedite the probe</a>, citing the fatal shootings of Renee Good and Alex Pretti by federal agents in Minneapolis as underscoring the “urgent need” for moving quickly.</p> 
<p>Republicans have raised concern about the shutdown’s effect on DHS agencies like TSA and FEMA, although <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499" target="_blank">it will likely take weeks</a> for the public to start feeling the effects of the funding lapse.</p> 
<p>Rep. Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.), who chairs the House Homeland Security Committee, said in a statement that “OIG investigations provide transparency and accountability, and any delay in funding will only disrupt these important efforts,” adding that the DHS appropriations bill passed in the House provided “critical funding” for the office.</p> 
<p>“As we experience yet another DHS shutdown because Senate Democrats refused to pass this legislation, I urge them to negotiate in good faith so we can ensure these resources and the resources for numerous other components, like FEMA and TSA, are not held hostage because of Washington’s dysfunction,” he said.</p> 
<p>ICE, on the other hand, is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/01/trump-protecting-priorities-from-shutdown-00588657" target="_blank">largely insulated</a> from the effects of the shutdown, with GOP lawmakers having appropriated billions of dollars for the agency in the One Big Beautiful Bill Act last year.</p> 
<p>But the lapse in funding raises several potential obstacles to the ability of members of Congress and investigators to conduct oversight of the agency. During the last government shutdown, ICE <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/29/congress/ice-quietly-furloughed-its-congressional-relations-team-during-shutdown-00627355" target="_blank">quietly furloughed</a> most of its congressional relations team and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/27/immigration-congressional-visits-ice-government-shutdown-00624066" target="_blank">blocked lawmakers</a> from visiting immigration detention facilities. (Prior to the shutdown, Democratic lawmakers on several occasions <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/19/new-jersey-congressmember-assault-00357934" target="_blank">clashed with DHS</a> over <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/18/ice-nyc-protest-00572418" target="_blank">their attempts to inspect detention facilities</a>.)</p> 
<p>And with approximately 60 percent of the OIG’s workforce furloughed — including auditors, data scientists and inspectors — only special agents like criminal investigators and personnel whose work is supported by secondary funding sources, like the Disaster Relief Fund, can continue working through the shutdown, per the office.</p> 
<p>The effect of the funding lapse for the inspector general’s work is also slated to affect the office’s reviews of the Secret Service’s handling of the July 2024 assassination attempt against Trump, in addition to probes of DHS’s cybersecurity and counterintelligence operations.</p> 
<p>The Council of the Inspectors General on Integrity and Efficiency — an independent government entity that lays out annual legislative priorities focused on government oversight and accountability — has for years called on Congress to establish authority for IGs to continue oversight during government shutdowns.</p> 
<p>Mark Greenblatt, who served as the Department of the Interior’s inspector general from 2019 until 2025, said while criminal investigations can sometimes continue despite a lapse in funding, IG offices are forced to pause oversight reviews, ceding valuable time on sensitive audits during shutdowns.</p> 
<p>“These situations are raw. They need an independent voice providing facts on what's happening on the ground with respect to these sensitive issues,” said Greenblatt, who was one of several IGs <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/01/25/donald-trump-inspectors-general-firing-00200611" target="_blank">dismissed by Trump</a> last year. “When they push the pause button on these things, they’re not delivering for the American people, and that, to me, is the problem.”</p> 
<p>Democrats have accused DHS Secretary Kristi Noem of deliberately attempting to stymie the OIG’s ongoing probes. In <a href="https://www.politico.com/document/duckworth-noem-letter" target="_blank">a letter sent to Noem</a> earlier this month, Sen. Tammy Duckworth (D-Ill.) cautioned that “repeated tacit threats from your Office of the Secretary to DHS OIG may have already succeeded in weakening DHS OIG’s operational independence.”</p> 
<p>That warning came after Duckworth met with Cuffari to discuss why her request for an independent investigation into use of force by federal agents during ICE’s “Operation Midway Blitz” in Chicago was denied. During the meeting, she wrote in the letter, Duckworth learned that DHS’s general counsel advised the OIG on several occasions that Noem has the power to halt its investigations.</p> 
<p>Cabinet secretaries are empowered by a 1978 law to prevent the OIG from carrying out audits or investigations if they determine the reviews could put national security at risk.</p> 
<p>“This broad authority effectively empowers you to select from a broad range of pretextual options to unilaterally prevent or halt any ‘independent’ DHS OIG investigation, regardless of your true intent,” Duckworth wrote.</p> 
<p>No DHS secretary has ever invoked the provision, Duckworth wrote in the letter.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-16T10:44:56-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>In South Texas, the GOP immigration hard line is now political kryptonite</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/15/south-texas-latino-republicans-immigration-00782129</link>
      <description>Texas Republicans bet on continuing to win over Latino voters. Then Trump began his aggressive deportation campaign.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-593e-de8a-a1fc-f97efab00001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ae/13/ca674b514278859253db6682b2ac/texas-daily-life-10531.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">David Goldman/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A U.S. Army Reserve soldier watches over the Rio Grande river separating Mexico, from the U.S., in Laredo, Texas, Oct. 14, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ae/13/ca674b514278859253db6682b2ac/texas-daily-life-10531.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson and Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson and Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Backlash to President Donald Trump’s immigration crackdown is putting vulnerable Republicans in a tough spot, forcing them to shift their tone to appease frustrated Hispanic voters — or risk losing key battleground seats.</p> 
<p>It’s a delicate pivot for Republicans in South Texas, who spent years taking a hardline approach on immigration and flipped historically blue districts in the process.</p> 
<p>Republican Rep. Monica De La Cruz, representing a majority-Hispanic district, has gone from calling for mass deportations to focusing on the “worst of the worst.” In lieu of expediting removals, she wants to create new visa categories for undocumented workers to fill jobs in construction and agriculture. And instead of slamming the Biden White House for its "border failure," she's setting up private meetings at the Trump White House to plead for temperance in immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>Rep. Tony Gonzales, whose district shares hundreds of miles with Mexico, wants his party to talk more about the border, and said he plans to “continue to advocate that the Republican Party needs to focus on convicted criminal illegal aliens” amid broad outrage over deportations of undocumented people with no proven risk to public safety.</p> 
<p>Like other Republicans, they are trying to slowly distance themselves from the massive immigration crackdown that has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270" target="_blank">quickly become political kryptonite for the GOP</a> — but without being seen as disloyal to the president or undercutting their previous positions.</p> 
<p>“President Trump made a promise, and he's kept that promise by securing the border. That was stage one,” De La Cruz said in an interview. “Now we're at stage two, which is having a conversation of true immigration reform.”</p> 
<p>Republicans’ efforts to change the conversation will test their ability to maintain, or even extend, Trump’s 2024 gains with Hispanic voters — and play a pivotal role in the fight for control of Congress in November. A slew of polls in recent weeks has shown many Hispanic voters across the country, repulsed by the Trump administration’s aggressive deportation campaign, are souring on the Republican president they supported to a historic degree in 2024.</p> 
<p>It’s a warning the White House appears to be taking seriously. In recent weeks, after the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by an immigration enforcement officer in Minneapolis, the White House has signaled openness to paring back its deportation operation. On Thursday, border czar Tom Homan announced the administration’s massive immigration surge in Minneapolis <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/homan-announces-end-to-minnesota-immigration-enforcement-surge-00777990" target="_blank">would come to a close</a>.</p> 
<p>Latino voters’ embrace of Trump was a political earthquake, and South Texas was the epicenter.</p> 
<p>De La Cruz’s district — which sprawls from the Rio Grande Valley on the U.S.-Mexico border up to the San Antonio suburbs — was represented by a Democrat in Congress for 120 years before De La Cruz won her seat in 2022. In 2024, Trump romped to an 18-point victory.</p> 
<p>The 15th Congressional District was among those redrawn by the Texas legislature’s redistricting gambit last year, offering De La Cruz an even more favorable electorate. But that bet relies heavily on Hispanic voters sticking with the GOP: Nearly 80 percent of the district identifies as Hispanic or Latino, and if those voters flip back to the Democratic Party or stay home, it could erase much of the new map’s intended friendliness to Republicans.</p> 
<p>“With the border secure and Latinos responding to ICE raids and government overreach, the districts that Republicans thought were their future a year ago are likely to be their undoing,” said Mike Madrid, a Republican strategist who is a frequent critic of Trump. “Hard to find another situation in the past 50 years where a political party has squandered a generational opportunity like this.”</p> 
<p>Flipping De La Cruz’s district is a top objective for House Democrats this cycle, who are salivating at the prospect of winning back Latino voters. She’ll face either Bobby Pulido, a Tejano music star with widespread name ID recruited by the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, or Ada Cuellar, an ER doctor who has an impressive penchant for fundraising.</p> 
<p>Local Republicans have begun sounding the alarm.</p> 
<p>Daniel Garza, president of the LIBRE Initiative, a grassroots conservative group based in South Texas, said “Biden’s border chaos” was directly responsible for Texas Republicans’ victories in recent election cycles, including De La Cruz’s, but that moving toward the other extreme — a harsh crackdown — could again dissuade Hispanic voters who might otherwise support the GOP.</p> 
<p>“We don't have to be a nation that has to decide between an ‘everybody-in’ or an ‘everybody-out’ approach,” Garza said. “I honestly feel that the counties across the entire Texan border shifted to the right because of the border chaos. … But this sort of everybody-out approach, I think, is also causing some reflection.”</p> 
<p>The immigration crackdown has wreaked havoc for the area’s business community. Greg LaMantia, who runs a major beer wholesaler in the region, said his company’s sales are down as a result of the raids. “You have people that are legal that are scared to death to get caught up in this fiasco and deported,” said LaMantia, who voted for Trump and has donated recently to both Republican and Democratic lawmakers. “It’s caused sales to go down, no doubt about it. It's chaos."</p> 
<p>Daniel Guerrero, CEO of the McAllen-based South Texas Builders Association, said rampant ICE activity has sent a shiver through the construction industry, leading to massive delays. He said ICE is notorious for following concrete trucks to job sites, then apprehending workers as they begin pouring a foundation, leaving half-poured concrete slabs.</p> 
<p>“The sentiment is pretty clear across the table, that nobody really expected this magnitude of enforcement,” said Guerrero, who voted for Trump and De La Cruz in 2024.</p> 
<p>He said the Hispanic Trump supporters he knows are souring on this administration, an observation <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/latino-voters-powered-trumps-comeback-now-theyre-turning-on-his-economy-00726548" target="_blank">supported by recent polling</a>. In the latest warning sign, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/republicans-hispanic-voters-texas-special-00763560" target="_blank">Latino voters helped a Democrat flip a reliably red seat</a> in Fort Worth last month. Taylor Rehmet, who picked up a state Senate seat in a special election, won about 4 out of 5 Hispanic votes <a href="https://votehub.com/2026/02/03/are-hispanic-voters-moving-back-toward-democrats/" target="_blank">across the district</a>, a massive 26-point improvement over Kamala Harris in 2024.</p> 
<p>Many Republicans are trying to steer the discussion around immigration to focus on how border crossings have dropped to historic lows under Trump — which they hope will remind Hispanic voters why they should stick with the GOP.</p> 
<p>“The Hispanic population gives President Trump and Republicans a lot of leeway with just how bad things were before and where they're at now,” said Gonzales, whose sprawling border district is majority Hispanic. “They have a lot of leeway to get a lot of runway, if you will.”</p> 
<p>De La Cruz successfully ran in 2024 on deportations and the “worst border security crisis in our nation's history.” Now she’s proposing <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/immigration-raids-restaurants-construction-visa-expansions-00754051" target="_blank">a new visa category, H-2C,</a> allowing employers like those in construction and hospitality to hire foreign workers. She also <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_4367?q=H.R.4367" target="_blank">introduced legislation</a> which would expand the H-2A visa category for seasonal agricultural workers.</p> 
<p>In recent weeks, De La Cruz said she has taken constituents to meet with the Labor Department, the White House and House Speaker Mike Johnson, pitching them on her bills and encouraging the administration to change its tact on immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>“There's limited resources, period. And we want those limited resources to be focused on the worst of the worst, the criminal immigrants that have come in,” De La Cruz said. “We have legal immigrants in our district who have work visas that they don't want to go out to work because some may have fear about the process that is currently being administered.”</p> 
<p>But De La Cruz’s shift in messaging has simultaneously earned skepticism from some industry leaders and frustration with the base, underscoring the political tightrope she must walk until November.</p> 
<p>Guerrero, the construction nonprofit leader, said he sensed political opportunism in De La Cruz’s newfound interest in helping his industry.</p> 
<p>“People feel abandoned because you never showed face, and now that there's an actual crisis, you want to show face?” Guerrero said. “It's like, dude, it's a little too late, man.”</p> 
<p>The MAGA base, meanwhile, doesn’t love the shift, either. Patricio County GOP Chair Rex Warner thinks De La Cruz has become too soft on deportations. “I align with some of it, but very little,” he said.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misspelled Ada Cuellar’s name.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shapiro grows his donor network ahead of 2028</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/shapiro-donor-network-fundraising-00779879</link>
      <description>The Pennsylvania governor is using his book tour and his reelection bid as a way to expand his donor list.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5494-d3b5-addf-f4d40a100000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e1/c2/08dc2fa545ceaea355d1af9898be/governor-josh-shapiro-in-conversation-at-92ny-14176.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photo by Evan Agostini/Invision/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro is raising campaign cash on the side of his book tour.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e1/c2/08dc2fa545ceaea355d1af9898be/governor-josh-shapiro-in-conversation-at-92ny-14176.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro is using his book tour and 2026 reelection campaign to further build out a national fundraising network that could prove quite useful in a potential 2028 run.</p> 
<p>The governor held a fundraising event over lunch while visiting Massachusetts for his book tour last month, two people familiar with the planning for it confirmed — making it at least the third fundraiser he attended in the last year in the deep-blue state with deep-pocketed donors who have long bankrolled presidential contenders. One of the others was held at the home of Jewish philanthropist and New England Patriots president Jonathan Kraft in April, details of which have not previously been reported. Shapiro attended <a href="https://secure.actblue.com/donate/071925nantucket" target="_blank">another on Nantucket</a>, a summer fundraising mecca, in July, according to an attendee and invitations obtained by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>They add to an extensive list of networking events for the possible White House aspirant who’s long been a prolific fundraiser within and beyond Pennsylvania.</p> 
<p>He amassed $23 million in 2025 with the help of $2.5 million from former New York City Mayor Michael Bloomberg; $1 million from a Soros family PAC, $500,000 from James and Kathryn Murdoch, the left-leaning son and daughter in law of Rupert Murdoch; and over $120,000 from Kraft and his father, New England Patriots owner Robert Kraft. That’s helped him build a $30 million war chest to unleash this year against his likely GOP opponent, state Treasurer Stacy Garrity, who raised nearly $1.5 million last year and had $1 million in the bank to start 2026.</p> 
<p>His book tour side-hustle comes as several of Shapiro’s would-be rivals for the Democratic nomination in 2028 take donor meetings across the country as they navigate their own reelection bids and start laying the groundwork for White House runs.</p> 
<p>Shapiro routinely dismisses talk of 2028 in public, keeping a laser focus on his reelection bid and on his efforts to help Democrats down the ballot.</p> 
<p>“No one should be looking past these midterms,” the governor recently told reporters in Washington, D.C., who were peppering him with hypotheticals.</p> 
<p>Sources say he is just as disciplined behind closed doors: Shapiro has kept his pitch focused on his leadership in purple Pennsylvania and how Democrats should be centering pocketbook issues in the midterms, while declining to engage with questions about his future beyond 2026, according to two people who attended donor events with Shapiro last year.</p> 
<p>“The smartest thing Shapiro and other folks on the ballot in 2026 can do right now is say ‘I’m running for reelection right now and I’m in the middle of the fight.’ [It] makes ‘26 a nice little audition for their eventual 2028 runs,” said Alex Hoffman, a Democratic strategist and donor adviser.</p> 
<p>His out-of-state networking is already paying off. Shapiro raked in over $700,000 from prominent donors in Massachusetts alone in 2025, including $260,000 from construction magnate John Fish and $50,000 from telecommunications tycoon Robert Hale. He also hauled in cash from Hollywood bigwigs and tech titans, including $100,000 from Sony film executive Tom Rothman and $200,000 from Ripple co-founder Chris Larsen.</p> 
<p>But the governor’s expansive donor pool is also drawing scrutiny. Garrity has called on Shapiro to <a href="https://www.pennlive.com/politics/2026/02/garrity-says-shapiro-should-return-over-2m-from-billionaire-mentioned-26k-times-in-epstein-files.html" target="_blank">return over $2 million</a> his campaign has taken over the years from billionaire LinkedIn co-founder Reid Hoffman, who is <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/02/09/tech-leaders-epstein-records-silicon-valley-sergey-brin-thiel-sinofsky-reid-hoffman-musk-gates.html" target="_blank">referenced repeatedly in the Jeffrey Epstein files</a>. Hoffman gave $500,000 to Shapiro last year. Shapiro also received $50,000 from New York Giants co-owner Steve Tisch, who is <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/7040342/2026/02/12/steve-tisch-jeffrey-epstein-new-york-giants/" target="_blank">also mentioned in the Epstein files</a>, as is <a href="https://www.boston.com/news/local-news/2026/02/04/jeffrey-epstein-wanted-robert-kraft-to-hire-his-lawyer-amid-patriots-owners-prostitution-case-documents-show/" target="_blank">Robert Kraft</a>. Both <a href="https://x.com/reidhoffman/status/1989483179716075874?s=20" target="_blank">Hoffman</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/7040342/2026/02/12/steve-tisch-jeffrey-epstein-new-york-giants/" target="_blank">Tisch</a> have issued statements distancing themselves from the late convict.</p> 
<p>“Stacy Garrity should stop playing politics with the Epstein files. Donald Trump is mentioned in the files over 5,000 times. Is she going to ask him to rescind his endorsement?” Shapiro spokesperson Manuel Bonder said in a statement. Bonder declined comment on the governor’s fundraisers.</p> 
<p>He'll need to keep building out that network. Shapiro has benefited from what longtime Pennsylvania Democratic strategist Neil Oxman described as “institutional donors” in the state who’ve given to successive Democratic governors. But of “the thousands of people who raise money nationally, he probably knows a fraction of them. He has some [national] recognition, but he’s not Gavin Newsom. He’s not the Clintons.”</p> 
<p>Shapiro also won’t be able to use the gobs of money he’s raised for his state campaign account to fund a run for federal office, leaving him at an initial disadvantage against other potential 2028ers who are already <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/newsletter/2026/02/democrats-eying-2028-rake-in-the-cash-and-build-their-donor-lists-00763383" target="_blank">squirreling away millions of dollars into federal leadership committees</a>, super PACs and congressional campaign accounts that can be converted when the time comes.</p> 
<p>“That’s why sometimes it’s hard to run for office when you have to run for another office,” Oxman said.</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fetterman on ICE, Israel and identifying as a Democrat | The Conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/13/fetterman-on-ice-israel-and-identifying-as-a-democrat-the-conversation-1910882</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-53df-d3b5-addf-f3df3c310000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 09:56:10 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">Fetterman on ICE, Israel and identifying as a Democrat | The Conversation</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6389143915112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/c56c6757-74eb-4779-a63a-f0a9dc929bbf/d27fb1e8-f674-4644-85ae-6bcf7cb167ea/main.mp4" src="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/c56c6757-74eb-4779-a63a-f0a9dc929bbf/60946689-aa37-4319-8fc2-650a657e4d4b/1280x720/match/image.jpg">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
