<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 21:29:52 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-14T22:16:27-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Tim Scott postpones Senate Banking crypto vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/scott-delays-senate-banking-crypto-vote-00730162</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bf7b-dd3c-a5df-ff7b20020000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 21:29:52 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> is abandoning plans to hold a vote Thursday on landmark cryptocurrency legislation amid surprise new opposition from a leading crypto firm and uncertainty about the whip counts on both sides of the aisle.</p> 
<p>The South Carolina Republican’s move to punt a scheduled markup comes after the largest U.S. crypto exchange, Coinbase, <a href="https://x.com/brian_armstrong/status/2011545247105355865?s=20" target="_blank">came out against the latest draft</a> of the bill Wednesday afternoon, thrusting the effort into chaos less than 24 hours ahead of a scheduled markup.</p> 
<p>“I’ve spoken with leaders across the crypto industry, the financial sector, and my Democratic and Republican colleagues, and everyone remains at the table working in good faith,” Scott said in a statement. “This bill reflects months of serious bipartisan negotiations and real input from innovators, investors, and law enforcement. The goal is to deliver clear rules of the road that protect consumers, strengthen our national security, and ensure the future of finance is built in the United States.”</p> 
<p>Scott has been working for months negotiate with a bloc of crypto-friendly Senate Democrats on Senate Banking, but they remained opposed to the bill as of late Wednesday, meaning it was unlikely to draw bipartisan support if he forged ahead with a markup. Some Republicans also had outstanding concerns with the bill.</p> 
<p>Coinbase CEO Brian Armstrong wrote on X Wednesday afternoon that the bill as written “would be materially worse than the current status quo.”</p> 
<p>“We’d rather have no bill than a bad bill,” he said. “Hopefully we can all get to a better draft.”</p> 
<p>Coinbase has led the crypto industry’s Washington influence efforts in recent years, but other digital asset firms pushed back on social media after Armstrong’s post on Wednesday, saying the bill remained workable and pushing for it to advance.</p> 
<p>Armstrong said the bill would erode the Commodity Futures Trading Commission’s authority, “stifling innovation and making it subservient to the” Securities and Exchange Commission.</p> 
<p>He also raised concerns about potential “amendments that would kill rewards on stablecoins, allowing banks to ban their competition.” Coinbase offers a rewards program that pays an annual percentage yield to premium subscribers who hold so-called stablecoins — an arrangement that banks are pushing to ban as part of the bill.</p> 
<p>The banking lobby’s position gained steam from lawmakers on both sides of the aisle in recent days, and it looked increasingly likely that provisions cracking down on stablecoin rewards programs would make it into the bill during a markup. Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/466203" data-person-id="466203">Angela Alsobrooks</a> (D-Md.) were preparing a slate of amendments aimed at addressing concerns raised by banks, which have said that allowing stablecoin holders to earn yield risks sparking deposit flight.</p> 
<p>It is unclear when Scott will try again to hold a markup.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66891" data-person-id="66891">Cynthia Lummis</a> (R-Wyo.), who chairs a Senate Banking subcommittee on crypto, said in a statement that lawmakers “have spent thousands of hours working in good faith to deliver a bill that offers the digital asset industry the clarity it needs to thrive on U.S. soil and solidify America's leadership in financial innovation for generations to come.”</p> 
<p>“Today's response from some in the industry proves they just are not ready, and while I am deeply disappointed, I am committed to taking this feedback and partnering with the industry to deliver a product that helps them thrive,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans point fingers at Democrats, Biden at first Jan. 6 committee hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/republicans-hold-first-jan-6-hearing-00730206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beb7-dcbd-afbb-feff17f90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:59:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans used the first hearing of the new committee to investigate the Capitol attacks on Jan 6, 2021, to explore the Biden-era investigation into the pipe bombs left at the Democratic and Republican National Committee headquarters the day before riots — and relitigate conspiracy theories and grievances.</p> 
<p>It illustrated how Republicans plan to use their new select subcommittee and how far apart the two parties remain five years later in their accounts of the day a violent mob stormed the Capitol to contest the results of the 2020 presidential election.</p> 
<p>Rep. Barry Loudermilk (R-Ga.), the chair of the new GOP-led panel, questioned why it took nearly half a decade for law enforcement to identify a suspect in the pipe bombs case, when the Trump Justice Department apprehended the alleged perpetrator, Brian Cole, late last year.</p> 
<p>“How is it that the Biden-Wray FBI was able to flawlessly execute a cellular dragnet to capture the information and eventually apprehend those trespassing at the Capitol, but failed to exercise the same investigative technique into the pipe bomber,” Loudermilk said, referring to President Joe Biden and his FBI chief, Christopher Wray.</p> 
<p>“How is it that the [Democratic]-controlled select committee to investigate January 6th managed to write a final report in which they cover more than 700 pages and 8 chapters without ever mentioning the pipe bombs until an appendix in the back of the report?,” Loudermilk added.</p> 
<p>Michael Romano, the former deputy chief of the Justice Department’s Capitol Siege Section called to testify by the Democrats, said the pipe bombs investigation was particularly difficult, given the “needle-in-a-haystack nature of the evidence.”</p> 
<p>At one point, Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Tex.) physically brandished a binder that appeared to be the report of the previous Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee in his hands, calling that panel’s work a “total sham.”</p> 
<p>And Rep. Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) noted that Stewart Rhodes, a leader of the Oath Keepers, was in attendance for the hearing. Rhodes had been convicted of seditious conspiracy before he was pardoned by President Donald Trump, along with other rioters who stormed the Capitol on Jan. 6.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee who also served on the Democratic-led Jan 6. panel, called Cole’s apprehension a “rare bright spot” in the last year of federal law under the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Still, Raskin maintained that Cole voted for Trump twice and believed the conspiracy championed by Trump and his allies that Biden unfairly won the 2020 election. He also questioned whether Trump’s sweeping pardons for the Capitol rioters<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2026/01/06/jan-6-pipe-bomber-trump-pardon-column-00712039" target="_blank"><u>included Cole</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“Nothing will ever whitewash the indelible facts of that day,” Raskin said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embarrassing floor meltdown has House Republicans questioning their leaders</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/embarrassing-floor-meltdown-has-house-republicans-questioning-their-leaders-00730119</link>
      <description>A group of pro-labor holdouts handed the GOP its latest setback and underscored the tough path for party-line legislation this year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beb8-dd3c-a5df-fefa9c260001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:57:51 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4c/98/fb19fba3415eaf593527ff6105fc/u-s-congress-16351.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mike Johnson (center) is the speaker, but members are questioning the leadership of Tom Emmer (left) and Steve Scalise (right) after Tuesday's implosion.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4c/98/fb19fba3415eaf593527ff6105fc/u-s-congress-16351.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Frustrations are growing among House Republicans as their majority dwindles and agenda sputters — and it’s not just Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> who is feeling the heat.</p> 
<p>Members were aghast after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-defections-labor-bill-overtime-rules-00725803" target="_blank">stunning Tuesday night meltdown</a> on the House floor, where opposition from a handful of GOP members led to the defeat of one labor bill and the postponement of three others. Some questioned why the Republican floor and whip teams — under the direction of Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> and Majority Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227580" data-person-id="227580">Tom Emmer</a>, respectively — had allowed the votes to be scheduled.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) was among the members who voted no Tuesday. He said he told leaders about his opposition and questioned why they are “bringing bills to the floor they don't have the votes for, other than to think that they're going to strong-arm people.”</p> 
<p>“I think it's really a question for them as to where they're getting their math,” he added.</p> 
<p>The rising concerns about the GOP whip operation come as the party struggles to hang onto its razor-thin voting majority. Since the beginning of the year, Georgia Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene resigned, Rep. Doug LaMalfa of California <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">suddenly died</a> and a spate of medical-related absences and family emergencies have plagued the party.</p> 
<p>The GOP currently has a 218-213 majority if all members are present and voting — which day-to-day is a huge “if.”</p> 
<p>Leaving the floor after the failed vote Tuesday night, Johnson insisted, “We're totally in control of the House.”</p> 
<p>Asked in an interview if GOP leaders have a whipping problem, Scalise said, “We ultimately have a vote count problem with the limited number of members.”</p> 
<p>“You have absences, you have other things — I mean, we just had a member pass away,” he added. “It's going to be a tough road, but we're going to keep moving our agenda.”</p> 
<p>Still, the Tuesday episode led to a significant waste of precious floor time for House Republicans as they try to convince voters they’re working to address cost-of-living issues ahead of the midterms and Johnson continues to insist on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/johnson-pledges-to-push-ahead-on-another-party-line-megabill-00729264" target="_blank">pursuing a party-line policy bill</a> this year — a follow-up to last year’s tax-cuts-focused GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Top leaders did see some success last year eking out tough votes, calling the question and then cajoling and cutting deals with holdouts before bringing the gavel down. One procedural vote for the GOP megabill last year was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/02/congress/longest-vote-ever-00438166" target="_blank">held open for more than nine hours</a> while leaders and White House officials negotiated a deal securing the legislation’s passage.</p> 
<p>“I have a magic power of being able to whip everybody at the end, and it usually works,” Johnson told reporters Wednesday.</p> 
<p>But that didn’t happen Tuesday, when leaders had to give up on a bill that would rewrite wage rules so employers would not have to pay overtime rates for training in some cases. Pro-labor GOP Reps. Fitzpatrick, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478639" data-person-id="478639">Rob Bresnahan</a> (Pa.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/81211" data-person-id="81211">Nick LaLota</a> (N.Y.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew</a> (N.J.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51627" data-person-id="51627">Chris Smith</a> (N.J.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/26827" data-person-id="26827">Riley Moore</a> (W.Va.) all voted against the legislation.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51135" data-person-id="51135">Pete Sessions</a> (R-Texas), a former Rules Committee chair, largely reserved judgment about the floor chaos. But he did note that “in the past, we focused on an entirely different process than I believe is done today.”</p> 
<p>Other GOP members granted anonymity to speak candidly about the episode were less restrained.</p> 
<p>“They didn’t even whip the fucking bill,” one House Republican said. “It was unbelievably dumb and unbelievably reckless,” said another.</p> 
<p>Members of the whip team led by Emmer checked in with key Republicans during House votes the night before about how they planned to vote on the labor bill. They heard concerns from some members, but not many hard "nos," according to three people granted anonymity to describe the internal process. A spokesperson for Emmer did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>“I let them know,” Moore said. “We need to be standing up for the American worker, not making it more difficult.”</p> 
<p>Van Drew said he didn’t decide to vote against the bill until the day of the vote and did not inform leaders in advance, but he also said they never asked about his view on it.</p> 
<p>“Our majority is so tight — it's a problem,” he said. “They should have whipped it, No. 1. And then secondly, my bad. I should have let them know, even if it was only a half-hour before.”</p> 
<p>The heads-up likely wouldn’t have made a difference. Other Republicans directly warned Emmer and Scalise of the labor problem, according to four people granted anonymity to describe private conversations about the legislation.</p> 
<p>Scalise said in the interview that when a bill is unanimously approved by Republicans on a committee — as was the case for the overtime bill — “then we're going to make our best effort to get it passed.”</p> 
<p>“You don't want days like yesterday,” he said. “But … on the bills that are the top priorities of our agenda, which we make very clear well in advance, we're moving those bills. We have moved them, and we've got a lot more we're going to be bringing this year, and we will pass those bills.”</p> 
<p>In other words, Scalise gave no indication GOP leaders plan to abandon their get-close-and-roll-the-dice approach in 2026.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, Johnson’s leadership team knew there would be some GOP absences, and at least some idea of the intraparty opposition, according to four other people with direct knowledge of the matter, but they believed they could wrangle enough votes to pass the scheduled bills.</p> 
<p>Among the Republicans leaders tried to work over was Smith — one of the longest-serving members of the House and one who has long held pro-labor positions. Smith held his ground, saying he had made commitments to people in his district and he was not going to vote for the legislation, according to three people who heard the conversation.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters Wednesday Smith was among a group of members “that didn't let us know in advance, and it was nobody's mistake.”</p> 
<p>“He was with his wife in an oncology appointment all morning, so he wasn't here to inform us,” he said. “But not a big deal, just part of the process.”</p> 
<p>The episode underscored how GOP leaders are effectively unable to move pro-business and anti-union labor legislation, a key plank of the party agenda. The slim majority allowed the small band of pro-labor Republicans to corner Johnson late last year, signing a Democratic-led discharge petition forcing a vote on a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-passes-bill-federal-workers-bargaining-rights-00687594" target="_blank">bill protecting federal worker unions</a>.</p> 
<p>Democrats are eager to push other discharge petitions on labor matters in the wake of the recess successes, while the GOP is unlikely to bring the issue to the floor themselves.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think you’re going to see another labor bill on the floor this year,” another House Republican said.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Judiciary Committee schedules Bondi testimony for Feb. 11</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/bondi-set-to-testify-00729891</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-be8e-d6ec-a99b-ffef40780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:16:03 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi will appear before the House Judiciary Committee Feb. 11, Rep. Jim Jordan, who chairs the panel, said in an interview Wednesday night.</p> 
<p>Her appearance, which had been postponed due to the government shutdown, comes at a perilous time for the Justice Department. Bipartisan lawmakers have criticized her agency's handling of the release of files in the case against Jeffrey Epstein as mandated by Congress under law and now will have to answer for the legality of President Donald Trump's actions in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Decisions under Bondi's watch to prosecute the president’s political adversaries, including former FBI Director James Comey and New York Attorney General Letitia James, have also drawn scrutiny after Trump ordered Bondi to pursue them. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slotkin says she is under investigation for November military video</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/slotkin-investigation-trump-00728241</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd66-d6ec-a99b-ff6f8eaf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:16:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Elissa Slotkin on Wednesday confirmed she is under federal investigation for her participation in a November video urging military members not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/SenatorSlotkin/status/2011472739693912187?s=20" target="_blank">In a video response</a> to the investigation, the Michigan Democrat said President Donald Trump was weaponizing the federal government against those who disagree with him. Slotkin is the latest video participant to face investigation from the administration.</p> 
<p>“To be clear, this is the president's playbook,” Slotkin said. “Truth doesn't matter. Facts don't matter, and anyone who disagrees with him becomes an enemy, and he then weaponizes the federal government against them. It's legal intimidation and physical intimidation meant to get you to shut up.”</p> 
<p>Slotkin, who was recruited by the CIA as a Middle East analyst and served three tours in Iraq, was among five other Democratic military veterans <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2558895077819811" target="_blank">featured in the video</a>, including Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.) and Reps. Maggie Goodlander (N.H.), Jason Crow (Colo.), Chris Deluzio (Pa.) and Chrissy Houlahan (Pa.).</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">Trump at the time called the lawmakers' actions</a> “seditious” and said they should face trial.</p> 
<p>Crow said he had been contacted by the Trump administration as well about the video.</p> 
<p>"Donald Trump is using the Department of Justice as a weapon to harass and intimidate me in particular, as well as the other members who filmed that video," he told reporters. "We are not going to stop it from us doing our job." </p> 
<p>Kelly this week <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/mark-kelly-pete-hegseth-lawsuit-00722382" target="_blank">filed a lawsuit</a> against Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth and other senior military leaders after his own investigation was announced and the Defense Department <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/hegseth-kelly-punish-video-00710555" target="_blank">began to take steps</a> to downgrade his retirement rank.</p> 
<p>Slotkin <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/13/us/politics/slotkin-pirro-trump-justice-dept-video.html" target="_blank">first told The New York Times</a> she had learned about the investigation from the office of Jeanine Pirro, the U.S. attorney for the District of Columbia. Pirro’s office told POLITICO it does not confirm or deny the existence of federal investigations.</p> 
<p>Following Trump’s response to the November video, Slotkin on Wednesday said that threats against her and her family “went through the roof.”</p> 
<p>“We had over 1,000 threats come in. Over 100 were credible and are being investigated,” she said. “I went on 24/7 security from Capitol Police. I had a bomb threat at my house. My parents were swatted in the middle of the night, and my siblings had cop cars placed in their driveways, and now [Trump] is using his political appointees at the FBI and the Department of Justice to follow through with his threats.”</p> 
<p>Slotkin said that freedom of speech is “worth fighting for.”</p> 
<p>“Right now, speaking out against the abuse of power is the most patriotic thing we can do,” she said.</p> 
<p><i>Nick Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-14T14:36:03-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>GOP scrambles to kill Venezuela war powers resolution</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/senate-war-powers-scramble-00728197</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd64-d6ec-a99b-ff6d11060000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 11:44:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate GOP leaders are working overtime to quash a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_SJRES_98" target="_blank">resolution</a> requiring President Donald Trump to come to Congress before taking additional military action in Venezuela. They don’t yet know if they have the votes.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said Wednesday they are in conversations with rank-and-file GOP members, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">five of whom voted with Democrats</a> to advance the measure last week. The administration has offered “assurances,” he said, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/admin-works-to-flip-republicans-on-war-powers-vote-00723922" target="_blank">by stating there are no U.S. troops currently in Venezuela</a> and no plan to send them in.</p> 
<p>“These are consequential, big decisions and people want to feel like they're honoring their obligations to the people that they represent and their own views on some of these issues,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans will first vote on a procedural off-ramp turning off the “privilege” of the resolution, Thune confirmed in a later interview. Under that strategy, senators will be asked to concur in a point of order that the resolution should not be subject to a simple-majority vote since there are no ongoing hostilities.</p> 
<p>One of the five, Missouri Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a>, told reporters earlier Wednesday that he would support that proposal if it is offered, pointing to Secretary of State Marco Rubio's pledge to abide by notification procedures if the administration sends in troops.</p> 
<p>Besides Hawley, GOP leaders would need to win one more of the four remaining Republicans who previously voted to advance the resolution. Thune said in the interview it was "to be determined" if leaders could win the necessary votes.</p> 
<p>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) said Wednesday she is going to continue to support the war powers resolution, while Sen. Rand Paul (R-Ky.) said he would also vote against the point of order. "I don't think they have the votes right now," he said about leadership's legislative gambit.</p> 
<p>Sen. Todd Young (R-Ind.), a key swing vote, said wouldn't say how he planned to vote on the procedural question but praised the Trump administration for being responsive to Congress' concerns.</p> 
<p><i>Connor O'Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hillary Clinton defies subpoena, skips deposition in congressional Epstein inquiry</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/hillary-clinton-skips-deposition-00728000</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd3a-d22e-a1db-bf3f7fee0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 11:20:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Oversight and Government Reform Committee will vote next week to hold former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in contempt of Congress after she defied a subpoena and failed to appear Wednesday morning for her scheduled deposition.</p> 
<p>It follows former President Bill Clinton's refusal the day before to comply with a subpoena and sit for an interview with lawmakers as part of their investigation into Jeffrey Epstein — an outcome that resulted in Comer's pledge to hold him in contempt of Congress, too.</p> 
<p>“I think what's most disappointing to the Oversight Committee is the fact that we have, in good faith, negotiated with the Clintons’ attorney for five months,” Comer (R-Ky.) told reporters. “We felt like Hillary Clinton could offer some information on [Epstein associate Ghislaine] Maxwell.”</p> 
<p>Comer said his panel would vote on contempt for both Clintons during a markup slated for next Wednesday, which would then be brought to the House floor. A contempt vote could have implications ranging from symbolic to criminal. But the Justice Department has already shown an interest in prosecuting President Donald Trump's political adversaries, signaling there could be grave consequences for the couple — especially Hillary Clinton, who ran against Trump in 2016.</p> 
<p>In a public letter to Comer sent Tuesday, Bill and Hillary Clinton argued the subpoenas issued to them over the summer were invalid and maintained the exercise was designed to embarrass and put them in prison. They also said they have already given Congress whatever information they have about Epstein, the late convicted sex offender with whom Bill Clinton had a documented rapport.</p> 
<p>Comer also said Wednesday his panel would depose Maxwell, Epstein's co-conspirator who is now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in the sex trafficking scheme. He had previously indicated he did not intend to call her up to sit for an interview after issuing her a subpoena because her legal team had indicated she would not cooperate with their questioning.</p> 
<p>A committee spokesperson said the panel had reached out to Maxwell's attorney to schedule a deposition as a result of lawmakers' renewed interest, but is still expected she would invoke her Fifth Amendment rights. The deposition would require members and staff to visit Texas, where Maxwell remains incarcerated. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: More floor meltdowns threaten funding bills</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/gop-floor-meltdowns-appropriations-funding-bills-00727200</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bae8-dca0-ad9b-fbe957610000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders are losing control of the floor to non-stop intraparty revolts ahead of the rapidly approaching deadline to avoid another shutdown.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson needs his ranks united in order to keep federal operations afloat after Jan. 30. But the stark reality is settling in that Republicans are stuck with an essentially unworkable margin that could derail not only their government funding plans but their entire legislative agenda.</p> 
<p><b>— Hard math warning signs:</b> “We’re totally in control of the House,” Johnson insisted Tuesday. Yet <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-defections-labor-bill-overtime-rules-00725803" target="_blank">six Republican defectors</a> sunk a bill earlier that afternoon designed to incentivize employers to offer more training and education programs — at the expense of having to offer some overtime pay, Lawrence Ukenye reports.</p> 
<p>The measure’s collapse led leadership to scrap scheduled votes on two other labor-related bills Tuesday evening. Leaders are now expected to cancel consideration of yet another measure slated for Thursday — related to <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/07/house-advances-joint-employer-portable-benefits-bills-00470942" target="_blank">franchise stores’ liability for employee working conditions</a> — that Republicans privately say will also fail.</p> 
<p>It comes as Republicans have been dealing with a series of absences tightening their already threadbare majority. Rep. Jim Baird (R-Ind.) has returned after recovering from a recent car crash, but Reps. Derrick Van Orden (R-Wis.) and Greg Murphy (R-N.C.) will not be in Washington for at least the rest of the week, adding up to a harrowing single-vote margin for the speaker. They’re also running a deficit following the sudden death last week of Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.). </p> 
<p>None of this bodes well for Wednesday's floor vote to advance the State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services funding package, as rule votes are typically party-line affairs.</p> 
<p><b>— The Homeland fight:</b> Republican leaders are on a separate uphill climb to reach a deal with Democrats on the fiscal 2026 spending bill for DHS, which stalled after an ICE agent shot and killed a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis last week.</p> 
<p>Top Democrats are feverishly working to put new guardrails on immigration enforcement agencies and curb President Donald Trump’s immigration agenda. They’re facing the reality that the only way to do so is by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552" target="_blank">working through the process to fund DHS</a>.</p> 
<p>They’re hoping that Republicans who also have hesitations about the DHS bill will team up with them on provisions to enforce new rules for ICE agents, like requiring them to use body cameras and banning masks.</p> 
<p>It’s unclear, however, what concessions GOP leaders are willing to make, as there are unsavory results for each party if lawmakers can’t strike a deal. Nobody wants an extended stopgap funding measure that maintains the DHS status quo without new funding levels and policy changes.</p> 
<p>“We’re trying to work with our colleagues. I know they’re trying to get a bill. But I’m very sensitive to the political challenges they have on this particular bill,” House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) told reporters this week.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— GOP mulls war powers off-ramp: </b>Senate Republicans are discussing whether to use a procedural maneuver to effectively quash the Venezuela war powers resolution — challenging the resolution’s "privilege." Under that scenario, Republicans would call up a vote on a point of order that the resolution shouldn’t enjoy a privileged status because troops are not currently engaged in hostilities. If it is approved it would effectively kick the underlying war powers resolution off the floor agenda.</p> 
<p><b>— Jan. 6 committee hearing: </b>House Judiciary’s select subcommittee on Jan. 6 will have its first hearing at 2 p.m. Wednesday. The panel is expected to scrutinize the investigations into the pipe bombs left near the Democratic and Republican National Committee headquarters the day before the Capitol attack in 2021. </p> 
<p>Witnesses will include Chris Piehota, a former FBI special agent; John Nantz, a former FBI special agent; and Thomas Speciale, a former senior adviser for the Office of the Director of National Intelligence.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu, Katherine Tully-McManus, Jordain Carney and Lawrence Ukenye contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Abolish ICE’? Many Democrats are ready to fund it — with conditions</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552</link>
      <description>It's not clear a Homeland Security funding bill can get done, but furious negotiations are underway.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b99c-d65c-affb-bb9f90ce0009</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/29/4c/79c6270d401e88e2a9e946e9761b/u-s-congress-30098.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Top Democratic leaders, including California Rep. Pete Aguilar, say they want to restrain ICE — not defund it.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/29/4c/79c6270d401e88e2a9e946e9761b/u-s-congress-30098.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>New calls to “defund ICE” are reverberating through the Democratic Party following <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/minneapolis-republicans-democrats-dig-in-heels-00721471" target="_blank">last week’s deadly shooting</a> by a federal agent in Minneapolis. Behind the scenes, top Democrats are feverishly working to fund the agency — with strings attached.</p> 
<p>The mismatch between the anti-ICE rhetoric and the actions of Democratic appropriators reflects a Catch-22 of congressional power: The only way lawmakers can put guardrails on the controversial agency and curb President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda at this moment is to hand it billions of taxpayer dollars.</p> 
<p>As they negotiate fiscal 2026 funding for the Department of Homeland Security with Republicans ahead of a Jan. 30 shutdown deadline, Democrats are demanding new rules for DHS agents, such as forcing them to use body cameras, refrain from wearing masks and go through more extensive training.</p> 
<p>Even as <a href="https://d3nkl3psvxxpe9.cloudfront.net/documents/econtoplines_YpmxDW2.pdf" target="_blank">new polling fielded after</a> the fatal Jan. 7 shooting of Renee Good shows that a plurality of voters back ICE’s elimination, top Democrats on Capitol Hill are seeking to restrain the agency under Trump’s leadership — not disband it.</p> 
<p>“House Democrats want accountability and oversight of ICE,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/226960" data-person-id="226960">Pete Aguilar</a> of California, the No. 3 Democratic leader, told reporters Tuesday. “They should have to continue to testify to Congress as to what they are doing. But more importantly, we need to look out for the American people right now. They are terrorizing people in the streets of this country.”</p> 
<p>Among the rank-and-file, there is also a deep desire to rein in the agency. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189828" data-person-id="189828">Darren Soto</a> (D-Fla.), deputy chair of the Congressional Hispanic Caucus, said in an interview his group supports “reforms” for the agency.</p> 
<p>“It's not the CHC's position that we're terminating ICE,” Soto said. “But there is a culture of violence that's happening that does need to be addressed.”</p> 
<p>The Congressional Progressive Caucus, meanwhile, announced Tuesday it had “adopted an official position” opposing new DHS funding “unless there are meaningful and significant reforms to immigration enforcement practices.”</p> 
<p>It’s not clear what GOP leaders are willing to accept in return for the Democratic votes that will be necessary to pass any DHS funding bill. They have not publicly ruled out new rules for ICE, despite equating Democrats’ demands with support for lax immigration policies.</p> 
<p>“Understand, what happened last week gave them more things to yell about,” House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> told reporters this week, referring to Democrats’ response to the shooting. “But they've been against ICE — and frankly, they've been for open borders, more importantly — for years as well.”</p> 
<p>Part of a calculation for both sides is that the alternatives to a negotiated compromise are unsavory for each party. Democratic lawmakers are in no mood to default to a lengthy stopgap funding patch that would maintain the status quo on immigration enforcement and give the Trump administration more leeway to decide how the money is spent. And if Republicans refuse to enact restraints, they warn, funding for DHS could lapse altogether in a few weeks.</p> 
<p>“The question is for Republicans: Are they willing to shut down the government simply to endorse the most lawless Department of Homeland Security in the history of the country?” Connecticut Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a>, the top Democrat on the Homeland Security funding panel, said on NBC’s “Meet the Press” over the weekend.</p> 
<p>Despite the tough rhetoric, Murphy showed a willingness to compromise in comments to reporters this week. Appropriators, he said, are “not going to write a comprehensive immigration enforcement reform bill” within the DHS funding measure.</p> 
<p>“But in every bill there's language on how our money is spent. And I want to make sure that our money is spent lawfully,” he continued. “So yes, we're having conversations about how we can pass a bill — but a bill that makes sure that ICE is operating legally.”</p> 
<p>One of the challenges for lawmakers is that Republicans already gave ICE billions of dollars within the party-line tax and spending package they enacted over the summer. The “big, beautiful bill” included $75 billion for the agency over the following decade, above and beyond the nearly $11 billion it was granted in the fiscal year that ended in September.</p> 
<p>“It's important to understand that a lot of the funding that's being unleashed on the American people in such extreme ways right now was provided not through the traditional appropriations process,” House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> told reporters this week.</p> 
<p>In spite of the major roadblocks to clinching a bipartisan funding deal, there are lawmakers on both sides of the aisle who are interested in putting at least some fetters on immigration enforcement agencies.</p> 
<p>The day after the fatal shooting in Minnesota, GOP Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska said footage of the killing was “deeply disturbing” and called for “policy changes to help prevent future tragedies” that would ensure ICE agents work “safely — and with empathy and respect for human life.”</p> 
<p>Both Democrats and Republicans in the Senate objected to moving forward this week with the DHS funding bill, House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) said, forcing it to be stripped from a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2026/01/13/congress-to-reject-trump-global-health-cuts-00723037" target="_blank">planned multibill package</a> at the 11th hour.</p> 
<p>“This one's tricky, just simply because of the political situation,” Cole told reporters. “We're trying to work with our colleagues. I know they're trying to get a bill. But I'm very sensitive to the political challenges they have on this particular bill.”</p> 
<p>Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) also acknowledged this week that “obviously the agency and some of its actions have raised questions lately,” adding that while a deal on DHS funding hasn’t yet been notched, “it doesn’t mean it won't be eventually.”</p> 
<p>Even before the shooting in Minnesota, lawmakers in both parties had <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/dhs-reprogramming-crackdown-00713569" target="_blank">agreed to new limits</a> on the Trump administration’s ability to redirect DHS money to purposes other than what Congress prescribes.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/177013" data-person-id="177013">Mark Amodei</a>, the Nevada Republican who chairs the Homeland Security funding panel, told reporters last week that House and Senate appropriators are crafting the spending measure to make it “harder to make the money mobile.”</p> 
<p>He called the Trump administration’s penchant for shifting around cash “bullshit” and acknowledged that Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem would not be fond of the new restrictions.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, Amodei struck an upbeat note on the negotiations, saying the DHS bill is “progressing nicely.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP tees up 2 amendment votes on latest funding package</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/amendment-votes-appropriations-funding-package-chip-roy-00726560</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b994-d65c-affb-bb9785570000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:10:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders are allowing floor votes this week on several proposed tweaks to the latest government funding package after hard-liners <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/appropriations-funding-bills-hardliners-chip-roy-00715032" target="_blank">demanded more input</a>. </p> 
<p>The House Rules Committee voted Tuesday to allow votes on two amendments to the package that would fund the departments of Treasury and State, as well as the IRS and the Federal Trade Commission. </p> 
<p>Texas Republican Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a>, a member of the panel, secured a vote on an amendment that would cut appeals court funding for the District of Columbia by 20 percent and eliminate the budgets of two judges. </p> 
<p>The panel’s top Democrat, Massachusetts Rep.<a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512"> Jim McGovern</a>, complained that the sponsors of that amendment didn’t even testify before the committee.</p> 
<p>“It seems like this process gets worse and worse and worse,” McGovern said. “Talk about revenge. I mean, we're going after judges and their staff. … This is not the way this place should be run.” </p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51389" data-person-id="51389">Virginia Foxx</a> (R-N.C), the panel’s chair, said House Republicans are ensuring the appropriations process is “member-driven and deliberate.”</p> 
<p>The House will also vote on an amendment from Rep.<a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/407516" data-person-id="407516"> Eli Crane</a> (R-Ariz.) that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-hardliners-amendment-vote-funding-national-endowment-democracy-00725512" target="_blank">bar funding for the National Endowment for Democracy</a>, an independent nonprofit that supports projects around the world with the stated goal of promoting democracy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers meet Danish officials to rebuke Trump’s Greenland grab</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/lawmakers-meet-danish-officials-rebuke-trump-greenland-00726166</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b941-da56-afff-bdd3f9ab0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 16:42:41 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Arctic Caucus co-Chairs <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine) will meet on Wednesday with Danish Ambassador Jesper Møller Sørensen to reaffirm their opposition to President Donald Trump’s effort to acquire Greenland.</p> 
<p>The closed-door meeting comes as Trump has floated the idea of obtaining Greenland “one way or another” — rhetoric that has drawn sharp rebukes from Copenhagen and Nuuk. The idea of taking over the Danish territory has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-lawmakers-denounce-trump-seize-greenland-00714611" target="_blank">met resistance from some senior Republicans</a> and outright opposition from Democrats.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she would support a war powers resolution to bar Trump from taking action to invade Greenland, if it were offered. A bipartisan group of House lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/house-lawmakers-introduce-bipartisan-nato-bill-00723206" target="_blank">has introduced like-minded legislation</a> that covers any NATO ally.</p> 
<p>“There’s been a lot of talk about that, which, in fairness, is crazy,” Murkowski said in an interview, referring to speculation that Congress could eventually invoke war powers authorities in connection with Greenland. “Who would have ever thought you would say the word Greenland in the same sentence as war powers resolution?”</p> 
<p>The new legislation comes as Hill Democrats search for ways to keep the Trump administration from taking further military action in Venezuela. The Senate is poised to vote this week on a war powers resolution tied to Venezuela, though its path in the House remains unclear.</p> 
<p>Trump administration officials, meanwhile, are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-greenland-military-force-00713315" target="_blank">openly discussing options</a> — including the use of force — to seize Greenland, a move that would trigger NATO’s mutual defense clause and risk shattering the alliance.</p> 
<p>“It’s easier,” <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/greenland-pm-wont-sell-country-jd-vance-meeting/" target="_blank">Trump said Sunday</a>, referring to buying the island. “But one way or the other, we’re going to have Greenland.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski said the goal of Wednesday’s meeting <b>—</b> with Møller Sørensen and other officials from Denmark and Greenland — is “a constructive dialogue” with Danish and Greenlandic officials and to underscore that Capitol Hill is not a bystander as Arctic tensions rise.</p> 
<p>“We here in this Congress actually have a role, have some input on whether or not it might be appropriate to take some of these actions that the president is suggesting,” she said.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she will travel to Copenhagen later this week with a small bipartisan bicameral group to reinforce congressional concerns directly with Danish leaders.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deepfake porn bill allowing victims to sue passes Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/deepfake-porn-bill-allowing-victims-to-sue-passes-senate-00725817</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b8e6-d65c-affb-bbe706610000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:49:28 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate passed legislation Tuesday to allow victims of nonconsensual deepfake pornography to sue the producers and distributors of such content.</p> 
<p>The proposal was put forward by Democratic Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/845fda6f-4459-46f0-a956-263e74780ae5" target="_blank">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.) on the Senate floor for unanimous consent, and is co-sponsored by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/aaf51c1d-d223-401e-8a6b-22ee557e6bdf" target="_blank">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.).</p> 
<p>It represents the latest in a line of congressional efforts to address harms caused by the distribution of nonconsensual deepfake imagery, including the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_146" target="_blank">TAKE IT DOWN Act</a>, which was championed by First Lady Melania Trump and was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/19/trump-signs-take-it-down-act-criminalizing-deepfake-and-revenge-porn-00357151" target="_blank">signed into law</a> last year by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>The bill, known as the Disrupt Explicit Forged Images and Non-Consensual Edits Act, or <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_118_S_3696" target="_blank">DEFIANCE Act</a>, cleared the Senate last Congress but failed to progress in the House. If it passes into law, the legislation would give victims the right to sue over deepfake pornography.</p> 
<p>Sen. Durbin highlighted the harm and profound consequences victims of such nonconsensual imagery suffer, and said he was proud to work with Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez on the issue, who has been a victim of explicit deepfakes.</p> 
<p>The number of nonconsensual deepfake porn videos available online has increased ninefold since 2019, according to <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-08-24/google-microsoft-tools-behind-surge-in-deepfake-ai-porn?embedded-checkout=true" target="_blank">one researcher</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP leaders throw cold water on Trump’s credit-card push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/trump-credit-cards-thune-johnson-00725061</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b855-da56-afff-bcd7550b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:11:06 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> voiced skepticism Tuesday on President Donald Trump’s move to temporarily cap credit card interest rates.</p> 
<p>“I think that would probably deprive an awful lot of people of access to credit around the country,” Thune told reporters. “Credit cards would probably become debit cards.”</p> 
<p>“That's not something I'm out there advocating for — let's put it that way,” he added.</p> 
<p>Thune’s comments come after Trump posted on Truth Social that he was calling for a one-year cap of 10 percent interest on credit cards starting Jan. 20.</p> 
<p>Johnson also appeared to tamp down the prospects for immediate action Tuesday, telling reporters he spoke to Trump about it on Monday. He called it among a "long list" of affordability ideas Trump has in mind.</p> 
<p>“The president is the ideas guy," Johnson said, adding later, "I wouldn't get too spun up about ideas that are out of the box, that are proposed or suggested."</p> 
<p>Johnson also raised similar concerns as Thune, saying credit-card issuers “would just stop lending money” if rates are capped.</p> 
<p>In addition to the proposed temporary cap on interest rates, Trump has also thrown his weight behind a long-controversial <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/02/congress/crypto-senate-genius-act-swipe-fees-00380677" target="_blank">bill limiting credit-card merchant fees</a> sponsored by Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259544" data-person-id="259544">Roger Marshall</a> (R-Kan.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.) that has been the subject of intense financial industry lobbying since its introduction in 2022.</p> 
<p>Republicans are on both sides of that bill, Thune noted, but he said he believed it would be up for a floor vote “at some point.”</p> 
<p>“That's what we do around here,” he said. “We cast hard votes.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Megabill 2.0? These House Republicans have some ideas.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/rsc-reconciliation-framework-megabill-00724594</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b814-d15b-abff-fc5ee0920000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:00:08 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A major House GOP faction unveiled its framework Tuesday for a new party-line Republican policy bill that aims to slash the costs of housing and health care.</p> 
<p>Among the <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/13NyKUdSH-uSrZi0YHkTZ3HO7J63Qv0R1" target="_blank">slew of proposals under the Republican Study Committee framework</a> is the “Don payment” — a program creating a new zero-to-low-down-payment option for mortgage shoppers. The plan would also create new tax-advantaged “health freedom accounts” that would allow Americans to directly receive federal subsidies for insurance.</p> 
<p>In addition, the plan suggests cutting energy costs by accelerating the permitting process and refilling the Department of Energy’s strategic oil reserve with “discounted Venezuelan oil.” Overall, the framework would include cuts of $1.6 trillion to government spending.</p> 
<p>“There’s three major things that I think are threatening the American dream right now: housing costs, health care costs and energy costs,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> (R-Texas), the RSC’s chair, at a Tuesday news conference. “We’ve got to get this done. We know we have a narrow window of time.”</p> 
<p>While the release of the framework signals buy-in from a large swath of House Republicans, a second massive party-line bill is sure to create further divisions within the GOP’s slim House majority. The chairs of critical House committees, including tax-writing chief <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> (R-Mo.), have expressed skepticism that there’s a path forward under the multistep budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>Vulnerable Republican moderates are especially wary of further changes to health policy as they maneuver to fight for their seats in November and defend against Democratic attacks on the Republicans’ steep cuts to Medicaid enacted last year.</p> 
<p>While Speaker Mike Johnson has not yet endorsed the RSC plan, he told reporters Monday that he hopes to do a narrower reconciliation bill in 2026 and that GOP leaders would work to build internal consensus around potential policies in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>Republicans’ House majority has dwindled in recent weeks with the retirement of Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and the death of Rep. Doug LaMalfa of California. Other members have been absent for health reasons, making the GOP’s control of the chamber especially tenuous.</p> 
<p>But Pfluger said, with the help of President Donald Trump, complete unity is within reach for the House GOP, and he called on the White House to get on board.</p> 
<p>“I hope that they take note of this plan,” he said. “When the president says, ‘Let’s go do this,’ I think … skepticism will fly out the window.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-13T15:10:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Clintons defy subpoena to testify in Epstein investigation, risking being held in contempt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/clintons-defy-subpoena-to-testify-in-epstein-investigation-risking-being-held-in-contempt-00724394</link>
      <description>House Oversight Chair James Comer says he will have members vote to hold Bill Clinton in contempt of Congress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b7e2-dca0-ad9b-ffeb2fdd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:43:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b0/50/c7d3de49468b90e6c467c7255c94/u-s-congress-22015.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Oversight Committee Chair James Comer (R-Ky.), flanked by Reps. Lauren Boebert (R-Colo.), Michael Cloud (R-Texas), Andy Biggs (R-Ariz.), and Scott Perry (R-Pa.), speaks with reporters after former President Bill Clinton did not appear for a deposition on Capitol Hill Jan. 13, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b0/50/c7d3de49468b90e6c467c7255c94/u-s-congress-22015.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bill and Hillary Clinton have officially refused to testify in the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee's investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein — defying subpoenas and risking being held in contempt of Congress.</p> 
<p>The former president and Secretary of State were scheduled to appear on Capitol Hill for closed-door depositions Tuesday and Wednesday. But, <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-b7df-d15b-abff-ffdfa3490000" target="_blank"><u>in a letter</u></a> to House Oversight Chair James Comer, attorneys for the Clintons said their clients would not be complying.</p> 
<p>The letter, obtained by POLITICO, claims both Clintons have already provided all the information they have regarding the late Epstein and his co-conspirator, Ghislaine Maxwell, who is now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in the sex trafficking scheme.</p> 
<p>The attorneys called the episode “nothing more than a ploy to attempt to embarrass political rivals, as President Trump has directed.”</p> 
<p>They also brushed off threats of legal action by arguing that, because the subpoenas issued to the Clintons are "not related to a valid legislative purpose," the subpoenas are therefore "invalid and legally unenforceable."</p> 
<p>Speaking to reporters Tuesday morning outside the hearing room where the interview with Bill Clinton was due to take place, Comer, a Kentucky Republican, announced a vote to hold Bill Clinton in contempt of Congress would be scheduled to take place during next week's committee markup.</p> 
<p>“We've communicated with President Clinton's legal team for months now, giving them opportunity after opportunity to come in, to give us a day, and they continue to delay, delay, delay to the point where we had no idea whether they were going to show up today or not,” Comer said. “I think it's very disappointing.”</p> 
<p>A similar vote could be scheduled for Hillary Clinton, assuming she does not appear Wednesday.</p> 
<p>In a separate letter to Comer <a href="https://x.com/billclinton/status/2011098958236697021?s=46" target="_blank"><u>published on X</u></a> dated Jan. 13, the Clintons said the committee leader’s focus should be on preventing crimes like Epstein’s from happening again, but is instead playing “partisan politics.”</p> 
<p>“Despite everything that needs to be done to help our country, you are on the cusp of bringing Congress to a halt to pursue a rarely used process literally designed to result in our imprisonment,” they wrote. “This is not the way out of America’s ills, and we will forcefully defend ourselves.”</p> 
<p>They also suggested they might be willing to appear in a public hearing: "We are prepared to make our case to your 45 committee members and, if need be, more importantly, we also will defend ourselves in the public arena to ensure this country knows exactly what you are doing and why you are doing so, instead of helping the American people who need this Congress's work and protection."</p> 
<p>The seldom-used congressional power to hold someone in contempt of Congress can range in implications — from a symbolic action to a precursor to forcing jail time. But there’s reason to believe a contempt vote at this time, for these individuals, could have dramatic consequences.</p> 
<p>The Trump Justice Department has not hesitated in the past to go after its perceived enemies. The administration has sought to cast Bill Clinton at the center of the Epstein files saga, despite there being no evidence of misconduct against him.</p> 
<p>Hillary Clinton, meanwhile, was the subject of a “lock her up” rallying cry among President Donald Trump’s supporters during the 2016 presidential campaign, largely amid revelations she used a private email server while serving in the Obama administration.</p> 
<p>In previous examples of the potential serious consequences to contempt of Congress charges, two Trump associates, Steve Bannon and Peter Navarro, were sentenced to prison time for failing to cooperate with subpoenas from the Democratic-led select committee investigating the Jan. 6, 2021 attacks on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>"We trust you will engage in good faith to de-escalate this dispute," the attorneys wrote in the letter, dated Jan. 12 — a day before Bill Clinton's scheduled appearance.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Member stock-trading is the latest target for a Democratic discharge petition</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/stock-trading-discharge-petition-00724344</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b800-da56-afff-bc92f5ae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:38:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A senior House Democrat, in a long-shot move to force a member stock-trading ban to the floor, said Tuesday he will launch a discharge petition after Republican leaders moved to sidestep bipartisan efforts to address the issue.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7008" target="_blank">GOP-written bill</a> is expected to move through the House Administration Committee on Wednesday, and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196354" data-person-id="196354">Joe Morelle</a> of New York — the top Democrat on the panel — said he is "troubled" by that legislation, which would allow members to keep stocks they currently own.</p> 
<p>“I'm also troubled by the notion that it's being sold as a stock-trading ban — it is not that at all,” said Morelle, who is pushing alternative legislation with other Democrats that would force members to divest individual stocks, as well as the president. But with the GOP bill on offer, it's not clear whether the discharge petition can pick up enough Republican support to force Morelle's bill to the House floor.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, the Republican-backed bill has so far picked up support from one Hill Democrat, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/65300" data-person-id="65300">Josh Riley</a> of New York.</p> 
<p>“I don't look at this as a Democratic issue or Republican issue," he said in an interview Tuesday. "And frankly I don't give a shit who's scoring political points in this place.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Powell probe stiffens GOP spines</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/republicans-react-powell-fed-doj-investigation-00724102</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b5d3-d15b-abff-fddfc8b50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Justice Department’s move to investigate Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell is shaping up to be one of the Trump administration’s most unpopular actions yet among Capitol Hill Republicans.</p> 
<p><b>— Republicans recoil:</b> The <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679" target="_blank">DOJ probe into Powell’s June hearing testimony</a> is causing heartburn in the Senate, which controls the fate of his successor. After Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) threatened Sunday to vote against any nominee until the criminal investigation is resolved, other Senate Banking Republicans like Sens. Kevin Cramer (N.D.) and Dave McCormick (Pa.) joined in to signal their disapproval Monday.</p> 
<p>Cramer is no fan of Powell and called him a “bad” Fed chair. But he added, “I do not believe, however, that he is a criminal.”</p> 
<p>Few Republicans are openly cheering the decision. Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), who referred perjury allegations against Powell to the DOJ last summer, is <a href="https://x.com/RepLuna/status/2010755530005069992" target="_blank">the exception</a>. Even other hard-liners who have long wanted to see Powell gone declined to comment on whether the probe was justified.</p> 
<p>“That’s way outside my jurisdiction,” House Freedom Caucus Chair Andy Harris (R-Md.) told POLITICO when asked if the probe was warranted.</p> 
<p><b>— A notable silence:&nbsp;</b>Despite the critiques from members of his committee, Banking Chair Tim Scott has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/tim-scott-jerome-powell-silence-00723902" target="_blank">stayed mum</a>. It’s not unusual for Scott, who declines hallway interviews, to stay quiet. But it’s conspicuous as others in the GOP speak up on behalf of the Fed’s independence.</p> 
<p>Scott’s silence contrasts with public statements from the likes of Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who called for the probe to be “resolved quickly,” and House Financial Services Chair French Hill (R-Ark.), who said it “creates an unnecessary distraction” that “could undermine this and future Administrations’ ability to make sound monetary policy decisions.”</p> 
<p>Asked if the investigation would make it hard to confirm the next Fed leader, Thune acknowledged “it could make it challenging.”</p> 
<p><b>— Powell's staying power: </b>At this point, it seems almost certain Powell will stay on until his term as chair ends in May. Many expect him to leave after that, forgoing his longer term as a rank-and-file Fed governor.</p> 
<p>But that probability has dropped amid the DOJ's probe, and Powell could stick around. And the likelihood that he might ever be prosecuted for his June testimony is remote. </p> 
<p>“The kind of things we’re talking about here is whether Powell lied when he said there were ‘no rooftop gardens’ when there will in fact be ‘vegetated roof spaces,’” Victoria Guida writes <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2026/01/13/why-powell-isnt-flinching-at-trumps-attack-00723847" target="_blank">in her latest column</a>. "Of course, the investigation might also cover the cost overruns themselves ... but mismanaging a project is not in and of itself a crime."</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House math: </b>Speaker Mike Johnson’s margins in the House could pose a problem for party-line action this week, including passing the rule teeing up a final vote on the bundled State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services funding bills. </p> 
<p>The recent passing of Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.) brought the balance of the House to 218-213. But with Rep. Jim Baird (R-Ind.) recovering from a car accident and Rep. Derrick Van Orden (R-Wis.) expected to be out indefinitely as his wife undergoes surgery, Johnson is facing some harrowing math.</p> 
<p><b>— Dem joins GOP stock trading bill: </b>The new GOP-leadership-backed bill to ban lawmaker stock buying has its first Democratic co-sponsor, New York Rep. Josh Riley. The bill, drafted by House Administration Chair Bryan Steil (R-Wis.), now has 71 GOP co-sponsors. </p> 
<p>The legislation is on track for a Wednesday morning markup. Senior Democrats who oppose the bill — which allows lawmakers to hold onto the stocks they already own — say they’ll try to force changes.</p> 
<p><b>— Health care talks shape up: </b>The bipartisan group of senators working to craft an agreement to revive the expired Affordable Care Act subsidies is honing in on a potential compromise around abortion language. According to a Senate GOP aide briefed on the group’s discussions and another person granted anonymity to describe the private talks, the lawmakers are considering increasing penalties and audits for insurance plans to ensure funds for abortion are properly segregated from funds for nonabortion health services.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jack Smith to testify publicly before Congress next week</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/jack-smith-to-testify-publicly-00724047</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b55d-d65c-affb-bfdf8ea20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 22:38:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former special counsel Jack Smith will testify in a public hearing next week, setting up a potentially dramatic retelling of his investigations into President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan said Monday that Smith will appear Jan. 22 as part of the congressional probe of the investigation into Trump's efforts to subvert the 2020 election. </p> 
<p>The former special counsel testified for eight hours in a closed-door Judiciary Committee hearing in December and transcripts were later released. </p> 
<p>Smith’s legal team requested he be permitted to appear in public. </p> 
<p>On Friday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/jack-smith-will-testify-in-public-00718945" target="_blank">Jordan told POLITICO</a> he planned to invite Smith to a public hearing.</p> 
<p>The public hearing will allow Republicans to openly question Smith’s investigation, which the president and many Republicans in Congress have labeled a witch hunt. It will allow Democrats to highlight the evidence that led the special counsel to charge Trump with attempting to reverse the 2020 presidential election and mishandle classified documents.</p> 
<p>In his closed-door testimony, Smith defended his investigation and said he is interested in sharing the results but that the Department of Justice prevented him based on its interpretation of a court order keeping details of the case under seal.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans are speaking out on behalf of the Fed. Not Banking Chair Tim Scott.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/tim-scott-jerome-powell-silence-00723902</link>
      <description>The South Carolina Republican has not weighed in on the central bank’s independence after a hearing he led comes under DOJ scrutiny.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b504-dca0-ad9b-fd8d541d0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 20:47:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0b/d0/16b8fa524a5fb63bed25816f43c2/u-s-congress-19641.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tim Scott, seen in December, repeatedly refused to comment to reporters about Jerome Powell on Monday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0b/d0/16b8fa524a5fb63bed25816f43c2/u-s-congress-19641.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Washington erupted over the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679" target="_blank">Justice Department’s subpoena</a> of Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell, a Republican lawmaker at the center of the dispute is keeping silent.</p> 
<p>That would be Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> of South Carolina, who presided over a June hearing of the Senate Banking Committee where he and other Republicans quizzed Powell about the Fed’s pending renovation projects. Powell’s answers from the meeting are now the subject of a perjury investigation, the Fed chair revealed Sunday — the apparent culmination of months of attacks from the president.</p> 
<p>Many lawmakers of both parties <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/gop-angst-grows-powell-investigation-00721939" target="_blank">quickly spoke out in protest</a> of the probe and in favor of Fed independence — including several Republican members of Scott’s own committee — but Scott himself has so far remained mum as he tries to advance major cryptocurrency legislation this week. In addition to serving as Banking chair — where he leads oversight of the Federal Reserve — Scott also chairs the Senate GOP campaign arm, which requires him to work closely with Trump and his orbit.</p> 
<p>“I already said no,” he told reporters who repeatedly pressed him for comment as he entered the Capitol Monday.</p> 
<p>Scott’s silence is not unusual — he does not respond to questions in the Capital hallways. Still, it was conspicuous as Republican after Republican spoke out against the apparent targeting of the Fed chairman — starting almost immediately Sunday night when Sen. Thom Tillis of North Carolina not only objected to the move but said he would use his vote on the Banking Committee to block any future Fed nominee until the investigation is resolved.</p> 
<p>Also speaking out Monday was Scott’s House counterpart, Financial Services Chair French Hill, who called Powell a “man of integrity” and said the investigation threatened “sound monetary policy decisions.” Senate Majority Leader John Thune, meanwhile, called for the probe to be “resolved quickly.”</p> 
<p>"I want to see [the Fed] operate in an independent way free of politics,” he added.</p> 
<p>Among the questions left unaddressed by Scott is whether he shares his GOP colleagues' concerns about Fed independence or feels misled by the June testimony, where Powell sought to rebut allegations that Fed officials had let the costs of an ambitious headquarters renovation spiral out of control.</p> 
<p>Pressed by Scott on accusations that the rehab project was needlessly lavish — many of them amplified by Trump and his allies, such as reports of a private elevator and garden terrace — Powell responded that many of the claims were “flatly misleading” and had long since been dropped from the plans.</p> 
<p>Scott has generally avoided weighing in on questions about the Fed’s independence as Trump has taken aim at the central bank and its longtime chair. He appeared with Trump last year when the president went to tour the renovation project at the Fed’s Constitution Avenue headquarters. He unsuccessfully ran for president against Trump for the 2024 nomination, but never broke with him personally, was on Trump’s VP shortlist and has won praise from the president after he took office a second time.</p> 
<p>Neither the Justice Department nor the Federal Reserve have detailed what information investigators are seeking, but a <a href="https://d12t4t5x3vyizu.cloudfront.net/luna.house.gov/uploads/2025/07/APL-Referral-Letter-on-Powell.pdf" target="_blank">prior Justice Department perjury referral</a> brought by Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) cited contradictions between Powell’s statements and plans the Fed submitted to a federal review agency. Luna’s letter references answers Powell gave to Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.) during the Banking hearing last year after Scott first aired concerns about the renovation.</p> 
<p>News of the probe caught some White House aides, GOP lawmakers and Wall Street players off guard — especially after Powell himself recorded a videotaped statement calling it part of a Trump administration intimidation campaign.</p> 
<p>That includes members of Scott’s committee. Republicans on the panel met privately Monday evening to discuss the cryptocurrency bill he wants to push through the panel this week — a measure that is backed by the Trump administration and many of the president’s allies in the crypto industry.</p> 
<p>During the meeting, Scott did not address how he or how the panel would approach the Powell investigation, according to one attendee, who said the South Carolina Republican has his hands full trying to get an agreement on the cryptocurrency bill.</p> 
<p>A bigger headache could be coming down the pike: Scott could find it difficult to move a successor through his committee later this year when Powell’s term as Fed chair expires — with even Thune acknowledging moving a nominee could be a challenge.</p> 
<p>Tillis said Sunday night he would not advance a Fed nominee, including filling the upcoming chair vacancy, “until this legal matter is fully resolved.”</p> 
<p>Tillis’ opposition alone is enough to block the panel from being able to advance a Trump nominee to the full Senate on party lines given its 13-11 member breakdown.</p> 
<p>But he’s far from alone among Banking Committee Republicans who have raised alarm bells over the investigation. While Sen. Kevin Cramer (R-N.D.) called Powell a “bad” Fed chair, he added, “I do not believe, however, that he is a criminal.”</p> 
<p>Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.), a Banking Committee member, said if administration officials thought Powell had committed perjury, then they needed to back up the accusations. He added, “I would be stunned if he had done anything wrong.”</p> 
<p>“We need this like we need a hole to the head,” Kennedy said, warning of a possible spike in interest rates as markets lose faith in Fed independence.</p> 
<p>Powell also reached out to at least two Republicans who do not serve on the Banking Committee, with Sens. Susan Collins of Maine and Lisa Murkowski of Alaska describing calls from the Fed chair to reporters. Thune said in a brief interview that Powell had not called him, but that he’s spoken to other GOP senators who had contact.</p> 
<p>“I believe strongly in the independence of the Federal Reserve, and I know Jay Powell to be a person of integrity,” Collins told reporters Monday, cautioning that she had not yet reviewed his comments at the hearing.</p> 
<p>But she added that “one can't help but wonder if it has more to do with the chairman's resistance to pressure from the White House when it comes to interest rates than it does his testimony at the hearing.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes and Jasper Goodman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T19:13:40-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Bipartisan group of lawmakers introduces bill to prevent military action against NATO members</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/house-lawmakers-introduce-bipartisan-nato-bill-00723206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b442-dca0-ad9b-fdcb3eae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:29:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan group of lawmakers is introducing legislation to prevent President Donald Trump from taking action to invade a NATO country or territory, like Greenland. </p> 
<p>“This is about our fundamental shared goals and our fundamental security, not just not just in Europe, but in the United States itself,” said Rep. Bill Keating (D-Mass.), who’s leading the legislation along with retiring centrist Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.), Rep. Steny Hoyer (D-Md.) and Rep. Brendan Boyle (D-Pa.). The lawmakers are starting to round up support for the legislation Monday night and hope more Republicans will join the effort, Keating said.</p> 
<p>Keating said he thinks targeting funding is a stronger way to pressure the administration. </p> 
<p>“War powers are important, but we've seen with Democratic and Republican presidents that that's not as effective,” he said. “It's hard to get around having no funds or not allowing personnel to do it.”</p> 
<p>The new legislation comes as Hill Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/house-democrats-venezuela-war-powers-00713669" target="_blank">search for ways</a> to constrain further military action in Venezuela by the Trump administration after the ousting of President Nicolás Maduro. The Senate could clear a war powers measure on Venezuela later this week, though it faces an uncertain future in the House.</p> 
<p>Trump officials are openly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-greenland-military-force-00713315" target="_blank">weighing options</a> including military force to take Greenland, a Danish territory. Doing so would violate NATO’s Article V, which states an attack on one member is an attack on all of them, and could end the 76-year-old alliance. The prospect of military force has drawn a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/johnson-trump-greenland-military-force-00713476" target="_blank">skeptical response</a> from some top Republicans and universal opposition from Democrats.</p> 
<p>In a letter to colleagues obtained by POLITICO, Keating told lawmakers “this legislation takes a clear stand against such action and further supports NATO allies and partners.”</p> 
<p>Although the legislation doesn’t name any specific countries, it’s a clear reference to Trump’s threats against Greenland. The omission was deliberate, said Keating, who wanted to broaden the legislation’s focus. He said he met with the Danish Ambassador and the head of Greenland representation as the legislation came together.</p> 
<p>"This isn't just about Greenland. This is about our security,” Keating said.</p> 
<p><i>Eric Bazail-Eimil contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Civil rights board slips into Dem hands amid ‘threats’ to oust chair</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/trump-thune-gop-civil-rights-commission-00722667</link>
      <description>The board has a Democratic majority after GOP lawmakers failed to make an appointment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b3e4-d65c-affb-bbe7e3b20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:20:53 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0d/03/384579cf48ceb7bed10e6711759a/u-s-congress-27046.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks with reporters as he walks into his office at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 15, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0d/03/384579cf48ceb7bed10e6711759a/u-s-congress-27046.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hassan Ali Kanu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hassan Ali Kanu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Inaction by Republican lawmakers has stymied <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/11/trump-civil-rights-commission-00286049" target="_blank">the Trump administration's efforts</a> to wrest control of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, allowing the panel to slip back into Democratic hands for the time being.</p> 
<p>That could have significant implications for the commission’s ongoing investigation into antisemitism on college campuses — making it more likely that the probe will scrutinize the Trump administration’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/31/trump-institutions-grovel-law-media-business-028840?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nrid=d052e1a9-e4d0-4466-9680-7f67289b5341" target="_blank">unprecedented</a> <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/11/federal-judge-restricts-trumps-pressure-campaign-against-the-university-of-california-00653371" target="_blank">pressure campaign</a> against universities and dismantling of federal civil rights offices.</p> 
<p>The commission lapsed into a 4-3 Democratic majority in December, after Senate Majority Leader John Thune failed to appoint a member to the 8-seat commission after a GOP appointee’s term expired.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Thune told POLITICO that the senator’s staff is “working on a number of appointments right now and look forward to filling this slot.”</p> 
<p>Until then, the commission’s work will continue under a Democratic majority and Democrat-appointed Chair Rochelle Garza, who has maintained her role <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/30/trump-firings-federal-agencies-00432223" target="_blank">despite a purported demotion</a> by the White House — and more recent threats that she would be detained by federal authorities and forcibly removed from her position.</p> 
<p>“A lot of this is about intimidation and it's about bullying and ... taking over the commission,” she told POLITICO. “If we are here to champion civil rights we have to do it above board and we cannot let anybody push us around, it doesn’t matter if you're the president of the United States, there are rules.”</p> 
<p>The White House did not respond to requests for comment for this story. White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt told POLITICO in April that Trump “reserves the right to fire anyone he wants” within the executive branch, shortly after Garza <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/11/trump-civil-rights-commission-00286049" target="_blank">declined to comply</a> with the administration’s decision to replace her as chair.</p> 
<p>There’s an open seat on the panel after commissioner Gail Heriot’s term expired on Dec. 12. Heriot, an affirmative action critic who is formally listed as an independent, has been appointed by Republicans to multiple terms, <a href="https://www.congress.gov/congressional-record/volume-165/issue-198/senate-section/article/S6995-2?" target="_blank">most recently in 2019</a>.</p> 
<p>She stunned commission members and staffers last year by alleging a campaign of threats against Democratic members during an unusually contentious business meeting, according to four people who attended the meeting and spoke on condition of anonymity due to the sensitive circumstances.</p> 
<p>The alleged threats also include freezing the pay of staffers who work for Democrat appointees and terminating others if their bosses do not accede to the White House’s moves to demote Garza and the Democratic vice chair, Heriot said during the September meeting.</p> 
<p>“I would love to be able to move full speed ahead on all of this and vote in favor of the President's” nominees to replace the panel’s leadership, <a href="https://youtu.be/DAHNkRRfdhA?t=1515" target="_blank">the former commissioner said</a>. “But there is a much deeper problem … and that is that threats have been made to get the four Democratic Commissioners to vote ‘yes.’ I cannot be a party to that.”</p> 
<p>Three other commission staff members familiar with the developments confirmed that employees heard about vague threats to their jobs and to physically remove the Democratic chair. The White House said last spring that it was “de-designating” Garza from her post, and elevating a Republican member instead. But the commission has not put the White House’s directive to a vote.</p> 
<p>“I have no reason to believe that these threats are coming from President Trump himself or from his top advisors … but it does seem to be coming from somewhere in the administration,” Heriot said at the meeting, adding that she could not offer further details.</p> 
<p>Heriot, whose term expired Dec. 12, did not respond to multiple requests for comment.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the commission told POLITICO that its campus antisemitism investigation is ongoing and a final report is expected in September.</p> 
<p>Colleges and universities “are cooperating with the investigation” and have sent back some interrogatories and data, the commission said. “Relevant agencies such as the Department of Education, the Department of Justice, and the Department of Health and Human Services, have been in communication with the Commission [and we are] currently awaiting responses and information from these federal agencies.”</p> 
<p>Garza told POLITICO she would continue to resist the moves to oust her, which she views as unlawful. “I’m not going to let anyone threaten or intimidate me into doing something I know is wrong,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boozman delays Senate Ag crypto markup</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/boozman-delays-senate-ag-crypto-markup-00723101</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b43b-d15b-abff-fc7f8d240000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:03:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Agriculture Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51287" data-person-id="51287">John Boozman</a> is delaying a markup on major cryptocurrency legislation in order to allow bipartisan talks to continue, punting a committee vote until the last week of January.</p> 
<p>The Arkansas Republican, who was initially preparing to hold a markup on Thursday, said in a statement that he remains “committed to advancing bipartisan crypto market structure legislation.”</p> 
<p>Boozman has been negotiating for months over the bill with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/211545" data-person-id="211545">Cory Booker</a> (D-N.J.).</p> 
<p>“We have made meaningful progress and had constructive discussions as we work toward this goal,” he said. “I appreciate the leadership and engagement of Senator Booker and his team as we address these complex policy issues. To finalize the remaining details and ensure the broad support this legislation requires, additional time is needed before moving to markup. The committee will mark up this legislation during the last week of January.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T17:07:05-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump phones Warren on affordability</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/trump-phones-warren-affordability-00722747</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b408-d65c-affb-bf8b272b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:08:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Monday called Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> (D-Mass.) after she slammed him in a speech criticizing his efforts to address rising costs.</p> 
<p>“After my speech, the President called me, and I delivered this same message on affordability to him directly,” Warren said in a statement. “I told him that Congress can pass legislation to cap credit card rates if he will actually fight for it.”</p> 
<p>The president on Friday via Truth Social <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/09/trump-says-he-will-temporarily-cap-credit-card-rates-00721147" target="_blank">called for a one year cap</a> of 10 percent for credit card interest rates in the name of affordability, starting Jan. 20.</p> 
<p>Warren, in a previous statement, said she told Trump a year ago that she would work on legislation to cap interest rates.</p> 
<p>In her speech on Monday at the National Press Club on the Democratic party’s future, Warren said she made clear that if the president “really wants to get something done, including capping credit card interest rates or lowering housing costs, he would use his leverage and pick up the phone.”</p> 
<p>"President Trump and Sen. Warren had a productive call about credit card interest rates and housing affordability for the American people," said a White House official.</p> 
<p>The Democratic lawmaker also said she urged Trump to put pressure on House Republicans to pass the Senate’s bipartisan legislation aimed at addressing housing costs.</p> 
<p>Trump previously gave his nod of approval to the Senate’s massive, bipartisan housing package. However, the House Financial Services Committee has been hard at work advancing their own major housing legislation, with a floor vote expected in the next several weeks.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T17:02:06-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Kelly sues Hegseth over effort to punish him for anti-Trump video</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/mark-kelly-pete-hegseth-lawsuit-00722382</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b3be-d65c-affb-bbbfada20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:47:22 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/163882" data-person-id="163882">Mark Kelly</a> is suing Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth and other senior military leaders over the Pentagon's attempt to punish him for telling troops not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p>The Arizona Democrat, <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.288365/gov.uscourts.dcd.288365.1.0.pdf" target="_blank">in filings made public Monday</a>, asked a federal court to block a review that could demote the former Navy captain’s rank and reduce his retirement pay. Hegseth <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/hegseth-kelly-punish-video-00710555" target="_blank">announced the review this month</a> and censured Kelly for his comments against the administration.</p> 
<p>The lawsuit is the latest salvo in a fight that began in November after Kelly and five other Democrats with national security backgrounds released a video reminding troops of their duty not to follow illegal orders. President Donald Trump and Hegseth have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">attacked their remarks</a> as “seditious.”</p> 
<p>The suit names Hegseth as a defendant along with Navy Secretary John Phelan, the Defense Department and the Navy. Kelly served for 25 years in the military, including time as a NASA astronaut and a fighter pilot who flew missions in Operation Desert Storm.</p> 
<p>Kelly said in a statement that the lawsuit is necessary to stand up to improper and baseless behavior by Hegseth.</p> 
<p>“His unconstitutional crusade against me sends a chilling message to every retired member of the military: if you speak out and say something that the president or secretary of Defense doesn’t like, you will be censured, threatened with demotion, or even prosecuted,” he said. “That’s not the way things work in the United States of America, and I won’t stand for it.”</p> 
<p>The Pentagon declined to comment on the suit, citing pending legislation. </p> 
<p>While Kelly and the other lawmakers did not specify in the video what orders they considered illegal, Democrats in recent weeks have argued Trump is putting the military in a legal gray area with deadly strikes against suspect drug smuggling boats in Latin America, the capture and arrest of Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro and by deploying the National Guard to U.S. cities.</p> 
<p>The Pentagon <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894" target="_blank">announced an investigation into Kelly</a> in November for “serious allegations of misconduct” that could result in recalling him to active duty for a court martial. The department last week stopped short of that, with Hegseth announcing proceedings to demote Kelly to a lower rank and reduce his retirement pay.</p> 
<p>Kelly’s lawyers argue in the filing that the attacks from Hegseth “violate numerous constitutional guarantees and have no basis in statute” and “should proceed no further.”</p> 
<p>Kelly contends Hegseth and Trump’s attacks on him pointed toward a preordained outcome that deprived him of a legitimate opportunity to rebut the allegations against him.</p> 
<p>“If permitted to stand, the Secretary’s censure and the grade-determination proceedings that he has directed will inflict immediate and irreparable harm,” his lawyers wrote. “The Constitution does not permit the government to announce the verdict in advance and then subject Senator Kelly or anyone else to a nominal process designed only to fulfill it.”</p> 
<p>Kelly said he’s being targeted over commentary on issues that are central to his role as a lawmaker: the management of the military by Hegseth, legislation related to war crimes and the military justice system.</p> 
<p>The lawsuit argues that punishment for his comments would violate protections — codified in the Constitution’s speech or debate clause — meant to insulate Congress from executive branch pressure.</p> 
<p>Kelly and his lawyers also note that “a sitting Member of Congress has never been subject to military punishment based solely on his speech."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T15:31:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>GOP angst grows over Powell investigation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/gop-angst-grows-powell-investigation-00721939</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b2ef-d15b-abff-feff179f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:00:33 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A growing number of Republicans on Capitol Hill are expressing unease with the Justice Department’s move to investigate Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell, a sign that the probe could become a major inflection point over GOP lawmakers’ concerns about central bank independence.</p> 
<p>Powell <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679?vct=1.76818488101e9" target="_blank">announced Sunday</a> that the DOJ is investigating him over statements to Congress about renovations of the Fed’s headquarters in Washington. He said the issue was a pretext to target him in response to President Donald Trump’s frustration over the Fed’s hesitance to aggressively lower interest rates.</p> 
<p>House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) rebuked the probe in a statement Monday, saying it “creates an unnecessary distraction” that “could undermine this and future Administrations’ ability to make sound monetary policy decisions.”</p> 
<p>“I’ve known Chairman Powell since we worked together at Treasury during the George H.W. Bush Administration," he said. "Then, as now, I know Mr. Powell to be a man of integrity with a strong commitment to public service. While over the years we have had our policy disagreements, I found him to be forthright, candid, and a person of the highest integrity."</p> 
<p>In the Senate, at least four Republicans — including three members of the Banking Committee, which oversees the Fed — have signaled opposition to the DOJ moving against Powell, including close Trump allies like Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422906" data-person-id="422906">Dave McCormick</a> (R-Pa.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198816" data-person-id="198816">Kevin Cramer</a> (R-N.D.).</p> 
<p>GOP lawmakers on Capitol Hill, Republican senators in particular, have heard conflicting views from inside the White House about the Powell probe, according to three Republicans with direct knowledge of the matter. One of the Republicans noted "the internal disagreements are intense" inside the White House and Trump's circle, about whether DOJ should pursue its probe into Powell.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said Monday that he hadn't seen the specific allegations, "but I would say they better — they better be real and they better be serious."</p> 
<p>Cramer, a Powell critic who sits on Senate Banking, said in a statement Monday that “Jerome Powell is a bad Fed Chair who has been elusive with Congress, especially regarding the overruns of the elaborate renovations of the building.”</p> 
<p>“I do not believe however, he is a criminal,” he said. “I hope this criminal investigation can be put to rest quickly along with the remainder of Jerome Powell's term. We need to restore confidence in the Fed.”</p> 
<p>McCormick, who served as CEO of the hedge fund Bridgewater Associates prior to running for Senate, said in a statement that he believes “strongly in an independent Federal Reserve."</p> 
<p>“I also agree with President Trump that Chairman Powell has been slow to cut interest rates," he said. "I think the Federal Reserve renovation may well have wasted taxpayer dollars, but the proper place to fix this is through Congressional oversight. I do not think Chairman Powell is guilty of criminal activity.”</p> 
<p>Separately, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) on Monday offered among the harshest GOP <a href="https://x.com/lisamurkowski/status/2010743755603948017?s=20" target="_blank">rebukes yet on X</a>, writing that "the administration’s investigation is nothing more than an attempt at coercion."</p> 
<p>"If the Department of Justice believes an investigation into Chair Powell is warranted based on project cost overruns—which are not unusual—then Congress needs to investigate the Department of Justice," she said. "The stakes are too high to look the other way: if the Federal Reserve loses its independence, the stability of our markets and the broader economy will suffer."</p> 
<p>Senate Banking Republicans are expected to meet Monday night to discuss major cryptocurrency legislation the panel is aiming to hold a vote on this week — and some members are expecting to discuss the Powell probe as well, according to two Republicans with knowledge of the plan who were granted anonymity to discuss closed-door matters.</p> 
<p>“There will be a lot of chatter,” said one of the Republicans.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.), who sits on the House Financial Services Committee, told POLITICO: “While I fundamentally believe Chairman Powell was late in addressing inflation under Joe Biden and has been woefully slow in lowering interest rates over the past year, the independence of the Federal Reserve is paramount and I oppose any effort to pressure them into action."</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51492" data-person-id="51492">Frank Lucas</a> (R-Okla.), who chairs a House Financial Services task force on monetary policy, said in a statement that the "president is laser focused on creating the best economic outcomes possible."</p> 
<p>"The independence of the Fed is critical in doing so, and I’m confident the judicial system will produce the right results, while setting the appropriate precedents for future administrations and FOMCs," he said.</p> 
<p>Other Republicans are signaling less concern about the probe. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66891" data-person-id="66891">Cynthia Lummis</a> (R-Wyo.) said in a statement that “whether Chairman Powell was unprepared for his testimony or intentionally misled Congress about the Fed’s extravagant spending, the American people deserve answers."</p> 
<p>"I will wait for the DOJ to release its findings before commenting further,” she said.</p> 
<p>Asked about the Powell investigation on Fox Business on Monday, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259544" data-person-id="259544">Roger Marshall</a> (R-Kan.) bashed the central bank chief and said the “president is sending a message to everybody that we're going to be looking out for fraud, waste and abuse.” But, pressed by host Maria Bartiromo about whether Powell lied to Congress, Marshall said he would “let the system play through here,” and added: “I think there's other issues that we should be focused on.”</p> 
<p>The controversy over the renovations to the Fed’s Washington headquarters has been amplified by Senate Banking Republicans, including Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> (R-S.C.), who pressed Powell about the issue during a hearing last June following a New York Post article about cost overruns on the project.</p> 
<p>Now, the DOJ probe is threatening to derail the Senate’s consideration of future Fed nominees. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a>, a retiring North Carolina Republican who sits on the Banking panel, said Sunday he will “oppose the confirmation of any nominee for the Fed — including the upcoming Fed Chair vacancy — until this legal matter is fully resolved.” Murkowski, who does not sit on Banking but is a key swing vote on the Senate floor, said on X that Tillis "is right in blocking any Federal Reserve nominees until this is resolved."</p> 
<p>“If there were any remaining doubt whether advisers within the Trump Administration are actively pushing to end the independence of the Federal Reserve, there should now be none,” Tillis said in his statement. “It is now the independence and credibility of the Department of Justice that are in question.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: A previous version of this story misstated the state of Sen. Kevin Cramer.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP stock trading ban bill set for Wednesday markup</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/stock-trading-bill-markup-scheduled-00721884</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b2cf-dca0-ad9b-fbcf52aa0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:27:39 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Administration Committee will hold a markup Wednesday morning on a closely watched plan from GOP leadership to crack down on lawmaker insider trading, according to three people granted anonymity to share scheduling plans not yet made public.</p> 
<p>The legislation from Chair Bryan Steil and House GOP leaders would allow lawmakers to hold the current stocks they own but require a seven-day notice before making sales, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/johnson-steil-insider-trading-stocks-00698141" target="_blank">as POLITICO first reported</a>. It also would bar lawmakers and their spouses from buying new stocks.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson and GOP leaders have been searching for a legislative compromise to appease Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) and other rank-and-file House Republicans, who have for months been threatening to launch a discharge petition effort to circumvent leadership and force a floor vote on a full congressional stock trading ban.</p> 
<p>Luna, in a promising sign for Johnson, said in an interview last week she supports the current legislation pending before the House Administration Committee because it would force a "disgorgement" period.</p> 
<p>But the bill still faces an uphill climb. Senior House Democrats are deeply opposed to the plan and will seek to make changes, arguing the legislation does not constitute a full ban on congressional stock trading.</p> 
<p>Key senators, including many Republicans, also deeply oppose any changes to the current rules around lawmaker stock trading, and it's possible the Senate doesn't take up the legislation at all should the measure pass the House.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump tests GOP with Fed probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/trump-gop-doj-fed-jerome-powell-00721769</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b07f-d65c-affb-bbff33d40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is once again forcing a tough fealty test on GOP lawmakers — this time over the fate of the Federal Reserve and Chair Jerome Powell.</p> 
<p>The Fed chair’s Sunday night revelation of a DOJ probe into the central bank immediately rattled a number of Capitol Hill Republicans and raised serious doubts about the confirmation of Trump’s upcoming pick to succeed Powell.</p> 
<p>“Will they stop at nothing to force their way on everything?” one senior House Republican granted anonymity told POLITICO. “The administration is setting a standard they cannot achieve themselves and will haunt us all for a generation.”</p> 
<p>The DOJ move is the epic culmination of Trump’s years of enmity toward Powell over interest rates. It may be the point at which Republicans who believe in Fed independence — and who are generally fans of Powell — can no longer stand on the sidelines.</p> 
<p>Powell himself, whom DOJ is scrutinizing over Senate testimony about office building renovations, is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679?vct=1.76818488101e9" target="_blank">pushing back like never before</a>. Powell is warning out loud that it all comes down to whether monetary policy “will be directed by political pressure or intimidation.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) is now threatening to use his seat on Senate Banking to derail the confirmation of Powell’s successor. Assuming no Democrats voted for the yet-to-be-named nominee, it would take only Tillis to stand in the way of the pick from being reported out of committee.</p> 
<p>“If there were any remaining doubt whether advisers within the Trump Administration are actively pushing to end the independence of the Federal Reserve, there should now be none,” Tillis said. “It is now the independence and credibility of the Department of Justice that are in question.”</p> 
<p>The latest Trump rift comes as Senate Republicans are poised to defy the president later this week when the chamber votes on whether to check his war powers in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>The Senate is currently looking at Wednesday to hold a vote-a-rama before final passage of the war powers resolution. Republican leaders are trying to flip at least some of <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">the five GOP senators</a> who agreed to advance the measure last week and enraged Trump.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see what happens,” Senate Majority Leader John Thune told POLITICO. “I can’t make any predictions at this point, but I think you have to be prepared for all contingencies but also realize you’ve got to pivot and move forward.”</p> 
<p>Democrats hope GOP support stays firm — or even increases — as Trump floats the prospect of military action elsewhere, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/trump-briefed-options-iran-00721524" target="_blank">including Iran</a>.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— What’s next in government funding: </b>House GOP leaders want to pass the latest bicameral, bipartisan funding deal as soon as Wednesday, after appropriators <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/appropriators-release-two-bill-funding-package-ahead-of-january-shutdown-deadline-00721280" target="_blank">nailed down a two-bill package</a> consisting of State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services.</p> 
<p>Appropriators were hoping to include a third bill to fund DHS but were unable to reach an agreement after last week’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/minneapolis-immigration-crackdown-shooting-00714034" target="_blank">fatal ICE shooting in Minneapolis</a> created new complications.</p> 
<p>Senate leaders are working to clear the previous appropriations minibus the House passed last week for the departments of Justice, Interior, Energy and Commerce.</p> 
<p><b>— Senate negotiators close in on ACA deal: </b>A bipartisan Senate group is poised to release a plan as soon as Tuesday or Wednesday to revive expired Obamacare subsidies, according to Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio), one of the negotiators.</p> 
<p>The main sticking point is how to address the use of federal funds for abortions. The bipartisan Senate group is expected to meet Monday night to continue talks.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Jennifer Scholtes and Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This GOP senator says reviving Obamacare subsidies would be ‘putting America first’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/bernie-moreno-obamacare-talks-00719585</link>
      <description>Ohio Sen. Bernie Moreno is part of an unlikely new generation of Senate dealmakers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a4cf-da56-afff-acdfbf66000b</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0f/04/70ad978241c1ba3e7396df85e970/u-s-congress-93131.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“Putting America first means putting Americans first,” Sen. Bernie Moreno said, reconciling his pro-Trump views with his health care efforts.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0f/04/70ad978241c1ba3e7396df85e970/u-s-congress-93131.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If the Senate is going to strike a deal to revive a signature Democratic policy, it will be in part because of an unlikely broker: a freshman Republican from the party’s MAGA wing.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> of Ohio is, on paper, an odd fit in the core group of about a dozen senators <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/senate-deal-obamacare-subsidies-00714048" target="_blank">in talks to extend Obamacare credits</a> that lapsed Jan. 1. Most are well-known bipartisan dealmakers, such as Republican <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> and Democrat <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a>.</p> 
<p>Moreno, on the other hand, joined the Senate a year ago as a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/03/19/trump-backed-moreno-wins-ohio-senate-primary-00147945" target="_blank">President Donald Trump-anointed loyalist</a> who had just defeated longtime Democratic Sen. Sherrod Brown with hard-line attacks focused mainly on immigration. But he has a key asset — a close relationship with Trump, who will need to bless or at least tacitly accept any agreement to smooth its passage through Congress.</p> 
<p>Asked in an interview about his decision to take a leading role in the politically fraught health care negotiations, Moreno deployed one of Trump’s best-known slogans.</p> 
<p>“Putting America first means putting Americans first,” he said. “People are being affected, and I want to help the people who need help. That’s what we should be doing.”</p> 
<p>He said his goal is to get roughly 35 of the Senate’s 53 GOP senators to support an eventual deal — not just a handful joining Democrats on a “defection vote” — and that he’s keeping the White House and Senate leaders closely apprised of the discussions.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> praised Moreno in an interview as “whip-smart” and “willing to do the work.”</p> 
<p>“He’s willing to sit down with people and try and find common ground, which I think on an issue like this is challenging,” he said. “Around here, that’s worth a lot.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ef/c5/3f9e764b4ad3840cb1a23ae91295/u-s-congress-99303.jpg" alt="Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine) speaks with reporters as she arrives for a Senate Republican Conference meeting at the Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown Nov. 7, 2025. " data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine) speaks with reporters as she arrives for a Senate Republican Conference meeting at the Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown Nov. 7, 2025. "/><p>His involvement is also a sign that a new generation of bipartisan dealmakers might be starting to emerge after some of the Senate’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/29/senate-gop-dealmakers-depart-just-as-congress-control-splits-00075068" target="_blank">old hands headed for the exits</a> in recent cycles. Moreno is now in close touch with not only Collins and Shaheen but other Senate pragmatists such as <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine).</p> 
<p>Moreno’s text chain with the dozen-member group is labeled the “EPTC OG gang” — a reference to the enhanced premium tax credits, the technical name for the Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>At times, Moreno’s new-kid-on-the-block status has been on display. After Moreno and Collins convened a meeting in December near the Capitol Rotunda, the Ohio Republican asked a reporter for directions to the room, inadvertently tipping off its location.</p> 
<p>Minutes later, Collins walked toward the meeting seemingly astounded that word had gotten out about what she said was a “secret meeting.” Told about Moreno’s request for help, a bemused Collins put a hand to the side of her face.</p> 
<p>Moreno said his freshman status means he doesn’t have “scars” from previous congressional fights.</p> 
<p>“‘Oh, I don’t want to be working with this person,’ or ‘They screwed me back in 1972,’ you know?” he said. “I was in Kindergarten, so it doesn’t affect me.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/00/de/21413c30406bb51223a756478777/u-s-congress-13168.jpg" alt="Moreno sprints to a vote at the U.S. Capitol on the 41st day of a government shutdown, Nov. 10, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25315750013168" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Moreno sprints to a vote at the U.S. Capitol on the 41st day of a government shutdown, Nov. 10, 2025."/><p>At 58, Moreno is on the younger side for the Senate, but he is already airing frustrations about the chamber’s growing polarization and making points about addressing it that jibe closely with complaints frequently heard from older generations of senators.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think there’s enough muscle memory here about actually going in with good faith, good intentions and getting together and seeing if the deal can be cut,” he said.</p> 
<p>The group of negotiators have their work cut out for them. They are discussing a two-year extension of the Obamacare tax credits that were beefed up under former President Joe Biden. Since their lapse at the end of last year, the tax credits — which were used by more than 500,000 Ohioans, <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/state-indicator/average-monthly-advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/?currentTimeframe=0&amp;sortModel=%7B%22colId%22:%22Location%22,%22sort%22:%22asc%22%7D" target="_blank">according to KFF data</a> — have reverted to their original 2010 levels, benefiting only those with incomes under 400 percent of the federal poverty level.</p> 
<p>The Senate group’s proposed extension would include new restrictions including a $5 a month minimum premium payment and an income cap set at 700 percent of the federal poverty level. In the second year, the proposal would also give enrollees to take their subsidy as cash in pre-funded health savings accounts — an arrangement favored by Trump.</p> 
<p>Moreno believes the group is in the “red zone,” and could be ready with text as soon as Tuesday or Wednesday. But some Democrats involved in the discussions have been more circumspect, wary about a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/republicans-trump-obamacare-abortion-00669389" target="_blank">thorny dispute over abortion</a>.</p> 
<p>Many Republicans say they will not be able to support a compromise unless the subsidies are tightened so they cannot fund abortions in any manner. Democrats say the safeguards built into the Affordable Care Act upon its passage in 2010 are sufficient.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/8a/d5/2f6151f4488b96693d0a219aac91/u-s-congress-51941.jpg" alt="Sen. Dick Durbin (D-Ill.) arrives for a Senate Judiciary Committee hearing on Capitol Hill, on Oct. 7, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Sen. Dick Durbin (D-Ill.) arrives for a Senate Judiciary Committee hearing on Capitol Hill, on Oct. 7, 2025."/><p>“I think we’ve made clear from the start, the Democrats feel we have to come to the rescue and I hope we can do it,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> of Illinois, the No. 2 party leader. But he warned that if the Republicans “decide they want to make this an abortion issue, I’m afraid that’s the end of the conversation.”</p> 
<p>Moreno said the group wasn’t trying to relitigate questions over federal funding for abortions but acknowledged there is a “dispute” over whether that is currently happening.</p> 
<p>Republicans’ heartburn over the issue flared last week after Trump suggested in remarks to House members that they should be “flexible” on abortion language — sparking <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/conservatives-anti-abortion-trump-health-care-gop-00712565" target="_blank">outrage from outside conservative groups</a> that ricocheted back on Congress.</p> 
<p>A person granted anonymity to discuss the negotiations said Republicans in a larger negotiating group of roughly two dozen senators haven’t yet landed on a consensus position — much less the entire Senate GOP conference.</p> 
<p>“There’s no need to come to a compromise because it’s already been dealt with in the Affordable Care Act,” Shaheen said when asked about the issue.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/59/a0/7b46c3ee4a4299cea1d74b5438ba/u-s-congress-64774.jpg" alt="Sen. Jon Husted (R-Ohio) displays data about major health insurance company stock performance after Obamacare as he speaks with reporters at the U.S. Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown, Nov. 7, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25312009964774" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Sen. Jon Husted (R-Ohio) displays data about major health insurance company stock performance after Obamacare as he speaks with reporters at the U.S. Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown, Nov. 7, 2025."/><p>While the abortion question is a powerful force pulling some Republicans away from a deal, there are also compelling reasons for many to embrace a compromise — not least of which is the threat the expiring subsidies pose to the GOP majorities in November.</p> 
<p>Among the vulnerable lawmakers is Moreno’s GOP partner in the Ohio delegation, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307927" data-person-id="307927">Jon Husted</a>, who is facing a likely matchup with Brown.</p> 
<p>Moreno acknowledged that despite a feeling among negotiators that they are close to an agreement, it could all come to naught. Lawmakers “are on the clock,” he said, and getting a deal is an “if.”</p> 
<p>“Capital I, capital F,” he said. “75-point font.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rep. Salazar touts Venezuela's Machado before her visit</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/salazar-throws-support-behind-venezuela-machado-00721587</link>
      <description>The Florida Republican said Trump will be ‘highly pleased’ with the opposition leader and winner of the Nobel Peace Prize.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ae86-dca0-ad9b-ff8f70c80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 15:20:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/ff/0b/4134def9479cbb2f3f98fb29abd2/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2250564219">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Odd Andersen/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump will be "highly, highly pleased” with Maria Corina Machado when she visits Washington this week, said Rep. Maria Elvira Salazar.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ff/0b/4134def9479cbb2f3f98fb29abd2/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2250564219" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307604" data-person-id="307604">Maria Elvira Salazar</a> on Sunday said Venezuela’s opposition leader Maria Corina Machado has “earned” enough to receive President Donald Trump’s backing as the South American country recovers from the capture of Nicolas Maduro.</p> 
<p>“She proved to the international community that they, the opposition forces, had won the election,” the Florida Republican told CBS’ “Face the Nation.”</p> 
<p>Salazar, who said she was in contact with Machado during the time she was in hiding during Maduro’s rule, added that Trump will be ”highly, highly pleased” with Machado when she visits Washington this week.</p> 
<p>“I am sure that she will have a very good, long, solid conversation with the President,” Salazar said. “I think we are going to welcome her in Congress, and I'm sure that President Trump is going to be highly, highly pleased with that meeting.</p> 
<p>Salazar’s optimism comes as the organization that oversees the Nobel Peace Prize announced Machado cannot give her recent award to Trump.</p> 
<p>Machado won the prestigious prize in October, and quickly dedicated the award to the president. Trump had repeatedly expressed his desire to be awarded the prize, particularly in light of his work to end the Israel-Hamas war and other conflicts.</p> 
<p>Trump declined to endorse Machado as the nation's new leader in the wake of the raid that netted Maduro and left Venezuela at least temporarily leaderless. But Salazar on Sunday said Machado “is part of the transition” in Venezuela now that Maduro is no longer in power — a sharp difference from Trump’s previous statements that the U.S. will run Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Salazar said there are things that the U.S. may not know about what is happening in Venezuela under Maduro’s allies, Delcy Rodríguez and Diosdado Cabello.</p> 
<p>Still, her optimism continued as she said she is confident American prisoners will soon be released.</p> 
<p>“We do not want to make any mistakes and I am sure that the political prisoners will be coming out and that we're not giving them, meaning Diosdado and Delcy, any type of leeway for them to really run the country,” said Salazar. “We will see. I happened two, three weeks ago. Let's give them a little bit more time before we see more results.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rand Paul: Bombing Iran ‘is not the answer’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/rand-paul-bombing-iran-not-the-answer-00721432</link>
      <description>“I don’t think it’s the job of the American government to be involved with every freedom movement around the world,” the Kentucky senator said.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ae15-d65c-affb-af9761340000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 12:52:48 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8e/bb/9ae9b2134ed28a6db68a873f1ae7/u-s-congress-65498.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Rand Paul speaks during a hearing on Capitol Hill on July 15, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8e/bb/9ae9b2134ed28a6db68a873f1ae7/u-s-congress-65498.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Rand Paul expressed concerns Sunday over President Donald Trump’s threats to bomb Iran as the Middle Eastern country sees widespread protests continue.</p> 
<p>Speaking with ABC’s “This Week,” the Kentucky Republican said he is not sure striking Iran “will have the effects intended.”</p> 
<p>“We wish freedom and liberation the best around the world, but I don’t think it’s the job of the American government to be involved with every freedom movement around the world,” Paul said.</p> 
<p>Paul also expressed concerns over how the administration would distinguish between Iranian protesters and law enforcement if Trump were to approve military action in the region.</p> 
<p>“How do you drop a bomb in the middle of a crowd or a protest and protect the people there?” Paul said. “Plus there's the constitution that we don't let presidents bomb countries when they feel like it. They are supposed to ask the people through the Congress for permission.”</p> 
<p>Protests erupted in the Islamic Republic late last month as Iranians expressed dissatisfaction over the country’s economic free fall. But as demonstrations have continued, many have begun to demand total regime change.</p> 
<p>Reports indicate thousands have been arrested, and agencies have been unable to confirm the total death toll due to an internet blackout as the regime works to quell the dissent. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/iranian-death-toll-spikes-00721390" target="_blank">The latest Associated Press report</a> put the figure as at least 538.</p> 
<p>Trump on Friday warned Iranian leaders, “You better not start shooting, because we’ll start shooting, too.” And an a post to Truth Social on Saturday, the president wrote that “Iran is looking at FREEDOM, perhaps like never before. The USA stands ready to help!!!”</p> 
<p>But Paul on Sunday said that U.S. involvement may unintentionally rally protesters behind the Ayatollah.</p> 
<p>“If you bomb the government, do you then rally people to their flag who are upset with the Ayatollah but then say, gosh, we can't have a foreign government invading or bombing our country?” Paul said. “It tends to have people rally to the cause.”</p> 
<p>He added that the protests are justifiable.</p> 
<p>“The best way is to encourage them and say, we would recognize a government that is a freedom-loving government, that allows free elections, but bombing is not the answer,” Paul said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
