<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 19:44:56 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Shapiro backs Brooks in primary for top Dem target</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/shapiro-backs-brooks-in-key-pa-house-race-00690263</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1f67-da65-a1bf-ffffae960000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 19:44:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro is endorsing firefighter union head Bob Brooks in the state’s 7th Congressional District — the potential 2028 presidential contender putting his thumb on the scale in a crowded primary for a seat that’s among Democrats’ top targets to flip in the midterms.</p> 
<p>Shapiro’s endorsement, shared first with POLITICO, comes as the governor is plotting an aggressive push to help his party wrest back control of the House by turning as many as four Pennsylvania districts blue — throwing his weight behind candidates as other governors attempt to nab seats for their parties via redistricting. It’s a strategy that will serve as a major test of Shapiro’s coattails in a critical swing state in 2026, when he’s also up for reelection. And if successful, it could give him a launchpad for a 2028 White House bid.</p> 
<p>Shapiro helped recruit Brooks into the race and is headlining a <a href="https://x.com/JuliaTerruso/status/1993402862563737754?s=20" target="_blank"><u>fundraiser for Brooks’ campaign</u></a> Thursday in Philadelphia. Brooks is competing in a five-way primary as Democrats attempt to unseat GOP Rep. Ryan Mackenzie, who flipped the Lehigh Valley district last year by one of the narrowest margins in the country.</p> 
<p>“[Brooks] is the fighter our friends and neighbors all across the Lehigh Valley deserve in Washington. Throughout his career, Bob has worked hard for the men and women of organized labor — standing up for higher wages, better healthcare, and safer working conditions,” Shapiro said in a statement. “Bob has always had my back — and I am proud to endorse him in this race and stand with him in the fight to make life more affordable and get stuff done for our communities.”</p> 
<p>Brooks called Shapiro’s support “a powerful vote of confidence in our campaign.” Brooks, the head of the statewide Pennsylvania firefighters union, <a href="https://www.cityandstatepa.com/politics/2022/06/shapiro-picks-big-endorsement-statewide-firefighters-union/368357/" target="_blank"><u>backed Shapiro early</u></a> in his 2022 gubernatorial bid.</p> 
<p>It’s part of a broader undertaking by Shapiro to remake the state Democratic Party and spearhead its midterms efforts. Shapiro has <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-5285-dc40-a1bb-77e578660000" target="_blank"><u>installed allies atop the state party</u></a> and funneled cash into its coffers. He’s already endorsed Janelle Stelson in her repeat bid to unseat GOP Rep. Scott Perry in the state’s 10th District, after she lost by barely a percentage point last year. Formal endorsements of Scranton Mayor Paige Cognetti and Bucks County Commissioner Bob Harvie against vulnerable GOP Reps. Rob Bresnahan and Brian Fitzpatrick, respectively, are expected in the new year.</p> 
<p>Brooks has racked up endorsements from across the political spectrum — from the moderate Shapiro to progressives like Sen. Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.) and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.).</p> 
<p>But Shapiro’s endorsement is unlikely to clear a field that has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/democrats-2026-primaries-house-00670194" target="_blank"><u>divided Democratic special interest groups</u></a> and where another candidate, Ryan Crosswell, has so far been the fundraising leader.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump seems to wave the white flag on his US attorneys gambit</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/13/donald-trump-us-attorneys-senate-confirmation-00689692</link>
      <description>The president is pushing for an end to the so-called “blue slip” to solve for the disqualification of a handful of unconfirmed U.S. attorneys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1455-d983-affb-d5dfa93d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/23/0e/7aff57534eee8ff13dce3ff26285/trump-22183.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Brandon/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump speaks during a signing ceremony in the Oval Office on Dec. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/23/0e/7aff57534eee8ff13dce3ff26285/trump-22183.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erica Orden</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erica Orden</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For months, President Donald Trump has used unconventional tactics to install loyalists as top federal prosecutors across the country, and battled challenges to their authority. Now, he appears to be conceding defeat.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration has signaled in recent days that it may refocus its efforts on trying to eliminate a Senate procedural tool used to block U.S. attorney nominees, rather than continuing to challenge the disqualifications in court. The move comes after New Jersey U.S. Attorney Alina Habba <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/alina-habba-steps-down-as-new-jerseys-top-federal-prosecutor-00680823" target="_blank">resigned from her post</a> following a court ruling upholding <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/alina-habba-appeals-court-ruling-00671224" target="_blank">her disqualification</a> along with a handful of other U.S. attorneys who have been stripped of their positions by federal judges.</p> 
<p>On Friday, Delaware U.S. Attorney Julianne Murray also <a href="https://x.com/Murray4DE/status/1999475044494532645" target="_blank">left her post</a>, citing the Habba ruling.</p> 
<p>The administration’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/19/trump-us-attorneys-senate-confirmation-bypass-00515124?cid=apn" target="_blank">tactics with U.S. attorneys</a> — bypassing the Senate or sidestepping federal judges to keep unvetted prosecutors in place — are a crucial component of Trump’s effort to deploy the Justice Department against his perceived enemies. He has relied on loyalist U.S. attorneys to pursue what critics call baldly political investigations and prosecutions, including those against New York Attorney General Letitia James and former FBI Director James Comey.</p> 
<p>On Thursday, Trump called the so-called “blue slip” process, in which home-state senators can veto judicial or U.S. attorney nominees, a “scam.” It’s his latest attack after Trump has spent months <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/trump-us-attorneys-republicans-00617024" target="_blank">pressuring Senate Republicans</a> to review <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/25/grassley-trump-blue-slip-criticism-00522724" target="_blank">the practice</a>.</p> 
<p>“‘Blue Slips’ are making it impossible to get great Republican Judges and U.S. Attorneys approved to serve in any state where there is even a single Democrat Senator,” Trump wrote in <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115701239677984151" target="_blank">a social media post</a>. “So unfair to Republicans, and not Constitutional.” He directed Senate Majority Leader John Thune “to get something done, ideally the termination of Blue Slips.”</p> 
<p>Thune quickly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/b-00686585" target="_blank">rejected</a> that call, and Senate Judiciary Chair Chuck Grassley has indicated <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/25/grassley-trump-blue-slip-criticism-00522724" target="_blank">no interest</a> in scrapping the practice. Grassley also blamed the administration for failing to advance more U.S. attorney nominees, saying he has been “hamstrung waiting for background investigations and other paperwork from the administration.”</p> 
<p>Asked for comment, a White House spokesperson referred to Trump’s public statements.</p> 
<p>Earlier in the week, Trump appeared to acknowledge that the court rulings disqualifying his U.S. attorneys will ultimately force them out of their offices, even though many have remained there following the rulings.</p> 
<p>Trump-installed federal prosecutors in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/28/judge-los-angeles-top-federal-prosecutor-illegally-appointed-00626804" target="_blank">Los Angeles</a> area, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/30/us-attorney-nevada-cases-00589343" target="_blank">Nevada</a> and in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/james-comey-letitia-james-cases-lindsey-halligan-00666896" target="_blank">Eastern District of Virginia</a>, for example, have continued working in those offices despite being deemed disqualified. Trump, however, seemed to predict that may not continue.</p> 
<p>“We have about seven U.S. attorneys who are not going to be able to keep their jobs much longer because of the blue slip,” Trump <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rHBAMvZ-mc4" target="_blank">told reporters</a> Monday.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Next stop: SCOTUS?</h5> 
<p>Carl Tobias, a law professor at the University of Richmond, said the administration appears now to have only two options: continue to try to install temporary U.S. attorneys, only to repeatedly have those choices disqualified by courts, or attempt the traditional process of Senate confirmation.</p> 
<p>Tobias said he suspects the administration doesn’t want the U.S. attorney gambit to reach the Supreme Court. “I think the last thing they want is to have the Supreme Court say no, right? Because then the game is over.”</p> 
<p>That way, he said, “they can continue to do what they've been doing, and that is avoiding advice and consent, which is in the Constitution, which they've done in more than half the districts, and continue to play games with the system.”</p> 
<p>But other legal experts said it wasn’t clear how the Supreme Court might rule. Nina Mendelson, a professor at the University of Michigan Law School and an expert on acting officials, said she could envision the court leaning either way.</p> 
<p>“If [the administration] does appeal, the Supreme Court may, on the one hand, be interested in preserving the Senate's constitutional function of advice and consent and thus narrowly interpret the President's authority to appoint acting US Attorneys,” she wrote in an email. “On the other hand, the Supreme Court has, in a series of cases, expressed its concern for presidential control and flexibility, which might prompt it to more generously interpret the President's power.”</p> 
<p>Though the administration can appeal the rulings disqualifying the prosecutors, it hasn’t in two key instances. In the Habba case, the Justice Department has said publicly that it will pursue an appeal, but asked the 3rd Circuit Court of Appeals for an extension to decide how it will proceed. New Jersey’s Democratic senators, Cory Booker and Andy Kim, have urged the White House to <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/booker-kim-ask-white-house-to-discuss-suitable-habba-replacement-00686144" target="_blank">work with them</a> to select Habba’s replacement.</p> 
<p>In the case involving Lindsey Halligan in the Eastern District of Virginia, Attorney General Pam Bondi said in late November that it would pursue an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/james-comey-letitia-james-cases-next-00672339" target="_blank">“immediate”</a>appeal — but it hasn’t.</p> 
<p>Instead, it kept Halligan in place and attempted, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/letitia-james-indictment-grand-jury-00678079" target="_blank">but twice</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/letitia-james-indictment-fails-00687508" target="_blank">failed</a>, to re-indict James. On Thursday, in a sign the White House may be adopting a more traditional approach to installing U.S. attorneys, the administration began seeking Senate confirmation for Halligan by <a href="https://www.judiciary.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/halligan_sjq.pdf" target="_blank">submitting her questionnaire</a> to the Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the committee, however, noted that Halligan doesn’t have blue slips from Virginia’s senators, and “nominees without blue slips don’t have the votes to advance out of committee or get confirmed on the Senate floor.”</p> 
<p>The administration is appealing disqualification rulings in the Los Angeles area and Nevada. In the Northern District of New York, a federal judge appears <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/john-sarcone-letitia-james-subpoeanas-00677169" target="_blank">poised to disqualify</a>John Sarcone III, the Trump-aligned U.S. attorney whose office is pursuing a separate investigation of James.</p> 
<p>Despite Trump’s griping about having his choices blocked, he is on pace to match the Biden administration for the number of U.S. attorneys confirmed during its first year. To date, Trump has seen 13 U.S. attorneys confirmed by the Senate, up from <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/26/donald-trump-us-attorneys-senate-confirmation-00583005" target="_blank">just two in September,</a> and 18 more are expected to be confirmed next week, bringing the total to 31.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/ChuckGrassley/status/1999154682246144409?s=20" target="_blank">“ATTN WH; SEND MORE NOMS,”</a> Grassley wrote on social media on Thursday.</p> 
<p>Legal experts said the uptick in Senate-confirmed top federal prosecutors is a welcome development, even if they aren’t in some of the highest-impact districts.</p> 
<p>“That’s promising for the system,” Tobias said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inside Republicans’ new health bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/whats-in-the-gop-health-bill-00689950</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-152b-d7be-a79b-bd7f27d00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 19:54:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders plan to take a vote next week on conservative-friendly health policies they’ve pursued for years. It’s the latest GOP counter to Democrats’ push to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>Here is what’s in the bill, <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-149e-d5ec-abbb-dc9e1e070000" target="_blank">the text of which was released Friday</a>.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">CHOICE accounts</span><br>Oklahoma GOP Rep. Kevin Hern’s <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_118_HR_3799" target="_blank">CHOICE legislation</a> would allow employers to offer workers tax-advantaged funds to pay for individual health insurance, in lieu of offering a traditional group plan. It would also offer tax incentives for employers who adopt the arrangements.</p> 
<p>Both Republicans and Democrats like the concept because it promotes individual choice in health coverage while also encouraging Obamacare sign-ups.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Funding cost-sharing reductions</span><br>When Obamacare was first implemented in 2014, the federal government paid insurers directly to offset cost-sharing reductions, or discounts on deductibles that insurers must offer to people making between 100 and 250 percent of the federal poverty level.</p> 
<p>In response to a lawsuit filed by congressional Republicans, a federal judge in 2016 ruled the government’s payments were illegal because the funding wasn’t explicitly appropriated by Congress. The Obama administration appealed, but the first Trump administration dropped the case and stopped the payments.</p> 
<p>Insurers are still required to offer the cost-sharing reductions, they just no longer get reimbursed by the federal government.</p> 
<p>To make up for the loss of federal dollars, insurers substantially increased silver premiums, a process known as “silver loading.” That’s driven up the amount of federal premium subsidies the government pays insurers, because the subsidy amounts are tied to the second-lowest-cost silver plan in the marketplace.</p> 
<p>Republicans now want to put an end to that practice and start funding the cost-sharing reductions again, which is expected to lower premiums for silver plans, thus lowering the amount Obamacare enrollees receive in premium subsidies, regardless of what type of plan they’re enrolled in.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Association health plans</span><br>Association health plans enable several small businesses to band together to get health insurance. The framework includes <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_2528" target="_blank">a bill</a> from Education and Workforce Chair Tim Walberg (R-Mich.) that would permit self-employed people to buy an association health plan.</p> 
<p>Democrats oppose the idea. In addition to not guaranteeing essential benefits, the plans can distort the insurance market by drawing away healthy, young people, according to a statement from Virginia Rep. Bobby Scott, the top Democrat on the Education and Workforce Committee.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Stop-loss policy</span><br><a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_2571" target="_blank">The Self-Insurance Protection Act</a> from Rep. Bob Onder (R-Mo.) would expand access for employers to “stop-loss” policies that enable them to protect against catastrophic health costs from just a few employees.</p> 
<p>The bill would ensure that such policies are not classified as traditional health insurance by the federal government. But it has generated pushback from Democrats because it can also restrict states from regulating them.<br><span class="story-text__heading-medium"></span><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Pharmacy benefit managers</span><br>The bill aims to overhaul how pharmacy benefit managers operate. Those are companies that negotiate drug prices on behalf of insurers and large employers. Pharmaceutical companies and lawmakers have long blamed them for high drug prices.</p> 
<p>A push to change the rules governing the PBMs fell apart last year after Trump adviser Elon Musk tanked year-end legislation, but there continues to be overwhelming bipartisan interest in advancing changes that shed light on the PBMs’ business practices.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comer threatens the Clintons with contempt for refusing to be deposed in Epstein probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/comer-threatens-the-clintons-00689936</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1500-d5ec-abbb-dd960a880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 19:05:45 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Oversight Committee Chair James Comer has threatened to pursue contempt charges against former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton if they do not sit for depositions in Congress’ probe of the Jeffrey Epstein investigation.</p> 
<p>His warning Friday came after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/trump-clinton-gates-included-in-epstein-photo-trove-00688628" target="_blank">the committee released new photos</a> from the estate of the late convicted sex offender, including a signed photo depicting the former president smiling alongside Epstein and Ghislaine Maxwell, who is serving 20 years in prison for her role in his child sex trafficking operation.</p> 
<p>Comer excoriated the Clintons in a statement for apparently refusing to participate in the investigation. The House Oversight Committee subpoenaed the Clintons in August, and has requested they sit for depositions next week.</p> 
<p>“It has been more than four months since Bill and Hillary Clinton were subpoenaed to sit for depositions related to our investigation into Jeffrey Epstein and Ghislaine Maxwell’s horrific crimes. Throughout that time, the former President and former Secretary of State have delayed, obstructed, and largely ignored the Committee staff’s efforts to schedule their testimony,” Comer said.</p> 
<p>He said the House Oversight Committee will seek to hold both Clintons in contempt of Congress if they do not appear for depositions or reschedule in the coming weeks. Comer scheduled Bill Clinton’s deposition for Wednesday and Hillary Clinton’s deposition for Thursday.</p> 
<p>“If the Clintons fail to appear for their depositions next week or schedule a date for early January, the Oversight Committee will begin contempt of Congress proceedings to hold them accountable,” said the statement.</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton’s ties to Epstein have been publicly known for years. His association included traveling on Epstein’s private plane after he left office. A spokesperson for the former president has said he cut off ties with Epstein prior to his 2019 arrest and was unaware of Epstein’s alleged crimes.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-12T12:17:18-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House GOP leaders race to release health care package Friday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/house-health-plan-obamacare-00688701</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1368-d983-affb-d7fb921e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 11:34:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders are rushing to release a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/johnson-house-gop-health-care-plan-00676661" target="_blank">new health care package</a> Friday, but a morning meeting with members of key GOP faction left unsettled whether to allow a floor vote on extending expiring Obamacare tax credits.</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and other members of his leadership team want to file text of the health care legislation as soon as possible in order to comply with House notice requirements and prepare it to be take up by the House Rules Committee early next week. But the matter has been held up as they negotiate with conservative hard-liners who are wary of teeing up a vote to extend the expiring insurance subsidies.</p> 
<p>“This is going to be a great piece of legislation that everyone will be united around," Johnson told reporters after the meeting.</p> 
<p>The core package is expected to include an expansion of health savings accounts and association health plans, as well as funding for cost-sharing reductions that help low-income Obamacare enrollees afford their plans. But moderate House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-republicans-weigh-vote-on-obamacare-extension-00688189" target="_blank">want an amendment vote</a> to add what is likely to be a two-year extension of the enhanced tax credits that were enacted by Democrats during the Covid-19 pandemic and are set to expire Dec. 31. </p> 
<p>GOP leaders had been planning to let the subsidies expire, but they are now inclined to allow a floor amendment on an extension, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the closed-door Friday morning meeting with Johnson and a swath of senior Republicans.</p> 
<p>The current thinking among House GOP leaders, three of the Republicans said, is that the amendment would fail on the floor. But the GOP moderates who support a subsidy extension would be likely to support the final package anyway, two other Republicans said, believing that voting for something to lower health care costs would be better than nothing.</p> 
<p>One possible wrinkle: Some Democrats could end up supporting the amendment, giving it enough backing for adoption. But that could lead some conservative Republicans to abandon the bill, and Democrats are not likely to support its other provisions — potentially tanking the final product.</p> 
<p>Conservatives, including Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259549" data-person-id="259549">Jodey Arrington</a> (R-Texas), have strongly objected to any attempt to continue the tax credits.</p> 
<p>"I pity the Republican that has to explain why they would propagate or perpetuate, I should say, a fraud-ridden subsidy from the Covid era to prop up a failed health care program," Arrington said Friday, saying it would make Republicans "complicit in propping up the very driver" of rising health care costs.</p> 
<p>But he suggested a vote on an extension would happen regardless: "I expect people are going to have an opportunity to vote their conscience and then go defend their votes back home like we always do."</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said the topic was “heavily discussed” in the meeting, which another senior House Republican described as “lively.” Leaving the session, Scalise said leaders would be "making final decisions shortly, because we have to file text later today.”</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-12T18:21:28-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump, Clinton, Gates included in Epstein photo trove</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/trump-clinton-gates-included-in-epstein-photo-trove-00688628</link>
      <description>The House Oversight Committee Democrats released photos from the Epstein estate linking powerful men to the late convicted sex offender.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-131a-d983-affb-d7db33b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 10:20:13 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ce/8c/8c777a6348e0b19f26453d2f47ac/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-018.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">House Oversight Committee</media:credit>
        <media:title>An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Donald Trump with unidentified women, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ce/8c/8c777a6348e0b19f26453d2f47ac/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-018.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Photos from the estate of Jeffrey Epstein tie the convicted sex offender to President Donald Trump, former President Bill Clinton, tech billionaire Bill Gates and former Treasury Secretary Larry Summers.</p> 
<p>These men and others are featured in the roughly 95,000 photos the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee has received from the Epstein estate as part of its ongoing investigation. House Democrats released batches of photos on Friday. </p> 
<p>“It is time to end this White House cover-up and bring justice to the survivors of Jeffrey Epstein and his powerful friends,” the Oversight Committee's top Democrat, Rep. Robert Garcia of California, said in a statement. “These disturbing photos raise even more questions about Epstein and his relationships with some of the most powerful men in the world. We will not rest until the American people get the truth. The Department of Justice must release all the files, NOW.”</p> 
<p>When asked about the latest photos, Trump said he had not seen them.</p> 
<p>"There are hundreds and hundreds of people that have photos with him. So that's no big deal," he told reporters Friday in the Oval Office. "I know nothing about it."</p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson in a statement accused Democrats of "selectively releasing cherry-picked photos with random redactions."</p> 
<p>"The Democrat hoax against President Trump has been repeatedly debunked and the Trump Administration has done more for Epstein’s victims than Democrats ever have by repeatedly calling for transparency, releasing thousands of pages of documents, and calling for further investigations into Epstein’s Democrat friends," she continued. "It’s time for the media to stop regurgitating Democrat talking points and start asking Democrats why they wanted to hang around Epstein after he was convicted.”</p> 
<p>Jackson also accused House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries (D-N.Y.) and Del. Stacey Plaskett, Democratic delegate for the Virgin Islands, of maintaining ties with Epstein following his sex trafficking charges. Plaskett was found in a recent release of Epstein emails to have been texting with Epstein during a congressional hearing to get information about the panel's witness, Trump's ex-fixer Michael Cohen.</p> 
<p>A Jeffries spokesperson pointed to a recent CNN interview where the leader said he had no knowledge of email outreach to Epstein, nor did he receive a donation.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Plaskett did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Other individuals in the photographs beyond Trump also did not respond to requests for comment Friday. </p> 
<p>The Justice Department is required to release the full tranche of Epstein-related documents by Dec. 19, per the terms of legislation Congress passed last month.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/0e/37/685cef5140028f8517d3b0951d0c/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-016.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Clinton, center, Ghislaine Maxwell, center right, and Epstein, far right, with two unidentified people, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Clinton, center, Ghislaine Maxwell, center right, and Epstein, far right, with two unidentified people, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p>Of the photos shared Friday, one features Trump alongside someone who appears to be a young woman (her face has been redacted). Another shows Trump standing beside Epstein — who died by suicide in his jail cell in 2019 — chatting with a woman, while a third has Trump grinning among a half-dozen women whose faces have also been redacted. In that shot, he appears to have his arm around one woman’s waist.</p> 
<p>There is another photo in the tranche showing pictures of "Trump condoms" being sold for $4.50 each, branded with the words, “I’M HUUUUGE!”</p> 
<p>There is a signed photo from Clinton depicting him smiling alongside Epstein and Epstein’s associate Ghislaine Maxwell, who is serving 20 years for her part in the sex trafficking scheme. While Clinton's association including travel on Epstein's plane after the former president left office is well-documented, Clinton has said he cut ties with Epstein before his 2019 arrest and had no knowledge of his crimes.</p> 
<p>The images underscore Epstein’s long and storied network of connections to powerful men across industries, from filmmaker Woody Allen to conservative strategist Steve Bannon. They were sent to Capitol Hill after a subpoena from the Oversight panel for materials from the late financier’s estate, separate from the documents demanded from the Justice Department by legislation.</p> 
<p>While Epstein’s connections with these public figures are far from new revelations, they highlight the extent to which Epstein reveled in his relationships with powerful people.</p> 
<p>Gates, the Microsoft founder, is seen smiling at Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, in one photo and grinning beside a pilot in front of a plane in another. That photo has been published previously.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/19/d4/d433a4794d03843cd6e2aa31900e/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-011.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Gates and Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Gates and Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p>Summers, the former Treasury Secretary, is seen in one photo on what appears to be a small plane. He and Epstein forged a relationship during Summers' tenure as president of Harvard University, and he's the latest public figure to face fallout from his connections to the financier, including being <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/american-economic-association-imposes-lifetime-ban-on-larry-summers-00673686" target="_blank">banned from</a> the American Economic Association and forced to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/larry-summers-steps-back-from-harvard-responsibilities-00661238" target="_blank">step back from his roles</a> at Harvard.</p> 
<p>In a November statement, Summers said he took "full responsibility for my misguided decision to continue communicating with Mr. Epstein."</p> 
<p>Bannon, who served as Trump’s chief strategist during his first term, is seen in the photos talking with Epstein at a desk and standing beside Epstein in front of a mirror, posing for a selfie. </p> 
<p>In another photo, Bannon appears to be speaking with Allen. </p> 
<p>Bannon has not responded to requests for comment from various news outlets since appearing in some of the earlier Epstein file releases, but over the summer <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/07/14/maga-factions-epstein-fallout-reactions-00452358" target="_blank">told attendees at a Turning Point USA summit</a> that “Epstein is a key that picks the lock on so many things, not just individuals but also institutions.”</p> 
<p>Allen <a href="https://www.thetimes.com/culture/film/article/woody-allen-jeffery-epstein-prince-andrew-wife-jrkm02l6l" target="_blank">has said</a> he attended dinner parties with Epstein and said the financier "couldn't have been nicer." He also said he never saw Epstein with underage girls.</p> 
<p>One photo shows Epstein with a smiling Richard Branson, the billionaire businessman who founded the Virgin Group.</p> 
<p>Trump has maintained that he ended his relationship with Epstein years ago and called the efforts clamoring for the release of the files a “hoax.” In a pivot last month, he gave congressional Republicans his nod of approval to vote to release the Epstein files and swiftly signed the legislation into law.</p> 
<p>Those files are due in the coming days, after courts cleared the way for the Justice Department to release grand jury materials and the 30-day clock for Attorney General Pam Bondi to make the contents public is winding down. A Justice Department spokesperson did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Clinton, meanwhile, has been subpoenaed by the Oversight panel, but a date has not yet been announced for his testimony to congressional investigators. Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-epstein-investigation-department-of-justice-00651851" target="_blank">has ordered Bondi</a> to investigate Democrats with ties to Epstein, including Clinton and Summers. Bondi asked Jay Clayton, U.S. attorney in the Southern District of New York, to lead the charge.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/4a/a8/c17119e94ce886b523c1b2de0178/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-015.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Woody Allen, left, and Steve Bannon, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Woody Allen, left, and Steve Bannon, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p>It's not clear when the rest of the photos will be released, though a Garcia press release noted that Oversight Democrats would be released "to the public in the days and weeks ahead," while remaining "committed to protecting the identities of survivors."</p> 
<p>Speaking with reporters on Capitol Hill Friday, Garcia said his staff had only gone through a small portion of the materials and appropriate redactions would require days and weeks of committee work. Other photos turned over to lawmakers include depictions of women and Epstein's properties, he added.</p> 
<p>"Obviously, there are photos of powerful men and folks that we want to have an opportunity to speak with and ask questions of," said Garcia.</p> 
<p>"The so-called Department of Justice under the Trump administration needs to comply with the law," House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries said at his weekly press conference Friday. "We as Democrats, led by Robert Garcia ... are going to continue to make sure that we're holding this administration accountable."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for House Oversight Republicans blasted Democrats' unilateral release.</p> 
<p>“Once again, Ranking Member Robert Garcia and Oversight Committee Democrats are cherry-picking photos and making targeted redactions to create a false narrative about President Trump. We received over 95,000 photos and Democrats released just a handful," the spokesperson said in a statement. "Democrats’ hoax against President Trump has been completely debunked. Nothing in the documents we’ve received shows any wrongdoing. It is shameful Rep. Garcia and Democrats continue to put politics above justice for the survivors.”</p> 
<p>Oversight Committee Democrats released several dozen additional photos Friday evening showing what appears to be the Epstein property and a dental chair in a room surrounded by wall-mounted masks of men's faces, as well as a zoom-in of a "massage therapy system" and Epstein himself in a bathtub.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/7e/b1/7bc38c2b4f4d8fb07a85c45fc28b/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-019.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate shows a massage therapy system, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate shows a massage therapy system, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p><i>Nicholas Wu, Sam Sutton, Lisa Kashinsky, Gregory Svirnovskiy and Faith Wardwell contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Johnson stares down another revolt — this time on energy permitting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/mike-johnson-republicans-energy-permitting-reform-00688529</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1090-da65-a1bf-f7f915880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson is facing another intraparty revolt — one that has nothing to do with health care, defense policy or pay for college athletes.</p> 
<p>Johnson wants the House to vote on a bill next week from Natural Resources Chair Bruce Westerman (R-Ark.) that would accelerate the production and delivery of domestic energy. For Republicans, the energy permitting revamp would fulfill a yearslong legislative priority — and for President Donald Trump, his dreams of achieving U.S. energy dominance.</p> 
<p>But some conservatives want to speed up the federal permitting process only for fossil fuels. <a href="https://www.eenews.net/articles/conservatives-sound-alarm-about-westermans-nepa-bill/" target="_blank">And they’re furious</a> that Westerman’s measure, which advanced out of committee with bipartisan support last month, would ease the path for green energy projects, too.</p> 
<p>The GOP will likely need to supply all the votes on a procedural rule — as per usual in the majoritarian House — to tee up the measure for floor debate. Right now, the votes may not be there.</p> 
<p>“We’re taking in … whether [the legislation] goes far enough to free up all the constraints put on oil, gas and nuclear and whether it’s still promoting too much wind and solar,” said Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas), who sits on House Rules. </p> 
<p>The meltdown prompted Johnson to delay consideration of the bill from this week to next. But hard-liners have yet to budge, and Westerman told POLITICO Thursday there are no plans to remove some of the most controversial language to appease them.</p> 
<p>Freedom Caucus Chair Andy Harris (R-Md.) and Reps. Jeff Van Drew (R-N.J.) and Chris Smith (R-N.J.) <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/conservative-lawmakers-warn-trump-against-gop-led-nepa-overhaul-00684686" target="_blank">escalated their campaign against the measure</a> this week in a new letter to Trump and Interior Secretary Doug Burgum.</p> 
<p>“Your administration would have fewer tools to rightfully halt offshore wind development, and projects currently being blocked by successful court actions brought by your administration would see a second life,” they warned of the consequences of Westerman’s bill becoming law.</p> 
<p>Van Drew told POLITICO he plans to share his concerns directly with the White House in the coming days.</p> 
<p>For now, Johnson plans to plow ahead as GOP leadership aides work to resolve outstanding issues, three people close to negotiations told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“We are working through it,” Westerman said in an interview. “We’re just taking everybody’s input under consideration right now and focusing on the big picture of getting permitting reform done.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House moves on health care: </b>Moderate House Republicans are talking with leadership about possibly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-republicans-weigh-vote-on-obamacare-extension-00688189" target="_blank">setting up an amendment vote</a> that could add an extension of expiring Obamacare subsidies to a health care package expected on the floor next week, according to four people granted anonymity to describe internal conversations.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders will likely meet with a few more Republican groups Friday morning before finalizing the package. House Majority Leader Steve Scalise said Thursday he is hoping to file the bills Friday.</p> 
<p><b>— Speaking of health care: </b>The Republican Study Committee is hosting a briefing Friday morning on health care polling with the Foundation for Government Accountability, according to a copy of the event invitation obtained by POLITICO. The invite says the briefing will feature “critical polling showing what the American people really care about when it comes to health care.”</p> 
<p><i>Kelsey Brugger, Josh Siegel, Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘We don’t have a lot of time’: Congress comes to terms with an all-but-certain lapse in Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/obamacare-congress-negotiations-health-care-00688191</link>
      <description>Some Republicans are scrambling to see if a deal can come together in the final weeks of 2025, but most are skeptical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0fdb-d7be-a79b-afff5f860006</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 19:01:58 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f5/c1/5b4d275d4b529de761c972eecbc5/u-s-congress-44512.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) is among the senators trying to use Thursday's failed votes to spark new momentum toward compromise.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f5/c1/5b4d275d4b529de761c972eecbc5/u-s-congress-44512.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hopes for a quick patch saving millions of Americans from sharply higher health insurance premiums have given way to expectations of a long slog on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>It is now all but certain that enhanced Obamacare subsidies first implemented by Democrats as a Covid relief measure will expire Dec. 31 after the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/senate-rejects-health-care-bills-00686855" target="_blank">Senate voted down</a> competing partisan health plans Thursday and House GOP leaders indicated they had no plans to bring an extension up for a vote this year.</p> 
<p>Less certain is when lawmakers might begin to pick up the pieces — or if they have any hope of finding a solution. A bipartisan group of lawmakers continues to talk about a possible 11th-hour path forward, hoping that the failed votes this week can give them some badly needed momentum. But most of their colleagues are convinced the discussions won’t bear fruit until 2026.</p> 
<p>A major obstacle is that leaders in both parties are, at least so far, prioritizing plans that don't bridge existing political gaps. Top Republicans are putting forward proposals that would not extend the expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies, while Democrats are sticking to proposals that most in the GOP say they cannot accept.</p> 
<p>“We don’t have a lot of time,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a>, an Alaska Republican who voted for both parties’ proposals Thursday. She said she was “talking to people of good will and good faith about how we might be able to sketch” out a compromise.</p> 
<p>But Murkowski also said in a subsequent statement that Congress needs to reach an agreement by Jan. 15 — a concession talks are likely to slip into next year.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/221844" data-person-id="221844">Mike Rounds</a> (R-S.D.), who has been involved in loose bipartisan health care discussions for months, said he hoped the failed votes would lead negotiators to “bridge the impasses.” But asked if there was any way to prevent the subsidies from lapsing, he said, “I honestly don’t know.”</p> 
<p>The stakes for American families are considerable. Independent analysts say those who purchase insurance directly from the ACA exchanges could <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/aca-marketplace-premium-payments-would-more-than-double-on-average-next-year-if-enhanced-premium-tax-credits-expire/" target="_blank">see their premiums spike</a> by an average of about $1,000 a year. For some, it could be considerably more. The political stakes are also vast, with many moderate Republicans fretting that a lapse would threaten their reelection campaigns and endanger the GOP’s congressional majorities.</p> 
<p>That sense of panic has not trickled up to Republican leaders, who appear ready to send lawmakers home next week until Jan. 6. By that time, the enhanced subsidies will have lapsed — returning the tax credits to prepandemic levels that assist a much narrower swath of Americans. The Congressional Budget Office <a href="https://www.cbo.gov/publication/61734" target="_blank">has estimated millions of Americans</a> will go without insurance as people drop their plans to avoid having to pay higher premiums.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> left the door open Thursday to an 11th-hour deal but also acknowledged the obvious: They don't have a lot of time.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see where the discussions go,” Thune told reporters after the failed votes. “I think we’ll get a sense for that here pretty soon.”</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, meanwhile, is plowing forward with a plan to hold a vote next week on a House GOP-authored health care framework that, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal discussions, will not include a subsidy extension. Instead it is likely to mirror aspects of the Senate proposal that mostly united Republicans Thursday but failed to leapfrog the chamber’s 60-vote legislative threshold.</p> 
<p>Yet to weigh in is President Donald Trump. While he voiced support this week for giving federal money “to people,” not insurance companies, he also has avoided taking a firm stance for or against an extension of the subsidies.</p> 
<p>The White House appears to be tacitly on board with Johnson’s decision not to pursue an extension, with administration officials believing that path unifies the GOP.</p> 
<p>"The idea is to put together a package before Christmas that has unity with 218 Republican votes in the House," said a person familiar with health care discussions on the Hill and in the White House who was granted anonymity to discuss them.</p> 
<p>“The biggest threat these days is the discharge petition," the person said, adding that the only way to avoid it is to "put together a consensus plan" among House Republicans.</p> 
<p>It was a reference to ongoing bipartisan effort to circumvent leadership and force floor votes on legislation that would temporarily extend the expiring Obamacare subsidies while imposing new eligibility requirements. Two such petitions have been filed and received Republican sign-ons in recent days.</p> 
<p>Neither petition has yet to garner the sweeping support from Democrats needed to succeed, however. Instead, Democratic leaders are pushing to discharge a bill that would simply extend the current subsidy framework for three years — to the doorstep of the next presidential election.</p> 
<p>“Every single House Democrat is supportive of a straightforward extension of the Affordable Care Act tax credits,” House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> told reporters Thursday. “All we need are four Republicans to join us.”</p> 
<p>With nothing likely to make it to Trump’s desk by the end of the year, lawmakers are increasingly turning their attention to January. Many view the Jan. 30 government shutdown deadline as the real cutoff for a bipartisan health care deal.</p> 
<p>Some conservative Republicans are pushing their party to simply pursue a partisan health care bill under the budget reconciliation process, which can skirt the Senate’s 60-vote supermajority requirement. They argue that Democrats are not actually interested in compromising and instead want to run their midterm campaigns on the expired subsidies.</p> 
<p>“I know there are some on my side who say 60-vote bills stand the test of time, yadda yadda yadda,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said. “There are not going to be 60 votes. The Democrats think this is a great political issue for them.”</p> 
<p>But others are talking about paths to compromise, even as bipartisan negotiations have struggled to gain traction over months of attempts before, during and after the 43-day government shutdown where Democrats made extending the subsidies the centerpiece of their demands.</p> 
<p>One idea already floating around the Senate Thursday was to merge the GOP plan, which expands health savings accounts, with an extension of the subsidies accompanied by the kinds of restrictions contemplated in the House bills subject to discharge petitions. Thune said he is being kept in the loop on the bipartisan and bicameral conversations about how to quickly come up with a deal before the holidays.</p> 
<p>Few, however, thought that approach could come together that quickly.</p> 
<p>“It would be great if we could get it done next week, but realistically I think we’ve got to look at it as next week but also January,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151837" data-person-id="151837">John Hoeven</a> (R-N.D.).</p> 
<p>Among Republicans, the pressure posed by the subsidy cliff is rivaled by the anxiety they are feeling about the approaching midterms. GOP lawmakers in both chambers are warning that they are handing Democrats’ a political cudgel to use against them next year if the tax credits expire.</p> 
<p>Democrats will pick “sympathetic cases” to use against Republicans, retiring Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) predicted, “and there will be plenty of them.” Sen. Jim Justice (R-W.Va.) added that if Republicans are not concerned about the midterm implications, “then you're living in a cave.”</p> 
<p>But Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> warned it might already be too late.</p> 
<p>“The toothpaste is out of the tube,” he said Thursday. “Once Jan. 1 comes and everyone is locked into their insurance proposals, you can't put the toothpaste back in the tube.”</p> 
<p><i>Megan Messerly and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Republicans weigh vote on Obamacare extension</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-republicans-weigh-vote-on-obamacare-extension-00688189</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0fd8-d983-affb-cfdbfe820004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:58:48 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Moderate House Republicans are talking with GOP leaders about possibly setting up an amendment vote that could add an extension of expiring Obamacare subsidies to a health care package expected to move across the floor next week, according to four people granted anonymity to describe internal conversations. </p> 
<p>GOP leaders have been skeptical of such a move. But they’re currently working through whether it could pass muster with other Republicans, and it’s under discussion as centrist House Republicans grow desperate to hold off the expiration of the subsidies that more than 20 million Americans use, the four people said. </p> 
<p>Those leadership conversations also include whether to include Texas Rep. August Pfluger’s bill redirecting the tax credits into health savings account contributions as part of the GOP health package next week. </p> 
<p>Other options are under consideration as GOP leaders continue working on a plan Thursday, with Majority Leader Steve Scalise saying in a brief interview he wants to file the bills Friday. </p> 
<p>Two of the GOP moderates, Rep. Jen Kiggans of Virginia and Brian Fitzpatrick of Pennsylvania, have launched discharge petitions to force an extension vote, but those are unlikely to succeed before the subsidies expire on Dec. 31. </p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick spoke to Johnson about the push during a meeting in his office Thursday, according to another person granted anonymity to describe the meeting. Fitzpatrick and Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.) also huddled with Johnson on the floor later Thursday. </p> 
<p>But Republican leaders are still working through what have so far been intractable issues over using the subsidies to fund abortion coverage, which risks the ire of at least some GOP hard-liners. There are fears adding it as an amendment could imperil the entire package, with key conservatives on the Rules Committee opposed to an ACA extension able to block its consideration. </p> 
<p>But many more House Republicans — even some conservatives — believe there needs to be some sort of subsidy extension as a bridge. “I think we have to have that,” one conservative granted anonymity to speak candidly about a possible amendment. </p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman (S.C.), one of the hard-liners on the Rules Committee, said he opposes the inclusion of a subsidy extension but would not say if he would move to block it from getting a vote.</p> 
<p>“I don't want the discharge petition where you won't have anything,” he said. “We'll see how it goes.”</p> 
<p>The House wrangling over an Obamacare patch comes after four Republican senators voted Thursday to advance a Democratic proposal for a three-year subsidy extension. There are ongoing bipartisan conversations among rank-and-file senators about how to get a deal across the finish line before they leave for the holidays. </p> 
<p>Senate Majority John Thune has left the door open to taking up a bill if it can get through the House but said in an interview Thursday evening that he was not personally encouraging House Republicans to send over a bill. </p> 
<p>“I’ve talked to the speaker, and I think he’s trying to gauge where his members are and see what the traffic will bear over there,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noem defiant as Democrats decry Trump administration treatment of migrants</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/noem-defiant-as-democrats-decry-trump-administration-treatment-of-migrants-00687101</link>
      <description>Several names have been floated as replacements to the Homeland Security secretary amid questions about her future in the Trump administration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0ed3-d5ec-abbb-ded7805f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 14:13:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/6b/4a/989950214e31a957ea1a2ed714f6/u-s-congress-33702.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem testifies before the House Homeland Security Committee on Capitol Hill Dec. 11.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/6b/4a/989950214e31a957ea1a2ed714f6/u-s-congress-33702.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem offered an uncompromising defense of the administration’s aggressive approach to immigration enforcement before lawmakers on Thursday, as questions swirl about her future in the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>In her opening remarks at the House Homeland Security Committee’s annual threats hearing, Noem argued that the number of people who have left the United States voluntarily since President Donald Trump took office shows that the administration’s approach to immigration enforcement is working.</p> 
<p>“Under President Trump’s leadership, DHS is securing our borders, we’re restoring the rule of law, and we’re protecting the homeland,” Noem said. “We have sent a strong message to criminal illegal aliens that we will find you, we will arrest you, and we will deport you.”</p> 
<p>In the face of criticism from Democrats about alleged misconduct on the part of U.S. immigration officers, Noem also defended the conduct of Immigration and Customs Enforcement officers, arguing that Democrats were unfairly villainizing immigration officials and contributing to violence against them and their families.</p> 
<p>The hearing, an annual occasion which sees Homeland Security secretaries and FBI and NCTC directors testify before congressional committees about the threats the country faces, came at a particularly precarious moment for Noem. While Trump reiterated <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/trump-declares-support-cabinet-official-after-report-he-considering-replacement" target="_blank">confidence in Noem on Wednesday</a>, Trump allies have floated the names of several potential replacements as frustrations have boiled over in recent months with how DHS has spent money intended to boost the government’s deportation efforts and how DHS has managed federal disaster relief money.</p> 
<p>Democrats took advantage of the rare appearance by Noem on Capitol Hill to re-up allegations that Noem gave a $220 million contract to a firm tied to the spouse of DHS spokesperson Tricia McLaughlin and argue that immigration enforcement officers have violated the civil rights and due process of unauthorized immigrants and U.S. citizens alike.</p> 
<p>Ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51647" target="_blank" data-person-id="51647">Bennie Thompson</a> (D-Miss.) and other Democrats called on Noem to resign, arguing that her tenure has been marked by incompetence, corruption and other malfeasance.</p> 
<p>Democrats also noted it was only Noem’s second appearance before the House committee and one of the few times a DHS official had testified before the committee, as they slammed DHS for a lack of transparency with Congress. Thompson claimed that it had been very difficult to secure DHS officials as witnesses for hearings.</p> 
<p>“Never in the history of the committee has a secretary of Homeland Security hidden from congressional oversight like you and your department have, Secretary Noem,” Thompson said at the start of the hearing.</p> 
<p>House Homeland Security Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/240947" target="_blank" data-person-id="240947">Andrew Garbarino</a> (R-N.Y.). also asked Noem to commit to providing more DHS officials to testify before the committee, which the secretary agreed to do.</p> 
<p>Noem received most of the questions from Democrats and Republicans at the hearing, which also included fellow witnesses Michael Glasheen, the operations director of the FBI’s national security branch, and National Counterterrorism Center Director Joe Kent. The two faced more questions once Noem left the hearing early to helm a FEMA-related meeting.</p> 
<p>In a potential sign that Republicans see Noem’s position as relatively secure, GOP lawmakers went soft on Noem, voicing general satisfaction with the administration’s approach to immigration enforcement and homeland security broadly.</p> 
<p>“The border is secure, the flow of drugs is slowing, and violent criminals are being taken off the streets. America is once again a symbol of global strength,” Garbarino said.</p> 
<p>“Please go back to your agencies and thank the men and women that are serving every day and helping to keep this country safe,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/523822" target="_blank" data-person-id="523822">Tony Gonzalez</a> (R-Texas), who represents a district along the U.S.-Mexico border.</p> 
<p>But Republicans did push Noem to help them conduct oversight of the department’s work. New York lawmakers from both parties asked Noem to explain why DHS decided to cut counterterrorism grants to the Empire State. Trump reversed that decision following advocacy from New York lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Democrats also confronted Noem with videos and specific cases that they claim demonstrate the excesses of the Trump administration’s zero-tolerance policy toward unauthorized immigration.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/431425" target="_blank" data-person-id="431425">Seth Magaziner</a> (D-R.I.) pointed to a case where a Korean-born U.S. Marine who served in the U.S. invasion of Panama was deported to Korea earlier this year over drug possession charges from the 1990s. His staffer had the Marine join the hearing via Zoom and held up the livestream with the Marine over Magaziner’s shoulder while the Rhode Island Democrat questioned Noem.</p> 
<p>“These people are not the worst of the worst,” Magaziner said. “You don’t seem to know how to tell the difference between the good guys and the bad guys. Go after the bad guys. Go after the terrorists. Do not go after veterans, Marines, children, United States citizens.”</p> 
<p>Noem pledged to review the individual cases brought up by Magaziner and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189588" target="_blank" data-person-id="189588">Lou Correa</a> (D-Calif.), but reiterated the Trump administration’s view that it cannot, and should not, make distinctions between the levels of criminal wrongdoing foreign nationals have committed.</p> 
<p>“It is not my prerogative, my latitude, or my job to pick and choose which laws in this country and in which broad discretion of the secretary used to follow you can issue,” Noem said.</p> 
<p>Democrats scoffed at that idea.</p> 
<p>“You have broad discretion as the secretary,” Magaziner responded. “You can do all kinds of things. You’re choosing not to.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Henry Cuellar will retake key spending post after Trump pardon</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/henry-cuellar-will-retake-key-spending-post-after-trump-pardon-00687105</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0ec6-da65-a1bf-efff95e20004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 13:58:33 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats on the House Appropriations Committee voted Thursday to return Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a> to his leadership position on a powerful spending panel following his pardon on federal corruption charges.</p> 
<p>“We got ratified,” Cuellar told reporters following the vote.</p> 
<p>The veteran Texas lawmaker overcame <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/henry-cuellar-appropriations-vote-00685842" target="_blank">private concerns inside his party</a> about restoring him as the top Democrat on the Homeland Security subpanel after President Donald Trump granted him clemency in a surprise move last week.</p> 
<p>But Cuellar remains popular in the Democratic Caucus, particularly among longtime colleagues — some of whom argued that with the pardon wiping away his bribery indictment, the legal process had run its course and there was no reason to bar Cuellar from the post under caucus rules.</p> 
<p>“Just look at the rules,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198762" data-person-id="198762">Lois Frankel</a> (D-Fla.). “There’s nothing more to say.”</p> 
<p>Still, the fact that the vote even happened meant that at least one Democratic appropriator privately objected to reappointing Cuellar by acclamation. If his party retakes the House majority next year, Cuellar would be in line as subcommittee chair to directly oversee more than $60 billion in annual spending on agencies including Customs and Border Protection and ICE.</p> 
<p>Democrats have made a high-profile push in recent weeks to police ethical transgressions in the party’s ranks. Nearly two dozen Democrats led by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/429181" data-person-id="429181">Marie Gluesenkamp Perez</a> of Washington broke ranks to reprimand Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/304652" data-person-id="304652">Chuy García</a> (D-Ill.) for apparently engineering his retirement announcement to ensure a favored ally would succeed him.</p> 
<p>Illinois Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307305" data-person-id="307305">Lauren Underwood</a> has served as the top Democrat on the subpanel since Cuellar’s indictment last year alleging he took some $600,000 in bribes from foreign entities. Cuellar has denied wrongdoing and cast his indictment under President Joe Biden as political retribution for his moderate immigration stances.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson acknowledges Obamacare ‘dilemma’ facing his members</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/mike-johnson-obamacare-dilemma-00687068</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0eba-da65-a1bf-effb79280000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 13:46:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said Thursday he understands the “dilemma” facing House Republicans who have launched or joined discharge petitions that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/frustrated-republicans-move-to-force-obamacare-vote-as-warnings-mount-about-the-midterms-00685423" target="_blank">force a vote to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies</a>. But he gave no indication he would change his current course of letting the tax credits expire.</p> 
<p>"Leadership’s never in favor of discharges,” Johnson said in a brief interview Thursday. “I understand the dilemma they see themselves in. But, I mean, I don't endorse it."</p> 
<p>GOP leaders are planning to put <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/no-house-gop-health-plan-00684401" target="_blank">several health care bills up for a vote</a> next week before lawmakers leave Washington for the holidays. But they still have no intention of including a subsidy extension, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal GOP plans.</p> 
<p>The two GOP-led petitions — one put forward by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.), another by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.) — picked up several more Republican signatures Thursday. But neither can trigger a floor vote on an Obamacare subsidy extension this month.</p> 
<p>That’s due both to a waiting period for discharged bills under House rules, as well as the fact that massive support from Democrats will be needed to reach the necessary 218 signatures. Democratic leaders are still deciding whether to support either bill.</p> 
<p>Republican leaders don’t plan to stand in the way if any petition reaches 218 signatures, but they are skeptical that will happen. They face serious challenges in rallying their party around any extension of the subsidies, including the GOP’s long opposition to Obamacare as well as abortion-related divisions within their conference.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-11T15:50:39-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Senate rejects dueling health care bills as Obamacare deadline looms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/senate-rejects-health-care-bills-00686855</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0e96-d983-affb-cfdfac890000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 13:06:08 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate rejected dueling health care bills Thursday, all but guaranteeing that Obamacare subsidies used by more than 20 million Americans will lapse at the end of the year.</p> 
<p>Senators voted 51-48 on advancing a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3386" target="_blank"><u>GOP health care plan</u></a> that would have expanded health savings accounts as an alternative to the expiring tax credits. <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3385" target="_blank"><u>Democrats’ plan</u></a> to extend the Covid-era enhanced subsidies for three years also received a 51-48 vote. Both proposals fell well short of the 60 votes needed to vault a key procedural hurdle.</p> 
<p>The votes both went largely, but not entirely, along party lines. Sen. Rand Paul of Kentucky was the only Republican to oppose the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/cassidy-crapo-unveil-alternative-to-obamacare-subsidies-00682315" target="_blank"><u>GOP plan</u></a>. Meanwhile, Republican Sens. Susan Collins of Maine, Josh Hawley of Missouri, Lisa Murkowski of Alaska and Dan Sullivan of Alaska voted to advance the Democrats’ health care plan. Sen. Steve Daines (R-Mont.), who would have voted for the GOP plan, missed the votes. </p> 
<p>Paul said his party’s bill, written by Sens. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana and Mike Crapo of Idaho, amounted to “Obamacare lite,” while Collins, Hawley and Murkowski have expressed sharp concerns about allowing the subsidies to expire.</p> 
<p>“Unfortunately, the votes that we have just had — neither one kind of gets us there. But there are elements in both that I support,” Murkowski said about her votes to advance both bills. </p> 
<p>Sullivan said he voted to open debate on the Democratic proposal but wanted to make changes to it. Meanwhile, Hawley said that while both parties' proposals would need changes, “I just think we’ve got to do something." </p> 
<p>"So I'm in the all-of-the-above category,” he said.</p> 
<p>Thursday’s Senate votes were part of a deal Senate Majority Leader John Thune made with Democrats to end the government shutdown that ended last month. Senators have widely acknowledged for weeks that the votes were aimed more at messaging than forcing through passable bipartisan compromise.</p> 
<p>Still, a deal in the Senate was likely Congress’ best shot at preventing the subsidies from lapsing and raising premiums for many Americans who buy their insurance directly through Affordable Care Act exchanges. While the lapse will not completely eliminate the tax credits, they will revert back to pre-pandemic levels and <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/aca-marketplace-premium-payments-would-more-than-double-on-average-next-year-if-enhanced-premium-tax-credits-expire/" target="_blank"><u>many families could still see their premiums rise</u></a> by $1,000 a year or more.</p> 
<p>“Our bill is the last train leaving the station,” Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said ahead of the vote, urging Republicans to support the Democratic bill.</p> 
<p>The House is similarly riven by partisan divides. Republican leaders have no plans at the moment to put a subsidy extension up for a vote before adjourning for the year next week. Democratic leaders in the chamber, like Senate Democrats, want to extend the expiring tax credits by three years; two bipartisan bills proposing shorter extensions are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/frustrated-republicans-move-to-force-obamacare-vote-as-warnings-mount-about-the-midterms-00685423" target="_blank"><u>subject to discharge petitions</u></a> that could force action — but not until next year.</p> 
<p>Thune said if a bill is able to pass the House, “obviously we’ll take a look at it.” But he shared a note of skepticism, saying, “We’ll cross that bridge when we come to it.”</p> 
<p>Rank-and-file senators are leaving the door open to trying to strike a last-minute bipartisan deal, but they are effectively out of time. The Senate is expected to adjourn next week until January, and, while bipartisan talks are ongoing, they’ve failed to gain momentum. </p> 
<p>After Thursday’s failed votes, senators were already floating trying to merge the health savings account flexibility in the GOP bill with an extension of the subsidies with an income cap and other eligibility restrictions. But multiple sticky political fights, including a clash over abortion restrictions, would need to be resolved in a passable deal.</p> 
<p>“I hope that after today they will feel like they’ve checked the messaging box and will get serious about actually doing something about the spiraling health care costs under Obamacare,” Thune said ahead of the vote. “Republicans are ready to get to work. I’m not sure yet if the Democrats are interested.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) said she was open to negotiating long-term health care reforms but added that with time running short, extending the credits is the “easiest” immediate solution.</p> 
<p>“We need to act now,” Shaheen said. “I know there are members in both parties who want to find a responsible path forward.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>David Trone launches primary bid for old House seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/david-trone-house-primary-bid-00686675</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0e4e-d7be-a79b-af7fb6f20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:57:57 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maryland Democrat David Trone, a former three-term House lawmaker who left his seat to launch an ill-fated Senate run in 2024, is making a play for his old job in a primary challenge against first-term Rep. April McClain Delaney, he announced Thursday.</p> 
<p>The battle — in a blue-leaning district Republicans have targeted in the past — could set up an extraordinarily expensive primary between Trone and Delaney, both of whom have multimillion-dollar fortunes.</p> 
<p>Trone hopes his opposition to President Donald Trump will help drive his campaign.</p> 
<p>“Watching Trump and Republicans’ assault on our democracy — weaponizing the government and tearing apart families — is intolerable and goes against everything we stand for,” he said in a statement. “Our fundamental freedoms are being dismantled piece by piece. The people of Maryland’s 6th District need a fighter who will stand up against these attacks every single day.”</p> 
<p>The wealthy wine magnate has self-funded his runs for office before. Trone <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/05/04/total-wine-trone-maryland-senate-campaign-00095218" target="_blank">spent some $17 million in his successful 2018 House campaign</a>. He then parted ways with more than $60 million in the 2024 Senate primary, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/05/14/angela-alsobrooks-wins-messy-democratic-senate-primary-in-maryland-00158054" target="_blank">which he lost by more than 10 points to then-Prince George’s County Executive</a> Angela Alsobrooks.</p> 
<p>But McClain Delaney, the wife of former House lawmaker and onetime presidential candidate John Delaney, isn’t ready to go quietly.</p> 
<p>“David Trone thinks I should ‘step aside’ so he can have his old office back after he abandoned the district to run and lose for Senate,” she said in a statement Thursday. “He has the arrogance of a Trump. But not so fast. On behalf of my district, I stand up to bullies.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Offshore wind foes want to drag Trump into permitting bill spat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/offshore-wind-foes-want-to-drag-trump-into-permitting-bill-spat-00685818</link>
      <description>A group of House Republicans are rebelling against legislation leadership intended to put on the floor next week.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0e39-d983-affb-cffb3c0d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:44:17 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8e/da/b94d859c46e98ea4493e2e22d54f/biden-classified-documents-14224.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jose Luis Magana/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Jeff Van Drew (R-N.J.) said, "Assurances sometimes just aren't good enough."</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8e/da/b94d859c46e98ea4493e2e22d54f/biden-classified-documents-14224.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Kelsey Brugger</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Kelsey Brugger</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A group of House Republicans is trying to bait President Donald Trump into the permitting wars on Capitol Hill, arguing that legislation up for a vote as soon as next week could green-light something he hates with fury: offshore wind power.</p> 
<p>Natural Resources Chair Bruce Westerman (R-Ark.) wants the House to pass his bill that would accelerate energy projects of all kinds, which would give him leverage in expected negotiations with the Senate in the coming months on overhauling the federal permitting process.</p> 
<p>But the legislation has drawn sharp opposition from conservatives who claim it could benefit renewable energy projects already benefitting from tax incentives, plus limit the Trump administration’s ability to block projects like offshore wind.</p> 
<p>“Believe me, nobody hates wind turbines more than me — except the president of the United States,” said Rep. Jeff Van Drew (R-N.J.). "We all need assurances."</p> 
<p>He paused, and added: "Assurances sometimes just aren't good enough."</p> 
<p>Van Drew and Reps. Chris Smith (R-N.J.) teamed up with House Freedom Caucus Chair Andy Harris (R-Md.) in writing a letter to Trump this week that warned the Westerman bill — which passed out of committee with bipartisan support — "undermines your stated policy agenda of rightfully ending offshore wind development and other 'Green New Scam' projects approved under the poor leadership of the Biden Administration, particularly development off the Atlantic Coast."</p> 
<p>They are mainly concerned about language added to the bill during the recent Natural Resources markup of the Westerman measure that could limit the administration’s ability to scrap an already-issued permit — a provision members on both sides of the aisle support.</p> 
<p>Van Drew said in an interview he had heard that the White House wanted to make sure the legislation would not promote offshore wind, which could make this bipartisan amendment problematic in a final product.</p> 
<p>But Westerman and other lawmakers want any permitting overhaul bill to be “technology neutral” after criticizing Democrats for putting policies in place that would benefit renewable energy.</p> 
<p>Westerman defended his product Wednesday, saying the White House has been briefed and is “well aware of where we are.”</p> 
<p>He added, “I expect the administration to still support the bill. I haven’t gotten any indication the administration isn’t supportive of the bill.”</p> 
<p>A White House spokesperson did not return a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas), one of the House's most conservative voices, has also expressed reservations about the Westerman legislation.</p> 
<p>"I don’t want to fast-track any of the wind and solar. It’s still not a neutral playing field because it’s subsidized," said Roy, who pushed — unsuccessfully — for the immediate repeal of renewable energy credits in the GOP megabill enacted over the summer.</p> 
<p>Although some Democrats support the bill — including co-sponsor Jared Golden of Maine — others want stronger language to prevent the president from scrapping permits, among other changes.</p> 
<p>The League of Conservation Voters is urging lawmakers to vote “no,” arguing that “the biggest problem right now is the fact the Trump administration is not allowing any wind, solar or battery projects to move forward in the permitting process.”</p> 
<p>This means opposition from even a handful of Republicans could tank a vote on a procedural rule to take up the bill on the chamber floor, which are typically party-line affairs.</p> 
<p>Westerman said earlier this week that he was looking to meet with bill critics. Indeed, he was seen chatting with Smith on the House floor Wednesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>“Hopefully we’ll work through it and get to a point where we can get the bill on the floor and get a good vote on it,” Westerman said.</p> 
<p><i>Reporters Josh Siegel and Nico Portuondo contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate GOP still not interested in nixing blue slips, Thune says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/b-00686585</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0e33-d983-affb-cffbe8cd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:35:21 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune poured cold water on a fresh call by President Donald Trump for Republicans to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/trump-us-attorneys-republicans-00617024" target="_blank">nix the "blue slip" practice</a> that gives senators an effective veto over presidential nominees to certain posts in their states.</p> 
<p>“There are many Republican senators, way more Republican senators who are interested in preserving that than those who aren’t," Thune told reporters. He comparing it to the overwhelming GOP sentiment in favor of keeping the 60-vote filibuster rule, which Trump also opposes.</p> 
<p>The blue slip precedent applies to nominees to serve as district judges, U.S. attorneys and U.S. marshals. Among the Trump appointees who have not gotten Democratic assent is Alina Habba, his pick for U.S. attorney in New Jersey who was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/alina-habba-steps-down-as-new-jerseys-top-federal-prosecutor-00680823" target="_blank">recently disqualified from her acting role</a> by a federal court.</p> 
<p>Opposition from Democrats is not the only obstacle to confirming more Trump appointees, however: Senate Judiciary Chair Chuck Grassley (R-Iowa) said during a committee meeting Thursday he would like to process more judicial nominees but is waiting on Trump to send them.</p> 
<p>According to his prepared remarks, Grassley said he would also like to advance more U.S. attorney picks, but “I’m hamstrung waiting for background investigations and other paperwork from the administration.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP’s health revolt heads to the Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/republican-health-care-plan-senate-vote-00686269</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0bda-d7be-a79b-afffcf9a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans just showed how divided they are over health care. Thursday's Senate votes could expose the party’s strife even further.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans know both parties’ health care proposals are doomed Thursday. But as Democrats prepare to unite behind a three-year extension of expiring Obamacare subsidies, Senate Majority Leader John Thune and Speaker Mike Johnson can’t get Republicans on the same page.</p> 
<p><b><i>—&nbsp;</i>In the Senate: </b>Sen. Rand Paul (R-Ky.) is the only definite GOP defector on Thursday’s vote on a framework by Sens. Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) and Bill Cassidy (R-La.) that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/cassidy-crapo-unveil-alternative-to-obamacare-subsidies-00682315" target="_blank">expand health savings accounts</a> rather than extend the enhanced Obamacare tax credits.</p> 
<p>But a handful of Republicans have not yet said how they would vote, including Sens. Lisa Murkowski of Alaska and Susan Collins of Maine. And Florida Sen. Rick Scott — who has a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/rick-scott-releases-obamacare-subsidy-alternative-00664146" target="_blank">competing proposal of his own</a> — said he’s still reviewing the Crapo-Cassidy bill.</p> 
<p>Thune is already messaging around Thursday’s near-certain failure and suggesting it’ll spur more serious negotiations.</p> 
<p>“When we get through this exercise this week the question is, ‘Are there enough Democrats who want to fix the problem?’” he told reporters Wednesday. “I think there’s a path forward. ... Obviously we don’t have a lot of time to do this, but I think there are ways in which you could, where there’s a will.”</p> 
<p><b>— In the House:</b> At least 10 Republicans on Wednesday <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/frustrated-republicans-move-to-force-obamacare-vote-as-warnings-mount-about-the-midterms-00685423" target="_blank">signed a bipartisan discharge petition</a> authored by Reps. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) and Jared Golden (D-Maine) that would extend the enhanced tax credits for two years while imposing new eligibility requirements. Reps. Josh Gottheimer (D-N.J.) and Jen Kiggans (R-Va.) also moved Wednesday to file a discharge petition on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/new-aca-subsidy-extension-bill-draws-16-gop-co-sponsors-00685285" target="_blank">their own proposal</a> that would extend subsidies for a year with new guardrails.</p> 
<p>Both efforts are direct challenges to House leaders who appear determined to let the subsidies lapse. But they would likely need all House Democrats — and Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries is pushing a measure to compel a vote on a three-year extension. Asked if he would support Fitzpatrick’s bill Wednesday night, Jeffries said he had not had the opportunity to look at it yet.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise told POLITICO he’s “not a fan of discharge petitions,” adding that the extension framework being proposed in the Fitzpatrick-Golden bill is one of many that has split the GOP conference.</p> 
<p>But Golden and other centrists are urging leaders not to brush off brewing discontent.</p> 
<p>“Leadership, no matter who they are, in both parties, House and Senate, should pay attention to what’s going on with discharge petitions,” Golden said.</p> 
<p><b>— From the White House: </b>Meanwhile, lawmakers are getting mixed signals about whether President Donald Trump wants Republicans to utilize the filibuster-skirting process of reconciliation to advance a party-line package to address affordability concerns, including health care.</p> 
<p>Asked Wednesday if he wants to see another megabill move through the Hill next year, Trump <a href="https://x.com/MicaSoellnerDC/status/1998866841314455599?s=20" target="_blank">told reporters</a> “we don’t need it.” But hours later, White House deputy chief of staff James Blair <a href="https://x.com/semafor/status/1998899662145646906?s=46&amp;t=ncdqfRV74gcQrRg3XkYQbA" target="_blank">told Semafor</a> the administration “would love to do” another reconciliation bill.</p> 
<p>“That’s really a partisan tool, and then obviously there’s bipartisan pathways too,” Blair said. “Which one opens up is largely contingent on whether or not the Democrats want to work on anything.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Will Cuellar get his gavel back? </b>Rep. Henry Cuellar’s (D-Texas) fate as an appropriations leader will be decided Thursday when House Democratic appropriators vote in a secret ballot on whether the recently-pardoned lawmaker will resume his former subcommittee chair role. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/henry-cuellar-appropriations-vote-00685842" target="_blank">Some Democrats are uneasy</a> with allowing a colleague who’s been accused of bribery regain control over more than $60 billion in annual spending as the top Democrat overseeing Homeland Security funding.</p> 
<p><b>— National Guard deployments in the spotlight: </b>Pentagon officials will be in the hot seat during a 9:30 a.m. <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/senate-panel-to-hold-hearing-on-trumps-guard-deployments-to-us-cities-00679187" target="_blank">Senate Armed Services Committee hearing</a> on Trump’s decision to send National Guard troops to cities like Washington and Los Angeles. The president has said the deployments were necessary to fight crime or crack down on protests; Democrats contend the administration is illegally wielding troops against blue cities.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy, Nicholas Wu and Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pardoned Democrat faces internal opposition as he seeks to regain powerful committee post</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/henry-cuellar-appropriations-vote-00685842</link>
      <description>Henry Cuellar faces a vote of fellow Democratic appropriators Thursday, and some have doubts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0a87-d7be-a79b-aff7f8800006</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:12:56 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/79/c8/c44d749c4b58b04526e830098011/u-s-congress-40131.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Cuellar stepped down as ranking member of the Appropriations subcommittee overseeing Homeland Security spending after his indictment last year.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/79/c8/c44d749c4b58b04526e830098011/u-s-congress-40131.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Democrats are uneasy about a push to restore Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a> to a powerful committee role following a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/henry-cuellar-pardon-reelection-party-00674518" target="_blank">pardon from President Donald Trump</a>, potentially complicating his bid to regain influence over federal spending.</p> 
<p>Cuellar relinquished his post as the top Democrat on the Appropriations subcommittee overseeing Homeland Security funding in 2024 after he was indicted on federal corruption charges. But following Trump’s pardon last week, party leaders have indicated that he is now eligible to retake the post under caucus rules.</p> 
<p>But not all of his fellow House Democrats are comfortable with a lawmaker accused of bribery and other offenses regaining direct control over more than $60 billion in annual spending, especially with a parallel Ethics Committee investigation still in motion. Compounding these concerns are Cuellar’s relatively conservative views on border policy and his potential sway over the budgets for agencies including Border Patrol and ICE.</p> 
<p>The matter is in the hands of the 27 Democratic members of the House Appropriations Committee, who are set to take a secret ballot vote Thursday to determine Cuellar’s future on the panel.</p> 
<p>Several have private misgivings, and the fact that the vote is even happening means at least one Democratic appropriator privately objected to Cuellar’s return as ranking member. Otherwise, he would have been approved by acclamation.</p> 
<p>“That position is critical — it's Homeland Security,” said a Democratic appropriator granted anonymity to discuss internal conversations. “Your moral values are important — at least mine are — and I can't look at myself in the mirror and vote for him.”</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307305" data-person-id="307305">Lauren Underwood</a> of Illinois, who has served as the top Democrat on Homeland Security since Cuellar was indicted, could vote to keep Cuellar out so she can keep the job. Another appropriator, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196272" data-person-id="196272">Grace Meng</a> of New York, said Wednesday she was undecided on the matter.</p> 
<p>Other wild cards include Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/429181" data-person-id="429181">Marie Gluesenkamp Perez</a> of Washington, who led a push to formally reprimand a Democratic colleague last month, and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/75165" data-person-id="75165">Mike Quigley</a> of Illinois, who might vote in state solidarity with Underwood. Quigley had <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/03/congress/mike-quigley-takes-a-shot-at-house-democratic-grandees-00382170" target="_blank">been leapfrogged</a> by a more senior lawmaker who returned to the panel and has voiced criticism of Democratic leaders since then.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Cuellar declined to comment.</p> 
<p>The veteran Texas Democrat has been quietly canvassing members about regaining his role and reassuring those in his party who question the optics of wiping away an indictment sought by former President Joe Biden’s Justice Department at a time when the party is focusing on Trump’s alleged ethical violations.</p> 
<p>Top party leaders have not weighed in directly on the matter. House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> said Tuesday that Cuellar was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/henry-cuellar-appropriations-00683379" target="_blank">likely to regain</a> his committee leadership position, citing the caucus rules, while Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a> of Connecticut, the top Appropriations Democrat, in a statement merely acknowledged the Thursday vote.</p> 
<p>“We are holding a meeting tomorrow to discuss several issues, including who will serve as Ranking Member of the Homeland Security Subcommittee,” the statement said.</p> 
<p>The dilemma comes as some Democrats are making a high-profile push to police ethical transgressions in the party ranks. Last month, almost two dozen Democrats led by Gluesenkamp Perez <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/mgp-vs-chuy-garcia-00650119" target="_blank">broke ranks to reprimand</a> outgoing Illinois Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/304652" data-person-id="304652">Chuy García</a> for apparently engineering his surprise retirement announcement to ensure a favored ally would succeed him.</p> 
<p>Democrats have railed against Trump’s use of his clemency powers, which has benefited political allies and major donors. Cuellar’s pardon puts him in the company of such figures as former Illinois Gov. Rod R. Blagojevich and ex-Rep. George Santos, who are odious to Democrats.</p> 
<p>“I've had nothing but good interactions with Henry in Congress, but we can't be the party of following the law and say it's just fine to break it and get a pardon from Trump,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227127" data-person-id="227127">Seth Moulton</a> (D-Mass.), who is running for Senate.</p> 
<p>Several other Democrats this week aired criticism of Trump’s pardons without specifically commenting on Cuellar and his bid to regain power inside the Democratic Caucus.</p> 
<p>“President Trump's continued efforts to pardon politicians that are either convicted or accused of corruption is just wrong,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/25648" data-person-id="25648">Andy Kim </a>(D-N.J.). “And this is exactly the kind of problem that causes so many Americans to lose trust and faith in our politics.”</p> 
<p>Kim, a former member of the House, succeeded Sen. Bob Menendez, the New Jersey Democrat who is currently serving a prison sentence for bribery and other charges.</p> 
<p>“I don’t agree with any of the president’s pardons of members of Congress,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259488" data-person-id="259488">Angie Craig</a> (D-Minn.), who is also running for Senate.</p> 
<p>Cuellar was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/05/03/congress/cuellar-indicted-00155977" target="_blank">indicted on federal corruption charges</a> that alleged he took some $600,000 in bribes from foreign entities. Still, the veteran lawmaker remains largely popular with his fellow Democrats, some of whom argued that with the indictment wiped away, the process had run its course.</p> 
<p>“Under our system of laws, you're still innocent until proven guilty,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/251521" data-person-id="251521">Troy Carter</a> (D-La.). “He was indicted but never went to trial — was never proven to be guilty, never proven to be innocent, because there was no trial, but the pardon overrides that. That’s how the ball bounces.”</p> 
<p>Others deflected criticism to Trump, who suggested in social media posts after the pardon that he expected Cuellar to retire or switch parties and run as a Republican in a gesture of gratitude. Instead Cuellar filed for re-election as a Democrat almost immediately after the pardon came through, and with the legal cloud over his campaign lifted, it increases the chances his seat will remain in Democratic hands in 2026.</p> 
<p>“Nothing else seems to compare to this president and the abuse of the pardon power to get things he wants, including potentially people switching their party affiliation,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422519" data-person-id="422519">Greg Landsman</a> (D-Ohio).</p> 
<p>Cuellar’s allies quietly insist he shouldn’t be sidelined given his unique ability to win a South Texas district that Republicans have targeted for years — and recently redrew in hopes of ousting him. Now, with the pardon, even some Republicans acknowledge he’s in prime position to remain in Congress — and potentially hold a gavel next year if the majority flips.</p> 
<p>“He’s going to have a very merry Christmas,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51507" data-person-id="51507">Michael McCaul</a> (R-Texas).</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-10T20:53:35-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Frustrated Republicans move to force Obamacare vote as warnings mount about the midterms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/frustrated-republicans-move-to-force-obamacare-vote-as-warnings-mount-about-the-midterms-00685423</link>
      <description>It’s not clear if House Democrats will coalesce behind the bipartisan two-year subsidy extension proposed by Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick and Jared Golden.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0a27-d5ec-abbb-dab7d55d0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 16:27:27 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/1e/33/5fb46ccc416aaf6d1b139ef94902/u-s-congress-52699.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) speaks with reporters as he walks to a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 10, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1e/33/5fb46ccc416aaf6d1b139ef94902/u-s-congress-52699.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A group of House Republicans moved to force a vote on extending Obamacare health insurance subsidies that will expire in just three weeks, directly challenging party leaders who appear <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/gop-obamacare-subsidies-expire-00684115" target="_blank">determined to let them lapse</a>.</p> 
<p>At least six Republicans signed a discharge petition filed Wednesday on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6501" target="_blank">bill</a> authored by Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/179757" data-person-id="179757">Jared Golden</a> (D-Maine) that would extend the expiring tax credits for two years while imposing new eligibility requirements. The subsidies are currently used by more than 20 million Americans.</p> 
<p>“It's a time-sensitive matter, and it's an existential matter,” Fitzpatrick told reporters after filing the petition. “You try to do things through the normal course. You try to do things through regular order. You know, [when] all those remedies are exhausted, then you’ve got to go this route, unfortunately.”</p> 
<p>Another discharge petition, seeking a vote on a one-year subsidy extension authored by Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260077" data-person-id="260077">Josh Gottheimer</a> (D-N.J.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.), was also filed Wednesday and quickly picked up support from several Republicans. </p> 
<p>The moves to sidestep Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> came as a growing number of mainstream House Republicans publicly warned that their leaders’ apparent plan to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/06/obamacare-plans-schumer-trump-congress-00679712" target="_blank">allow the tax credits to expire</a> without a replacement in place will cost them their majority in next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>“If we fumble this health care ball, nothing else is going to matter,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259537" data-person-id="259537">John Rutherford</a> of Florida said. “If we don't win the majority in the midterms, then none of this matters. We can't do anything good then. I think everybody understands that.”</p> 
<p>Johnson did not include a subsidy extension in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/no-house-gop-health-plan-00684401" target="_blank">menu of options he presented to members</a> in a closed-door meeting Wednesday morning, and some conservative hard-liners who attended spoke against the idea.</p> 
<p>But many members in the meeting spoke up to call for an extension, to the point that Republicans leaving the room thought that they had in fact decided to forge ahead with an extension.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew</a> (R-N.J.) said it would be a “bad move” for Republicans to allow the tax credits to lapse, adding that he was “worried about my colleagues.”</p> 
<p>“There's a lot of good people who won by one, two, three or four votes,” he said. “Do I think this issue is worth a couple points in an election? Yeah, I do.”</p> 
<p>The Republicans joining Fitzpatrick in signing the discharge petition include Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227109" data-person-id="227109">Don Bacon</a> of Nebraska, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478639" data-person-id="478639">Rob Bresnahan</a> of Pennsylvania, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260571" data-person-id="260571">Kevin Kiley</a> of California, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> of New York and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/194184" data-person-id="194184">Ryan Mackenzie</a> of Pennsylvania, with New York Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/81211" data-person-id="81211">Nick LaLota</a> also indicating he planned to sign. Kiggans signed the petition to discharge her own bill, along with Fitzpatrick, Lawler, Mackenzie and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/159021" data-person-id="159021">David Valadao</a> of California. </p> 
<p>That would be enough to force a vote eventually if all House Democrats sign on to the proposal, but that is by no means assured. House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> is pushing a separate discharge effort on a three-year subsidy extension that does not include new eligibility requirements.</p> 
<p>"There’s one discharge position that I'm committed to at the moment," he said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Even if either petition garnered the necessary 218 signatures, it would not trigger a vote before the Dec. 31 expiration of the enhanced Obamacare tax credits passed under former President Joe Biden. Either measure is subject to a waiting period of at least seven legislative days under House rules, with only six session days left in the year.</p> 
<p>Golden, a centrist Democrat who is retiring after his term ends, said leaders of both parties should pay heed to this discharge petition and others that have succeeded this Congress.</p> 
<p>“Leadership, no matter who they are, in both parties, House and Senate, should pay attention to what's going on with discharge petitions,” he said.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump has so far not weighed in publicly on the extension of the subsidies, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/donald-trump-full-interview-transcript-00681693" target="_blank">saying only</a> that he “wants to give money to the people,” not to insurance companies. Various GOP plans have been proposed that would direct money to health savings accounts instead of premium subsidies that go directly to insurers.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are expected to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/senate-republican-heath-vote-00683250" target="_blank">support one such proposal</a> in a Thursday vote, but it’s not clear it can get more support than the three-year clean extension favored by Democrats.</p> 
<p>None of the alternative proposals has reached critical mass inside the House GOP, and without an extension, premiums for some enrollees on Affordable Care Act marketplaces will soar by hundreds of dollars within a matter of weeks, fueling the panic in the Republican ranks.</p> 
<p>While more GOP lawmakers are speaking out about the subsidy cliff, it’s not clear how many more will be willing to sign a discharge petition — which is typically considered a major breach of party loyalty and an option of last resort.</p> 
<p>For instance, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/367391" data-person-id="367391">Monica De La Cruz</a> (R-Texas) said in an interview she wants to lower health care costs and noted she’s signed onto a plan including a two-year subsidy extension.</p> 
<p>But she said she would have to think about whether she would sign onto a discharge petition.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders have argued, including at Wednesday morning’s conference meeting, that the subsidies are wasteful and that there is not enough internal support to extend them. But others in the party ranks have their doubts.</p> 
<p>“I call bullshit on that,” said one conservative House Republican in a deep-red seat who was granted anonymity to speak frankly. “Most people here know we need a bridge.”</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dems press for changes to crypto bill in counteroffer to GOP</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/dem-crypto-counteroffer-00685364</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0a09-da65-a1bf-eff9d9ae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 16:16:17 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats negotiating a major cryptocurrency bill told key Senate Banking Republicans this week they hope to strengthen prohibitions on stablecoin yield payments and further address concerns about illicit finance, according to <a href="https://politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-09c4-d5ec-abbb-d9d64a3b0000" target="_blank"><u>a summary of a counteroffer obtained by POLITICO</u></a>.</p> 
<p>The document, which summarizes requests that Democrats sent to Senate Banking GOP negotiators on Monday, came after Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/gop-crypto-compromise-offer-00683813" target="_blank">sent an initial offer late last week</a> for a compromise market structure bill, titled the Responsible Financial Innovation Act.</p> 
<p>"We have accepted significant portions of RFIA – including meaningful concessions on major elements like token classification – in an effort to meet Republicans where they are," the summary of the Democratic counteroffer said. "However, despite these substantial compromises, the offer Republicans sent on December 4th still fails to meet the core principles Democrats released in September."</p> 
<p>The group of Democrats working on the crypto bill “is concerned that payments of interest or yield on stablecoin balances could pull deposits from the banking system, especially from community banks that play a pivotal role in supporting underserved communities and operate under Community Reinvestment Act obligations,” the document said. “Yield also incentivizes risky behavior and could threaten the financial system if a stablecoin were to lose its value.”</p> 
<p>The document also said the working group is “committed to ensuring full slates of commissioners at the” agencies that will be tasked with overseeing digital assets under the bill, the Commodity Futures Trading Commission and the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p> 
<p>It also said Democrats are pressing for “limits on elected officials and their families from issuing, endorsing, or profiting from digital assets while in office.” It additionally included an array of illicit finance provisions and token classification provisions that Democrats are seeking to include in the measure.</p> 
<p>Banking Chair Tim Scott (R-S.C.) is pressing to hold a markup before lawmakers leave for the holiday break at the end of next week, but Democrats are pushing back, casting uncertainty over the timeline for the effort. Crypto-friendly Democrats exited a closed-door meeting Wednesday morning pessimistic about the possibility of a committee vote next week.</p> 
<p>“We’re not ready for it,” said Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto, a centrist Nevada Democrat who sits on the Banking panel. “We’ve still got to work through illicit activity, money laundering issues that need to be addressed.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Mark Warner (D-Va.), a senior Banking Committee member, said “we have wide swaths where we don’t have agreement — even any language.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Scott said in a statement that “Republicans on the Senate Banking Committee have spent months negotiating in good faith, circulating multiple rounds of bipartisan text, soliciting extensive stakeholder feedback, and feedback from their Democratic colleagues.”</p> 
<p>“Chairman Scott remains committed to a bipartisan path forward, but progress requires coming to a compromise on legislative text, not press statements or shifting objections,” said the spokesperson, Jeff Naft.</p> 
<p>The comments come amid a flurry of crypto activity on Capitol Hill. Sen. Ruben Gallego met Wednesday with White House crypto adviser Patrick Witt, along with staff from the Treasury Department.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers involved in the talks are discussing a potential bipartisan member-level meeting on Thursday, according to two people with knowledge of the matter who were granted anonymity to discuss closed-door negotiations. Democrats are also set to meet separately with big bank CEOs on Thursday about the crypto bill.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bellwether suburban county’s red shift is now at the center of both parties’ future identities in New York</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/bellwether-suburban-countys-red-shift-is-now-at-the-center-of-both-parties-future-identities-in-new-york-00683750</link>
      <description>Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman is making electability the focus of his gubernatorial campaign message.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0553-dfec-abdf-47578d1b0005</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 14:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/82/31/d19003274557aae1710a365d128d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172980382">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Michael M. Santiago/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman speaks during a campaign rally for then-Republican presidential nominee Donald Trump at Nassau Veterans Memorial Coliseum on Sept. 18, 2024, in Uniondale, New York.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/82/31/d19003274557aae1710a365d128d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172980382" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Bill Mahoney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Bill Mahoney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — The <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/28/new-york-upstate-blue-wave-mamdani-00668749" target="_blank"><u>statewide blue wave</u></a> in which New York Democrats made big gains in nearly every corner of the state this November had one glaring exception: Nassau County.</p> 
<p>While Empire State Democrats scored one of their best election nights on record, Republicans held down America’s archetypal suburb, with GOP candidates notching an 11-0 record in contested executive branch races in Nassau. In the marquee race, County Executive Bruce Blakeman improved on his 2021 performance after four years of wholeheartedly embracing President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Blakeman is hoping to ride that success into next year: He launched <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/republican-bruce-blakeman-planning-to-enter-race-for-new-york-governor-00681465" target="_blank"><u>a 2026 gubernatorial bid</u></a> Tuesday touting his electability.</p> 
<p>“While Democrats made gains nationwide on election night, the Republican party shined bright on Long Island,” the narrator of <a href="https://x.com/NassauExec/status/1998383059863757225" target="_blank"><u>his launch video</u></a> said. “Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman won a Democrat County by 12 percent.”</p> 
<p>Whether Blakeman’s GOP primary opponent Rep. Elise Stefanik can replicate those numbers will be a key question facing Republican voters next June. Blakeman told POLITICO his recent win came down to holding fast to pocketbook issues, hiring more cops and connecting with groups Republicans have ignored in the past. Others say his decisive victory might simply stem from a strong local party organization.</p> 
<p>Whatever the secret of his success, the importance of Nassau extends far beyond next year’s gubernatorial race. It will also be crucial to determining control of the House. </p> 
<p>And it is not just Republicans whose future stands to be shaped by Nassau’s political trends. Democrats have spent years bickering over whether party members in the county have focused too much on distancing themselves from the far left. Moderate Nassau Democrats say progressives like New York City mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani have made their jobs tougher.</p> 
<p>“Most of the television commercials that they put up were all about ‘Mamdani, Mamdani, democratic socialists,’” Nassau Democratic Chair Jay Jacobs said. “Their tagline was, in effect, ‘Vote Republican and save Nassau County from becoming a socialist county.’ That plays well with a moderate audience.”</p> 
<p>Democratic struggles in Nassau County have become a regular through line, revisited with each election cycle. While it was at the heart of the national blue wave in 2017 and 2018, the GOP won big there in 2021 local races. Four years after a 16-point Democratic win in Nassau in the 2018 gubernatorial election, the party suffered an 11-point loss in 2022. Then in 2024, Trump became the first Republican presidential candidate to win Nassau County since 1988.</p> 
<p>How that pattern plays out next year remains an open question.</p> 
<p>Rep. Laura Gillen, a Democrat in a battleground Nassau swing district, “is the number one target in the country for Republicans,” said Larry Levy, executive dean of the National Center for Suburban Studies at Hofstra University. “They really think they can win in that district and they’re going to put an unlimited amount of money in.”</p> 
<p>An effective GOP candidate at the top of the ticket would help considerably toward that end.</p> 
<p>Stefanik’s team disputed the idea that Blakeman has a magic formula for electoral success, pointing to his unsuccessful bids for <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1998/06/03/nyregion/republicans-pick-challenger-for-state-comptroller.html" target="_blank"><u>state comptroller</u></a>, <a href="https://nypost.com/2009/01/07/goper-drops-out-of-mayoral-run/" target="_blank"><u>New York City mayor</u></a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2010/06/04/nyregion/04repubs.html" target="_blank"><u>U.S. Senate</u></a>. He last ran for higher office when he lost a congressional bid in 2014 — the same year Stefanik flipped a House seat with a 21-point victory.</p> 
<p>Yet Blakeman believes he has a solid case to make.</p> 
<p>He attributed his success this election cycle to holding true to past promises to not raise taxes and hire more police officers, while also building connections to groups Republicans haven’t focused on in the past. He rattled off a long list of outreach efforts undertaken by the county in recent years, such as a Feliz Navidad celebration and a Lunar New Year festival.</p> 
<p>“We also reached out to the Muslim community and talked to them about things that were important to them,” Blakeman said. “I appointed the first Muslim police chaplain in Nassau County history, and shortly I will be appointing the first Sikh police chaplain.”</p> 
<p>Trump, who has become politically toxic in many New York suburbs, will undoubtedly be a factor in next year’s race. On Monday, he described both Blakeman and Stefanik as “great,” and while he has not yet expressed a preference for either, that could change. And arguably no local official in the northeast has done more to associate themselves with Trumpism than Blakeman.</p> 
<p>Under his leadership, Nassau County <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/newyork/news/long-island-democrats-seek-reimbursement-for-trump-rally/" target="_blank"><u>spent more than $1 million</u></a> on police overtime hosting Trump for a campaign rally last fall. Blakeman has been New York’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/02/23/hochul-nassau-transgender-athletics-00142865" target="_blank"><u>most visible opponent</u></a> of letting transgender girls participate in female sports and has had the <a href="https://www.cityandstateny.com/policy/2025/02/nassau-county-deputizes-local-cops-act-ice-agents/402777/" target="_blank"><u>county partner</u></a> with ICE on immigration enforcement efforts. In late November, he announced a <a href="https://nypost.com/2025/11/28/us-news/nassau-exec-bruce-blakeman-plans-a-wall-of-surveillance-at-nyc-border-after-mamdani-win/" target="_blank"><u>wall of surveillance</u></a> on the Queens border to conduct facial recognition on visitors from Mamdani’s New York.</p> 
<p>“I never ran away from President Trump,” Blakeman told POLITICO. “I supported President Trump, and I was very vocal about my support for President Trump”</p> 
<p>The approach is a far cry from how Nassau County Democrats have handled Mamdani.</p> 
<p>Jacobs, who also serves as chair of the state Democratic Party, famously distanced himself from the mayor-elect in the fall, declining to offer an endorsement after Mamdani became the Democratic nominee. And he’s hardly the only local Democrat who falls into that category: “Mamdani’s reckless agenda filled with unachievable promises and contempt for certain groups threatens NY’s economy and safety,”<a href="https://x.com/LauraAGillen/status/1968005348037476728" target="_blank"><u>Gillen said</u></a> this fall.</p> 
<p>Democrats based in New York City contend this is exactly what their counterparts on Long Island should not be doing.</p> 
<p>“When the leading Democrats in the county are telling everyone that the Democratic Party sucks, it’s hard to convince voters to vote for your party,” said state Sen. Deputy Leader Mike Gianaris, who heads the Senate Democrats’ campaign arm. “They should start looking inside themselves and start trying to make a positive case for Democrats, or I think they can expect this to continue.”</p> 
<p>Unlike in Nassau, Long Island’s neighboring Suffolk County showed significant signs of the pendulum swinging back to the left this November. Democrats grew their share of the vote by 10 or more points in four of the five top town races, and they flipped seats in places like Shelter Island and Riverhead.</p> 
<p>Democrats haven’t been completely without hopeful signs in Nassau either.</p> 
<p>They won a victory last month in a newly-drawn county legislative district, denying Blakeman’s allies a supermajority and giving them the ability to put their foot in the door during budget talks. In 2024, Tom Suozzi broke the Republicans’ hold on four congressional seats by winning a special election. Gillen won another seat later that year, thanks to a two-point victory in a district that favored Democrats by 11 points as recently as 2020.</p> 
<p>But even the good Democratic vibes in the 2024 congressional races underscored a long-standing issue in the county — winning back the seat in Suozzi’s special election would not have been necessary if local Democrats had done opposition research into the now-disgraced former Rep. George Santos before the 2022 election.</p> 
<p>The failure to do so illustrates another reality in the area. After decades of controlling Nassau, Republicans built a well-oiled machine.</p> 
<p>“The relative strength of the organizations — it’s just not even close,” said Levy, who likened the GOP’s political operation to that of former Chicago Mayor Richard Daley. “At a time when all over the country, political organizations are shrinking in influence for a variety of reasons, Nassau still has an old-fashioned Daley machine-like operation that can get a vote out in ways that the Democrats can’t.”</p> 
<p>Democrats didn’t do much to end that structural disadvantage when they won power in 2017.</p> 
<p>“Arguably the Democrats could have, should have done more to leverage the patronage opportunities to raise money and create more foot soldiers to work politically,” Levy said. But any steps they made in that direction were halted when the political winds started to shift: “Anything that happened before the pandemic almost doesn’t count.”</p> 
<p>Jacobs, who said his party was outspent by a more than four-to-one margin in the county executive’s race, didn’t disagree with the characterization.</p> 
<p>“They raised and spent $15 million. That’s an extraordinary amount of money,” he said. “That was supplemented by both county mailings and town mailings that, in my judgement and other peoples’ judgement, were campaign-like pieces paid for by the taxpayer.”</p> 
<p>That onslaught of ads built off years of tying local Democrats to policies like bail reform or high-density housing or candidates like Mamdani, former New York City Mayor Bill de Blasio and Gov. Kathy Hochul. The Democratic brand “is really doing poorly” in the area, Jacobs said.</p> 
<p>“People — even at the doors when you’re collecting petitions, even when they’re Democrats — are upset with our party,” he said. “That’s been driven by a really well-funded consistent campaign by Republicans to set the narrative that all Democrats are either wild extremists themselves or so afraid of them that they bend to whatever the far left in our party wants. Neither of which is true, but too many people believe it.”</p> 
<p>Nassau Republicans, meanwhile, aren’t shying away from a president whom the opposition characterizes as an extremist.</p> 
<p>“In a county with 110,000 more Democrats, to win by 35,000 votes is something that is very special,” Blakeman said. “You have to be true to your values, and not a phony.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP erupts over health care as leaders hunt for a plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/no-house-gop-health-plan-00684401</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0911-d40e-a5bf-f937b98b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 11:23:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders presented no firm plan Tuesday for advancing health care legislation as anxiety rises in the GOP ranks over the impending expiration of key Obamacare subsidies at the end of the year.</p> 
<p>Instead, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> presented attendees of a closed-door conference meeting with list of 10 possible policies that could get votes in the coming weeks or months, according to five Republicans in the room. </p> 
<p>Some were more specific, such as an expansion of health savings accounts and an overhaul of pharmaceutical benefit manager oversight. Others were vague, including one bullet point that simply said, "Innovation." The list did not include an extension of the expiring tax credits.</p> 
<p>The presentation was followed by a heated discussion over the path forward on health care for the party, and vulnerable members including Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.) stood up to warn against the political fallout of failing to extend the expiring subsidies.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/0a/78/b9ba80724925888e1393fbcf672c/gop-health.jpg" alt="A slide on GOP health care legislative options presented at a House Republican Conference meeting on Dec. 10, 2025." data-portal-copyright="House Republican Conference" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="A slide on GOP health care legislative options presented at a House Republican Conference meeting on Dec. 10, 2025."/><p>Some later expressed their dismay at how poorly they believe GOP leaders have handled the topic.</p> 
<p>“There was a general uneasiness because nothing is coming together,” said a House Republican, one of several granted anonymity to speak candidly about the private meeting.</p> 
<p>“We wasted so much time,” one conservative Republican said, also lamenting the lack of a unified GOP plan with just seven session days left in the year. </p> 
<p>More than 20 GOP members spanning various factions inside the conference lined up at microphones to weigh in at one point. Hard-liners, for instance, raised opposition to any extension of the subsidies if they don't include further restrictions abortion coverage, a view that clashes with Republicans in at-risk districts next fall. </p> 
<p>“There was no consensus,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/195970" data-person-id="195970">Ralph Norman</a> (R-S.C.) said.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders continue to believe they are on track to vote on several bills next week on some less controversial items, such as the HSA expansion and funding a program to reduce out-of-pocket costs for Obamacare enrollees. But an extension of the expiring tax credits is not in the cards, according to three other Republicans granted anonymity to describe leadership thinking.</p> 
<p>Johnson indicated in the meeting that Republicans could continue working on health care into the first half of next year — just ahead of the midterm elections.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Judiciary Dems request administration records related to 'Seditious Six'</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/judiciary-dems-probe-00684293</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0870-d533-a99b-0c7011160000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 08:52:57 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Judiciary Committee Democrats are requesting the Justice Department and FBI hand over internal records related to six Democratic members of Congress with military and law enforcement backgrounds who filmed an anti-Trump video urging troops not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p>It comes after some of the Democrats who appeared in the video <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/democrats-fbi-trump-00668584" target="_blank">disclosed late last month</a> that the FBI had contacted the House and Senate sergeants at arms requesting voluntary interviews. Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth has separately requested a briefing by Dec. 10 of the review into the military record of one of the Democrats, Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), a Navy veteran.</p> 
<p>“We write with grave concern that the Trump Administration is weaponizing the Federal Bureau of Investigation against federal lawmakers who merely restated current law,” reads the letter, spearheaded by top Senate Judiciary Democrat Dick Durbin of Illinois <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-05f6-d744-a5db-0ff6f0d90000" target="_blank">and obtained first by POLITICO</a>. “This abuse of federal law enforcement authority as an instrument of retribution against the President’s political opponents is a threat to the constitutional freedoms of all Americans.”</p> 
<p>Senators added in the letter that it was "particularly alarming” that the FBI would reportedly push its domestic terrorism agents to open up a seditious conspiracy investigation into the six Democrats — two senators and four House members — who participated in the video message.</p> 
<p>“It is facially unconstitutional to prosecute protected speech, whether that speech is by the American people or their representatives in Congress, and it is absurd to contend that statements reiterating the law alone are a predicate for a seditious conspiracy investigation,” the Judiciary Democrats wrote.</p> 
<p>They added, “The Department of Justice’s resources would be better spent ensuring that the Department of Defense is following the law as it conducts military action.”</p> 
<p>Durbin and his colleagues are requesting Attorney General Pam Bondi and FBI Director Kash Patel hand over any documents or communications by Dec. 29, dating back to Nov. 18, between either of the two agencies and President Donald Trump or other White House officials relating to the six lawmakers’ statements.</p> 
<p>They are also seeking any related documents or communications since Nov. 18 between the DOJ or FBI with the Washington Field Office or the U.S. Attorney’s Office for the District of Columbia. They are additionally seeking any similar records between the FBI and Justice Department and the Department of Defense. </p> 
<p>Spokespeople for the FBI and DOJ declined to comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spanberger endorses Elaine Luria in her House comeback bid</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/spanberger-endorses-luria-00683599</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-04f1-d889-a1df-fdffe6940000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 08:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Virginia Gov.-elect Abigail Spanberger is endorsing her former House colleague Elaine Luria's comeback bid in the latest effort by Democrats to clear the primary in a highly targeted purple district. </p> 
<p>"I am excited to support Elaine Luria’s campaign for Congress, because Virginians deserve a dedicated public servant who is focused on delivering for the people of Hampton Roads and the Eastern Shore,” Spanberger said in a statement. </p> 
<p>Both women flipped GOP-held seats in the 2018 midterms and became part of a bloc of incoming House Democrats with national security backgrounds. </p> 
<p>"Since our first campaign together when we made history in 2018, Governor-elect Spanberger and I have worked closely together to lower prices, cut health care costs, and invest in Virginia. I look forward to continuing our work together to lower costs for working families and deliver for the people of Hampton Roads," Luria said. </p> 
<p>The district, which is currently represented by GOP Rep. Jen Kiggans, is the most competitive in Virginia and has flipped between parties four times over the past two decades. </p> 
<p>Virginia Democrats expect it to become bluer in a potential redraw. Navy reservist James Osyf suspended his Democratic campaign Tuesday, saying in a statement he would "await clarity on the outcome of the Commonwealth’s redistricting plan.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Johnson’s turn to deliver a health plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/mike-johnson-republicans-health-care-plan-obamacare-00684274</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-06b6-d533-a99b-06f671810000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Get ready for the enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies to lapse.</p> 
<p>All signs are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/gop-obamacare-subsidies-expire-00684115" target="_blank">pointing in that direction</a> as President Donald Trump refuses to endorse an extension and Senate Republicans coalesce behind a plan from Sens. Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) and Bill Cassidy (R-La.) that would end the Obamacare tax credits and instead expand <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/senate-republican-heath-vote-00683250" target="_blank">government-funded health savings accounts</a>.</p> 
<p>Now House Republicans are racing to prepare their own health care framework to vote on next week before leaving for the holidays — one that also likely would not extend the expiring Obamacare subsidies, which were supercharged as part of the Democrats’ 2021 pandemic relief package.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson and House Majority Leader Steve Scalise will brief their conference Wednesday morning on all the options for this framework, which Scalise and relevant committee chairs helped craft.</p> 
<p>“It won’t just be concepts we’re talking about ... It’ll be very specific things that are available in bill format,” Scalise told reporters Tuesday, noting some provisions will reflect proposals that ultimately did not make it into the final GOP megabill over the summer. He said each piece will be presented individually “to see where the consensus is and let members decide.”</p> 
<p><b>— Moderates sound the alarm:</b> Many rank-and-file Republicans are still pushing for an extension, worried about voter backlash over the ensuing skyrocketing premiums. Even some Trump aides have advised that an extension would be politically prudent.</p> 
<p>“We can agree that the current construct is flawed, but that letting them expire is not acceptable,” Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) said in an interview Tuesday. “That doesn’t work.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and Rep. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.) have been proposing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635" target="_blank">their own</a> blueprints <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/15/kiggans-house-gop-aca-00561747" target="_blank">that would include</a> extensions. But neither has earned approval from GOP leaders, who are under pressure from conservatives who say the tax credits are rife with fraud and abuse.</p> 
<p>Scalise didn’t rule out an extension Tuesday. Still, he said, “at the end of the day, we’ve got to do what the consensus of our members want to do.”</p> 
<p><b>— Don't rule out the discharge petition:&nbsp;</b>While Republicans might not currently have the support in their conference to pass an extension, the Fitzpatrick and Kiggans plans have bipartisan backing. Fitzpatrick told POLITICO last week he believes he has 218 votes for his bill and didn’t rule out filing a discharge petition to circumvent leadership and force a vote.</p> 
<p>Some House Republicans told POLITICO Tuesday they were even more inclined to back a discharge petition after Trump’s recent comments refusing to endorse an extension. That includes Rep. Jeff Van Drew (R-N.J.), who told reporters Tuesday he would support a discharge petition for either the Fitzpatrick or Kiggans proposal, if there were no other options.</p> 
<p>“I respect the speaker tremendously, but I disagree with them on this,” Van Drew said. “We just can’t listen to a handful of people.”</p> 
<p><b>— Eyes on the White House: </b>The Trump administration has yet to provide clear guidance on what they want Congress to pass. But Tuesday night, POLITICO saw James Braid and James Blair — the White House director of legislative affairs and deputy chief of staff, respectively — head into a meeting with House GOP leaders and committee chairs.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Dems blast Senate GOP health plan: </b>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer will host a news conference on health insurance premiums at 10:15 a.m. It comes a day after he criticized Senate Republicans’ <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/senate-republican-heath-vote-00683250" target="_blank">health plan</a> as “dead on arrival.”</p> 
<p><b>— House votes on NDAA: </b>The House is scheduled to vote on the National Defense Authorization Act Wednesday afternoon as a group of hard-liners weigh whether to hold up the bill over complaints it would give aid to Ukraine and wouldn’t include a central banking digital currency ban. The big question is whether Republicans will be able to adopt the procedural rule governing floor debate on the NDAA.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP moves to let Obamacare subsidies expire as Trump promises ‘money to the people’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/gop-obamacare-subsidies-expire-00684115</link>
      <description>As the president rails against insurance companies, other Republicans say allowing a subsidy lapse is “not acceptable.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-057e-d889-a1df-fd7ee5020000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 18:48:13 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/bd/0d/ca815173435fbf64d6e6a285d522/u-s-congress-11758.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Speaker Mike Johnson is scrambling to cobble together health legislation after promising a House vote this month.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bd/0d/ca815173435fbf64d6e6a285d522/u-s-congress-11758.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican leaders on Capitol Hill are moving decisively away from extending key Obamacare tax credits that help more than 20 million Americans pay for health insurance — following direct cues from President Donald Trump while also stoking ire among many in the GOP who fear severe political repercussions.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/donald-trump-full-interview-transcript-00681693" target="_blank">Monday interview with POLITICO</a>, Trump refused to endorse a continuation of the expiring subsidies, even as his administration faces mounting pressure to address rising costs for Americans. He instead laid out his own vision for health care: “I want to give the money to the people, not to the insurance companies.”</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans now plan to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/senate-republican-heath-vote-00683250" target="_blank">offer a proposal for a vote Thursday</a> that would let the subsidies expire and instead encourage the use of health savings accounts. That abrupt shift in strategy is in turn putting new pressure on House GOP leaders to come up with their own health plan, according to four people who attended a closed-door meeting with Speaker Mike Johnson and senior Republicans Tuesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>Yet after months of pressure from competing factions, lawmakers inside the meeting didn’t reach a conclusion and Johnson is <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/johnson-house-gop-health-care-plan-00676661" target="_blank">still trying to figure out</a> what that plan should be. House GOP staff Tuesday were prepping a health care framework to give Republicans something to vote on next week before they leave Washington for the holidays — one that, for now, does not include an extension of the enhanced Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>For many Republicans facing tough reelection races and even some in deep-red areas with a high reliance on the tax credits, following Trump’s one-sentence policy prescription would harm Americans and make for political disaster as the Dec. 31 expiration of the tax credits looms.</p> 
<p>“We can agree that the current construct is flawed, but that letting them expire is not acceptable,” Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) said in an interview Tuesday. “That doesn’t work.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick is pushing a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6501" target="_blank">competing proposal</a> that would extend the tax credits for two years while imposing an income cap and other eligibility restrictions. Fitzpatrick’s bill also includes new HSA provisions and a bipartisan package aimed at lowering drug costs, but he said it was unrealistic for GOP leaders to completely replace the subsidy framework in a matter of weeks.</p> 
<p>“They can just dig themselves into an ideological corner all day long — it’s not fixing the problem,” Fitzpatrick added. “We can’t live in this fantasy land.”</p> 
<p>But Johnson appears determined to cobble together a health care framework that will not include even a short-term extension of the subsidies, which <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/aca-marketplace-premium-payments-would-more-than-double-on-average-next-year-if-enhanced-premium-tax-credits-expire/" target="_blank">can cut premiums</a> for many families by $1,000 a year or more. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2025/12/08/gop-struggles-on-affordability-message-00680485" target="_blank">blindsided members of his own leadership circle</a> and senior Republicans who have been involved in health care policy work when he announced last week his intentions to unveil a GOP health plan early this week and hold a vote before year's end.</p> 
<p>“What health care plan?” said one of the senior Republicans who has been involved in the talks and was granted anonymity to share a candid reaction to Johnson’s pledge.</p> 
<p>Turning Johnson’s promise into legislation has been difficult. As of Tuesday evening, the House GOP framework centered on an expansion of health savings accounts and funding for cost-sharing reductions — a type of Obamacare subsidy meant to reduce out-of-pocket health costs, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the deliberations.</p> 
<p>While the plan does not currently include a temporary subsidy extension, some senior House Republicans say it might still be on the table — including Rep. Lisa McClain of Michigan, the No. 4 GOP leader, who said she believed it was still an option as she left the health care meeting Tuesday.</p> 
<p>It’s also still to be determined whether the plan will be offered up as a suite of individual bills or packaged together. But the goal is for GOP lawmakers to have “something” to vote on before the end of next week, according to one of the senior House Republicans involved in the talks — even if there is no time left for the Senate to pass it before the subsidies lapse.</p> 
<p>GOP members will be briefed on the talks during their closed-door conference meeting Wednesday morning, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal planning. They will not be presented with a formal plan, they said.</p> 
<p>The health care sprint also comes as Johnson faces down growing displeasure inside the GOP over his leadership style, where he has repeatedly sought to bulldoze internal dissent and march in lockstep with Trump. In this case, Johnson has so far sided with the bulk of his conference who want to see the Obamacare subsidies expire — even though some Trump aides have counseled that an extension would be politically prudent.</p> 
<p>The White House was on the cusp of endorsing a two-year continuation of the subsidies just before Thanksgiving, but top Republicans on the Hill were not fully consulted first and moved to quash the idea — to the horror of many in the rank-and-file who favor an extension.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think leadership understands just how upset people are,” said one House Republican who among several granted anonymity to speak frankly about internal conversations. “People are getting desperate.”</p> 
<p>In fact, according to six other House GOP lawmakers and senior aides with direct knowledge, enough Republicans could sign a discharge petition that would sidestep Johnson and force a vote on extending the expiring subsidies. One of those House Republicans said they would be willing to support a discharge of Fitzpatrick’s legislation, which largely mirrors the White House trial balloon, or another bill from Rep. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.) and is waiting to see details of what Johnson proposes as an alternative.</p> 
<p>“We shall see,” the lawmaker said.</p> 
<p>Some in the GOP who support an extension have floated a short-term patch until Jan. 30 in order to buy some more time to come up with a deal. Many Republicans in the White House and on Capitol Hill believe that once the tax credits expire, there could be a chance to work out a wider health care deal next month that could tackle issues such as HSAs and drug prices.</p> 
<p>While that argument has its merits on paper, people involved in the talks say a short-term punt wouldn’t make much sense for people trying to buy health insurance for the entire year and could create major logistical hassles.</p> 
<p>One of the many problems is the White House itself isn’t providing any clear guidance amid all the internal divisions. The Trump administration itself has been and still is deeply divided about allowing the Obamacare tax credits to lapse, according to two administration officials and three senior House Republicans involved in the conversations.</p> 
<p>“It depends on who you ask,” said a senior House Republican about the White House’s views on health care.</p> 
<p>One White House official said Tuesday that “policy teams are looking at a lot of different avenues” and that “three weeks is actually a lot of time for a lot of stuff to come together.” However, both the House and Senate are set to adjourn for the holidays at the end of next week.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3386" target="_blank">Senate plan</a> now set for a vote Thursday, from Sens. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana and Mike Crapo of Idaho, quickly won support inside the GOP this week amid fears that the party would look hapless if they did not put up an alternative to <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3385" target="_blank">Democrats’ plan</a> to extend the subsidies for three years.</p> 
<p>But there are still plenty of lawmakers who are anxious about voting to upend the health care system with the deadline looming and no signals from the White House on what Trump would accept.</p> 
<p>"There's just not enough time to do a comprehensive bill," one House Republican said, adding that the expiring subsidies will be “a problem for everyone” in the GOP.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Cheyenne Haslett and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-09T16:09:13-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Senate Republicans set to put Cassidy-Crapo health proposal up for a vote Thursday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/senate-republican-heath-vote-00683250</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-049c-d533-a99b-04fc70140003</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:38:15 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans will offer a <a href="http://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3386" target="_blank">health care plan</a> for a vote Thursday alongside a Democratic proposal to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies, capping off days of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/senate-republicans-obamacare-health-00682318" target="_blank">furious behind-the-scenes debates</a>.</p> 
<p>The decision announced Tuesday by Senate Majority Leader John Thune is a U-turn from just a day prior, when GOP leadership appeared likely to skip a vote on a Republican alternative to the Democrats’ proposal, which would continue the expiring subsidies for three years.</p> 
<p>But that strategy sparked grumbling from various corners of the GOP conference, who believed they should put up their own plan to illustrate that their party has health care ideas, even if some Republican senators ultimately aren't supportive. The matter was discussed at a closed-door GOP policy lunch Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Some corners of the conference were caught off guard by the expectation that there wouldn't be a vote, especially as Democrats hammer them over health care, according to two people granted anonymity to speak candidly about the reason for the shift.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans ultimately agreed to vote on a proposal from Sens. Mike Crapo of Idaho and Bill Cassidy of Louisiana, who chair the Finance and HELP committees respectively. Their bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/cassidy-crapo-unveil-alternative-to-obamacare-subsidies-00682315" target="_blank">expands health savings accounts and includes funding</a> for Americans to spend on health expenses but does not extend the Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>“Our members decided that we’re going to vote on a Crapo-Cassidy proposal,” Thune told reporters.</p> 
<p>That fits in with a rough framework supported by President Donald Trump, who declined to commit to extending the subsidies in a Monday interview with POLITICO. “I want to give the money to the people, not to the insurance companies,” he said.</p> 
<p>But a White House official, granted anonymity to discuss the administration’s thinking, said that there was not a preferred plan among the several currently floating around Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Neither the Crapo-Cassidy plan nor the Democratic proposal will get the 60 votes needed to advance Thursday. And it's far from clear if the Republican proposal will win the backing of all 53 GOP senators.</p> 
<p>Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.), who has his own competing proposals, said he’s “still looking at” the Crapo-Cassidy bill, for instance.</p> 
<p>Republicans have struggled perennially for years to unite around a health care plan. Thune acknowledged Tuesday that most, but potentially not all, of the conference would back the bill.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said some in her party “still have questions about implementation” of the Cassidy-Cassidy plan, though she said it was good Republicans were putting something forward.</p> 
<p>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) said Tuesday after the lunch that she was still reviewing the legislation.</p> 
<p>“There are many good provisions in that plan that I think would be helpful to driving down health care costs,” Collins said.</p> 
<p>Collins and Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/gop-senators-circulate-health-care-plans-ahead-of-thursday-vote-00680645" target="_blank">proposed a two-year extension</a> of the expiring Affordable Care Act credits with new eligibility restrictions such as income caps and minimum premium payments. If the enhanced subsidies expire, the tax credits will revert back to their original, pre-Covid levels.</p> 
<p>Other GOP senators could try to pass or set up votes this week on their own competing bills by seeking unanimous consent, according to their colleagues.</p> 
<p><i>Cheyenne Haslett and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brad Lander set to challenge Rep. Dan Goldman from the left</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/brad-lander-set-to-challenge-rep-dan-goldman-from-the-left-00682619</link>
      <description>The city comptroller and former mayoral candidate will have the endorsement of Zohran Mamdani, two people tell POLITICO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-038e-dea0-a7df-0bdff6c40001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:20:56 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4f/a1/7245c2624d1f8a0fde3179278fac/ice-protests-new-york-15327.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Olga Fedorova/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Brad Lander, the progressive New York City city comptroller, is set to launch his primary challenge to Rep. Dan Goldman.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4f/a1/7245c2624d1f8a0fde3179278fac/ice-protests-new-york-15327.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Emily Ngo</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Emily Ngo</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NEW YORK — Brooklyn progressive Brad Lander is planning to launch his bid for Congress as soon as Wednesday, challenging Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/320509" data-person-id="320509">Dan Goldman</a> from the political left in a district that went big for Zohran Mamdani, three people familiar with his preparations told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>The city comptroller is expected to open his campaign with a pivotal endorsement from Mamdani, the democratic socialist mayor-elect’s first formal nod since his November election win upended the Democratic landscape. Lander has also sought support from progressive Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51605" data-person-id="51605">Bernie Sanders</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a>, according to two people close to Lander.</p> 
<p>Lander shot his campaign launch video, with some scenes from his Park Slope community, two people with knowledge of his operations said. And he is interviewing for the Working Families Party endorsement, four more people confirmed to POLITICO. The people looped into Lander’s plans were granted anonymity to protect a sensitive rollout process.</p> 
<p>Lander’s entry will mark New York progressives’ boldest salvo yet in primaries to unseat more mainstream party members on the heels of Mamdani’s ascension to the helm of the country’s largest city. The fiscal wonk and Israel critic is a favorite of left-leaning voters in the liberal congressional district, which encompasses lower Manhattan and northwest Brooklyn and overlaps Lander’s former City Council district.</p> 
<p>“These are urgent times when ICE agents are abducting our neighbors, Donald Trump is stealing money from New York City’s bank account. I think people are looking for leaders who will put their bodies on the line,” Lander told reporters Friday after <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/2025/12/05/comptroller-brad-lander-pleads-not-guilty-in-ice-protest-as-he-mulls-run-for-congress/" target="_blank">pleading not guilty</a> to trespassing and related charges tied to <a href="https://x.com/emilyngo/status/1968769479623557346?s=20" target="_blank">his September sit-in protesting</a> the detention of migrants at 26 Federal Plaza. He said Friday he had not made a decision on running for Congress but was seriously considering it.</p> 
<p>Lander's team did not immediately comment on his plans Tuesday when contacted by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>Mamdani defeated Andrew Cuomo in Goldman’s 10th Congressional District by 23 points in the June mayoral primary. In that same contest, Lander placed third in the district, just a quarter of a percentage point behind Cuomo, the moderate former governor. Lander helped clear the democratic socialist’s path to the nomination <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/13/mamdani-lander-cross-endorsing-mayor-00405357" target="_blank">with a cross-endorsement deal</a> that many in the progressive movement <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/02/brad-lander-is-riding-a-wave-of-good-will-00436553" target="_blank">lauded as a sacrifice</a> for the cause. While Lander is a progressive and Working Families Party darling, he is not a member of the Democratic Socialists of America.</p> 
<p>Goldman — a Manhattan Democrat, second-term House member and former prosecutor — was lead counsel in President Donald Trump’s first impeachment process. While Goldman is a scion of the Levi Strauss empire and a staunch defender of Israel, he has championed progressive policies as co-sponsor of Medicare for All and Green New Deal legislation. The incumbent has advocated <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/12/05/mamdanis-volunteer-army-reassembles-00678203?nname=new-york-playbook&amp;nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b74f0000&amp;nrid=0000014f-8906-d780-a9ef-9d7e2a4c0000#:~:text=Rep.%20Dan%20Goldman-,TAX%20MYSELF%3A,-Rep.%20Dan%20Goldman" target="_blank">for taxing the ultra-wealthy</a> — including himself — and criticized settler violence in the West Bank. Both Goldman and Lander are Jewish.</p> 
<p>Lander and Goldman are aligned in the resistance against Trump’s ramped-up deportation agenda and have <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/10/01/what-the-shutdown-means-for-new-york-00589342?nname=new-york-playbook&amp;nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b74f0000&amp;nrid=0000014f-8906-d780-a9ef-9d7e2a4c0000#:~:text=Wong/Getty%20Images-,PRESSURE%20ON%20ICE%3A,-Rep.%20Dan%20Goldman" target="_blank">even worked in tandem.</a> Both Democrats are a frequent presence at 26 Federal Plaza, the lower Manhattan administrative building where migrants have been detained by masked federal agents as they attend immigration court hearings.</p> 
<p>“These are nonviolent, noncriminal people, often escaping terrible conditions in their country, seeking refuge here, and now, they are being yanked away from their families, detained and deported,” Goldman told reporters Monday as he and Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/193043" data-person-id="193043">Adriano Espaillat</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51659" data-person-id="51659">Nydia Velázquez</a> unveiled legislation to protect migrants from arrest as they attend their court dates and follow pathways to legal status.</p> 
<p>At least two other progressive Democrats are considering a bid for Congress in the district. City Council Member Alexa Avilés, chair of the council’s Immigration Committee and a democratic socialist, and former Assemblymember Yuh-Line Niou, who came in second place to Goldman in the 2022 primary for the district, also appealed to the Manhattan and Brooklyn chapters of the Working Families Party for their support. Goldman did as well.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: What Trump told POLITICO about health care</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/president-trump-health-care-obamacare-00682436</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0173-dc13-a39b-3bff436e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>TRUMP’S TAKE ON HEALTH TALKS —</b> President Donald Trump in an exclusive interview with POLITICO's Dasha Burns was noncommittal on the fate of Obamacare subsidies set to lapse at the end of the month, the latest sign that Republicans will let them expire.</p> 
<p>Pressed on whether he would intervene and ask Congress to extend the tax credits, Trump said, “I don’t know. I’m going to have to see.” He instead touted his rough vision for a health care revamp.</p> 
<p>“I want to give the people better health insurance for less money,” he said. “The people will get the money and they’re going to buy the health insurance that they want.”</p> 
<p>Watch the interview and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/trump-dasha-burns-interview-europe-immigration-ukraine-00682016" target="_blank">read a rundown</a> of the newsiest bits on Latin America, the economy, the Supreme Court and Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.). “She was a loyal person until I wasn’t able to answer her phone calls,” he said.</p> 
<p><b>SENATE GOP SEARCHES FOR UNITY —</b> With just two days until Democrats get a vote on their proposal to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies, Republican senators <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/senate-republicans-obamacare-health-00682318" target="_blank">have yet to coalesce behind an alternative</a> to put up alongside it.</p> 
<p>“What signal would that send if Republicans say, ‘Yeah, we’re going to say no to the Democrats’ plan, but we’re not going to offer anything?’” Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said. “The message that will send is, good luck to the American people, and we don’t really care.”</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are expected to discuss their options at a closed-door lunch Tuesday afternoon and make a decision about which direction to take.</p> 
<p><b>— The competing proposals:</b> Factions of the conference are either ready to extend enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies or replace them with new frameworks.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune on Monday praised a proposal by Sens. Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) and Bill Cassidy (R-La.) expanding the use of health savings accounts and directing funding toward them — without extending the tax credits. Thune took steps Monday night to make the bill available for a vote later this week, as Republicans try to keep options on the table. But he didn’t commit to putting it up for a vote Thursday.</p> 
<p>Sens. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) and Susan Collins (R-Maine) proposed a two-year subsidy extension with new income caps and other eligibility restrictions — a plan that won some Democratic interest from Illinois Sen. Dick Durbin, the No. 2 party leader.</p> 
<p><b>— The path ahead: </b>The Democratic proposal is likely to fail Thursday even though a handful of Republicans haven’t said yet how they will vote. Hawley, for instance, said Monday “everything is on the table.”</p> 
<p>But Thune is suggesting there will be further bipartisan negotiations afterward. There’s hope on both sides of the aisle that failure could spark new momentum as some lawmakers start eyeing Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cutoff to land a health care deal.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— NDAA hits Rules: </b>The House plans to vote on the National Defense Authorization Act Wednesday afternoon — assuming it gets through the Rules Committee Tuesday evening. House Democrats could support the defense policy bill after House Armed Services ranking member Adam Smith (D-Wash.) signaled he’s on board. That means the biggest issue for Republicans likely won’t be final passage, but instead the rule vote Wednesday if some in the GOP choose to tank the party-line vote.</p> 
<p><b>— Digital trade legislation: </b>Sen. Todd Young (R-Ind.) is introducing a bipartisan bill Tuesday that would empower the president to negotiate and enforce digital trade agreements — but also give Congress the opportunity to review and block those agreements. The move signals potential renewed interest from Congress in addressing the taxation of digital goods.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Mia McCarthy and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-08T23:25:20-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Why Senate Republicans aren't uniting behind a health care plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/senate-republicans-obamacare-health-00682318</link>
      <description>Voting on any alternative to Democrats' Obamacare extension is likely to highlight the divisions in the GOP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-00ba-d77a-a99f-09fe1e300000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 20:32:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/88/78/d79427e848daa2801ef8c856799d/u-s-congress-70222.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I don’t think they’re serious about wanting to do a deal yet," Thune said about Democrats Monday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/88/78/d79427e848daa2801ef8c856799d/u-s-congress-70222.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/gop-senators-circulate-health-care-plans-ahead-of-thursday-vote-00680645" target="_blank">no shortage of health care plans</a>. The challenge is getting all 53 of them to rally behind one.</p> 
<p>Three days before a high-profile vote on a Democratic proposal to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies, GOP senators are nowhere near coalescing behind any single alternative that could be put up alongside it. Instead, Republican leaders appear happy allowing their members to freelance, even as Democrats and some in their own ranks fume at the lack of clear direction.</p> 
<p>For Republicans, the risk of proceeding Thursday with a side-by-side vote is clear. While Democrats say they will have their entire 47-member caucus behind the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3385" target="_blank">three-year extension</a>, any GOP plan right now is likely to fall well short of complete unity — and highlight the divisions in their party.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> called the upcoming vote on Democrats’ plan “a political messaging exercise,” one he agreed to last month as part of a deal to end the 47-day government shutdown. He didn’t commit to putting up a GOP counteroffer for a vote.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think they’re serious about wanting to do a deal yet, so I think that may be what this week is about,” Thune told reporters Monday. “But we’ll see from there if there is a genuine interest in trying to do something.”</p> 
<p>GOP senators are expected to further discuss their options at a closed-door lunch Tuesday and make a final decision about their posture. But, according to three Republican aides granted anonymity to comment on internal conference dynamics, leaders are not currently expected to offer an alternative for a vote Thursday.</p> 
<p>One of the aides said Republicans will be prepared to make the case they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/06/obamacare-plans-schumer-trump-congress-00679712" target="_blank">have plenty of ideas</a> and are ready to talk with Democrats once they move off a proposal that won’t get the 60 votes needed to advance.</p> 
<p>But some Republicans want their leaders to put some concrete alternatives forward as more than 20 million Americans face the loss of enhanced Obamacare tax credits that were implemented as a Covid relief measure under President Joe Biden in 2021 and later extended through 2025. Without them, many families could see premiums rise by $1,000 a year or more.</p> 
<p>“What signal would that send if Republicans say, ‘Yeah, we’re going to say no to the Democrats’ plan, but we’re not going to offer anything?’” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.) said. “The message that will send is, good luck to the American people, and we don’t really care.”</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said in an interview that simply standing aside while Democrats vote to extend the subsidies would be “a big mistake.”</p> 
<p>“A lot of my colleagues, I think, will be very upset if we don't put something up,” he said.</p> 
<p>But there are multiple competing proposals that are favored by subsets of the Senate GOP. Some of them include shorter extensions of the expiring subsidies. Others seek to replace them with new frameworks, generally involving giving Americans cash in the form of health savings accounts to help underwrite premiums and other costs.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.) is among those pushing for a clean break from the Affordable Care Act subsidy framework that reflects “what we believe in” as free-market-oriented Republicans. “I always think it's good to have an alternative,” he said in an interview.</p> 
<p>But Thune praised another <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3386" target="_blank">proposal</a> being circulated by Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> of Idaho and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana, who chair the health-oriented Finance and HELP committees, respectively.</p> 
<p>Their proposal, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/cassidy-crapo-unveil-alternative-to-obamacare-subsidies-00682315" target="_blank">released Monday</a>, would expand the use of health savings accounts and direct funding toward them without extending the enhanced Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>Cassidy said Monday that it is a “leadership decision” if his proposal gets a vote Thursday. Thune took steps Monday night to make the bill available for a vote later this week, as Republicans try to keep options on the table ahead of Tuesday’s lunch.</p> 
<p>But Thune also acknowledged some of his members have other ideas centered on extending the enhanced subsidies with a new income cap and other eligibility restrictions. Republican Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> of Ohio and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> of Maine, for instance, propose to extend the expiring subsidies for two years with income cap restrictions and minimum premium payments.</p> 
<p>That proposal won some Democratic interest Monday from Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.), the No. 2 party leader, who called it “encouraging” and “in the ballpark” of a workable solution — though he cautioned he hadn’t seen the details.</p> 
<p>“It's not crazy,” Durbin said. “Let’s have a conversation.”</p> 
<p>The Senate GOP is straining to formulate a path forward as House Republicans race to come up with their own plan in hopes of putting some health care legislation up for a vote next week before lawmakers break for the holidays — and the enhanced subsidies expire, returning them to the original levels as passed in the 2010 Affordable Care Act.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders still need to make key decisions, including if they try to assemble one bill or put up a suite of bills for members to pick and choose from. But they, too, are under pressure from a slice of members to embrace an extension of the subsidies — even as most in the party are happy to see them expire.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump hasn't put forward his own framework, which could have helped rally the disparate factions of his party on Capitol Hill. And Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> hammered Republicans Monday, saying that they “have no plan.”</p> 
<p>“The question Republicans face this week is very simple: Will they support our bill and lower people’s premiums or will they block our bill and send premiums through the roof?” Schumer said from the Senate floor Monday.</p> 
<p>While the Democratic proposal is expected to fall well short of the necessary 60 votes, a handful of Republicans haven’t said yet how they will vote. Hawley, for instance, said Monday “everything is on the table.”</p> 
<p>“What I’m not going to do is do nothing,” he said.</p> 
<p>It's likely Thursday’s vote won't be the last word on health care this Congress. Thune left the door open to further bipartisan negotiations, and there’s some hope on both sides of the aisle that a failed vote — or votes — could in fact lend new momentum to the talks. Lawmakers are increasingly eyeing Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cutoff to land a health care deal.</p> 
<p>But getting to that point will require Democrats to compromise and Republicans to get together behind a plan of some kind. Asked Monday if his ranks were united or divided on health care, Thune acknowledged reality for a party that has struggled on the issue for decades.</p> 
<p>“I think we have people in different camps, as you would expect,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this article misstated the average premium increase for households losing enhanced subsidies. It is about $1,000 a year.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
