<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 22:29:16 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-07T22:29:16-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Steny Hoyer set to announce retirement from Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/steny-hoyer-retirement-00715790</link>
      <description>The former second-ranking House Democrat has held his seat since 1981.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9b6b-d65c-affb-bbebf26d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 21:31:22 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/25/68/8c33f4444db39211789bcdb863cc/steny-hoyer-37002.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Majority Leader Steny Hoyer speaks with reporters outside the Capitol on Sept. 21, 2022.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/25/68/8c33f4444db39211789bcdb863cc/steny-hoyer-37002.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maryland Rep. Steny Hoyer will announce his retirement from Congress Thursday, capping off a decades-long career that culminated in two four-year stints as House majority leader where he played a key part in passing major bills including the Affordable Care Act.</p> 
<p>Hoyer confirmed the news in an <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2026/01/07/steny-hoyer-retire-congress/" target="_blank">interview with the Washington Post</a> that was published shortly after POLITICO's initial report, which cited two people granted anonymity to confirm the news ahead of a public announcement.</p> 
<p>“I did not want to be one of those members who clearly stayed, outstayed his or her ability to do the job," he told the Post. </p> 
<p>Hoyer, who represents a district stretching from the eastern Washington suburbs to southern Maryland, has served in Congress since 1981, rising up through the ranks to become the second-ranking House Democrat under Speaker Nancy Pelosi.</p> 
<p>The two leaders were known for their personal rivalry dating back to their days as congressional interns in the 1960s, but after Pelosi defeated Hoyer in a 2001 leadership race they ultimately formed an effective partnership atop the Democratic Caucus. </p> 
<p>While Pelosi was known for her progressive views and strong fundraising, Hoyer was a master of interpersonal relations — both among fellow Democrats and across the aisle — making him a highly effective floor leader.</p> 
<p>He stepped aside from his senior role after Democrats lost the House in 2022 as part of a broader changing of the guard but remained in Congress, retaking a senior post on the House Appropriations Committee.</p> 
<p>Only two sitting House members — GOP Reps. Hal Rogers of Kentucky and Chris Smith of New Jersey — have served longer than Hoyer, and only by a few months.</p> 
<p>Now 86, Hoyer remained circumspect about his plans to run for re-election. The decision comes as numerous senior Democrats are facing primaries from younger candidates or choosing not to run for reelection. Pelosi <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/22/pelosi-to-announce-plans-after-california-election-in-november-00618093" target="_blank">announced in October she plans to retire</a> at the end of her term.</p> 
<p>Hoyer praised Pelosi, whom he lost a leadership contest to in 2001, in the Post interview as "tough-as-nails." </p> 
<p>“Sure, I would have loved to have been speaker. Who wouldn’t love to be speaker? But they’re not deep regrets,” he said.</p> 
<p>His decision to step aside is likely to create a free-for-all for the deep-blue seat. One candidate, Harry Jarin, is already in the race <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/29/hoyer-challenger-age-harry-jarin-00373866" target="_blank">after launching a primary in May</a> that specifically targeted Hoyer’s age.</p> 
<p><i>Jonathan Martin contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Oversight panel to issue more subpoenas in Epstein case</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/more-epstein-subpoenas-00715597</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9ad8-dca0-ad9b-fbd954dd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:52:26 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Oversight and Government Reform Committee will subpoena Les Wexner, the longtime friend and client of Jeffrey Epstein, along with two men who worked for the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>It was the culmination of a flurry of subpoena requests Wednesday from rank-and-file members of the panel, several of which were ultimately approved. The committee also voted to subpoena Darren Indyke and Richard Kahn — Epstein’s lawyer and accountant, respectively.</p> 
<p>It shows how the House Oversight Committee could continue to find itself at the center of efforts to re-investigate the Epstein case as the Justice Department presides over a prolonged and rocky rollout of materials.</p> 
<p>The successful motions, brought by the top Democrat on panel, California Rep. Robert Garcia, appeared to be the result of an agreement between Garcia and Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), who also successfully moved to subpoena American businessman Neville Singham and journalist Seth Harp.</p> 
<p>“There is probably no one more important as it relates to the financing and the work of this investigation, which both sides of the aisle are interested in,” Garcia said, of Wexner. “Public reporting has documented their longstanding ties. He should answer our questions in a non-partisan way to get the truth.”</p> 
<p>Luna concurred: “I think that this is a sound motion for subpoena because Les Wexner has been named by victims and also, too, is in a number of documentaries,” she said and urged her colleagues to join her in supporting the effort.</p> 
<p>In moving to subpoena Singham, Luna cited a letter signed by then-Sen. Marco Rubio, who now serves as Secretary of State, suggesting the entrepreneur may have been connected to activities that violated the Foreign Agents Registration Act. Luna also claimed Singham was funding groups that were adverse to American interests.</p> 
<p>Rep. Dave Min (D-Calif.) questioned why Luna was making her motion at this time. Still, Garcia recommended lawmakers vote “yes” despite Min’s concerns, explaining “the representative made clear her support for the deposition that we’re going to have with Mr. Wexner.”</p> 
<p>In an interview after the Wexner vote, Garcia said he did not negotiate the matter with Luna before the hearing.</p> 
<p>“[Congress is] about compromise, and I think for us, the Les Wexner subpoena is at the center of this investigation,” he said.</p> 
<p>Garcia also supported Luna’s motion to subpoena Harp, who has been accused of doxxing a Delta Force official involved in the operation to arrest Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>Separately, the committee rejected a bid from Democrats to subpoena the Department of Homeland Security for records related to the Wednesday shooting of a woman in Minneapolis by an ICE agent.</p> 
<p>The panel struck down an attempt from Rep. Ayanna Pressley (D-Mass.) to issue the subpoena at the end of an hours-long hearing around the welfare fraud scandal in Minnesota. Pressley requested “documents and footage” of the fatal incident.</p> 
<p>Garcia said he was hopeful the panel would investigate the episode.</p> 
<p>“We’re talking about Minnesota right now,” he said. “This was a killing by an ICE agent. There are videos that are now online. There’s testimony that’s being brought to light. It’s horrific. I encourage folks to watch those videos and see what’s happened for themselves.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-07T20:24:25-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump has ‘greenlit’ Russia sanctions bill, Lindsey Graham says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/russia-sanctions-lindsey-graham-00715548</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9acf-da56-afff-9edf9aa40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:35:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> said Wednesday after meeting with President Donald Trump that the Senate could vote as soon as next week to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/07/lindsey-graham-russia-sanctions-bill-trade-embargo-00393297" target="_blank">impose new sanctions aimed at pressuring Russia</a> to end its war with Ukraine.</p> 
<p>“After a very productive meeting today with President Trump on a variety of issues, he greenlit the bipartisan Russia sanctions bill that I have been working on for months with Senator <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151824" data-person-id="151824">[Richard] Blumenthal</a> and many others,” Graham (R-S.C.) said in a statement, referring to the Connecticut Democrat who coauthored the long-stalled legislation.</p> 
<p>Asked about Graham's remarks, a White House official said Trump supports the legislation. Graham said a Senate vote would take place “hopefully as early as next week.”</p> 
<p>Graham and Senate Republican leaders have been working with the White House for months to try to reach an agreement on a final version of the legislation — and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/23/congress/senators-eye-sanctions-vote-after-trump-targets-russian-oil-00620847" target="_blank">this isn’t the first time</a> Graham has declared that his bill could soon move, for it to only <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/14/trump-threatens-tariffs-on-russias-trading-partners-to-pressure-putin-00452131" target="_blank">stall out again</a>.</p> 
<p>The legislation would place secondary sanctions on countries such as China and India that buy oil and gas from Russia in a bid to cut off the cash flow for President Vladimir Putin’s war machine.</p> 
<p>“Ukraine is making concessions for peace and Putin is all talk, continuing to kill the innocent,” Graham said, saying the legislation would be “well-timed.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Graham didn’t immediately respond to a question about whether changes will be incorporated at Trump’s request. The president has previously requested absolute flexibility to impose and retract any sanctions at will.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-07T18:23:16-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House 1 step closer to passing 3-bill spending package</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/appropriations-funding-bills-hardliners-chip-roy-00715032</link>
      <description>The minibus is headed toward double-barrel final House votes Thursday before moving to the Senate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9a72-d65c-affb-bbf32f920003</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:34:54 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/dd/33/d4875373414497ce870e4fb70e0a/u-s-congress-78085.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Chip Roy and other conservatives raised concerns about what they called “outlandish” earmarks in the funding package.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/dd/33/d4875373414497ce870e4fb70e0a/u-s-congress-78085.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans pushed a three-bill spending package through a key procedural hurdle Wednesday afternoon after a hard-liner revolt threatened to derail the underlying bill.</p> 
<p>Republicans stayed largely united on a test vote to advance the package with a 214-212 vote that would fund the Departments of Energy, Commerce, Interior and Justice, as well as water programs, the EPA and federal science initiatives through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>But it didn’t come easy. A dozen GOP lawmakers withheld their vote, prompting Speaker Mike Johnson and House Appropriations Committee Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) to launch a real-time whip operation on the House floor. More than a dozen lawmakers and staff huddled for an extended period after everyone else in the chamber had voted, pulling in House Majority Whip Tom Emmer, House Rules Committee Chair Virginia Foxx (R-Va.) and a bevy of staff. </p> 
<p>Reps. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and Scott Perry (R-Pa.) led the hard-liner charge to push their issues with leaders and the chamber’s top appropriator. </p> 
<p>“Members want to participate. So we're requesting that members be allowed to participate fully,” Perry said after the vote.</p> 
<p>The fiscal hawks were laying out their demands for a different approach to earmarks on the next six spending bills that Congress hopes to tackle before the Jan. 30 deadline, which is set to become a major hurdle for finalizing the next bills, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss conversations on the floor Wednesday.</p> 
<p>“Going forward, we're going to be allowed a little more access to the bills and the ability to have an impact on them in the future — this next tranche,” Rep. Andy Harris (R-Md.) told reporters. “We’ll get to take a look at the earmarks too. I mean, that was part of the whole problem here.”</p> 
<p>While the last six spending bills are not yet finalized, earmark requests from both sides of the aisle were submitted months ago.</p> 
<p>Wednesday's planned procedural vote was first thrown into question after a contentious House Rules Committee hearing late Tuesday night where conservatives on the panel raised concerns about “outlandish” earmarks.</p> 
<p>The stalemate forced the committee to recess overnight and reconvene Wednesday morning with the promise of a deal in hand. House Republican leaders <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-earmark-angst-rears-ahead-of-spending-package-votes-00714135" target="_blank"><u>struck a compromise to kill</u></a> what Roy called “the most egregious" earmark for a community organization in the district of Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn).</p> 
<p>Leaders also agreed to pave the way for two separate final passage votes Thursday — one to advance the Commerce-Justice-Science bill and another to approve the Energy-Water and Interior portions.</p> 
<p>This procedural gambit will allow Roy and other hard-liners to vote “no” on the CJS measure, where other earmarks continue to be irksome, while still voting “yes” on the other two appropriations bills.</p> 
<p>If all three bills pass, they will be repackaged into a single bundle before being sent to the Senate for consideration as soon as next week.</p> 
<p>Congress is rushing to approve more spending bills before the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump's State of the Union set for Feb. 24</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/state-of-the-union-on-feb-24-00715125</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9a5b-d651-a1ff-be7b11760000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:28:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://x.com/SpeakerJohnson/status/2009008841405727229?s=20" target="_blank">has invited</a> President Donald Trump to deliver his State of the Union address to Congress on Feb. 24.</p> 
<p>The speech comes as Trump is working to address key cost of living issues, leading military intervention in Venezuela and threatening to seize Greenland.</p> 
<p>Trump's last address to Congress in March 2025 devolved into heckling and protests from Democrats. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congress wants oversight of Venezuelan oil revenues</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/congress-venezuelan-oil-revenue-oversight-00714107</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-99cd-d78e-af9f-fdff1f040000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 13:53:30 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congressional lawmakers from both parties are signaling that despite President Donald Trump's assertion that he will control the money gained from selling Venezuelan oil turned over to the United States, they’ll want to check the books.</p> 
<p>Democrats said they were appalled by the Trump administration’s plans to sell Venezuelan oil “indefinitely” and control the revenue, suggesting it would amount to a takeover of the country’s fledgling oil industry.</p> 
<p>“It’s an insane plan,” Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.) told POLITICO coming out of a briefing Wednesday with Trump administration officials on Venezuela. “They are proposing to steal Venezuela's oil at gunpoint forever and use that leverage to run the country.”</p> 
<p>Republicans expressed tepid support for the plan, and though they projected confidence in Energy Secretary Chris Wright’s ability to manage the funds, they demanded some oversight over how the money would be spent.</p> 
<p>“Chris Wright is brilliant when it comes to energy,” said Sen. John Hoeven (R-N.D.) after the briefing. “Nobody's going to do a better job than him in terms of making sure that that oil is properly marketed. Congress will have an oversight role. He'll [Wright] be up here testifying in front of us exactly how they're doing it.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Kevin Cramer (R-N.D.) said the U.S. controlling oil revenues would provide important “leverage” over Venezuela’s government, given the fragile state of its economy.</p> 
<p>“As long as we can control how they spend it, that could be a really important part of rebuilding the country and democracy in the region,” Cramer said after the briefing.</p> 
<p>But he expressed some hesitation around selling the oil in the United States that would compete with crude produced in the United States. Both Cramer and Hoeven represent a state that is one of the largest oil producers in the United States but has recently seen its output plateau amid weak prices. The type of oil it produces wouldn’t compete directly with the lower-quality grades coming from Venezuela, but could be pushed out at the margins.</p> 
<p>“As long as it's not sold at a discount I probably don't have a big problem with it. As long as they aren't going to use that dirty, cheap oil to flood the market,” Cramer said.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson in an interview earlier Wednesday said he didn’t have the full details of the administration's plans to secure oil fields and output in Venezuela, but he said he thought the plan “makes sense.”</p> 
<p>And he said he did not expect the Trump administration would spend taxpayer dollars for the effort. </p> 
<p>“I do not expect that they would,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP earmark angst rears ahead of spending package votes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-earmark-angst-rears-ahead-of-spending-package-votes-00714135</link>
      <description>Plans to kill one Democratic earmark and split the three-bill package up may keep hopes for passage alive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-99b1-df0c-a5bb-bdf786250000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 13:23:15 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c8/72/a060eb7a495a9ab246e1ccf38ed2/u-s-congress-34956.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A rebellion from Rep. Chip Roy and other conservatives against earmarks is threatening to tank a key procedural vote Wednesday afternoon on a three-bill spending package.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c8/72/a060eb7a495a9ab246e1ccf38ed2/u-s-congress-34956.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus, Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus, Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A conservative rebellion against earmarks is threatening to tank a key procedural vote Wednesday afternoon on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_DRAFT24" target="_blank">three-bill spending package</a> as House GOP leaders scramble to avoid another intraparty meltdown on the chamber floor.</p> 
<p>House leaders plan to strip out an earmark from Democratic Rep. Ilhan Omar, which could have major repercussions in a legislative body already plagued by partisan tensions and mistrust. </p> 
<p>The community project funding at the center of hard-liners’ ire is $1 million for an organization in Minneapolis focused on “wraparound services” that include job training, addiction recovery and housing support. The organization describes itself as “youth-led East African recovery organization.”</p> 
<p>The scrutiny over the earmark, which was also backed by Minnesota’s Senate delegation, comes as federal funding for childcare centers in Minnesota’s large Somali community is under fire by the Trump administration due to allegations of fraud. Some Republicans are claiming that this organization is also fraudulent.</p> 
<p>“Earmarks are the currency of corruption, and they're coming back in full force in these products,” Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) told reporters Wednesday morning about the spending package heading to the House floor later in the day. “And I just don't support it.”</p> 
<p>Following a GOP revolt inside the House Rules Committee late Tuesday night, House Republican leaders landed on a compromise to kill the earmark, according to four people granted anonymity to speak candidly about a private plan.</p> 
<p>Leadership also agreed to split up the three-bill package that would fund Energy-Water, Interior-Environment and Commerce-Justice-Science when it comes to the floor for a vote.</p> 
<p>That would give some Republicans the ability to vote against the CJS measure while backing the other two. The procedural gambit would then allow all three bills to be repackaged for the Senate to consider as one bundle.</p> 
<p>House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.), however, warned Wednesday the intense focus on one single earmark is a liability for carefully negotiated full-year funding bills, ahead of the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p>“I can't afford to have a million dollar project jeopardize a $184 billion package of bills,” Cole told reporters. “If we have an individual project that can pose a political problem, I've had these in the past from our side before, where we had to tell a member, ‘look, there might be a way to do this, but our advice to you is to withdraw this.’”</p> 
<p>Cole said the onus was on Democrats to convince Omar to abandon the request, or risk tanking the whole bipartisan spending package.</p> 
<p>“It is under discussion and it will be resolved. That's the way things go with these community projects. If there's a difficulty, if there's a problem, we try to work it out. Or it comes out,” Rep. Rosa DeLauro of Connecticut, the top Democratic appropriator in the House, said in an interview Wednesday afternoon. </p> 
<p>The underlying language of the bill will not change, but the earmark is expected to be functionally neutered by making a change to report language that accompanies the bill text.</p> 
<p>“It's too late in the process,” for changes to funding levels or the bill text itself, Cole said.</p> 
<p>Omar’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Earmarks were banned under Republican leadership for more than a decade before being revived and rebranded by Democrats as “community project funding” in 2021. The new process has tighter restrictions for eligibility than the old one, which has calmed angst among most Republicans about frivolous hyperlocal projects.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers from both parties request money for initiatives in their districts, and appropriators consider thousands of projects from both sides before narrowing down which will make it into spending bills.</p> 
<p>Roy and Freedom Caucus Chair Andy Harris (R-Md.) each stood up in Wednesday morning’s closed door House GOP Conference meeting to voice their frustration about the earmarks in the CJS funding bill and the lack of opportunity for rank-and-file members to offer amendments to the bill, according to four people in the room granted anonymity to speak candidly.</p> 
<p>With these changes, and if Republicans have perfect attendance Wednesday, House GOP leaders — for now — believe they will have enough votes to narrowly clear the at-risk procedural hurdle on the floor late this afternoon.</p> 
<p>This also would keep Republicans on track for final passage Thursday given strong support from Democrats, according to five people granted anonymity to share internal party dynamics.</p>CORRECTION:  This story has been updated to reflect that Republicans did not submit more earmark requests overall for fiscal 2026.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate group nears deal to revive Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/senate-deal-obamacare-subsidies-00714048</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9992-d78e-af9f-fdf77e4c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 12:49:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan Senate group is nearing an agreement to revive lapsed Obamacare subsidies, with a key negotiator saying the group could release draft legislation early next week.</p> 
<p>The deal being discussed by the senators would reestablish the enhanced tax credits that expired Jan. 1 for two years, with new restrictions including minimum premium payments and income caps. The developing agreement would pair that with new cost-sharing reduction measures and expanding access to health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> (R-Ohio), a key negotiator, said Wednesday that legislative text could be finalized “realistically, probably Monday.”</p> 
<p>Two other people granted anonymity to disclose private negotiations characterized the Senate group as close to an agreement. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) added she was “encouraged” by the group’s progress and agreed an agreement is close.</p> 
<p>Even if the fluctuating group of roughly a dozen lawmakers is able to come to a consensus, there’s no guarantee it will get the votes to pass. Senators have been keeping their leadership in the loop on the talks and will meet this week with House lawmakers to update them on their progress.</p> 
<p>The group is eyeing an income restriction for the subsidies that would exclude those earning more than about 700 percent of the federal poverty level, as well as a $5 a month minimum premium. They would also slap steep new fines on any insurance companies that add so-called phantom enrollees, meaning people who are signed up for subsidized coverage without realizing it.</p> 
<p>Under the discussions, according to Moreno, Americans who receive the Obamacare subsidies could choose to have the money go instead into a pre-funded health savings account during the second year of the extension.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.), who has been involved in some of the group’s discussions, cautioned that there were “still some major stumbling blocks.”</p> 
<p>Moreno, for instance, did not say how the group was going to resolve concerns that the tax credits could be used to subsidize coverage of abortions. But he said the framework of the agreement, as he had described it, does not change current abortion policy and that the abortion discussion remained a “peripheral” issue.</p> 
<p>“We’re trying to resolve how we ensure compliance with the spirit” of the Hyde Amendment, Moreno said, referring to the longstanding appropriations restriction preventing taxpayer funding of abortions.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Democrats eye Venezuela war powers vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/house-democrats-venezuela-war-powers-00713669</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9915-d78e-af9f-fd77c2950000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 10:33:26 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Democrats are making a fresh attempt to rein in President Donald Trump on Venezuela, plotting to force a vote on a war powers resolution in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>The resolution is likely to be similar to one that was introduced last year as the military began to marshal forces in the Caribbean. That measure was narrowly defeated in the GOP-controlled House. Democrats are hopeful they can garner more support from Republicans following the weekend operation to capture Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512">Jim McGovern</a> of Massachusetts, the top Rules Committee Democrat who co-authored the original measure, said he envisioned "something similar to what we did last time, maybe with a couple of minor adjustments." </p> 
<p>He and other top Democrats privately huddled Tuesday evening as they planned a way forward. Some Democrats are privately concerned that introducing a war powers measure that is broadly worded could fail and give the impression that the House is giving Trump permission to take further action in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders are involving lawmakers with military backgrounds such as Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227127" data-person-id="227127">Seth Moulton</a> (D-Mass.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307328" data-person-id="307328">Jason Crow</a> (D-Colo.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/433952" data-person-id="433952">Pat Ryan</a> (D-N.Y.) as they plan their response, according to Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51521" data-person-id="51521">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.), the top Foreign Affairs Committee Democrat. He said he expects “very little” to change from last year’s measure.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warren cuts checks to state Democratic parties</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/elizabeth-warren-dem-donations-midterms-00713176</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9543-dba9-addb-b7ff02f30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:06:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Elizabeth Warren is donating $400,000 to 23 state Democratic parties in an effort to fund Democratic infrastructure ahead of the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>In an interview, the Massachusetts Democrat called the “early money” investment “crucial” for state parties. She’s urging fellow Democrats to follow her lead on donating now because “the best time to do it is January, not waiting until next October.”</p> 
<p>The 23 states are ones with competitive congressional or statewide races in the 2026 midterms, and include Maine, North Carolina, Ohio and Texas.</p> 
<p>“They need the resources to build out infrastructure that all of our Democratic candidates will need to win in November,” Warren said. “They need money now to hire staff, recruit volunteers, knock on doors, make calls, do all the things that make Democrats competitive in these elections.”</p> 
<p>She’s also raised more than $1.1 million for candidates this cycle, while weighing in on a handful of contested primaries.</p> 
<p>Warren, a longtime progressive champion, is urging candidates to focus their campaign messaging on “the high costs that families are struggling with every day” and “make it clear that we have solutions and that we will fight to deliver real change.”</p> 
<p>In 2018, Warren also donated $250,000 to state parties, a sign of her early presidential primary preparations ahead of the 2020 campaign. But when asked if the same applied to this year’s investment, Warren said, “no.”</p> 
<p>“Democrats need to win elections everywhere, and I am 100 percent committed to making that happen in November 2026,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: The House GOP’s nerve-wracking return</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/what-were-watching-00713615</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-96ec-d78e-af9f-feff1dd60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The start of the second session of the 119th Congress isn’t going as planned for House Republicans.</p> 
<p>First, the GOP Conference’s long-planned, day-long policy retreat Tuesday at the Kennedy Center — intended to build unity around a legislative agenda in a midterm election year — was shaken by news of Rep. Doug LaMalfa’s (R-Calif.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">unexpected death</a> and Rep. Jim Baird’s (R-Ind.) hospitalization from a car accident.</p> 
<p>It brought into stark relief the major math challenges House Republicans now face. LaMalfa’s passing brings the balance of the House to 218-213. And as long as Baird is out recovering, Speaker Mike Johnson can afford to lose only a single GOP vote on party-line legislative business on the chamber floor.</p> 
<p>“We keep saying we are one breath away from the minority — that’s more true today than ever,” said one House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly about the mood.</p> 
<p><b>— The numbers game:&nbsp;</b>Johnson’s margins could be a major problem for Wednesday’s vote to move forward with consideration of a “minibus” funding package covering Commerce-Justice-Science, Energy-Water and Interior-Environment — if the measure makes it to the floor at all.</p> 
<p>Rules ultimately recessed Tuesday night without approving the rule to allow for floor debate on the funding bill after Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and other conservatives revolted over <a href="https://x.com/chiproytx/status/2008691088370942226?s=46" target="_blank">some of the earmarks</a> for projects in Democratic districts and states.</p> 
<p>The panel is expected to reconvene Wednesday morning to discuss a leadership-backed compromise, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the plans — though it wasn’t immediately clear what resolution could satisfy Roy’s demands without alienating Democrats whose support will be key in the Senate. </p> 
<p><b>— Health care:&nbsp;</b>Republicans who hoped a speech from Donald Trump at the Tuesday retreat would bring messaging clarity to their position on health care policy also had their dreams quickly dashed as the president suggested the GOP ought to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/conservatives-anti-abortion-trump-health-care-gop-00712565" target="_blank">be “flexible”</a> when it comes to federal funding for abortion.</p> 
<p>It caused an uproar among conservatives who insist any agreement to extend lapsed Affordable Care Act subsidies must include language banning the use of federal funds for abortions — while Democrats say abortion restrictions are a nonstarter.</p> 
<p>Republicans will have to soon decide what compromises they’re willing to make. The House is set to take a procedural vote Wednesday on whether to move forward with legislation that would revive the enhanced ACA subsidies for three years, which Congress let expire in December.</p> 
<p>The bill is expected to pass the House on Thursday with support from all Democrats and a handful of Republicans. Then, senators will have to make the next move.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— More Venezuela briefings: </b>Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth, Attorney General Pam Bondi, CIA Director John Ratcliffe and Joint Chiefs of Staff Chair Gen. Dan Caine will brief all lawmakers on the Venezuela operation Wednesday morning — first in the Senate, then in the House.</p> 
<p><b>— Appropriations movement: </b>Congress has just over three weeks to pass the remaining spending bills needed to avoid another shutdown.</p> 
<p>If lawmakers can pass the Energy-Water, Interior-Environment and Commerce-Justice-Science funding measure by early next week, appropriators are tentatively planning to move two more spending packages. The first, according to Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine), would include Homeland, State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services. A final minibus could contain Defense, Labor-HHS-Education and Transportation-HUD.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers seek to limit DHS power to shuffle cash in funding bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/dhs-reprogramming-crackdown-00713569</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9604-d651-a1ff-be6486900000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 20:45:55 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Top appropriators on Capitol Hill are seeking to tighten limits around how much money DHS can shift between accounts as they finalize funding bills ahead of the Jan. 30 shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/177013" data-person-id="177013">Mark Amodei</a>, the Nevada Republican who chairs the DHS funding panel, told reporters Tuesday night that House and Senate appropriators are crafting their spending measure to make it “harder to make the money mobile.” The effort comes as the Trump administration has spent the past year testing the limits of its power to disregard congressional intent and reprogram billions of dollars between accounts.</p> 
<p>“We did a bunch of reprogramming,” Amodei said of Republicans in the White House. “It’s like, hey, that's bullshit.”</p> 
<p>To limit the Trump administration’s ability to shift cash, appropriators plan to include tables within the bill that show exactly which accounts should be funded and lower the percentages of cash that can be used for other purposes, Amodei continued.</p> 
<p>Appropriators have briefed President Donald Trump’s budget office on the funding bill they hope to pass and have taken OMB’s input into account, Amodei said. Still, he acknowledged that some Trump administration officials, including Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem, will not be fond of new restrictions on moving around cash.</p> 
<p>“Now I know that the secretary doesn't like that,” Amodei said. “And it's like, well, we've all got our unlike departments. And so welcome to the club.”</p> 
<p>He also divulged that the funding bill will provide enough cash for DHS to keep 44,500 immigrants in detention facilities at any given time. Appropriators will be tracking detention capacity every month and expect the Trump administration to fill that “detention bed” capacity, he added.</p> 
<p>“They better, by God, be full,” said Amodei.</p> 
<p>Amodei is in the midst of final negotiations with senior Senate appropriators on the DHS funding bill. “We're real close,” he said. “We want to be able to publish the bill this week.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP-led Jan. 6 committee sets first hearing for next week</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/jan-6-hearing-scheduled-00713479</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-95d1-d78e-af9f-fdf749420000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 20:00:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The new Republican-led panel tasked with investigating the Jan. 6, 2021, Capitol attack will hold its first hearing next week, Rep. Barry Loudermilk said in an interview Tuesday — the five-year anniversary of the event.</p> 
<p>The Georgia Republican, who is the chair of the select subcommittee, said his panel was still ironing out its list of witnesses, but he anticipated the focus would be the pipe bombs left at the Democratic and Republican National Committee headquarters the day before the riots at the Capitol. </p> 
<p>“It’s gonna be sometime next week,” Loudermilk said. “We’re gonna be really looking at the pipe bomb and the FBI’s investigation — previous investigation. Why did it take five years?”</p> 
<p>News of the hearing that would look at the events of that day through the lens of security failures rather than attempts by President Donald Trump and his supporters to overturn the results of the 2020 election was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422" target="_blank">the culmination</a> of a daylong campaign from Republicans to offer an alternative memory of the Capitol attack. </p> 
<p>The White House published a website offering a largely false narrative of what unfolded at the Capitol five years ago — one that blamed then-Speaker Nancy Pelosi and forcefully denied Trump’s role in inciting the violence. Democrats and Republicans also fought over the fate of a commemorative plaque mandated by Congress to honor those who protected the Capitol on Jan. 6, with Speaker Mike Johnson maintaining the project was untenable.</p> 
<p>Loudermilk said he had not spoken to Johnson about the memorial tablet and hasn’t been following the controversy around it but suggested he wasn’t opposed to its display — something of a break with House GOP leadership have sought to either bury the matter or denigrate the effort.</p> 
<p>“I don’t have problem putting it up. I think you need to honor the police,” he said. “I mean, the rank and file police, they were just trying to do their job.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson: U.S. military action in Greenland ‘would not be appropriate’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/johnson-trump-greenland-military-force-00713476</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-95d1-d78e-af9f-fdf711160000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 19:39:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson Tuesday evening swatted down the idea of any U.S. military action to take over Greenland, just after the White House said President Donald Trump wanted to acquire the territory and would not take military action off the table.</p> 
<p>“No, I don't think that's appropriate,” Johnson told reporters Tuesday evening.</p> 
<p>White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-greenland-military-force-00713315" target="_blank">said in a statement Tuesday</a> that "utilizing the U.S. Military is always an option at the Commander in Chief’s disposal." </p> 
<p>The speaker, who said he hadn't seen the statement, appeared to not believe the White House would make such a comment. Johnson did say he believed “Greenland is viewed by a lot of people as something that would be a strategic positioning for the U.S." </p> 
<p>Johnson said the issue didn't come up in conversations with Trump earlier Tuesday at the House GOP retreat. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Jan. 6 was remembered — and rewritten — on its 5th anniversary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422</link>
      <description>At a march and a hearing, on a plaque and a website, the story of the Capitol riot was contested Tuesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-95a5-df0c-a5bb-b5f718560000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:51:35 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a2/cd/2c8cd8584d6f90726e7413ba7fc2/capitol-riot-anniversary-77658.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP Photo/Jose Luis Magana</media:credit>
        <media:title>Demonstrators march on Constitution Avenue in Washington as they rally during the Jan. 6 anniversary Tuesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a2/cd/2c8cd8584d6f90726e7413ba7fc2/capitol-riot-anniversary-77658.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu, Kyle Cheney and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu, Kyle Cheney and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Five years ago, Ryan Samsel <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/02/02/ryan-samsel-jan-6-defendant-00139344" target="_blank">ignited the Jan. 6 breach</a> of the Capitol grounds when he charged through a police barricade, injuring a police officer in the process.</p> 
<p>Samsel returned to the site Tuesday, part of a group of fellow mob members who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/03/07/proud-boys-march-toward-capitol-00085975" target="_blank">retraced the route</a> Trump supporters took from the Ellipse to the foot of the Capitol in 2021. They marched to celebrate their blanket pardon by President Donald Trump and attempt to reclaim Jan. 6 as a date of triumph, not tragedy.</p> 
<p>The march was the backdrop to a day marked by partisan sparring over a missing plaque and an endorsement by the White House of a torrent of conspiracy theories and lies about the attack and Trump’s pressure campaign to subvert the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>A new White House website, with ominous black-and-white images of former Speaker Nancy Pelosi and members of the Jan. 6 select committee, offered an alternate and largely false narrative of events at the Capitol that day — one that forcefully denied Trump’s role in stoking the riot and labeled those who stormed the Capitol “patriotic Americans.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Speaker Mike Johnson eschewed calls to mount a bronze marker legally mandated by Congress that would serve to honor those who protected the Capitol from the worst attack it had seen since the war of 1812.</p> 
<p>“He's trying to cover up for the fact that Republicans continue to disrespect those brave men and women of the Capitol Police department who defended our country on Jan. 6,” House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries said in a brief interview.</p> 
<p>Democrats held a mock hearing to mark the anniversary of the event featuring firsthand witnesses to the violence that day. Their testimony underscored the increasingly diverging narratives that continue to define the historic attack.</p> 
<p>Outside the Capitol, the former Jan. 6 defendants rallied without support from sitting lawmakers. Their most vocal champion, Georgia Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene, had resigned from Congress a day earlier. She was mentioned regretfully by some members of the crowd who soured on her after she began openly feuding with Trump last year.</p> 
<p>Democratic Rep. Tom Suozzi of New York exchanged tense words with Jake Lang — who was pardoned of numerous assault charges against police on Jan. 6 — from behind a line of officers as he walked past the participants as they prepared to lay flowers on the Capitol steps.</p> 
<p>Members of the march chanted, “Whose house? Our house!” — an echo of the rally cries from five years earlier. Mikki Witthoeft, the mother of Ashli Babbitt — the woman who was shot and killed by a Capitol Police officer outside the House chamber — described Jan. 6 as the day Congress “let the American people down.”</p> 
<p>Inside the Capitol, the missing plaque became a stand-in for the swirling controversy about how the infamous day will be remembered.</p> 
<p>Johnson said in a Monday statement that the plaque, which was authorized by a law passed in March 2022, was “not implementable" and that Democratic-led proposals for it were also not an option.</p> 
<p>That echoes arguments made by the Justice Department, which is trying to dismiss a federal lawsuit filed by two Capitol Police officers seeking to compel the plaque’s mounting.</p> 
<p>The law authorizing the marker requires it to list the names of all law enforcement officers who participated in the defense of the Capitol. DOJ lawyers argue in <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540.27.0_2.pdf" target="_blank">court filings</a> that the plaque that has been made does not comply with the law because it lists the departments who responded — not the individual officers. A deputy to the Architect of the Capitol said in a <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540.27.2.pdf" target="_blank">separate court declaration</a> that a plaque listing the officers’ names has not been made.</p> 
<p>Rep. Zoe Lofgren (D-Calif.) called Johnson’s claim that the plaque does not comply with the law “ridiculous, and so is he.” Many Hill Democrats have placed <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/23/congress/democrats-replica-jan-6-plaques-00418859" target="_blank">replicas of the plaque</a> outside their offices as Johnson refuses to mount the genuine article.</p> 
<p>In one effort to resolve the issue, Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said Tuesday he would seek to change the law to accommodate the existing plaque, but it was not immediately clear if he would be able to garner the unanimous support necessary to quickly act.</p> 
<p>Testifying at the Democratic shadow hearing, former Rep. Adam Kinzinger — who served as a Republican on the House’s previous Jan. 6 panel — said he was “convinced” the plaque would be put on display by next January, when the next Congress begins.</p> 
<p>“I’ll humbly suggest maybe you can double the size of it by then,” he said.</p> 
<p>The Democrats’ event was held in the basement after the speaker’s office declined to allow them to use a dedicated hearing room or the larger auditorium in the Capitol Visitor Center, according to a person granted anonymity because they were not authorized to comment publicly. Johnson’s office did not respond to a request for comment on the claim.</p> 
<p>No sitting House Republicans attended. They spent their day across town holding a policy retreat at the Kennedy Center, where Trump addressed them and brought up the events of Jan. 6 without prompting. He complained that the media failed to report how he told people to march "peacefully and patriotically" to the Capitol that day and renewed old gripes against Pelosi, whom he blamed for rejecting National Guard troops to guard the Capitol — even though only Trump could call up the Guard.</p> 
<p>The new White House website also accuses Pelosi and members of the Jan. 6 select committee of maneuvering to unfairly blame Trump for the riot. Not mentioned are any of the many comments critical of Trump from inside the GOP at the time nor the 10 House and seven Senate Republicans who voted against him in subsequent impeachment proceedings.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune sidestepped a question Tuesday about the website’s claim that Capitol Police helped instigate the riot. He told reporters he hadn’t seen the site and offered general praise for the force.</p> 
<p>The history of Jan. 6 will remain a live issue on Capitol Hill for the remainder of the current Congress, with a new Republican-led panel investigating the attack and the work of the prior Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee.</p> 
<p>Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Texas), who serves on the new panel, attacked those on the Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee for seeking to malign Trump.</p> 
<p>“Their Select Committee wasn’t about transparency or the truth; it was political theatre,” he said in a statement. “My colleagues and I are focused on uncovering the truth and following the facts wherever they lead.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The House GOP confronts a shocking loss and a difficult road ahead</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/house-republicans-anxiety-margins-midterms-00713358</link>
      <description>Members who gathered for a pre-midterm policy retreat were stunned by the death of longtime colleague Doug LaMalfa.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-958c-df0c-a5bb-b5dfea110000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:05:36 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5c/35/9a970eca401a8c9836bc2fc203e5/trump-32522.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Evan Vucci/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Speaker Mike Johnson attends a GOP policy retreat in Washington, on Jan. 6, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5c/35/9a970eca401a8c9836bc2fc203e5/trump-32522.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tuesday was supposed to be a rah-rah day for House Republicans — a chance to strategize with President Donald Trump about their agenda for the tough election year ahead.</p> 
<p>Instead, 2026 got off to an unexpectedly somber start as they confronted the sudden death of a well-liked colleague and pondered the dire political and policy straits their dwindling majority has to navigate.</p> 
<p>Most members learned about <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">California Rep. Doug LaMalfa’s overnight passing</a> as they boarded buses outside the Capitol to head to the Kennedy Center for their annual policy meeting. That news — as well as word that another Republican, Rep. Jim Baird of Indiana, had been <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/jim-baird-hospitalized-00712230" target="_blank">badly hurt in a car crash</a> — cast an immediate pall.</p> 
<p>“This is coming as a shock to all of us,” said one House Republican who, like others quoted for this story, was granted anonymity to speak candidly about the mood.</p> 
<p>Even a characteristically freewheeling speech from Trump — delivered at the performing arts center his hand-picked board had recently renamed for him without congressional approval — hardly lightened the mood. He remembered LaMalfa, a rice farmer who represented a rural northern California district for seven terms, as a loyal supporter and said he considered skipping the speech out of respect for his death.</p> 
<p>"But then I decided that I have to do it in his honor,” Trump said. “I'll do it in his honor because he would have wanted it that way.”</p> 
<p>But reality soon set in that the House GOP would be facing challenges that went well beyond mourning. For one, LaMalfa’s death and Baird’s hospitalization represented another blow to their razor-thin majority, leaving many contemplating whether Republicans could ever muster the votes they would need to pass a laundry list of pre-midterm policy priorities.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa’s death and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972" target="_blank">Georgia Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene’s resignation</a> this week left the GOP with a bare 218 votes for at least until early March. With Baird’s indefinite absence and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/thomas-massie-trump-jeffrey-epstein-00654214" target="_blank">unreliable support</a> of libertarian Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), Speaker Mike Johnson has to confront a day-to-day struggle to maintain control of the House.</p> 
<p>His leadership circle, for instance, quickly had to calculate whether they would have enough Republicans in attendance to clear a procedural vote Wednesday allowing them to pass on a critical government funding package and several other bills this week.</p> 
<p>“We keep saying we are one breath away from the minority — that’s more true today than ever,” another House Republican said.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-health-abortion-restrictions-hyde-00712507" target="_blank">Trump’s 84-minute speech</a> ultimately veered into myriad topics. He at one point commented on his own mortality and pushed back on reports about his aging and declining health, admonishing some Republicans in attendance for calling to check if he was “dead” last year after he was away from cameras for several days.</p> 
<p>He also raised concerns about keeping the House majority next year — a topic that lawmakers and White House aides say is frequently on the president’s mind.</p> 
<p>"They say that when you win the presidency, you lose the midterm,” Trump said. “So you're all brilliant people: I wish you could explain to me what the hell's going on with the mind of the public, because we have the right policy.”</p> 
<p>He then proceeded to throw a bomb into those policy plans as Republicans struggle to address rising health care costs — a topic that’s become an albatross for the party after a bitter December fight over extending Obamacare tax credits that have now expired, raising premiums for millions of Americans.</p> 
<p>The president directed Republicans to be “flexible” on abortion issues in ongoing health care talks — essentially asking many in his party to cross a moral red line by abandoning the longstanding ban on taxpayer funding for abortion known as the Hyde amendment.</p> 
<p>The remark <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/conservatives-anti-abortion-trump-health-care-gop-00712565" target="_blank">stunned House conservatives</a> in the audience and those listening in the Senate.</p> 
<p>“I almost fell out of my chair,” said one who attended the meeting.</p> 
<p>“Everything depends on details, but Hyde is nonnegotiable for most conservatives,” added a senior House Republican aide. That person didn’t rule out a potential “creative solution” on the matter but said “caving on Hyde is not an option.”</p> 
<p>Asked for his reaction on Capitol Hill, Sen. James Lankford (R-Okla.) said, “I’m not flexible on the value of every child’s life.” Others took it as an encouraging sign that Trump wants to notch a deal this month on an especially nettlesome election year issue.</p> 
<p>But inside the House GOP policy sessions that followed the Trump speech Tuesday — touching on energy, housing and other issues — members continued to struggle with the way forward on their health care plans, according to six Republicans with direct knowledge of the conversations.</p> 
<p>Many hard-line conservatives — who see abortion protections as an essential element in any health care legislation — would prefer Republican leaders pursue a party-line bill under filibuster-skirting budget reconciliation rules rather than cut a deal with Democrats.</p> 
<p>Otherwise, according to two people with knowledge of the retreat discussions, key lawmakers ran through a well-known menu of legislative options — albeit one that is unlikely to offset the impact of the expired Obamacare subsidies before Election Day.</p> 
<p>House Ways and Means Chair Jason Smith (R-Mo.) discussed proposals to expand tax-advantaged health savings accounts, while Energy and Commerce Chair Brett Guthrie (R-Ky.) talked through potential overhauls to a key prescription drug program and bills that would crack down on intermediaries known as pharmacy benefit managers.</p> 
<p>Trump directed House Republicans in his earlier remarks to work on so-called <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/prescription-pulse/2025/05/02/trumps-most-favored-way-to-cut-drug-costs-returns-00321936" target="_blank">“most favored nation” drug pricing legislation</a> — something he’s pursued in executive orders and deals with health care giants as he moves to lower the cost of prescription drugs.</p> 
<p>But the issue is deeply divisive among Hill Republicans, and GOP leaders have continued to rebuff Trump’s attempts to attach it to numerous legislative vehicles — including the sprawling megabill Republicans passed this summer.</p> 
<p>Senior GOP aides on Capitol Hill say they have plans to address drug prices via HSAs and other policies, but they are leaving it to the White House to promote the most-favored-nation and other direct drug pricing plans.</p> 
<p>That, Trump said — along with being “flexible” on Hyde and “directly” giving Americans money to purchase coverage — would allow Republicans to “take away” the issue of health care from Democrats, Trump asserted at the House GOP meeting.</p> 
<p>"You could own health care, figure it out!” Trump said.</p> 
<p>But House Republicans privately acknowledged throughout the day Tuesday it’s far from that easy.</p> 
<p>"We're still far from a solution on health care,” one GOP lawmaker said.</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T16:50:24-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Thune outlines 3 pieces of possible health care deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/thune-outlines-three-pieces-of-possible-health-care-deal-00713102</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9525-d78e-af9f-fd77f5f70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 16:12:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> laid out Tuesday the three components any bipartisan health deal would have to address in order for it to pass the Senate.</p> 
<p>That includes instituting minimum premium payments and other new restrictions, providing “a bridge to HSAs” including an expansion of the health savings accounts and dealing with the “Hyde issue” — language that limits federal funding for abortions. All three of the ideas are Republican priorities.</p> 
<p>“Those are kind of the ‘big three’ when it comes to something that could get through the Senate,” Thune told reporters of what it would take to land a "healthy majority” in support of any health care deal.</p> 
<p>"We want to ensure that if we do anything it's done in a way that reforms these programs and ... ensures that those dollars aren't being used to go against the practice that's been in place for the last 50 years around here when it comes to taxpayer dollars being used to finance abortions and that it also has this movement in the future toward HSAs," he continued. </p> 
<p>A bipartisan group of senators is currently negotiating a possible agreement that would merge a two-year extension of the lapsed Affordable Care Act credits with new minimum premium payments and income restrictions, alongside broader cost-sharing reductions that would be phased in during the second year. The lapse of the beefed-up ACA subsidies reset the tax credits to their original 2010 Obamacare levels.</p> 
<p>The lawmakers met Monday night and they said they are making progress — but they don't yet have a deal.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> (R-Ohio), one of the key negotiators, updated Thune Tuesday morning. Thune also met earlier Tuesday with Senate Finance Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> (R-Idaho) and Senate Health Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> (R-La.), who co-led the GOP proposal to expand health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>Cassidy said Tuesday he continued to work on the health savings accounts component, adding, “We’re gonna need the White House support to get something done.”</p> 
<p><i>Cheyenne Haslett contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T13:32:09-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Kemp sets date for special election to fill Greene’s seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/georgia-14-special-election-marjorie-taylor-greene-00712603</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-947a-dba9-addb-b7ffd31b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:15:06 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The race to replace Marjorie Taylor Greene in Congress is on.</p> 
<p>Georgia Gov. Brian Kemp authorized a special election to select a candidate to fill the remainder of the former MAGA acolyte’s term following her official resignation from the House late Monday night. Kemp’s office <a href="https://gov.georgia.gov/executive-action/executive-orders/2026" target="_blank">posted the signed writ of election</a> to his office’s website, setting the contest for March 10.</p> 
<p>Nearly two dozen candidates are already looking to run for the vacated northwest Georgia seat according to Federal Elections Commission filings — and almost all are Republicans hoping to represent the deeply conservative district.</p> 
<p>The race sets up as a potential test of what kind of candidate Republicans prefer in the deep-red district, following Greene’s controversial tenure in Congress.</p> 
<p>Republicans already in the race include District Attorney Clayton Fuller of the Lookout Mountain Judicial Circuit, state Sen. Colton Moore, and businessperson and former Paulding County Commissioner Brian Stover.</p> 
<p>Only two Democrats have entered the race so far: Greene’s unsuccessful 2024 challenger Shawn Harris, and Clarence Blalock, who had previously been running for state Labor Commissioner.</p> 
<p>House Republicans will be glad to have the seat filled: Greene’s resignation and the Monday death of Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.) means they have just a five-seat majority.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misnamed the California Representative who died Monday. It was Rep. Doug LaMalfa. An earlier version of this report also misspelled the county where Brian Stover was a commissioner.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Greenland war powers vote could be heading to Senate floor</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/greenland-war-powers-gallego-00712605</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9481-dba9-addb-b7bf49b50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:12:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189136" data-person-id="189136">Ruben Gallego</a> wants Congress to forestall a U.S. takeover of Greenland, requiring President Donald Trump to get lawmakers’ approval for any such action after this weekend’s military incursion into Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Gallego said he will introduce a war powers resolution focused on Greenland, an semiautonomous territory of Denmark that Trump has repeatedly suggested should be part of the U.S. instead.</p> 
<p>“We must stop him before he invades another country on a whim,” Gallego wrote on social media. “No more forever wars.”</p> 
<p>War powers resolutions are privileged under Senate rules, meaning Gallego and others can force the chamber to weigh in on the issue. Democrats have previously forced votes to rein in Trump’s strikes against suspected drug smuggling boats and on attacking Venezuela, though both efforts failed.</p> 
<p>Greenland could be different, however, given that it is territory belonging to a NATO ally. Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> is downplaying the chances of military action in Greenland, and other Republicans have ridiculed the idea of a hostile takeover.</p> 
<p>"That to me is not something anybody is contemplating seriously,” Thune said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>But Democrats are eager to put them on the record, with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.) hinting at many more attempts to rein in Trump.</p> 
<p>“He has repeatedly raised Greenland, Cuba, Mexico, Colombia. He's waged military action within Nigeria,” Kaine said. “So I think members of the Senate should go on the record about all of it.”</p> 
<p>The Senate is expected to vote Thursday on a bipartisan resolution to require congressional approval before Trump takes additional military action in Venezuela. But a similar push previously failed and Thune on Tuesday said he was “optimistic” it would fail again.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine), who opposed a previous Venezuela-focused measure, said she remained undecided but wanted the administration to further explain its strategy.</p> 
<p>“I don't understand what the president means when he says we will 'run' Venezuela,” she said. “The Venezuelans ought to run for Venezuela.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeSantis: Florida should require congressional candidates to answer about stock trades</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/desantis-florida-should-require-congressional-candidates-to-answer-about-stock-trades-00712308</link>
      <description>During his press conference, DeSantis called individual stock trading a “bipartisan ailment,” adding, “We need to clean both houses up there.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-943c-df0c-a5bb-b47f94010000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 12:15:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e0/f46abfb541e1bc13d70a2900721c/florida-budget-65894.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Chris O'Meara/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis speaks during a news conference.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e0/f46abfb541e1bc13d70a2900721c/florida-budget-65894.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gary Fineout</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gary Fineout</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>TALLAHASSEE, Florida — Gov. Ron DeSantis wants the state to take steps to discourage members of Congress from trading stocks, a topic that has seemingly divided Florida’s Hill delegation ahead of a potential vote in the House.</p> 
<p>DeSantis, during an event in Clearwater with GOP Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a>, gave his full backing to Luna’s proposed ban on individual stock trading for members. But he also said he is seeking state legislation to require people running for Congress in Florida to disclose ahead of time whether they intend to trade stocks if they are elected.</p> 
<p>During his press conference, DeSantis called individual stock trading a “bipartisan ailment,” adding, “We need to clean both houses up there.” He said members have either gotten windfalls — or avoided major losses — that defy normal investment patterns.</p> 
<p>In a social media post, <a href="https://x.com/RonDeSantis/status/2008555410584641803?s=20" target="_blank">he added that</a> “it is a farce how some members of Congress — including but not limited to Nancy Pelosi — suddenly become Warren Buffet on steroids when it comes to investment returns.”</p> 
<p>DeSantis acknowledged the state has limited authority to place restrictions on Florida’s congressional delegation. But he wants to require candidates to answer a question about stock trading on forms that are submitted at the time they qualify for the ballot. </p> 
<p>He said that would at least let voters know ahead of time what plan they to do. The governor added that such a requirement wouldn't really work for state legislators because they are only on the job part-time and many work in the financial sector.</p> 
<p>DeSantis also called on Florida’s congressional delegation to vote for Luna’s bill. <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/florida-playbook/2025/12/18/taking-stock-of-the-trading-ban-00697187#:~:text=Most%20of%20Florida's%20delegation%20didn,was%20by%20his%20adult%20son." target="_blank">Several Florida members signed on to a discharge petition</a>, but it’s not clear if all 28 will ultimately support the legislation.</p> 
<p>Luna said she’s spoken to House Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and she anticipates that her bill will be taken up during the first three months of the year.</p> 
<p>“It’s wrong and it needs to stop,” Luna said about individual stock trading.</p> 
<p>DeSantis’ support for the measure is not a surprise given his ongoing criticism of Congress. He has also advocated for congressional term limits.</p> 
<p>The governor made his stance amid the backdrop of 2026 elections, where the Republican front-runner for governor, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260201" data-person-id="260201">Byron Donalds</a>, has been dinged over his stock trading. Donalds <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/florida-playbook/2025/12/18/taking-stock-of-the-trading-ban-00697187#:~:text=Most%20of%20Florida's%20delegation%20didn,was%20by%20his%20adult%20son." target="_blank">has said previously that he relies on a financial adviser managing his IRA without his input</a> and that brokers who work for congressional clients should be required to publicly submit notes that would show whether members are directing trades.</p> 
<p>Donalds has been hit with ethics complaints alleging that he failed to disclose more than 100 stock trades in a timely fashion as required by federal law. He said <a href="https://donalds.house.gov/news/documentsingle.aspx?DocumentID=2423" target="_blank">during a radio interview in December</a> that he would vote for Luna’s bill, even though he wants a carve-out to allow stock trades if it is done by a broker on behalf of a member.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T11:45:49-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Indiana congressman Jim Baird and wife hospitalized after car crash</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/jim-baird-hospitalized-00712230</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-93e2-d651-a1ff-bfe2e62c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 10:32:33 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Indiana Rep. Jim Baird and his wife are being hospitalized following a serious car crash, President Donald Trump confirmed in televised comments to House Republicans on Monday. </p> 
<p>"They're going to be OK, but they had a pretty bad accident," Trump said at the top of his address to a House GOP legislative retreat, where he also paid tribute to the late California Rep. Doug LaMalfa following <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">his sudden death Monday</a>.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson also addressed LaMalfa's death and Baird's hospitalization before Trump spoke, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the closed-door comments. Johnson said he believed Baird was dealing with a spinal issue.</p> 
<p>Baird's office said in a statement that "his vehicle was struck in an accident."</p> 
<p>“Congressman Baird is in the hospital and is expected to make a full recovery, and he is extraordinarily grateful for everyone’s prayers during this time," the statement read.</p> 
<p>It is not clear when or where the crash involving Baird, 80, took place. Another Indiana Republican, Rep. Jackie Walorski, was killed in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/03/indiana-gop-rep-walorski-three-others-die-in-auto-accident-00049665" target="_blank">2022 auto collision</a> that also claimed the lives of two congressional aides and another driver.</p> 
<p>House Republicans are already dealing with a tight 218-213 margin following LaMalfa's death. Baird's hospitalization could further complicate Johnson's ability to wrangle his majority in the coming weeks — effectively leaving him with a two-vote margin.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misstated which day Trump spoke to House Republicans. It was Tuesday.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T11:01:47-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>GOP lawmaker Doug LaMalfa dies at 65</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222</link>
      <description>The Republican represented a rural northern California district.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-93b6-df0c-a5bb-b7f777590000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 09:35:05 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/36/a2/5ae1ba9643b49f079d8b7afa464a/house-republicans-press-conference-on-agriculture-and-food-production-93648.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.) speaks during a press conference on agriculture and food production on Capitol Hill June 15, 2022.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/36/a2/5ae1ba9643b49f079d8b7afa464a/house-republicans-press-conference-on-agriculture-and-food-production-93648.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jeremy B. White</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jeremy B. White</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Doug LaMalfa, a California Republican known for his expertise on water and forestry issues, has died at 65, according to statements from GOP officials.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa, a fourth-generation rice farmer and former state legislator, was serving his seventh term representing a rural district in the northeast corner of the state. He sat on the Agriculture, Natural Resources, and Transportation and Infrastructure committees.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump paid tribute to LaMalfa during a speech to House Republicans Tuesday as a reliable vote for his agenda.</p> 
<p><br>"And by the way, he wasn't a three-o'clock-in-the-morning person," Trump said, referring to GOP lawmakers who need presidential cajoling on critical votes. "With Doug, I never had to call. He was with us right from the beginning."</p> 
<p><br>His office said in a statement that LaMalfa is survived by his wife, Jill, four children and a grandchild. He "cared deeply for the people he served and worked tirelessly to hold the government to its word to fix our failing forests, build water storage, and leave people to be free to choose what is best for themselves," the statement said.</p> 
<p>Republicans who were close with LaMalfa were not aware of any health issues he had, and many were in shock Tuesday morning about his sudden passing, according to six GOP lawmakers who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss private matters.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa suffered an aneurysm and then a heart attack after being taken into surgery, according to one of the lawmakers and two others familiar with the matter.</p> 
<p>His death also further narrows an already slim Republican majority in the House. Now with a 218-213 advantage, Speaker Mike Johnson can afford no more than two defections on party-line votes where all members are present and voting.</p> 
<p>"We are mourning the loss of our friend and brother today and we send our respects for his life and work to his wife Jill and the LaMalfa family during this difficult time,” Johnson said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Rep. Richard Hudson (R-N.C.), chair of the House GOP campaign arm, remembered LaMalfa as a “real gearhead and motorsports fan" as well as a "principled conservative and a tireless advocate for the people of Northern California." </p> 
<p>"Doug brought grit, authenticity, and conviction to everything he did in public service," Hudson said.</p> 
<p>Under California law, Gov. Gavin Newsom has 14 days to set a date for a special election. He could set the date as soon as mid-May, though he could also schedule it to coincide with the state's June 2 primary. The winner would serve out LaMalfa's term under current district lines.</p> 
<p>His successor, however, will face a wildly different political landscape in the November election. LaMalfa's seat was among those targeted by California Democrats in their bid to redraw district lines to counter President Donald Trump's mid-decade redistricting push in Texas and other states. </p> 
<p>In November, California voters approved a gerrymandered House map that folded LaMalfa’s turf into a new, blue-leaning district — threatening to push him into a competitive race after years of cruising to reelection in a largely Republican district. He was up against a Democratic former state Senate leader who had already piled up money and endorsements.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa decried the gerrymander as anti-democratic even as he vowed to press ahead with meeting new constituents and holding onto office.</p> 
<p>“We've had a long-term relationship with people in northern California, and we’re not just going to walk away from that,” <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/california-gop-confronts-bleak-map-and-its-own-civil-war-00679331" target="_blank">LaMalfa told POLITICO</a> last month.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump huddles with House GOP</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/trump-house-gop-retreat-venezuela-briefing-00712179</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-91c1-df0c-a5bb-b5d7b9c10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans will hear directly from President Donald Trump on Tuesday for the first time since the administration’s extraordinary capture of Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>A wider group of lawmakers who want answers on the operation will have to wait till Wednesday, when all House and Senate members are expected to get briefed by administration officials. So far, both Democrats and Republicans are grumbling about the lack of details from the White House on what’s next for Venezuela.</p> 
<p><b>— Where things stand:</b> Speaker Mike Johnson emerged from a leadership briefing Monday night and said he does not believe the U.S. will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/venezuela-maduro-congress-briefing-mike-johnson-00712155" target="_blank">send troops to Venezuela</a>. And he played down concerns that Trump and his deputies reneged on pledges not to pursue regime change in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>“This is not a regime change,” Johnson said. “This is a demand for change of behavior by a regime.”</p> 
<p>But other Republicans struck a more skeptical note. “I think what the president was trying to communicate is hopefully facilitating a peaceful transition of power,” said Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), who was not at the briefing. “I don’t know how you do that without boots on the ground. And I don’t support boots on the ground.”</p> 
<p>The Senate is on track to take up a bipartisan war powers resolution Thursday aimed at constraining future Venezuela strikes. But don’t expect this attempt to succeed where prior ones have failed.</p> 
<p>Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.), who entertained supporting past resolutions, said he would not vote for the measure “at this time.”</p> 
<p><b>— Trump's turn to talk:&nbsp;</b>The president’s address to House Republicans Tuesday morning during their closed-door retreat at the Kennedy Center is expected to focus on touting GOP wins and rallying Republicans ahead of the midterms — not Venezuela.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders plan to discuss their 2026 legislative agenda with the rank-and-file. That includes whether Republicans will tackle another reconciliation bill and how to deal with health care and affordability issues.</p> 
<p>House Freedom Caucus members sent Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-9121-d78e-af9f-fd77beaf0000" target="_blank">a letter</a> Monday outlining policies they want to see accomplished in 2026, including reducing discretionary spending, codifying Trump’s border actions and preventing the Federal Reserve from issuing a digital currency.</p> 
<p><b>— What Democrats are doing:</b> Democrats are mulling options to force Venezuela-related votes, including during Tuesday's Rules Committee hearing. Democrats expect Reps. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) and Joaquin Castro (D-Texas) to reintroduce their own war powers resolution. And they are looking to keep the events of Jan. 6, 2021, in the spotlight on the five-year anniversary.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Jan. 6 anniversary split screen: </b>Johnson broke his silence Monday on the long-running saga of the missing plaque honoring the police who defended the Capitol during the Jan. 6, 2021, attack. His office made clear the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/23/congress/democrats-replica-jan-6-plaques-00418859" target="_blank">plaque now sitting in storage</a> won’t be hung on Johnson’s watch. The speaker’s comments come as House Democrats push to keep the attack in the public eye five years later. They are teeing up a Tuesday 10 a.m. presentation where they’re set to hear from former law enforcement officials, state officials, former members of the Democratic-led select panel and more.</p> 
<p><b>— Appropriations moves: </b>House and Senate GOP leaders are hoping to move a second funding package before the end-of-the-month shutdown deadline, according to four people granted anonymity to discuss the private strategy. That would be in addition to the three-bill package of Commerce-Justice-Science, Energy-Water and Interior-Environment, which the House will vote on this week and the Senate could take up as early as next week.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Don’t expect troops on the ground,’ Johnson says after Venezuela briefing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/venezuela-maduro-congress-briefing-mike-johnson-00712155</link>
      <description>Top Trump officials conducted a two-hour session with senior lawmakers — many of whom want more answers about what lies ahead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9125-dba9-addb-b3bfcb730000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:34:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d8/9e/2d56a47d4402939cbd12104a7166/u-s-congress-60959.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson speaks with reporters after a briefing with Trump administration officials on Capitol Hill Jan. 5, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d8/9e/2d56a47d4402939cbd12104a7166/u-s-congress-60959.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Connor O'Brien and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Connor O'Brien and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>U.S. troops will have a limited role in Venezuela, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said Monday, after top deputies to President Donald Trump briefed senior congressional leaders on the weekend operation that removed leader Nicolas Maduro from power.</p> 
<p>“We don’t expect troops on the ground,” Johnson told reporters after the two-hour evening briefing on Capitol Hill. “We don't expect direct involvement in any other way beyond just coercing the … the interim government to get that going. I expect that there will be an election called in Venezuela. … It should happen in short order.”</p> 
<p>The closed-door session was the first time top Trump administration officials briefed a group of lawmakers in person since the surprise Saturday morning raid that resulted in the capture of Maduro and his wife. Both pleaded not guilty Monday to drug trafficking and other charges in a federal courtroom in Manhattan.</p> 
<p>Hours later, Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth, Attorney General Pam Bondi, CIA Director John Ratcliffe and Joint Chiefs of Staff Chair Dan Caine met with top party leaders, as well as the bipartisan leaders of the Foreign Affairs, Foreign Relations, Armed Services and Intelligence committees.</p> 
<p>So far, the response to the administration’s actions in Venezuela has largely split along party lines. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> told reporters after the meeting that the briefing was “extensive” but it raised “far more questions than it answered.”</p> 
<p>“Their plan for the U.S. running Venezuela is vague … based on wishful thinking and unsatisfying,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Schumer added that he asked for “assurances that we would not try to do the same thing in other countries” but didn’t receive any.</p> 
<p>Johnson, meanwhile, sought to play down the broader implications of the military raid — and tamp down criticism that Trump and his deputies reneged on pledges not to pursue regime change in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>“The way this is being described — this is not a regime change,” Johnson said. “This is a demand for change of behavior by a regime.”</p> 
<p>The administration will brief all House members Wednesday, Johnson added. The Senate is also expected to get a briefing for all of its members that day, though that hasn’t been finalized.</p> 
<p>In addition to the operation over the weekend, administration officials and lawmakers in the room discussed explosions in Caracas that reportedly took place as the briefing unfolded, according to two people with knowledge of the briefing.</p> 
<p>A White House official granted anonymity to comment on the developing situation said the administration is closely tracking the reports of gunfire in Venezuela and that the U.S. is not involved.</p> 
<p>House Foreign Affairs Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259496" data-person-id="259496">Brian Mast</a> (R-Fla.), asked about the explosions, said in an interview that the briefers discussed everything “before, during and after” the U.S. operation. He later added, “I think it would be unreasonable to think there aren't disruptors there,” referencing the governments of Iran, China and Russia.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), the top Democrat on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, said she had some of her questions answered but added that “there are a significant number of questions that still need to be answered.”</p> 
<p>Asked if she believed that the Trump administration is considering similar actions in other countries, she said, “I don't think that's clear.”</p> 
<p>The top Democrat on the House Foreign Affairs Committee, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51521" data-person-id="51521">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.), voiced concerns about the Trump administration's plans for Venezuela following Maduro's ouster.</p> 
<p>"The military did its job. It had a plan," Meeks told reporters. "I don't like the orders that they were given. But I can't say the same for the plan after."</p> 
<p>But Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51675" data-person-id="51675">Roger Wicker</a> (R-Miss.), chair of the Senate Armed Services Committee, said “we have a lot of professionals running this, and I have confidence.”</p> 
<p>Some Republicans said they want more clarity from the administration on its ultimate endgame.</p> 
<p>“I've got to see what strategy there is,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.), who did not attend the briefing. “What the president was trying to communicate is hopefully facilitating a peaceful transition of power. We'll have to wait and see. I don't know how you do that without boots on the ground. And I don't support boots on the ground.”</p> 
<p>Other lawmakers grumbled not about the overall strategy but about the administration’s decision to brief lawmakers piecemeal instead of all at once. The Republican chair and ranking Democrat on the Senate Judiciary Committee, which has jurisdiction over the DOJ and FBI, jointly fumed about being cut out of the initial briefing despite administration officials describing Maduro’s capture as a law enforcement operation.</p> 
<p>“This business of coming over and just talking to some of us, I think is a special kind of stupid,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said in an interview Monday. “They need to sit down with every member of the Senate and explain what’s going on.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Daniella Cheslow contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ethics watchdog outlines allegations against Georgia Republican's chief of staff</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/new-ethics-allegations-00711424</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8fcf-df0c-a5bb-bfdfc1d70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 15:28:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A nonpartisan Congressional watchdog is alleging that Brandon Phillips, who has served as Rep. Mike Collins’ chief of staff, hired a romantic interest as an office intern and illicitly used his office’s Congressional resources.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://ethics.house.gov/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/OCC-Report-and-Findings-Brandon-Phillips-1.5.26.pdf" target="_blank">report from the Office of Congressional Conduct</a>, released Monday, also claims the intern “did not perform duties commensurate with her compensation.”</p> 
<p>“Based on the foregoing information, the Board finds that there is substantial reason to believe that Mr. Phillips discriminated unfairly by dispensing special favors or privileges by participating in the retention of an employee with whom Mr. Phillips had a personal relationship,” the report states.</p> 
<p>The status of Phillips' employment with Collins’ office at this point is unclear.</p> 
<p>Neither Phillips nor Collins, the Georgia Republican who is currently running for Senate, cooperated with the probe, though Collins’ office, in a statement, disputed the allegations.</p> 
<p>"This bogus complaint is a sad attempt to derail one of Georgia's most effective conservative legislators in Congress,” said a statement from Collins’ office. “Rep. Collins looks forward to providing the House Ethics Committee all factual information and putting these meritless allegations to rest.”</p> 
<p>The House Ethics Committee does not comment on ongoing investigations but said it is currently reviewing the allegations against both Collins and Phillips.</p> 
<p>The OCC, which fields allegations of misconduct against House members and staff, found evidence the Collins intern was paid thousands of dollars for her duties and appeared to have alternative employment while she remained on the congressional office payroll.</p> 
<p>Testimony from individuals who have worked in Collins’ district office said she never “perform[ed] any duties” there, while other people who worked for Collins in Washington said it did not appear that she ever interned for the Capitol Hill office, either.</p> 
<p>Some witnesses indicated that they were afraid of potential retaliation from Phillips, according to the OCC; the report cited a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/13/gop-operative-brandon-phillips-00073724" target="_blank">POLITICO story</a> alleging that Phllips kicked a dog.</p> 
<p>The report also detailed accusations that Phillips used Congressional funds for “Non-Official Travel-Related Expenses, Including Personal and Campaign-Related Expenses,” but OCC said it could not answer questions definitively about Phillips’ travel without Phillips’ and Collins’ cooperation.</p> 
<p>OCC recommended issuing subpoenas to Collins, Philips and the intern, among others.</p> 
<p>In a letter published with the report, Russell Duncan, a lawyer for Collins and Phillips, requested that the Ethics Committee vote to dismiss the allegations against his clients. Duncan claimed that the referrals were the result of testimony from “two disgruntled, former members of Congressman Collins staff.”</p> 
<p>Duncan also maintained that Phillips’ hiring of the intern was within his discretion, and she “provided valuable assistance to the Office throughout both years regarding communications and other work of the Office.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schumer calls out DOJ for not providing unredacted Epstein contacts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/schumer-doj-epstein-00711341</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8fa9-dba9-addb-bfbfb1b80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:45:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer on Monday blasted the Justice Department for not providing Congress with an unredacted report of political leaders referenced in documents related to convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/senschumer/status/2008232235673989381?s=46" target="_blank">In a post on X</a>, Schumer accused the Department of Justice of “lawlessness” as he vowed to “ensure all the files come out.”</p> 
<p>“Trump’s DOJ has failed to submit a report to Congress, which is required to include a list of all government officials and politically exposed persons named or referenced in the released materials, without redactions,” Schumer said. “What are they trying to hide?”</p> 
<p>The Justice Department did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>While the DOJ released thousands of documents in several waves last month in compliance with the Epstein Files Transparency Act, many were heavily redacted and some were deleted from the department’s website after initially being posted. Friday was the deadline for the Justice Department to explain the redactions.</p> 
<p>“It’s been 17 DAYS since the Trump DOJ first broke the law and failed to release all the Epstein files,” Schumer said. “It’s been 14 DAYS since Trump’s DOJ released anything at all — with the DOJ doing everything in its power to delay and obfuscate.”</p> 
<p>The Justice Department last month said it had uncovered <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/doj-epstein-documents-new-files-00706387" target="_blank">more than a million additional documents</a>potentially related to Epstein and that it may take “a few more weeks” before all could be released.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-05T11:28:23-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Krishnamoorthi steps down as top Democrat on House China panel</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/raja-krishnamoorthi-china-committee-00710551</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8eb2-dba9-addb-bfbf3b320003</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 10:08:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Illinois Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254656" data-person-id="254656">Raja Krishnamoorthi</a> is stepping down as the top Democrat on the select House committee on competition between the United States and the Chinese Communist Party, he announced Monday.</p> 
<p>Krishnamoorthi did not explain the reason for the move in a statement but is expected to focus on his Senate campaign for the seat being vacated by Democrat <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a>. </p> 
<p>The panel has been generally lauded as a bipartisan effort to investigate and analyze economic and political matters surrounding the Chinese government under President Xi Jinping.</p> 
<p>"I look forward to working closely with them to ensure that Democrats on this Committee continue to succeed, advancing policies that allow the United States to compete and win while remaining firmly grounded in the values that define us," Krishnamoorthi said.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> said Monday that Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/218327" data-person-id="218327">Ro Khanna</a> of California would take over as the top Democrat for the remainder of the 119th Congress.</p> 
<p>“We thank Ro for his continued determination, strong sense of purpose and commitment to the work needed to safeguard our economy, defend our national security and protect human rights around the world,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Congress confronts Venezuela fallout</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/venezuela-maduro-rubio-briefing-trump-war-powers-00710422</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8c6b-d78e-af9f-fc7f79b10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Venezuela will dominate the congressional agenda this week, with Republicans lacking a unified vision on what happens next after the capture of Nicolás Maduro and the Senate poised to vote to limit further attacks without lawmaker approval.</p> 
<p><b>— Briefings incoming: </b>Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth, Attorney General Pam Bondi, CIA Director John Ratcliffe and Joint Chiefs of Staff Chair Dan Caine will brief top lawmakers on this weekend’s Venezuela attack at 5:30 p.m. Monday.</p> 
<p>The members receiving the briefing include the top four congressional leaders as well as senior House and Senate members of the Intelligence, Armed Services, Foreign Affairs and Foreign Relations committees.</p> 
<p>Trump himself will speak to House Republicans Tuesday at their annual retreat at the Kennedy Center.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune and Minority Leader Chuck Schumer are also working to schedule an all-senators briefing as soon as mid-week, according to two people granted anonymity.</p> 
<p><b>— The big question: Who will 'run' Venezuela? </b>Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/gop-hawks-trump-maduro-venezuela-00709776" target="_blank">largely rallied behind</a> the administration’s capture of Maduro and his wife, Cilia Flores. But there’s some daylight between them when it comes to what happens next — and some emerging distrust with the administration.</p> 
<p>Trump, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/04/trump-warns-acting-venezuelan-leader-00710314" target="_blank">at least initially</a>, praised Venezuelan Vice President Delcy Rodríguez — now the country’s acting leader — as someone he could work with. His comments were at odds with the wishes of Florida Republican lawmakers who prefer Venezuelan opposition leader María Corina Machado. Trump dismissed her as not having the “support” or “respect” to lead the country. Other Republicans including Rep. Bill Huizenga of Michigan and Sen. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana are calling on Trump to look to Edmundo González, who many nations <a href="https://apnews.com/article/venezuela-presidential-election-maduro-colombia-petro-g20-f2c27ee80ed50cae7109499a23c59552" target="_blank">consider the rightful winner</a> of Venezuela’s 2024 presidential election.</p> 
<p>Behind the scenes, some Republicans are entering the week, as many Democrats are saying publicly, feeling misled by Rubio and the others in the administration about what the endgame has been for Venezuela. Lawmakers have generally trusted Rubio, their former colleague, but the Venezuela attack is straining the relationship.</p> 
<p>Rubio on Sunday was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/04/marco-rubio-venezuela-future-maduro-00710161" target="_blank">vague on the administration’s transition plans</a> for Venezuela. Instead of outlining Trump’s pledge to “run” the country, he said the U.S. is not occupying Venezuela and is instead implementing a “quarantine that allows us to exert tremendous leverage over what happens next.”</p> 
<p><b>— The war powers vote:&nbsp;</b>Despite some bipartisan misgivings, it doesn’t yet appear there will be a groundswell of GOP opposition to Trump’s move if the Senate votes this week on whether to limit further military action in Venezuela without congressional approval. A <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/06/congress/senate-venezuela-vote-00640088" target="_blank">November vote on the issue</a> garnered support from just two Republicans, Sens. Rand Paul (Ky.) and Lisa Murkowski (Alaska). </p> 
<p>House Democrats in a private meeting Sunday discussed how they could force Speaker Mike Johnson to hold a vote on war powers, according to three people granted anonymity. House Republicans in December narrowly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-gop-narrowly-defeats-boat-strike-limits-00696784" target="_blank">defeated a resolution</a> to block military action in Venezuela, with Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) breaking with their party to support it.</p> 
<p>Massie’s <a href="https://x.com/repthomasmassie/status/2007855570447913358" target="_blank">aggressive rebuke</a> of the weekend attack is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/thomas-massie-trump-venezuela-attack-america-first-00710350" target="_blank">opening a new front</a> in his primary as he faces off against Trump-backed challenger and former Navy SEAL Ed Gallrein.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Shutdown vibes not so bad: </b>House leaders are hoping to put a three-bill funding package on the floor Thursday covering Commerce-Justice-Science, Interior-Environment and Energy-Water. If the House passes it with Democratic support, it could also become a vehicle for a stop-gap continuing resolution in the Senate.</p> 
<p><b>— Health care action: </b>House Democrats will move as soon as Wednesday to force a vote on extending expired Affordable Care Act subsidies for three years, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal planning. The House could pass the bill by Thursday but it’s on track to die in the Senate.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Old headaches will plague Mike Johnson in the new year</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/mike-johnson-headaches-2026-00709400</link>
      <description>The speaker is working to refocus Republicans on cost-of-living matters. But he will find it hard to escape nasty internal clashes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-807d-df0c-a5bb-b47f87150000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/60/71/0ae8d3ed42dfa1069b21482c6453/u-s-congress-59984.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson (R-La.) speaks with reporters as he walks to a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 18, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/60/71/0ae8d3ed42dfa1069b21482c6453/u-s-congress-59984.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is back for the new year. But Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> isn’t exactly getting a fresh start in 2026.</p> 
<p>The House returns from the holiday recess to confront old issues that continue to bedevil Johnson — from politically perilous battle over health care and the ongoing release of the Jeffrey Epstein files to a messy intra-GOP fight over lawmakers’ stock trading and another looming government shutdown cliff.</p> 
<p>The speaker is working to refocus Republicans, seeking to rally members around initiatives aimed at reducing housing prices and efforts to hammer Democrats over public-benefits fraud in Minnesota and other states. President Donald Trump’s decision to depose Venezuelan leader Nicolas Maduro by force has also given the GOP a new rallying point amid doubts about <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/trump-victory-lap-raid-maduro-00709641" target="_blank">Trump's plan to indefinitely “run”</a> the South American country.</p> 
<p>But Johnson will find it hard to escape internally divisive clashes as the GOP feels pressure to address the rising cost of living and otherwise firm up its standing ahead of the November midterms.</p> 
<p>He will immediately confront a growing battle within his ranks this week over how to tackle high health care costs after Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">allowed enhanced Obamacare tax credits to expire</a> at the end of 2025.</p> 
<p>Democrats plan to move as soon as Wednesday to force a floor vote on a three-year straight extension of the lapsed subsidies, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal planning. That comes after four House Republicans mounted a mini-mutiny against Johnson last month by signing a discharge petition backed by Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>.</p> 
<p>While this three-year extension could pass the House by Thursday, the bill is set to die in the Senate, where Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> has indicated he has no plans to move it forward after a similar measure failed to garner the necessary 60 votes in a test vote last month. But a group of moderate senators continue to discuss a compromise proposal, and the rebellious House Republicans are hoping consensus legislation will eventually come back across the Capitol for final action.</p> 
<p>The prospects for a bipartisan deal are dim, however, with Trump continuing to slam the Obamacare tax credits as wasteful while pushing Republicans to instead send money directly to taxpayers via health savings accounts. That’s in addition to the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698" target="_blank">internal GOP battle on Capitol Hill</a> over whether to pursue a party-line health care bill this year that could include sending checks to Americans to offset high health care costs.</p> 
<p>Johnson is projecting confidence going into 2026, writing in a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/opinion/house-republicans-had-a-great-year-04efce46" target="_blank">recent Wall Street Journal op-ed</a> that Republicans have “laid the groundwork for an extraordinary new year — from containing the border crisis and stabilizing inflation to securing historic tax, trade and peace deals.”</p> 
<p>“The best is yet to come,” he wrote, predicting that Americans would “experience the tangible results of common-sense governance” and reward the GOP at the ballot box.</p> 
<p>But that isn’t likely to keep internal rivalries in check. On Venezuela, for instance, Johnson will have to grapple with a pro-intervention Florida delegation while other elements of the conference could be more skeptical of Trump’s threats of long-term military engagement.</p> 
<p>Another headache from inside Johnson’s own conference is coming from hard-liners such as Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a> of Texas and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> of Florida, who are demanding a vote on legislation to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/20/congress/chip-roy-stock-trading-vote-00615272" target="_blank">ban congressional stock trading</a>.</p> 
<p>Johnson and House Administration Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/32319" data-person-id="32319">Bryan Steil</a> (R-Wis.) are seeking to head off threats of a discharge petition that would force a vote on that proposal by drafting their own framework for cracking down on insider trading. They plan to move it out of Steil’s panel and onto the floor in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>But the GOP leadership-backed bill would, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/johnson-steil-insider-trading-stocks-00698141" target="_blank">as POLITICO first reported</a>, still allow lawmakers to hold stocks they already own — a concession that might pass muster with Roy and Luna but is stoking others’ ire. Democrats are already raising alarms over the plan they say falls short of a full ban on congressional stock trading.</p> 
<p>An even more explosive issue — the Epstein files — threatens to continue dogging House GOP leaders as well, as the Justice Department is under increasing criticism across party lines for its slow and incomplete release of materials related to the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>While Congress required DOJ to make its Epstein case files fully public last month, department officials say millions of pages of records continue to be reviewed. And critics say the records that have been released have been subject to improper redactions and other irregularities.</p> 
<p>The issue could come to a head in the coming weeks, with House Judiciary Republicans looking to schedule a routine oversight hearing with Attorney General Pam Bondi that is now expected to focus heavily on the administration’s handling of the Epstein case.</p> 
<p>“They are blatantly ignoring the law,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.), who helped lead the effort to release the files and sits on the Judiciary Committee, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>He and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/218327" data-person-id="218327">Ro Khanna</a> (D-Calif.), who co-sponsored the legislation compelling the release of the files, have said they are preparing to push for a rare “inherent contempt” vote against Bondi that could include fines and other sanctions for DOJ’s alleged noncompliance.</p> 
<p>If there’s any encouraging news for Johnson heading into 2026, it’s on the appropriations front.</p> 
<p>With only a handful of legislative days left before the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid a shutdown — and with many Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/appropriations-talks-jan-30-00701426" target="_blank">worried about the potential</a> for another short-term punt — the top four House and Senate appropriators have been making quiet progress on a three-bill funding package as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/trump-shutdown-january-00700940" target="_blank">appetites fade for allowing the government to shutter</a> yet again.</p> 
<p>Talks around a full-fiscal-year “minibus” that would include the Interior, Energy-Water and Commerce-Justice-Science appropriations bills are close to being finalized, three other people granted anonymity to discuss internal deliberations said. GOP leaders are hoping to put the package on the House floor Thursday if a deal can be reached.</p> 
<p>In the meantime, House GOP leaders are navigating internal politics around a major bipartisan housing package the Financial Services Committee approved last month. While it remains unclear whether the House and Senate can reconcile competing housing plans, Johnson is pushing forward after Trump’s top pollster told a closed-door briefing of House Republicans last month they should focus more on housing affordability issues ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>This week, House GOP leaders are planning to hold votes on a bill from Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/173107" data-person-id="173107">Erin Houchin</a> (R-Ind.) that would cut red tape and relax energy efficiency standards for manufactured housing as well as a measure from Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/250906" data-person-id="250906">Russell Fry</a> (R-S.C.) that would codify Trump’s effort to roll back a regulation instituted under former President Joe Biden limiting water flow for shower nozzles.</p> 
<p>But even Republican leaders’ unity-building proposals — such as highlighting the fraud convictions in Minnesota — could end up sparking fights.</p> 
<p>A growing number of conservatives want Trump to reinstate Elon Musk in his prior role as efficiency czar to probe reports of Medicaid fraud and other related projects. But other Republicans, especially key moderates, are cool to the idea.</p> 
<p>“We have fraud experts in the government that can do this,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227109" data-person-id="227109">Don Bacon</a> (R-Neb.) said in an interview. “They should be able to do their jobs.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-03T16:44:50-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘Iraq 2.0’: Democrats seethe at Trump’s surprise Venezuela strike</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/congress-democrats-war-powers-venezuela-reaction-00709636</link>
      <description>The operation quickly united lawmakers behind a message that the president illegally bypassed Congress and has no plan for the aftermath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8451-df0c-a5bb-b457333f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 10:05:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/97/78/f815d1294d01a260ce4b513b8ad5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2253839665">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Luis Jaimes/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>A fire is seen at Fuerte Tiuna, Venezuela's largest military complex, after a series of explosions in Caracas, Venezuela, on Jan. 3, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/97/78/f815d1294d01a260ce4b513b8ad5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2253839665" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy, Connor O'Brien and Leo Shane III</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy, Connor O'Brien and Leo Shane III</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are furious over President Donald Trump’s plans for Venezuela.</p> 
<p>The president’s latest show of force on the world stage, which Trump says saw the U.S. military capture Venezuelan President Nicolas Maduro and his wife, quickly united both party leaders and rank-and-file lawmakers behind one message: The White House illegally bypassed Congress and appears woefully underprepared for the aftermath of the surprise military operation.</p> 
<p>The top Democratic congressional leaders each released statements lambasting Trump after he revealed at a Mar-a-Lago news conference Saturday that the administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/trump-victory-lap-raid-maduro-00709641" target="_blank">plans to run Venezuela</a> for an undetermined amount of time.</p> 
<p>“The administration has assured me three separate times that it was not pursuing regime change or taking military action in Venezuela," Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said. "Clearly, they are not being straight with Americans. The idea that Trump plans to now run Venezuela should strike fear in the hearts of all Americans. The American people have seen this before and paid the devastating price."</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries was even more explicit in drawing parallels to recent U.S. efforts at regime change that were costly in both taxpayer dollars and American lives.</p> 
<p>"The promotion of security and stability in a region requires more than just military force as we painfully discovered in Iraq and Afghanistan," he said.</p> 
<p>Trump announced the strike in an <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115830428767897167" target="_blank">early morning post on Truth Social Saturday</a>, touching off a wave of praise from ideologically aligned members of his party. But while Democrats were largely careful not to defend Maduro, they had quick criticism for how Trump had secretly orchestrated the strike.</p> 
<p>The Gang of Eight, which includes senior congressional leaders and top members of the House and Senate Intelligence committees, was notified of the operation only after it had been launched, according to a person with direct knowledge granted anonymity to discuss private outreach.</p> 
<p>While several Republican lawmakers said Saturday they had been personally briefed by Secretary of State Marco Rubio, few if any Democrats appear to have gotten that courtesy.</p> 
<p>Schumer told reporters Saturday afternoon he still had not been briefed by the administration. In a separate joint statement, Schumer and Jeffries requested a Gang of Eight briefing as soon as Saturday, as well as a briefing for a wider group of lawmakers early next week.</p> 
<p>Trump defended the administration's tight lips in his news conference, telling reporters that "Congress has a tendency to leak."</p> 
<p>"This would not be good," he added. "If they leaked … I think this would be a very different result."</p> 
<p>But Schumer called that an “excuse for secrecy” that is “outrageous” and “dangerous.” Schumer said Saturday that he is already strategizing with top committee Democrats about what steps they could take to “hold the administration accountable.” House Democrats are scheduled to hold an emergency caucus meeting Sunday, according to an invitation sent to members.</p> 
<p>“Some of the Republican chairs, at least privately on the phone … have expressed a lot of troublesome comments about what Trump is doing and the way he is doing it, and those discussions will continue,” Schumer said, relaying private conversations between Democrats he had spoken to and the GOP chairs.</p> 
<p>Well before the top Democratic congressional leaders spoke out, rank-and-file lawmakers took the lead in angrily denouncing Trump’s decision to topple a foreign leader by military force without asking lawmakers for authorization first.</p> 
<p>“Congress did not authorize this war,” Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.) <a href="https://x.com/sethmoulton/status/2007419546458902795" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. “Venezuela posed no imminent threat to the United States. This is reckless, elective regime change risking American lives (Iraq 2.0) with no plan for the day after. Wars cost more than trophies.”</p> 
<p>Congress has not authorized military action against Venezuela, and lawmakers have been split for months on the legality of the Trump administration’s strikes against suspected drug smuggling vessels in the waters off Latin America and a potential move to oust Maduro. Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-gop-narrowly-defeats-boat-strike-limits-00696784" target="_blank">fended off several Democratic-led efforts</a> to require Trump to seek approval from Congress before attacking Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.), who sits on the Senate Armed Services Committee, announced Saturday he would again force the chamber to vote on his effort to constrain Trump’s war powers next week.</p> 
<p>"It’s time for Congress to get its ass off the couch and do what the Constitution mandates that we do,” Kaine told reporters during a call Saturday. “What we've seen is members of Congress who, frankly, lack the guts, lack the backbone, lack the courage to have that debate, and they've been willing to allow an increasingly declining and erratic president to make these decisions without them.”</p> 
<p>In addition to the war powers vote, Kaine raised the possibility that an upcoming government funding deadline could offer further leverage. Democrats, he said, would “press for a vote” to prohibit expenditures on military actions concerning Venezuela without congressional approval.</p> 
<p>Schumer, however, didn’t draw a red line on the spending fight, saying the immediate focus was on getting briefings and a war powers vote: “Let’s first get all the facts out,” he said.</p> 
<p>In addition to criticizing the murky legal justification for the operation, several Democrats said the move is an about-face for administration officials who they said argued regime change wasn’t the end goal of the administration’s aggressive military campaign in Latin America.</p> 
<p>“Secretaries Rubio and [Pete] Hegseth looked every Senator in the eye a few weeks ago and said this wasn’t about regime change. I didn’t trust them then and we see now that they blatantly lied to Congress,” Sen. Andy Kim (D-N.J.) <a href="https://x.com/SenatorAndyKim/status/2007399987596906501" target="_blank">said on X</a>. “Trump rejected our Constitutionally required approval process for armed conflict because the Administration knows the American people overwhelmingly reject risks pulling our nation into another war.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Sen. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.), a combat veteran who deployed to Iraq as an infantryman in 2005, wrote on X Saturday that “the American people did not ask for this.”</p> 
<p>And he wondered aloud about what comes next for the South American country, <a href="https://x.com/RubenGallego/status/2007448353584623708" target="_blank">asking on X</a>, “so who is in charge of Venezuela now?”</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/poll-trump-military-action-in-venezuela-00695694" target="_blank">December Quinnipiac poll</a> found that Americans overwhelmingly oppose military action against Venezuela, with just 25 percent of respondents saying they supported an intervention inside the country. Even the White House’s strategy of targeting boats with alleged drug traffickers proved broadly unpopular.</p> 
<p>“I fought in some of the hardest battles of the Iraq War,” <a href="https://x.com/RubenGallego/status/2007379621155930357" target="_blank">Gallego wrote</a>. “Saw my brothers die, saw civilians being caught in the crossfire all for an unjustified war. No matter the outcome we are in the wrong for starting this war in Venezuela.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Debbie Wasserman Schultz (D-Fla.), who is a co-chair of the Congressional Venezuela Democracy Caucus and represents a significant population of Venezuelan immigrants in South Florida, signaled agreement with the move to oust Maduro. She called his capture "welcome news" for Venezuela but argued Trump should have involved Congress before conducting the attack.</p> 
<p>"The absence of congressional involvement prior to this action risks the continuation of the illegitimate Venezuelan regime," Wasserman Schultz said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Other Democrats voiced stronger opposition to the administration’s military moves.</p> 
<p>“Millions of Americans voted in the last Presidential election to end frivolous conflicts and unnecessary foreign wars,” said Rep. Gabe Vasquez (D-N.M.), an Armed Services Committee member, in a statement. “This escalation of hostilities against Venezuela and the capture of a foreign leader without congressional authorization goes against the will of the Americans who put the president in power.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/democrats-trump-sedition-backfire-00670552" target="_blank">found himself accused of sedition by Trump in November</a> after encouraging American troops to disregard unlawful orders, urged Congress to reassert its war powers in this week's vote.</p> 
<p>“I want the people of Venezuela to be free to choose their own future, but if we learned anything from the Iraq war, it’s that dropping bombs or toppling a leader doesn’t guarantee democracy, stability, or make Americans safer,” he wrote in a statement. “More often, it leads to chaos or drags the U.S. into a war and lengthy occupation. I don’t trust that this administration has a plan, timeline, or price tag for what comes next.”</p> 
<p>But hawkish GOP Sen. Lindsey Graham of South Carolina <a href="https://x.com/lindseygrahamsc/status/2007466123009126597" target="_blank">offered a rejoinder on X</a> to critics of the operation who are "focus[ed] on absurd 'legal' theories" and "virtually AWOL for the cause of freedom."</p> 
<p>"To the pathetically weak and hand wringing liberal Democrats who seem to be okay with a perpetual drug caliphate in our backyard, the centerpiece of which is Venezuela," he wrote, "Get a grip."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
