<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 20:31:57 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Marjorie Taylor Greene resigns from Congress after clash with Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972</link>
      <description>The former Trump loyalist said she will step down Jan. 5.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a927-d49b-af9f-bde7834a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 20:31:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0e/b0/f9ff8c3e401c944363eaab591391/u-s-congress-45616.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene speaks alongside victims of convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a press conference outside the U.S. Capitol on Nov. 18.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0e/b0/f9ff8c3e401c944363eaab591391/u-s-congress-45616.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Marjorie Taylor Greene, the MAGA firebrand who rose to prominence as a combative supporter of President Donald Trump, announced late Friday she is resigning from Congress after a public feud with him.</p> 
<p>Greene, who was elected to Congress in 2020 from a rural northwestern Georgia district, made the surprise announcement in a surprise video address that referenced her falling out with Trump. The president branded her a “traitor” and withdrew his endorsement for supporting an effort he opposed to release files from the criminal investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“Standing up for American women who were raped at 14, trafficked and used by rich powerful men, should not result in me being called a traitor and threatened by the President of the United States, whom I fought for,” she said in a <a href="https://x.com/mtgreenee/status/1992037226415554642?s=20" target="_blank">statement posted on X</a>.</p> 
<p>Her resignation reflects increasing divisions within the MAGA movement that propelled Trump to power on a populist agenda that Greene had aggressively supported.</p> 
<p>The Republican lawmaker’s relationship with Trump soured after she joined calls from Democrats to release the Epstein files, criticized the president’s focus on foreign affairs and called for action on the expiring Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>“Loyalty should be a two-way street and we should be able to vote our conscience and represent our district’s interest because our job title is literally representative,’' she said.</p> 
<p>Greene said she will step down from office on Jan. 5.</p> 
<p>She did not provide advance notice to to anyone in House Republican leadership, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal matters.</p> 
<p>Her resignation threatens to further tighten Speaker Mike Johnson’s Republican majority early next year.</p> 
<p>The GOP holds a 219-213 advantage following Democrat Mikie Sherrill’s resignation this week after her election as New Jersey governor. That means Johnson can lose no more than two Republicans on a party-line vote.</p> 
<p>Greene highlighted her record of supporting Trump since she entered Congress, noting that she only disagreed in a "few areas” with some of the president’s recent proposals on immigration, artificial intelligence and foreign policy along with her stance on the Epstein documents.</p> 
<p>The White House had no immediate comment and appeared to be caught off-guard by her resignation. </p> 
<p>“It is surprising to absolutely no one that she would exit in the most selfish way possible,” an administration official, who was granted anonymity to discuss the resignation before a statement had been released. </p> 
<p>Rachel Scott, a senior political correspondent for ABC, <a href="https://x.com/rachelvscott/status/1992056507953754215?t=YE1da1BAx7NV3wFu_EzpSA&amp;s=19" target="_blank">said on X</a> that she spoke with Trump and he was surprised but pleased with the resignation. "I think it's great news for the country. It's great," he said.</p> 
<p>The growing divide between Trump and Greene came to a head last week when the president revoked his endorsement of Green in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-mtg-aca-epstein-massie-00653412" target="_blank"><u>scathing social media post</u></a> in which he labeled her “wacky” and a “ranting lunatic.” Days later, he reversed his position on the Epstein case files and encouraged House Republicans to support a bill that would for the Department of Justice to release the documents.</p> 
<p>Johnson later tried to paper over the rift between the Georgia Republican and Trump. The speaker acknowledged the dispute over the Epstein documents but said it was important that the party hold together.</p> 
<p>“But look, I work on unity in the party, and my encouragement of everybody is to get together,” he said. “We’ve got to do all that in order to deliver for the people.”</p> 
<p>Greene suggested in her statement that a looming primary challenge from a candidate aligned with the president factored into her decision — referring to the pro-Trump super PAC MAGA Inc. as one of the actors pushing her aside.</p> 
<p>“I have too much self respect and dignity, love my family way too much, and do not want my sweet district to have to endure a hurtful and hateful primary against me by the President we all fought for, only to fight and win my election while Republicans will likely lose the midterms,” she said.</p> 
<p>Her resignation brings a stunning conclusion to a tumultuous tenure that included promoting outlandish conspiracy theories. In 2021, the House voted to strip her of her committee assignments for social media posts promoting violence towards prominent Democrats.</p> 
<p>She also earned a reputation as a wild card among the House Republican caucus. In 2024, she attempted to remove Johnson from his position as the party was still recovering from a protracted fight that led to the ouster of former Speaker Kevin McCarthy.</p> 
<p>Days after being sworn into office for the first time, she joined a group of Republican members of Congress seeking to block the certification of Joe Biden’s presidential election victory over Trump on Jan. 6., 2021.</p> 
<p>Greene did not rule out a future run for office, suggesting she might run as an independent if she returned to politics. </p> 
<p>"When the common American people finally realize and understand that the political industrial complex of both parties is ripping this country apart, that not one elected leader like me is able to stop Washington's machine from gradually destroying our country, and instead the reality is that they, common Americans, the people, possess the real power over Washington," she said, "then I'll be here by their side to rebuild it." </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-21T15:23:14-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House members move to force Russia sanctions vote as Trump pushes peace deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/russia-sanctions-discharge-petition-00665210</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a7f6-df0f-abfa-e7fe1e3a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 14:52:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan coalition of pro-Ukraine lawmakers will seek to force a House vote to impose crippling sanctions on Russia, even as President Donald Trump is moving to swiftly clinch a peace deal between the two warring nations.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) <a href="https://x.com/RepBrianFitz/status/1991940517584666907?s=20" target="_blank">said in an X post Friday</a> that he and his allies have “officially notified both the Clerk of the House and House leadership of our discharge petition to force a vote on crushing Russian sanctions immediately upon our return” from the Thanksgiving holiday recess.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick was responding to news that Trump wants the Ukrainian government to approve the draft peace deal <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/witkoff-back-channel-push-ukraine-alarms-allies-00660247" target="_blank">assembled by his envoy Steve Witkoff</a> no later than Thursday. The plan would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/trump-plan-to-end-ukraine-war-cedes-donbas-to-russia-00664204" target="_blank">cede vast portions of eastern Ukraine</a> to Russia in exchange for a security guarantee from western nations.</p> 
<p>Trump appeared to be putting pressure on Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy with his Thanksgiving ultimatum, but the House lawmakers have their eye on Russian President Vladimir Putin — and they believe they have Trump’s blessing.</p> 
<p>House and Senate GOP leaders have held off for months, awaiting a clear signal from Trump, but with the president more determined to impose a peace plan than ever, rank-and-file members are determined to act.</p> 
<p>“The President’s appeasement plan to Russia is forcing our hand," said Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.).</p> 
<p>A discharge petition can circumvent the majority leadership if 218 House members sign it; it has been used to pressure Speaker Mike Johnson multiple times this year — most recently to pass legislation on the so-called Epstein files.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and other members of the Ukraine Caucus have offered sanctions legislation alongside Sens. Richard Blumenthal (D-Conn.) and Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.). Fitzpatrick <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/house-resolution/438?s=1&amp;r=3" target="_blank">filed a resolution</a> earlier this year setting up a possible effort to discharge that bill but did not immediately trigger it.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers could also force a vote on a bill from Reps. Gregory Meeks (D-N.Y.) and Steny Hoyer (D-Md.) that would pair Russia sanctions with assistance for Ukraine. The bipartisan Ukraine Caucus is set to hold a virtual meeting Monday to “talk about what the best strategy is to get something done quickly,” Fitzpatrick said in an interview Friday.</p> 
<p>“We’re talking about potentially moving them together if the sanctions are not brought to the floor in short order,” Fitzpatrick said ahead of his social media post.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick said he has been talking to Johnson about the sanctions bill and believes the speaker is supportive of the legislation. Noticing his intention to force a vote now, with the House leaving for a weeklong recess, effectively gives Johnson until early December to find an off-ramp.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ghislaine Maxwell will plead Fifth in House Epstein probe, Comer says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/ghislaine-maxwell-plead-fifth-house-oversight-00664640</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a785-d739-a3ba-fffd93bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:26:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ghislaine Maxwell, the convicted co-conspirator of the late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, will refuse to answer questions in the House Oversight Committee's probe into Epstein and the Justice Department’s handling of the case, Oversight Chair James Comer said.</p> 
<p>Maxwell's legal team said she would invoke her Fifth Amendment rights if she sat with congressional investigators, the Kentucky Republican said in an interview. He also suggested it would be unlikely that his staff or lawmakers would sit down with Maxwell, who is in a federal prison camp in Texas, under the circumstances.</p> 
<p>“Her lawyers have replied that she's not going to answer any questions," Comer said. "She's only going to plead the Fifth. I mean, I could spend a bunch of taxpayer dollars to send staff and members down there, and if she's going to plead the Fifth, I don’t know that that's a good investment.”</p> 
<p>Comer <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/23/congress/epstein-james-comer-subpoena-ghislaine-maxwell-testify-00471644" target="_blank">issued a subpoena</a> in July for Maxwell’s testimony, and her legal team initially suggested that she would be willing to answer questions <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/29/congress/maxwell-makes-demands-00481769" target="_blank">under certain conditions</a>, including that her appeals had been resolved. The Supreme Court recently rejected a request to revisit her conviction.</p> 
<p>In return for her cooperation, Maxwell requested immunity from further criminal proceedings and to receive questions in advance. Comer said both immunity and advanced notice was a nonstarter.</p> 
<p>An attorney for Maxwell, David Oscar Markus, did not immediately return a message seeking comment. He signed a July letter saying Maxwell "will have no choice but to invoke her Fifth Amendment rights" unless her demands were met.</p> 
<p>Maxwell was sentenced to 20 years in prison in 2022 on child sex trafficking charges. In the context of government investigations, the Fifth Amendment protects against witnesses from being forced to give testimony that would potentially incriminate themselves.</p> 
<p>Maxwell sat for a two-day interview with the Justice Department in July and shortly afterward was transferred to the minimum security facility in Texas. Critics have argued she has received favorable treatment from the administration. Maxwell is also preparing a commutation application for President Donald Trump's consideration.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This House GOP centrist is plotting a new health care bill aimed at winning over Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635</link>
      <description>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick wants to pair an extension of Obamacare subsidies with new flexibility for health savings accounts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a779-d739-a3ba-fffd33380000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 12:33:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/89/1f/76c377164f26953c2731101ac4a9/u-s-congress-94407.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“We’re going to have to move quickly,” Fitzpatrick said.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/89/1f/76c377164f26953c2731101ac4a9/u-s-congress-94407.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A key House Republican moderate is drafting a new bill that would extend soon-to-expire Obamacare subsidies and offer a carrot to try to win over more-conservative GOP colleagues and President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.), who co-chairs the bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus, outlined in an interview Friday several elements he is eyeing for the new proposal: an extension of the Affordable Care Act tax credits, with income limits and required minimum premium payments; new flexibility for health savings accounts, a conservative priority aimed at wooing Trump and conservatives; and potentially a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2025/09/08/can-congress-revive-pbm-reform-00549936" target="_blank">stalled bipartisan package</a> overhauling the role of pharmaceutical benefit managers.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, who has been working with fellow GOP centrists who are desperate to address the subsidy cliff, said it was “our hope” that they would soon introduce a bill encompassing those provisions.</p> 
<p>“We’re going to have to move quickly,” he said.</p> 
<p>The proposal would be <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/rick-scott-releases-obamacare-subsidy-alternative-00664146" target="_blank">competing with</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/cassidy-fund-hsas-trump-aca-subsidies-00655213" target="_blank">multiple alternatives</a> from conservative Republicans who are proposing to at least partially end the federal subsidies for plans purchased on Affordable Care Act exchanges, replacing them with individual accounts that they say would give Americans more flexibility to purchase health care.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and his allies are open to moving toward more flexibility for HSAs, but they don’t want to allow the Obamacare tax credits to expire as well. Some in the group strongly believe they need to focus on extending the existing subsidies first, then develop a broader health care overhaul.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and several other Republicans in the Problem Solvers group spoke about their health care plans during a private dinner Thursday night. Bacon <a href="http://politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/house-denounces-horrors-of-socialism-00664412" target="_blank">rolled out a separate bipartisan plan</a> Friday with GOP Rep. Jeff Hurd of Colorado and Democratic Reps. Tom Suozzi of New York and Josh Gottheimer of New Jersey that would extend the subsidies for two years, albeit with new restrictions on eligibility.</p> 
<p>But Fitzpatrick said that, based on conversations with colleagues, more than an extension will need to be included in order to attract a critical mass of GOP votes. Trump and top House GOP leaders have signaled they are opposed to continuing the ACA tax credits, and scores of House Republicans have signaled the same.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise, asked about the centrist Republicans’ aims in an interview Friday, said GOP leaders had other plans. He indicated Republicans are planning to bring legislation dealing with HSA flexibility, the PBM overhaul, cost-sharing reductions and other conservative policies to the floor in the coming weeks — but not an ACA tax-credit extension.</p> 
<p>“There are a lot of really good ideas that we're going to be bringing to the floor for votes that lower premiums for families, bring more transparency and more options for families,” he said.</p> 
<p>When asked if GOP leaders believe it’s tenable to allow the subsidies to expire, letting those other policies fill the gap, he replied: “We don't have all the final things agreed upon, and we will work through it with our whole conference.”</p> 
<p>The House GOP centrists feel left in the lurch by their own leaders, who have followed the lead of more conservative factions in advocating for the subsidies to expire. But they’ve also been angered by moderate Democrats, who they say are insisting on first sketching out a larger “framework” for negotiations.</p> 
<p>Democrats have been cool to the GOP proposals that would substitute individual spending accounts for the existing subsidies, arguing that they would not fully fill the financial gap for many Americans and could <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/11/obamacare-could-collapse-under-trumps-new-plan-policy-experts-say-00647246" target="_blank">destabilize health insurance markets</a>.</p> 
<p>One House Republican who was at the Thursday night dinner said colleagues spent a large portion of the evening kvetching about Democrats, whom they remain angry at after the lengthy government shutdown.</p> 
<p>“We’re past talking about frameworks,” said another House Republican, who was granted anonymity to speak candidly about the internal discussions. “This is an emergency.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jordan seeks info from banks in probe of Jack Smith</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/jordan-writes-to-banks-00664520</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a744-df0f-abfa-e76e57d70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 12:00:19 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan is asking major banks to hand over communications and materials related to former special counsel Jack Smith’s far-reaching investigations into President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Bank of America, JPMorgan Chase, Citigroup and Morgan Stanley are among more than a dozen financial institutions receiving letters from the Ohio Republican, who wants documents relating to requests for financial data from federal law enforcement officials.</p> 
<p>“During the Biden-Harris Administration, the Department of Justice subpoenaed financial institutions … for financial records of private customer data in its politicized investigations into President Trump,” Jordan wrote in the letters obtained by POLITICO. “We write to request relevant materials in [your] possession.”</p> 
<p>Smith was appointed by then-President Joe Biden to investigate Trump’s retention of classified documents and efforts to subvert the results of the 2020 election — the latter of which has prompted renewed outrage among Republicans after revelations that Smith’s office requested GOP senators’ private phone data without their knowledge. Republicans see that move as an overreach and the investigation itself as a politicization of the Justice Department.</p> 
<p>Jordan was already conducting his own investigation into Smith’s work, including asking Smith to sit for a transcribed interview with his committee. Smith has countered he will answer lawmakers’ questions in a public forum, after he has the opportunity to view his records from the Justice Department. The two men have not yet reached an agreement.</p> 
<p>In the meantime, Jordan has just recently discovered that two years worth of his own phone records were also subpoenaed by the Biden DOJ — though the legal document showing the seizure was dated before Smith’s appointment in 2022.</p> 
<p>“The thing that got me was the length of time,” Jordan said in an interview Friday. “It's just creepy, and it's ridiculous … I want to know who signed off on it.”</p> 
<p>He said he had not yet decided if he would call Biden’s attorney general, Merrick Garland, to sit for an interview with his committee, too.</p> 
<p>"We do not share client account information with the government voluntarily — we were compelled to do so by law," said a spokesperson for JPMorgan Chase in a statement. "Responding to subpoenas is a legal obligation, not a choice or a sign of collusion."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson with Morgan Stanley did not immediately return a request for comment about Jordan’s Friday letter, while spokespeople for Bank for America and Citigroup declined to comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House votes to denounce ‘horrors’ of socialism ahead of Mamdani-Trump meeting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/house-denounces-horrors-of-socialism-00664412</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a724-d739-a3ba-fffca88b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 11:03:52 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House voted 285-98 to approve a resolution condemning the “horrors of socialism” Friday morning, just hours before President Donald Trump is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/mamdanis-meeting-with-trump-comes-with-a-power-disadvantage-00664265" target="_blank">set to meet</a> with New York’s incoming democratic socialist mayor Zohran Mamdani.</p> 
<p>Eighty-six Democrats joined with Republicans to approve the measure. Two others voted present. No Republican voted to oppose it.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson and House GOP leaders have decried Mamdani’s election as the next mayor of the country’s largest city, citing his far-left politics and arguing he is the new, radical face of the Democratic Party. They’ve vowed to make him a centerpiece of their attacks against Democrats ahead of the 2026 midterm elections.</p> 
<p>Democrats on Capitol Hill have dismissed the Republicans broadsides over Mamdani, and party leaders criticized the GOP-written measure ahead of Friday’s vote, saying it “selectively lists certain despotic leaders and the harms of totalitarian regimes self-labeled as ‘socialist.’”</p> 
<p>They did not, however, formally recommend a no vote. A swath of moderate Democrats, especially from New York, are uncomfortable with Mamdani’s rise in their party.</p> 
<p>The debate over the symbolic measure was derailed for about 10 minutes after Rep. Maria Salazar (R-Fla.) verbally attacked Rep. Maxine Waters (D-Calif.) on the floor, accusing her of being a “friend” of the late Cuban dictator Fidel Castro despite traveling to the country and seeing the abuses of his regime.</p> 
<p>Waters asked for Salazar’s words to be taken down, but Salazer instead withdrew her remarks, allowing the debate to continue.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warren Davidson slams Lindsey Graham over Senate data payout provision</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/davidson-slams-graham-over-data-payout-measure-00664369</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a6ef-df0f-abfa-e7efc8760000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 10:18:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Warren Davidson on Friday denounced Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.) for his plans to capitalize on a new measure that allows senators — but not House members or the general public — to sue the federal government for accessing their electronic data without proper notice.</p> 
<p>The provision, inserted by Senate Majority Leader John Thune in last week’s shutdown-ending continuing resolution, was written for senators targeted in former special counsel Jack Smith’s investigation into President Donald Trump’s efforts to overturn the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>“This Senator wants the Constitution to protect him (Senators), but no one else,” <a href="https://x.com/warrendavidson/status/1991820152032363006?s=46" target="_blank">Davidson (R-Ohio) wrote Friday morning on X</a>. “Literally no one other than a United States Senator could sue for damages. The House unanimously opposed this corrupt carve out for Senators. Protect every American citizen. End 3rd party doctrine.”</p> 
<p>Senate Judiciary Chair Chuck Grassley (R-Iowa) <a href="https://x.com/chuckgrassley/status/1975297712712262100" target="_blank">disclosed records in October</a> that Smith’s investigation obtained phone records of nine GOP members of Congress. The eight senators on the list would be eligible to sue under the current provision, but Rep. Mike Kelly (R-Pa.), the lone House member, is not.</p> 
<p>The House on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-votes-to-overturn-thunes-controversial-subpoena-measure-00661169" target="_blank">Wednesday voted 426-0 to reverse the provision language</a>, but it is unlikely to be taken up further in the Senate, where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/thune-phone-records-payout-jack-smith-00658393" target="_blank">Thune doesn’t appear bothered by</a> the discord within the GOP.</p> 
<p>Graham’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment. But the longtime South Carolina senator has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">proposed expanding the class of people given standing to sue</a> under the provision to “any private group” targeted by Smith over the course of his investigation.</p> 
<p>“All of us who were wronged need to have a remedy to that wrong,” he said in a speech at the Capitol on Thursday. “And we’re creating a chance to go to court for what happened to us in a fashion to make sure it never happens again.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Things are not normal on the Hill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/house-censure-votes-bacon-beyer-trump-threats-00664290</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a4af-d49b-af9f-b4ef9fd80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After a seven-week recess, Speaker Mike Johnson was optimistic about making progress on urgent priorities like government funding and rising health care costs. Instead, the House used hours of floor time to vote five times this week on measures rebuking other members.</p> 
<p>“The only thing we can apparently do is condemn each other,” says Rep. Mark Pocan (D-Wis.). “I’ve not seen the House hit this low of a point since I’ve been here.”</p> 
<p>Once a rare tactic, censures have become commonplace partly for their use as a political rallying cry and a fundraising boon. Concerned lawmakers are now scrambling to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/house-censure-death-spiral-00663655" target="_blank">stop the censure wars from escalating</a>.</p> 
<p>Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and Don Beyer (D-Va.) introduced bipartisan legislation Thursday that would require 60 percent of the House — rather than the current simple majority — to approve a censure of a member, disapprove their conduct or remove them from committee assignments.</p> 
<p>“The institution needs some protection,” Bacon said in an interview.</p> 
<p>House leaders seem open to curbing the personal brawling. Johnson called the general suggestion of a rule change “an intriguing idea” and said he’d be “open to having that conversation.” Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries also said he is “open-minded about what the possibilities are in terms of getting the Congress out of this repeated effort by Republicans to censure members.”</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump added fuel to the fire when he declared Thursday morning that six Democratic lawmakers are engaged in “<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOUR, punishable by DEATH!</a>” The Democrats — Sens. Elissa Slotkin (Mich.) and Mark Kelly (Ariz.) and Reps. Jason Crow (Colo.), Chrissy Houlahan (Pa.), Maggie Goodlander (N.H.) and Chris Deluzio (Pa.) — shared a video Tuesday encouraging U.S. military members to disobey unlawful orders.</p> 
<p>Johnson initially <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/mike-johnson-trump-sedition-00662754" target="_blank">defended Trump</a>, saying it was the Democrats who were acting “wildly inappropriate.” He later conceded “the words that the president chose are not the ones I would use.” Senate Majority Leader John Thune said of Trump’s suggestion of executions: “I don’t agree with that.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Russia sanctions action: </b>Some Republicans are prepared to introduce a discharge petition as soon as Friday to force a vote on stalled Russia sanctions legislation if House leaders don’t take action. Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) told POLITICO he huddled with Johnson on the House floor Wednesday night and that Johnson “shares the sense of urgency” but “doesn’t necessarily” agree with Thune’s assessment that the bill must start in the House.</p> 
<p><b>— Another discharge petition threat: </b>House Republicans interested in forcing a vote to ban congressional stock trading say they’re ready to kick off the process Friday if leaders continue to stall. Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) told POLITICO she’s first waiting to see whether House Administration Chair Bryan Steil (R-Wis.) will mark up and offer an amendment process Friday on a potential separate bill related to stock trading.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu, Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mourning Dick Cheney — and the US House</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/11/20/mourning-dick-cheney-and-the-us-house-00663709</link>
      <description>The former vice president’s funeral marked the end of a certain kind of Congress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a35e-d739-a3ba-fffe57c30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 19:04:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e9/16/9f4e81564e3e86874ad8a1499920/aptopix-cheney-funeral-44262.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Rep. Liz Cheney, R-Wyoming, walks past her fathers casket after speaking a tribute, during the funeral for former Vice President Dick Cheney, at the Washington National Cathedral, Thursday, Nov. 20, 2025 in Washington. (AP Photo/Matt Rourke)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e9/16/9f4e81564e3e86874ad8a1499920/aptopix-cheney-funeral-44262.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jonathan Martin</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jonathan Martin</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was just another Thursday in Washington.</p> 
<p>Donald Trump was threatening to <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/white-house/trump-democrats-death-penalty-sedition-military-orders-rcna245003" target="_blank">execute congressional Democrats</a>, House members were mounting <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/house-censure-death-spiral-00663655" target="_blank">gangland-style political reprisals</a> on one another and the following people sat next to each in the same pew at Washington’s National Cathedral to remember the life of Dick Cheney: Anthony Fauci, Rachel Maddow, Ken Mehlman and James Carville.</p> 
<p><br>The former vice-president, who died earlier this month after modern medicine and a new heart let him see his grandkids become adults, would have been appalled at Trump’s conduct, amused by his coalition of the willing (mourners) and depressed by what has become of the House, where he represented Wyoming for a decade.</p> 
<p>Cheney’s service was fittingly held the first full week his beloved House was back in session after a 54-day absence following the government shutdown. The dispiriting part is that after they reopened the government, lawmakers quickly turned on one another. Resolutions of disapproval and even expulsion were teed up, with the usual tribal, red-vs.-blue targeting of the other party — but also intra-party warfare between rival factions.</p> 
<p>It was enough to make the bipartisan vote on the release of the Jeffrey Epstein files look like a historic triumph of Article I power and legislative branch independence.</p> 
<p>Now a decade into the Trump era, it’s easy to focus on his aberrant and indefensible behavior. In fact, we should — it’s important to not be inured to how he acts. Calling a female reporter “piggy,” treating visiting autocrats like they’re former Canadian Prime Minister Brian Mulroney, and saying of the Federal Reserve chair: “I’d love to fire his ass.” Which was all before he went on social media to say “Hang Them” of those Democratic lawmakers who recorded a video urging military service members to refuse illegal orders.</p> 
<p>And that was all just this week.</p> 
<p>Yet what’s disheartening about the breakdown of the House is it illustrates that the political rot runs deeper than just one man. Yes, Trump sets the example and has modeled the worst behavior. But we know who he is. This year makes clear, however, that the institutional decay in Washington may outlast his presidency.</p> 
<p><br>Republicans have full control of the government, yet there have been more resolutions of disapproval or censure (three) voted on individual lawmakers than there have been votes on major bills (one). It has gotten so bad that a bipartisan duo is introducing legislation to raise the vote threshold to censure a member, to “raise the level of sanity in the House.”</p> 
<p>Yes, the lack of legislative activity is in part because House members wrapped many of their priorities in legislation formerly known as the “one big, beautiful bill.”</p> 
<p>But would any student of Congress really say this has been a productive year for the House? And could anyone tell you what their legislative priorities for the rest of this session have been since the BBB was signed in July?</p> 
<p><br>And then there’s that pesky Article I language, the power distributed to Congress by the Constitution. There’s not a single member of Congress who could argue with a straight face, at least in private, that they’re acting the part of a co-equal branch.</p> 
<p><br>Arriving for Cheney’s service, I encountered a former Republican congressional and White House aide, a conservative, dejected by Congress’s abdication of its authority. Had I seen, he asked, the clip of House Speaker Mike Johnson earlier this month in which the speaker says he’s “cheering for the president” to win the Supreme Court case challenging Trump’s power to levy tariffs without congressional approval? “I say that as a jealous guardian of the legislative branch of government,” Johnson added, irony unintended.</p> 
<p>Not far away was John Thune, the Senate GOP Leader and a House member himself at the turn of the century. “It’s a different era,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>“It’s a different era,” he said again, and without taking pleasure in the observation as he surveyed a sanctuary full of old guard Republicans and the Democrats doing their duty, whether out of obligation or respect for the Cheney family’s opposition to Trump after January 6.</p> 
<p>The audience reflected the end of Cheney’s career, and the eulogists spoke of Cheney the father, grandfather, boss and heart patient more than they did the controversial vice-president, 30-something presidential chief of staff or Desert Storm-era defense secretary.</p> 
<p>But there were reminders of the post that Cheney cherished so much, serving as Wyoming’s sole House member between 1979 and 1989.</p> 
<p><br>There were a handful of his colleagues from that era, including the few still left in Congress such as Nancy Pelosi and Steny Hoyer, as well as those who also ascended to higher office, like Al Gore and Dan Quayle.</p> 
<p>And the man who, had he won, would have been Cheney’s classmate in the House class of ’78 couldn’t help but stand in the pulpit and recall his own defeat that year.</p> 
<p>“The Republican wave didn’t reach West Texas that year,” said George W. Bush, recounting his only loss while generously noting that Cheney was undefeated.</p> 
<p>More telling, though, were the descriptions of Cheney’s mind and curiosity. Nobody dared say it outright in such a solemn setting, but I couldn’t help but think of what has been lost in today’s House. There’s not many Dick Cheneys walking through that door (at Cannon) and the few who are soon look to run for the Senate, governor or walk away entirely.</p> 
<p>Liz Cheney, his eldest daughter and the former congresswoman, recalled her father as a college dropout, working on power lines in Wyoming by day but reading Churchill’s history of World War II in a sleeping bag at night. She and her sister, Mary, would grudgingly go along with him as young girls as he took them to museums and battlefields, reading every word on every plaque to their consternation.</p> 
<p>And then in the winter of his life, as Liz recalled, she and her father went back to some of those same historic sites. And even as he declined, he would still come armed with that day’s newspapers, the latest issue of <i>The Economist</i> and a book.</p> 
<p>He was, Bush noted, “a serious man.”</p> 
<p>If only the same could be said for so many in today’s House.</p> 
<p>This isn’t to bask in blind nostalgia — those beneath the gravestones at Section 60 in Arlington and even more Iraqis should have their say in any full appraisal of Cheney’s career.</p> 
<p>Yet nobody would argue that the current Congress and particularly this House are worthy of a great country.</p> 
<p>There are still members who would’ve flourished in Cheney’s day, but even they are sober about the state of the institution.</p> 
<p><br>“This is one of those eras in which you read Kipling’s classic <a href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/46473/if---" target="_blank">poem</a>, ‘If—’ over and over and then get up and go to work every day,” Rep. Tom Cole (R-Okla.), the House Appropriations Chair, told me. “The aim isn’t to rebuild Rome in a day. It is just to make things a bit better every day.”</p> 
<p><br>Liz Cheney can’t because, unlike most all of her former GOP colleagues, she couldn’t and wouldn’t get over what Trump did on January 6 — and her state rejected her because of it three years ago.</p> 
<p>I thought Thursday about that 2022 primary and recalled what stood out to me about an interview I conducted with Liz shortly before her inevitable defeat that summer.</p> 
<p>She inveighed against Trump and the danger he posed, but she said something more about her party and the institution in which she then served.</p> 
<p>“What the country needs are serious people who are willing to engage in debates about policy,” Cheney told me then, wishing Americans would “vote for the serious candidate.”</p> 
<p>Then she went further.</p> 
<p><br>“I would much rather serve with Mikie Sherrill and Chrissy Houlahan and Elissa Slotkin than Marjorie Taylor Greene and Lauren Boebert,” she said, adding of her then-House Democratic colleagues with national security backgrounds: “They love this country, they do their homework and they’re people who are trying to do the right thing for the country.”</p> 
<p>Cheney’s father had just recorded an ad for her, calling Trump “a coward,” and she was thrilled to have him by her side in her final House campaign.</p> 
<p>“I talk to him every day,” she said. “He’s just a source of tremendous wisdom across the board, he’s such a student of American history.”</p> 
<p>I reminded her that he co-wrote a <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=691f9749a909714d3fa60d34&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoFwkEKgCAQAMAX6UpKSLfoEnTpC4uaCrqKGkKvj5kwRu0bwJyTY8avEDclwxXJd3bGlNhdpmvPm9gRkLyzbM-uRYMEtoJYtdKLVEL-2qQZEA%3D%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.amazon.com" target="_blank">book</a> with his wife, Lynne, on House greats — <i>Kings of the Hill</i> – and she laughed for one of the few times that day. “Well, my mother wrote that — a sore subject,” she joked.</p> 
<p>Would you have stayed in the House had your dad not so revered the body? I asked.</p> 
<p>She dodged the question but turned more serious, explaining she was “so glad” she stayed — even though her career was nearly over.</p> 
<p>“Having the opportunity to help make sure that we protect any future January 6ths, it’s the right thing to be doing,” Cheney said.</p> 
<p>Her father also left the House without becoming one of those <i>Kings of the Hill</i>.</p> 
<p>Had he not been appointed Defense Secretary under George H.W. Bush, the taciturn Wyomingite may well have become speaker. Cheney was House Minority Whip when he left Congress in 1989, the back-up plan for Bush after John Tower’s Pentagon nomination was rejected by the Senate.</p> 
<p>He was a man of the House and relished that his daughter, Liz, followed him there and was even happier when she declined to run for the Senate in 2020. She seemed in that moment poised to eventually claim the post that eluded her father once he left Congress.</p> 
<p>But five years later Liz Cheney was out of Congress, honoring her father’s fidelity to the Constitution over party and then, in a moment that spoke louder than words, stopping on her way down the aisle as his funeral ended to hug Pelosi.</p> 
<p>It was a poignant moment, the two mothers of five and daughters of House members who rose to the leadership as political opposites but bonded when duty called.</p> 
<p>Former Rep. Richard B. Cheney (R-Wyo.) would’ve liked it.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The House is scrambling to avoid a censure death spiral</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/house-censure-death-spiral-00663655</link>
      <description>In their first full week back after the shutdown, lawmakers voted five times on measures to rebuke colleagues, eating up hours of floor time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a344-d49b-af9f-b7e45d090000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 17:03:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/87/62/d6a902ed4833b3966ab117f38b10/u-s-congress-38283.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“Most of us know this isn’t good for the institution," Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) said about the escalating tit-for-tat.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/87/62/d6a902ed4833b3966ab117f38b10/u-s-congress-38283.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As he reconvened the House this month after a seven-week recess, Speaker Mike Johnson promised to recommit lawmakers to making laws — adding session days and keeping them voting into the night to catch up on lost time.</p> 
<p>His members instead spent much of their first full week back after the shutdown sniping at each other and using the House floor to carry out attacks on colleagues. Lawmakers voted five times on measures to rebuke other members, eating up hours of floor time.</p> 
<p>The spasms of personal pique crossed party lines, with Democrats targeting Democrats and Republicans targeting Republicans in some cases. It left at least a few lawmakers fuming about the depths of the House’s dysfunction and looking for ways to address it.</p> 
<p>“The only thing we can apparently do is condemn each other,” said Rep. Mark Pocan (D-Wis.), slamming the legislative agenda. “I’ve not seen the House hit this low of a point since I’ve been here.”</p> 
<p>An effort by a fellow Democrat to rebuke Rep. Jesus “Chuy” Garcia (D-Ill.) over his apparent scheme to install his top aide as his successor <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/house-rebukes-garcia-00657309" target="_blank">succeeded Tuesday</a>. A Republican effort targeting Del. Stacey Plaskett (D-V.I.) over her communications with the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-escapes-censure-vote-epstein-texts-00658334" target="_blank">narrowly failed</a>, as did a GOP-led effort to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-punts-mills-censure-attempt-to-the-ethics-committee-00661242" target="_blank">censure Rep. Cory Mills</a>(R-Fla.) over various alleged ethical misdeeds.</p> 
<p>The Plaskett and Mills measures failed in part because of a small but vocal group of lawmakers determined to put a stop to the tit-for-tat floor antics before they spiraled into something even more disruptive.</p> 
<p>Two of them — Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and Don Beyer (D-Va.) — introduced legislation Thursday that would change House rules to make it harder for members to target colleagues, warning that the chamber is at risk of devolving into an irreparable cycle of caustic personal brawling.</p> 
<p>“The institution needs some protection,” Bacon said in an interview.</p> 
<p>The Bacon-Beyer proposal would require 60 percent of the House to approve the censure of a lawmaker, disapprove of their conduct or remove them from their committee assignments — up from the current simple majority threshold.</p> 
<p>“The censure process in the House is broken — all of us know it,” the two wrote in a letter to colleagues, saying the back-and-forth battles “impair our ability to work together for the American people, pull our focus away from problems besetting the country, and inflict lasting damage on this institution.”</p> 
<p>Johnson called the general suggestion of rules changes “an intriguing idea” this week. He made no commitments to act but said he’d be “open to having that conversation.”</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries also told reporters he was “open-minded about what the possibilities are in terms of getting the Congress out of this repeated effort by Republicans to censure members.”</p> 
<p>In addition to the five votes on Garcia, Plaskett and Mills, House leaders also worked to try and fend off an effort to censure or expel Rep. Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick (D-Fla.), who was indicted Wednesday on federal fraud charges. She has called the indictment an “unjust, baseless sham.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Greg Steube (R-Fla.), who publicly teased the effort to sideline his indicted colleague, said in an interview Thursday that he would hold off until the House Ethics Committee releases its report on Cherfilus-McCormick.</p> 
<p>That’s at least a nod to how things used to be done in the House, where members were given a chance to make their case in court or to an effective jury of their peers on the Ethics panel before being subjected to public discipline.</p> 
<p>Steube said he was ready to follow a more recent precedent: the House’s 2023 ouster of then-Rep. George Santos over claims of fraud and campaign finance irregularities.</p> 
<p>Efforts to punish the New York Republican erupted soon after revelations of his checkered personal history emerged following his 2022 election. But it was only following the release of a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/11/16/santos-ethics-reports-finds-substantial-evidence-of-criminal-wrongdoing-00127527" target="_blank">scathing Ethics report</a> that members acted overwhelmingly to expel him.</p> 
<p>“If [Cherfilus-McCormick] does not resign by the time the Ethics Committee releases its report detailing their investigation, then I’ll move forward," Steube said.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers now expect that report to be released in a matter of weeks, according to two people granted anonymity to describe internal House conversations.</p> 
<p>Extreme cases involving allegations of criminal conduct like Santos and Sherfilus-McCormick are not primarily what Bacon and Beyer are seeking to curtail.</p> 
<p>Instead, they are registering more concern about a recent spate of censures that have been doled out across party lines to lawmakers who have engaged in behavior that is crude, distasteful or simply objectionable to their political enemies.</p> 
<p>Rep. Paul Gosar (R-Ariz.), for instance, was censured in 2021 under a Democratic majority for posting an animated video depicting the murder of Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez (D-N.Y.). When Republicans retook the chamber, GOP members targeted Rep. Adam Schiff (D-Calif.) for his role in investigating President Donald Trump’s alleged connections to Russia and Rep. Rashida Tlaib (D-Mich.) for comments about Israel, among others.</p> 
<p>Once a rare and embarrassing rebuke, censure has <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-nightly/2025/09/19/how-censure-lost-its-bite-00574046" target="_blank">now become commonplace</a> — in no small part because it has become a political rallying cry and fundraising boon for the lawmakers who lead the disciplinary efforts as well as those they target.</p> 
<p>Without new protections, lawmakers fear the censure wars will continue to escalate.</p> 
<p>“It's an easy way for an individual member to elevate his or her profile, throw a rock at the other side and force your way onto the floor,” said one House Democrat granted anonymity to speak candidly about his colleagues’ motivations. “There doesn't appear to be any kind of mutually assured destruction kind of deterrence on this. So my guess is, it'll just keep going and going and going.“</p> 
<p>A handful of members have stood against that trend. Bacon was among six House Republicans who saved Plaskett from censure and removal from the House Intelligence Committee this week by voting no or present on the resolution targeting her.</p> 
<p>That sparked <a href="https://x.com/RepMTG/status/1991141316978155732" target="_blank">accusations from some colleagues</a> that they had struck a corrupt bargain to protect Mills. But Bacon said there were larger principles at stake and many more than six who wanted to avoid a doom spiral of retribution.</p> 
<p>Several Republicans told Bacon they “were voting yes but hoping I was a no,” he said. “Most of us know this isn’t good for the institution.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Thune offers to tweak controversial phone records language</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/john-thune-phone-records-tweak-00663527</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a313-d51c-a39e-af1bec840000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 16:27:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune offered Thursday to amend the controversial provision he slipped into last week's government funding package that could award GOP senators hundreds of thousands of dollars for having their phone records seized without their knowledge as part of an investigation into President Donald Trump's effort to overturn the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>Thune's proposal, presented on the Senate floor Thursday afternoon, would clarify that any payout to senators seeking damages would be directed back to the U.S. Treasury and would not personally enrich lawmakers. </p> 
<p>It comes less than 24 hours after the House voted unanimously to repeal the legislative language. It also follows a tense GOP lunch meeting Wednesday, where Thune got an earful from his own members upset they had no advance warning about the provision.</p> 
<p>Republicans discussed how to change the legislative language during the closed-door meeting and spent much of Thursday working to nail down the changes before Sen. Martin Heinrich (D-N.M.) came to the floor seeking unanimous consent to pass the House repeal measure.</p> 
<p>The provision passed last week would allow lawmakers to be personally awarded at least $500,000, which could have resulted in millions of dollars transferred to several GOP senators who were singled out by former special counsel Jack Smith's investigation into Trump's activities following the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>There was no agreement on the floor Thursday to move forward with Thune's proposed measure, which would not have changed the underlying statutory language. He instead offered a resolution that would have been binding only in the Senate and would not require House approval.</p> 
<p>Heinrich, the ranking member of the legislative branch appropriations subcommittee, objected to Thune's offer, saying the law itself needs to be changed and that both parties should keep talking about addressing the retroactivity of the provision.</p> 
<p>“Frankly, this is just outrageous to me,” said Heinrich. “This is at the exact same time as 22 million Americans could see their health insurance premiums skyrocket because Republicans refuse to extend the [Affordable Care Act] tax credits.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), who was among the lawmakers Smith subpoenaed, objected to Heinrich's unanimous consent request and made clear he wasn't interested in anything that would prevent him from filing a lawsuit.</p> 
<p>“What did we do to justify having Jack Smith issue a subpoena for the phone records of a branch of government — the Senate — where all of us had to decide whether or not to certify the election?” Graham asked on the Senate floor. “We’re not going to let the Democratic Party decide my fate. We’re going to let a judge decide my fate.”</p> 
<p>Graham also thanked Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, who negotiated the language with Thune. Schumer told reporters yesterday he supported a repeal.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-20T21:41:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Mike Johnson defends Trump's 'sedition' attacks on Democrats</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/mike-johnson-trump-sedition-00662754</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a24d-d49b-af9f-b6ed635f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 12:42:03 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson defended Donald Trump's declaration Thursday that <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">some congressional Democrats engaged in "sedition</a>" after the president suggested those Democrats should be executed Thursday.</p> 
<p>Johnson said it was the Democrats who were acting “wildly inappropriate” by suggesting that military members should disobey unlawful orders from Trump. By post "SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR, punishable by DEATH," according to Johnson, Trump was simply “defining the crime of sedition."</p> 
<p>"That is a factual statement," Johnson said, adding attorneys would have to "parse" the language in the criminal act.</p> 
<p>Trump had previously reposted another Truth Social user, who wrote, "HANG THEM GEORGE WASHINGTON WOULD!!"</p> 
<p>Johnson said he did not see the full scope of Trump's comments and reposts, but he joined in Trump's attacks on the six House and Senate Democrats who posted a video addressing military members.</p> 
<p>“For a senator like Mark Kelly or any member of the House or Senate to behave in that kind of talks is to me so just beyond the pale,” Johnson said, before telling reporters, “I’m not going to say anything more on it.”</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune pushed back on Trump's suggestion of executions, saying, "I don't agree with that." But he, too, criticized Democrats: "Obviously everybody has a First Amendment right [but] what they did was ill-advised and provocative and unnecessary."</p> 
<p>Later in the day — after White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt clarified that Trump did not actually want to execute members of Congress — Johnson softened his remarks, saying that “the words that the president chose are not the ones that I would use.”</p> 
<p>“Obviously, I don't think that ... these are crimes punishable by death or any of that," Johnson said. "But what the point [that] we need to emphasize here is that members of Congress in the Senate [and] House should not be telling troops to disobey orders. It is dangerous.”</p> 
<p>Speaking in a morning floor speech, Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer denounced Trump's comments, saying the president "is lighting a match in a country soaked with political gasoline."</p> 
<p>"Every senator, every representative, every American regardless of party should condemn this immediately and without qualification," he said. " Because if we don't draw a line here, there is no line left to draw."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-20T14:22:36-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump calls for Democratic lawmakers to face trial for ‘seditious behavior’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a1de-df0f-abfa-e1feb7990000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 10:42:12 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Thursday called for six Democratic lawmakers to face arrest and trial after they made a video encouraging U.S. service members and members of the intelligence community to refrain from following orders if they broke the law.</p> 
<p>“It’s called SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115582417825161974" target="_blank">Trump charged in a post on Truth Social</a>. “Each one of these traitors to our Country should be ARRESTED AND PUT ON TRIAL. Their words cannot be allowed to stand - We won’t have a Country anymore!!! An example MUST BE SET.”</p> 
<p>The president then reposted 16 Truth Social posts, <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@P78/115580255469225519" target="_blank">including one that advocated for hanging the Democrats</a>, like “GEORGE WASHINGTON WOULD.”</p> 
<p>“This is really bad, and Dangerous to our Country,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115582451169685243" target="_blank">he wrote later</a>. </p> 
<p>“SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR, punishable by DEATH!” he said in a separate post. </p> 
<p>Sens. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.) and Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), as well as Reps. Jason Crow (D-Colo.), Chrissy Houlahan (D-Pa.), Maggie Goodlander (D-N.H.) and Chris Deluzio (D-Pa.) were featured in the Tuesday video. They are all either military veterans or worked in national security-focused roles before taking office.</p> 
<p>“We know you are under enormous stress and pressure right now,” <a href="https://www.facebook.com/SenElissaSlotkin/videos/2558895077819811/" target="_blank">they said</a>. “Americans trust their military. But that trust is at risk. This administration is pitting our uniformed military and intelligence community professionals against American citizens. Like us, you all swore an oath to protect and defend this Constitution. Right now, the threats to our constitution aren’t just coming from abroad, but from right here at home. Our laws are clear, you can refuse illegal orders.”</p> 
<p>As part of a stated push to crack down on street crime and bolster deportations, Trump has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/30/national-guard-dc-deployment-extended-00629725" target="_blank">federalized National Guard troops in American cities</a>, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/02/trump-chicago-national-guard-00540357" target="_blank">Washington, Chicago</a> and Portland. Democratic officials have argued the president’s deployments constitute an illegal overreach of federal power and have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/06/lawsuits-national-guard-cities-trump-00595430" target="_blank">sued to stop them</a>.</p> 
<p>White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt in a Thursday briefing defended Trump's comments, saying the media had unfairly focused exclusively on his Truth Social posts, "but not what brought the president to responding in this way."</p> 
<p>But in a joint statement Thursday, House Democratic leadership condemned Trump’s “disgusting and dangerous death threats” and called for him to delete the posts, urging their Republican colleagues to say the same.</p> 
<p>The statement — co-signed by Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, Minority Whip Katherine Clark and Caucus Chair Pete Aguilar — said House leadership had been in contact with the House sergeant at arms and the United States Capitol Police to "ensure the safety" of the members mentioned in Trump's posts.</p> 
<p>“Donald Trump incited a violent attack on the Capitol on January 6th as part of a treacherous attempt to overturn the results of the 2020 presidential election,” they wrote. “The President’s violent and unhinged rhetoric against American patriots is consistent with his well-documented history of attacking prisoners of war, Gold Star families and war heroes. There is no bottom when it comes to Donald Trump.”</p> 
<p>The six Democrats later panned Trump's reaction, <a href="https://x.com/SenatorSlotkin/status/1991568438804763103" target="_blank">writing in a joint statement</a> that "no threat, intimidation, or call for violence" would deter them from defending the Constitution.</p> 
<p>“What’s most telling is that the President considers it punishable by death for us to restate the law," they said. "Our servicemembers should know that we have their backs as they fulfill their oath to the Constitution and obligation to follow only lawful orders. It is not only the right thing to do, but also our duty."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-20T11:54:32-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Indicted House Dem will step down from committee leadership position</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/jeffries-on-cherfilus-mccormick-00661418</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a1aa-d49b-af9f-b5eecd1e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 09:52:12 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Indicted Democratic Rep. Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick of Florida will step aside from her leadership position on a House Foreign Affairs subcommittee "while the matter is ongoing," House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries' office said Thursday morning.</p> 
<p>Democratic Caucus <a href="https://democrats.house.gov/imo/media/doc/democratic_caucus_rules_119th.pdf" target="_blank">rules require</a> indicted lawmakers to relinquish committee leadership slots. </p> 
<p>"Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick has proudly represented the people of Palm Beach and Broward Counties since 2022. Consistent with the United States Constitution, she is entitled to her day in court and the presumption of innocence," Jeffries spokesperson Christie Stephenson said in a statement. </p> 
<p>These are the first comments from the New York Democrats' team since news broke Wednesday night of the new allegations against the lawmaker. </p> 
<p>Cherfilus-McCormick has been charged with <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/florida-democrat-indicted-on-federal-fraud-charges-00661162" target="_blank">stealing federal disaster relief funds</a> and using the money to support her campaign for Congress, using straw donors to funnel FEMA funds to friends and having them contribute to her campaign, and conspiring to file a false tax return.</p> 
<p>In a statement Thursday, Cherfilus-McCormick called her indictment "an unjust, baseless, sham" and insisted "and I am innocent." </p> 
<p>She added, "The timing alone is curious and clearly meant to distract from far more pressing national issues. From day one, I have fully cooperated with every lawful request, and I will continue to do so until this matter is resolved."</p> 
<p>The Florida Democrat has also been the subject of an ethics investigation into campaign finance issues and requesting community project funding, known as earmarks, to a for-profit entity, potentially in violation of House rules. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Where health care talks stand</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/health-care-obamacare-extension-premium-hsa-00661368</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9fac-d739-a3ba-dffcba900000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate’s leaving Thursday for Thanksgiving recess without clear bipartisan agreement on how to address expiring Obamacare subsidies. But after a busy week of talks across the Capitol, we’re starting to get some clarity on what will or won’t pass muster in a year-end health care deal.</p> 
<p>Here’s what we’ve learned:</p> 
<p>— Sen. Bill Cassidy’s (R-La.) plan to redirect funds into health savings accounts isn’t going to fly with Democrats. Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer told reporters Wednesday his party only wants an extension of the Affordable Care Act credits that expire next month, and that “Cassidy’s proposal, as I understand it, replaces them.”</p> 
<p>“It’s privatizing health insurance, and it looks like it’s really problematic,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Health experts say Cassidy’s plan, which aligns with a proposal floated by President Donald Trump, also won’t necessarily do much to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/cassidys-obamacare-plan-will-not-lower-skyrocketing-premiums-democrats-and-policy-experts-say-00660894" target="_blank">offset looming premium spikes</a>. Those talking points could bolster Democrats’ opposition as they argue for a clean extension of the subsidies.</p> 
<p>— More Republicans are acknowledging it might be too late to enact major new health care policy before Dec. 31.</p> 
<p>“It’s a welcome discussion,” Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) told POLITICO. “But we’re not gonna get that done by Dec. 31.”</p> 
<p>When asked about the timeline on Wednesday, Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said there’s not enough time to make “major changes.”</p> 
<p>That could give a boost to Democrats who were promised a standalone vote on an ACA extension bill next month in exchange for reopening the government.</p> 
<p>But it could also embolden conservatives who are eager to ditch bipartisan talks and go their own way on a health care-focused, party-line reconciliation package, as White House deputy chief of staff James Blair teased Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Senate Budget Chair Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.) said Wednesday he plans to pursue a new budget reconciliation bill. However such a move would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">likely have to happen next year if at all</a>.</p> 
<p>— There’s one area of bipartisan promise on health care. Senate Finance Chair Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) and ranking member Ron Wyden (D-Ore.) say they’ll soon unveil a proposal to crack down on the health intermediaries known as pharmacy benefit managers — a longtime priority for the panel.</p> 
<p>Wyden told POLITICO he’s hopeful the Senate will advance a bill by the end of the year. When he chaired Senate Finance in 2023, the committee approved a PBM bill in a 26-0 vote.</p> 
<p>Committee Republicans are eager for the bill to hitch a ride on a must-pass legislative vehicle. One Senate aide involved in the negotiations tells POLITICO the package is likely to be in the mix in January as Congress approaches the next government funding deadline.</p> 
<p>Sen. Steve Daines (R-Mont.) told reporters Wednesday there could be a “window” to put it on the floor as a standalone measure.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p>— <b>More censures?</b> Look out for <a href="https://x.com/repgregsteube/status/1991317294870392922?s=46" target="_blank">whether there’s a move</a> to censure Rep. Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick (D-Fla.) after she was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/florida-democrat-indicted-on-federal-fraud-charges-00661162" target="_blank">indicted on federal fraud charges</a> Wednesday. This week has been heavy on censure efforts in the House, with Rep. Chuy García (D-Ill.) formally rebuked Tuesday and derailed attempts against Democratic Del. Stacey Plaskett of the Virgin Islands and GOP Rep. Cory Mills of Florida.</p> 
<p><b>— Next steps on permitting talks:</b> Key negotiators regard Thursday morning’s House Natural Resources Committee markup as an important step in reaching a comprehensive permitting reform deal this Congress. Chair Bruce Westerman’s (R-Ark.) bill would ease permitting reviews and limit legal challenges for projects under the National Environmental Policy Act, a bedrock environmental protection law many conservatives believe is mired in too much red tape.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA down to the wire:</b> The “Big Four” leaders of House and Senate Armed Services are racing to reach a compromise defense bill just a week before their self-imposed deadline. The lawmakers are hoping to drop the bill text the day they return from Thanksgiving break and are targeting an early December vote on the House and Senate floors.</p> 
<p><i>Robert King, Calen Razor, Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Josh Siegel and Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thune and Johnson suffer rare split over Epstein, Jack Smith fallout</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/thune-johnson-epstein-jack-smith-00660066</link>
      <description>The two men meet regularly and enjoy a good rapport, but the House speaker and Senate majority leader have found themselves caught up in intraparty drama.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9f35-d739-a3ba-dffd1fa10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5c/00/8438b9014c40aad978463feec8df/main-dumain-johnsonvthune-illustration.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Jade Cuevas/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.Dumain.JohnsonvThune.Illustration</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5c/00/8438b9014c40aad978463feec8df/main-dumain-johnsonvthune-illustration.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> have largely worked in lockstep since January. This week, they hit a rough patch.</p> 
<p>The two men are known for rising above whatever theatrics are embroiling their respective conferences. But in recent days they became enmeshed in just that, when they publicly split and shadowboxed over a pair of internal GOP dilemmas over politically toxic issues.</p> 
<p>The fissure emerged when Johnson trashed a measure that Thune tucked into last week’s <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_5371" target="_blank">government funding deal</a> to allow senators to sue the government and reap damages for electronic records seizures. With the Louisiana Republican calling the provision “a bad look,” the House on Wednesday unanimously passed a bill to repeal it in a major rebuke.</p> 
<p>Johnson suffered his own loss at the hands of Thune this week when the South Dakota Republican rebuffed the speaker’s calls to amend the House’s Jeffrey Epstein disclosure bill to include more protections for victims and whistleblowers. The Senate passed the bill by unanimous consent, after months of Johnson trying to slow it down in the House and ultimately succumbing to an end-run by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.).</p> 
<p>In an interview Wednesday, Thune downplayed the episodes, calling the phone records provision a “Senate issue” to work through and noting the congressional debate over the Epstein files “took on a life of its own” in the final stages.</p> 
<p>“We work very well together. Communicate regularly. There are always going to be hiccups along the way,” Thune said. “And I’ve served in the House. They are very different institutions and different cultures and ways of doing things but we make it work.”</p> 
<p>The split marked an unexpected round of turbulence for the mild-mannered GOP leaders, who meet weekly when both chambers are in session and are generally viewed as having a good working rapport.</p> 
<p>Now they face two huge challenges they will need to navigate together: Obamacare subsidies are set to expire at the end of next month, threatening health insurance premium hikes for millions of Americans, and the leaders face competing factions in both chambers when it comes to how to respond. In January, Thune and Johnson will once again have to rally their members around a bill to avoid another government shutdown. At stake in all the fights is how the GOP’s handling goes over with voters ahead of next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>The friction points reflect a well-worn dynamic of congressional life — the House and Senate operate at times in split-screen political realities despite Thune, Johnson and their conferences belonging to the same party.</p> 
<p>Thune, like most of the Senate, didn’t know Johnson before the low-key House member ascended to the speakership in the fall of 2023. But the two men developed a rapport before Thune took over as GOP leader in January. They are viewed as more aligned in their day-to-day operations and temperament than some of their predecessor pairings, including former Senate GOP leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51216" data-person-id="51216">Mitch McConnell</a> and the House’s former top Republican Kevin McCarthy.</p> 
<p>“They work well together. And they get along well,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151837" data-person-id="151837">John Hoeven</a> (R-N.D.), a close Thune ally, said of the two GOP leaders. “They not only have a professional relationship, they like each other.”</p> 
<p>Another Republican senator who knows Thune and Johnson said they had “worked very well together” so far, adding that some tension between the two chambers is “probably healthy.”</p> 
<p>“They’re very similar,” said the senator, who was granted anonymity to speak candidly about the leaders.</p> 
<p>That doesn’t change the fact that senior House Republicans, including some Johnson allies, are still smarting over the inclusion of the payout language for senators in last week’s funding package. It was designed to give special recourse to Senate Republicans who had their phone records seized during Jack Smith’s investigation into Trump’s 2020 election interference. House Republicans have said they didn’t learn about it until after the Senate passed the bill and it was the House’s turn to act on reopening the government.</p> 
<p>For an angry swath of House Republicans, the episode reinforced their long-standing anxieties about being jammed by the Senate and painted Johnson — who also said he didn't find out about the provision until after Senate passage — as embarrassingly out of the loop.</p> 
<p>Johnson quickly promised the House would vote on separate legislation to repeal it, and the House passed the rollback Wednesday night with zero opposition. Thune <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">also got an earful</a> from his own members during a closed-door lunch Wednesday, including from typical leadership allies like Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine).</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a> (R-Texas), a former Senate staffer, said Wednesday as he made the case for repealing the provision ahead of the vote that the House needed to “hip check” the Senate.</p> 
<p>Johnson, meanwhile, told reporters that Thune was “a trustworthy, honest broker, and that's why I was so surprised when we found out about that [phone records] provision.”</p> 
<p>Across the Capitol, Senate Republicans believe Johnson dropped a hot potato in their lap in the form of the bill to release the Epstein files. Johnson presided over bitter infighting for months over the bipartisan push to force a vote on the matter. By the time Johnson agreed to it, he was on the verge of being on the losing side of an open rebellion within his ranks and seemingly at odds with Trump, who suddenly urged Republicans to support it Sunday night.</p> 
<p>Johnson framed his pivot around a hope the Senate would alter the bill before clearing it for Trump’s signature.</p> 
<p>“I talked to John Thune over the weekend. I just texted him. We’re going to get together. We’ll talk about this,” Johnson told reporters as he left the House floor Tuesday following the 427-1 vote to release the files.</p> 
<p>But Senate Republicans, including members of leadership, never had an appetite for making changes. Many GOP senators privately made clear they didn’t want Thune to drag out the Epstein discussion as Johnson had, and Thune never publicly opened the door to amending the bill.</p> 
<p>Two people granted anonymity to discuss private party dynamics said that if Thune had bowed to Johnson’s push for changes, it would have risked keeping Republicans mired in the Epstein issue for weeks.</p> 
<p>"What was [Thune] supposed to do with a bill that passed the House 427-1 ... had no objections in the Senate and the president said he'd sign?" one of the people said.</p> 
<p>“That is House drama,” said another GOP senator granted anonymity to speak candidly about the situation. “We don’t need that over here.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House unanimously rebukes Thune on data seizure payouts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-votes-to-overturn-thunes-controversial-subpoena-measure-00661169</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9f00-d739-a3ba-dffc61f40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 21:03:46 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House unanimously voted 426-0 Wednesday night to <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6019" target="_blank">claw back language</a> in last week's government funding bill that could award some GOP senators hundreds of thousands of dollars in damages for having their phone records unknowingly obtained by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>The language, which was quietly slipped into the shutdown-ending package last week by Senate Majority Leader John Thune, drove bipartisan outrage in the House. Even outspoken critics of Smith — including House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio), who is leading an investigation into the Biden-era probe — supported the effort to repeal a politically toxic measure that was quickly branded as a taxpayer-funded windfall for a select few.</p> 
<p>“That policy, in my opinion — in the opinion I think of all the members of this institution — is unacceptable,” said House Administration Committee chair Bryan Steil (R-Wis.), during floor debate. “No one should be able to enrich themselves because the federal government wronged them, no elected official should be able to.”</p> 
<p>The provision would allow senators to sue the federal government for $500,000 or more if their electronic data was subpoenaed without proper notification. But there are concerns over the language’s retroactivity — which would extend protections to at least eight Republican senators whose records were obtained as part of Smith’s investigation into Donald Trump’s attempts to subvert the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>There are no guarantees the bill to repeal the language will get a vote in the Senate.</p> 
<p>The revelations that Smith obtained lawmakers’ private data has enraged Republican senators, who argue his probe amounted to a politicization of the Justice Department. But Smith’s subpoena was narrowly tailored for data around the Jan. 6 Capitol attack, and investigators did not receive the contents of their calls.</p> 
<p>Several GOP lawmakers whose phone data was subpoenaed have distanced themselves from the provision. But it may be too late. Thune hasn’t shown any interest in bringing the bill to the Senate floor, even amid the pushback from his members over his quiet decision to include it in the funding package.</p> 
<p>Thune told reporters Wednesday that additional conversations are necessary to reach a consensus about how to change the provision.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), who has indicated he intends to sue for a significant monetary reward, has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">proposed expanding who can sue</a> under the legislative language.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Ethics Committee establishes panel to investigate Cory Mills</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/ethics-investigates-mills-00660582</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9e3e-d51c-a39e-bf3ff0ef0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 17:37:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Ethics Committee launched a formal investigation Wednesday into myriad allegations against the embattled Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398811" data-person-id="398811">Cory Mills</a>, with the House poised to vote on whether to censure the Florida Republican later tonight.</p> 
<p>The bipartisan panel responsible for adjudicating accusations against House members has stood up an investigative subcommittee to review various allegations against Mills. It will be responsible for evaluating whether Mills broke House rules, laws or other standards in violating campaign finance rules; engaging in sexual misconduct or dating violence; or misusing his position or House resources; among other potential charges.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Mills did not immediately return a request for comment.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/06/cory-millis-threats-allegations-gop-00496518" target="_blank">Outside allegations against Mills</a> are numerous. He has been accused of stolen valor, benefiting from federal contracts while in office and assaulting a onetime girlfriend in his Washington apartment. That woman has since denied being assaulted, and Mills was never charged.</p> 
<p>More recently, another ex-girlfriend <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/05/gop-rep-mills-accused-of-threatening-to-release-nude-videos-of-ex-girlfriend-00495059" target="_blank">accused Mills of threatening</a> to release explicit videos of her. Last month, a judge in Florida <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/cory-mills-restraining-order-florida-00608307" target="_blank">granted the woman a restraining order</a> against the lawmaker.</p> 
<p>The announcement from the Ethics Committee Wednesday afternoon said members will also consider whether Mills “failed to properly disclose required information on statements required to be filed with the House;” “improperly solicited and/or received gifts, including in connection with privately sponsored officially-connected travel;” or “received special favors by virtue of his position.”</p> 
<p>The panel had already been looking at some allegations against Mills, after a referral from what was then the Office of Congressional Ethics. The nonpartisan watchdog found “substantial reason to believe” Mills may have violated campaign finance rules, benefited from federal contracts while in office, or misreported his financial information.</p> 
<p>The Ethics Committee's announcement comes on the same day that Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/282851" data-person-id="282851">Nancy Mace</a> (R-S.C.) introduced a resolution to censure Mills and strip him of his committee assignments. Republican leaders are expected to attempt to refer the matter to the Ethics Committee as a way of tabling the matter on the House floor, and the disclosure of the panel's investigative steps could help provide political cover to GOP conference members who might have otherwise felt pressure to formally admonish Mills.</p> 
<p>Still, the allegations against Mills have become a growing headache for House GOP leaders. Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, asked about the restraining order against Mills last month, replied: “I have not heard or looked into any of the details of that.”</p> 
<p>He added: “I’ve been a little busy. We have a House Ethics Committee. If it warrants that, I’m sure they’ll look into that.”</p> 
<p>Mills did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congress plots path for Russia sanctions bill with Trump's blessing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/congress-plots-path-forward-on-russia-sanctions-bill-with-trumps-blessing-00660067</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9de6-d51c-a39e-bdefeeca0005</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 15:56:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawmakers are quietly discussing how to quickly move new Russia sanctions legislation — this time with President Donald Trump’s blessing.</p> 
<p>“The president has now weighed in, in support of the Russia sanctions legislation,” Senate Majority Leader John Thune told reporters Wednesday, adding that he believed the House would need to make the first move in advancing the measure. However, House GOP leaders have long believed the Senate needs to act first.</p> 
<p>Members of the House and Senate are expected to talk Wednesday about advancing the long-stalled bill after Trump privately told top Republicans he supports it, according to Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.).</p> 
<p>Graham also told reporters Wednesday that the White House sent him a statement that very day about the bill, and that lawmakers involved in its drafting have signed off. The bill would impose tariffs on countries that import Russian energy and implement secondary sanctions on foreign firms that support Russian energy production.</p> 
<p>“It's moving,” Graham declared after a closed-door GOP conference lunch.</p> 
<p>Rep. Joe Wilson (R-S.C.), who is supporting a bipartisan companion bill of Graham’s in the House, said in an interview Wednesday he believes his chamber could quickly pass the sanctions bill if Trump gave his public blessing. Wilson predicted it would receive overwhelming support from Republicans and Democrats.</p> 
<p>He conceded that “15 percent” of members of the House GOP Conference “are isolationist” and will vote against Russia sanctions in any scenario. Despite potentially loud protests from that sliver of Republicans, however, Wilson predicted it wouldn’t be enough to tank the effort.</p> 
<p>But House leadership hasn't yet said if, or when, it will take up the Russia sanctions legislation, and Congress is quickly running out of time before the end of the year to take action.</p> 
<p>Thune, on Wednesday, pointed to a December agenda in the Senate already overloaded with appropriations, a defense policy bill, nominations and health care vote.</p> 
<p>Asked if he believed sanctions could pass this year, he said, “we’ll see.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mace moves to censure fellow Republican Mills</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/maces-goes-after-mills-00659722</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9d92-df0f-abfa-fdfaa3ce0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 14:29:06 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Nancy Mace is moving ahead with an effort to censure and strip a fellow Republican of his committee assignments in a rare intraparty escalation.</p> 
<p>The South Carolina Republican came to the House floor Wednesday afternoon to roll out a measure to formally rebuke Rep. Cory Mills (R-Fla.) over his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/06/cory-millis-threats-allegations-gop-00496518" target="_blank">alleged ethical violations</a> and to remove him from the Armed Services and Foreign Affairs committees.</p> 
<p>A vote is expected as soon as Wednesday night on the censure resolution. Republicans are expected to offer a motion to set the matter aside.</p> 
<p>It comes the day after Democrats threatened to force a vote on their own measure to censure Mills — if Republicans were successful in censuring Del. Stacey Plaskett. But Democrats stood down after Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-escapes-censure-vote-epstein-texts-00658334" target="_blank">fell short</a> in efforts to kick the Virgin Islands Democrat off the House Intelligence Committee following revelations she was texting the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a 2019 House Oversight Committee hearing. </p> 
<p>The series of events on the House floor sparked accusations from some Republicans that there was a backroom deal between the two parties to facilitate a detente. House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries demurred at a press conference Wednesday when asked if he’d cut such a deal, instead re-upping threats to bring forward more censure resolutions against Republicans as partisan tensions boil over across the chamber.</p> 
<p>“Democrats are not going to unilaterally disarm, and there's a long list of Republicans worthy of censure. Not enough time in the legislative calendar if Republicans want to go down this road of censuring members,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>Rep. Don Bacon of Nebraska, one of three House Republicans who voted with all Democrats against the Plaskett censure resolution, said some rank-and-file members tried “to talk me into” voting “yes” but that he “didn’t talk to leadership about the matter.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Speaker Mike Johnson didn’t immediately respond to an inquiry, nor did Mills.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bessent talks midterms ‘acid test,’ tariff rebates with House Republicans</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/bessent-talks-midterms-acid-test-tariff-rebates-with-house-republicans-00659480</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9d4b-d739-a3ba-ddff89be0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 13:06:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent chatted Wednesday with a group of House Republicans about how voters will judge the GOP’s tax and trade moves heading into the 2026 midterm elections, according to House Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259549" data-person-id="259549">Jodey Arrington</a>.</p> 
<p>During the private meeting Arrington hosted on Capitol Hill, Bessent discussed President Donald Trump’s economic policy strategy with Republican members of the budget panel, including steps to spurring economic growth and reducing the amount of red ink the federal government racks up each year as the national debt tops $38 trillion.</p> 
<p>The group discussed the “acid test of the midterms,” Arrington said, which is, “Am I doing better today than I did when we first elected this new unified Republican leadership in our nation’s capital?”</p> 
<p>When tax refunds roll in this spring, U.S. voters are going to “see historic refunds” that put “more money in their pockets” thanks to the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_1" target="_blank">GOP megabill</a> Trump signed into law in July, Arrington said. “And that was all part of the plan — of not just bringing prices down and growing the economy but making life more affordable for the American people.”</p> 
<p>The group also discussed Trump’s proposal to send $2,000 rebate checks to Americans by tapping into the hundreds of billions of dollars in new revenue generated by the president’s tariffs. Arrington is not a fan of the idea, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/republicans-in-congress-lukewarm-to-the-idea-of-tariff-rebate-checks-00650747" target="_blank">like many other Republican lawmakers</a>.</p> 
<p>“The best way to put money in people's pockets is to have good pro-growth policies, and to believe and trust that those policies will work to the end of more jobs and bigger paychecks,” Arrington told reporters after the meeting.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans put pressure on Johnson to advance congressional stock trading ban bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/gop-pressured-stock-trading-ban-00659452</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9d2e-d49b-af9f-bdee854e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 12:35:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two House Republicans vowed Wednesday to pressure Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and GOP leaders to advance a bill banning congressional stock trading in the coming weeks, not content to settle for a mere hearing on the topic.</p> 
<p>“A bill will come to the floor,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) said at a press conference outside the House Administration Committee hearing room, where academics were preparing to testify about the ins and outs of current stock trade ethics enforcement.</p> 
<p>“This is a fist fight, folks,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/306837" data-person-id="306837">Tim Burchett</a> (R-Tenn.) chimed in.</p> 
<p>The lawmakers, appearing alongside Democratic Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/239242" data-person-id="239242">Pramila Jayapal</a> of Washington and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/431425" data-person-id="431425">Seth Magaziner</a> of Rhode Island, have been pushing for Congress to crack down on member stock trading.</p> 
<p>They got a modest win with Johnson’s willingness to let a committee convene a hearing on the politically divisive topic. But they are now doubling down in their efforts to make sure the chamber also holds a markup and floor vote on actual legislation — either the compromise <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_5106?activeTabs=overview" target="_blank">bill requiring members to divest</a> from individual stocks, which the four lawmakers co-sponsored with a bipartisan coalition in September, or another version with similarly strong restrictions.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> (R-Fla.), who is also advocating for the bipartisan stock trading legislation, said in an interview Tuesday she plans to <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2025/11/19/gop-dreams-face-harsh-legislative-reality-00658617" target="_blank">unleash a discharge petition</a> to end-run Johnson and try to force a floor vote on if GOP leaders fail to notice a markup on a congressional stock trading ban bill by the end of Wednesday.</p> 
<p>But House GOP leaders are wary that a bipartisan bill or a similar measure will trigger blowback from a swath of Republicans, including some who say stock trading is an important source of income for themselves and their families.</p> 
<p>Burchett disagreed, saying that if the House votes to ban congressional stock trading, members who are currently skeptical of the idea of a ban behind the scenes are “going to be our biggest cheerleaders[s]” on the chamber floor.</p> 
<p>Political pressure to embrace a ban on stock trading, though, could run up against lawmakers who are protective of their activities in this space.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick also warned that members’ individual stock performance will be discussed in hearings on any stock trading bill.</p> 
<p>“Part of the fact finding is what members have done in terms of trading, sometimes on a daily basis,” Fitzpatrick said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plaskett remains defiant over Epstein communications</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/plaskett-remains-defiant-00659210</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9cd8-d51c-a39e-bdd9ca080000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 11:54:46 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Virgin Islands Del. Stacey Plaskett on Wednesday expressed no regret for her prior contact with convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a 2019 House Oversight Committee hearing.</p> 
<p>In an interview with CNN’s “The Situation Room,” the Democrat acknowledged that she initiated contact with the disgraced financier on the day she was set to question President Donald Trump’s former fixer Michael Cohen but refused to say if she regretted the communication.</p> 
<p>“I believe that Jeffrey Epstein had information, and I was going to get information to get at the truth,” Plaskett said. “I’m moving forward, and I think that that’s what we as American people should do.”</p> 
<p>Plaskett, who drew scrutiny recently following the release of documents from the Epstein estate that <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2025/11/14/epstein-text-messages-cohen-house-hearing/" target="_blank">revealed her texts with him</a>, argued that Epstein was a constituent and that “lots of people were texting me. Lots of people were giving me information.”</p> 
<p>“I’ve been a prosecutor for many years, and there are a lot of people who have information that are not your friends that you use to get information,” she added.</p> 
<p>Still, she admitted that she “probably” would not have asked Cohen about former Trump executive assistant Rhona Graff if Epstein had not mentioned it to her first in their texts.</p> 
<p>During the hearing, Cohen accused Trump of financial fraud, mentioning Graff in his testimony. Epstein appeared to flag the name to Plaskett.</p> 
<p>“Cohen brought up RONA - keeper of the secrets,” Epstein texted, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2025/11/14/epstein-text-messages-cohen-house-hearing/" target="_blank">according to The Washington Post</a>. The person believed to be Plaskett asked who — or what — RONA was, adding “Quick I’m up next is that an acronym.”</p> 
<p>Epstein replied “RONA” was actually Trump’s former assistant. Plaskett then questioned Cohen about Graff, who said she was “involved in a lot that went on.”</p> 
<p>Plaskett <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-escapes-censure-vote-epstein-texts-00658334" target="_blank">narrowly avoided a censure</a> in the House on Tuesday, with lawmakers voting 209-214 against formally reprimanding the delegate and removing her from the House Intelligence Committee.</p> 
<p>Both the House and Senate have officially passed legislation forcing the Justice Department to release more information about the federal case it built against Epstein. It now <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-clears-epstein-files-bill-00659041" target="_blank">heads to Trump’s desk</a> for his signature.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate sends Epstein files bill to Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-clears-epstein-files-bill-00659041</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9caf-d51c-a39e-bdaf93e30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 10:29:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate has officially passed legislation forcing the Justice Department to release more information about the case it built against the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>Senators had locked in an agreement to automatically pass the bill as soon as it was received from the House, which overwhelmingly passed it on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>It now heads to President Donald Trump’s desk, where he has said he will sign it. That comes despite the fact that Speaker Mike Johnson sought eleventh-hour changes to the House-passed bill and didn’t rule out the possibility he would encourage Trump to veto it.</p> 
<p>Assuming Trump follows through, the Justice Department will have 30 days to release the materials with redactions to protect Epstein’s victims.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-19T10:32:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Jordan refers former Jack Smith aide to Department of Justice</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/jim-jordan-jack-smith-investigation-00659037</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9ca2-d51c-a39e-bdab4cc80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 10:16:45 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) referred a top aide to former special counsel Jack Smith to the Justice Department for criminal prosecution over obstruction of a congressional investigation.</p> 
<p>Thomas Windom, who was senior assistant special counsel under Smith, sat for an interview with congressional investigators in June and a deposition in September.</p> 
<p>In a Wednesday letter to Attorney General Pam Bondi, Jordan wrote that Windom declined to answer questions by citing a lack of authorization from her department, along with other justifications. But the DOJ had authorized his testimony before he sat for an interview with congressional investigators, Jordan argued.</p> 
<p>“The Committee on the Judiciary writes to refer significant evidence that Thomas Windom, former Senior Assistant Special Counsel to Jack Smith, has, by his conduct during a deposition before the Committee, obstructed a congressional investigation,” Jordan <a href="https://judiciary.house.gov/sites/evo-subsites/republicans-judiciary.house.gov/files/evo-media-document/2025-11-19-jdj-to-doj-re-windom-referral.pdf" target="_blank">wrote in the letter</a>.</p> 
<p>This letter is part of a wide-ranging effort from Republicans across both chambers of Congress to target Smith and his office for their investigations into Donald Trump. Republicans have repeatedly argued that Smith’s work constituted a kind of politicization of federal law enforcement, even as Trump has broken with modern precedent by publicly calling on his attorney general to prosecute his political adversaries.</p> 
<p>In July, Jordan subpoenaed Windom to compel his cooperation after the voluntary transcribed interview. At the September deposition, Jordan recalled that Windom’s attorney cited “an unspecified First Amendment privilege, attorney-client privilege, a misguided belief that the Committee had no legitimate legislative purpose for the inquiry, and his Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination.”</p> 
<p>Jordan argued that Windom's justifications were unpersuasive.</p> 
<p>“We have received the letter from Chairman Jordan,” a DOJ spokesperson said in a statement. “Consistent with longstanding policy, the Department does not comment on active or potential investigations. We share the Chairman’s concerns and will continue to ensure that justice is applied fairly and equally to all Americans.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Windom referred to the transcript of his testimony, during which Windom's lawyer argued that Jordan’s probe was unserious and violated Windom’s First Amendment rights.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP dreams face harsh legislative reality</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/trump-gop-reconciliation-megabill-policy-agenda-unity-00658619</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9a96-d51c-a39e-bf9f0e3c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House’s hopes for big legislative wins in the coming months are about to crash into the reality of the congressional GOP.</p> 
<p>Deep divisions remain among Republicans over how to address spiking health care costs — and whether they should jam through a potential solution with a party-line vote in the Senate. And, of course, Democrats have little interest in helping them out.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, President Donald Trump’s willingness to go to war against Republicans <a href="https://politico.com/news/2025/11/19/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">isn’t helping party unity</a>.</p> 
<p>The GOP rift is playing out ahead of the end-of-year expiration of enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies. While vulnerable moderates want GOP leaders to extend the tax credits, Trump and some conservatives are calling for an entirely new framework, like an overhaul of health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>Trump’s top political aide, James Blair, on Tuesday raised the possibility of a megabill sequel — pursuing GOP health care priorities through the party-line reconciliation process, which lets Republicans skirt a Democratic filibuster. House Majority Leader Steve Scalise said Tuesday that Republican leaders are talking to members about the possibility to see if “consensus forms.”</p> 
<p>That pitch is being rejected by Republicans who remember how excruciating it was to pass the megabill this summer. They worry another attempt could undermine efforts to work across the aisle on matters like government funding.</p> 
<p>“I don’t want another one-sided, partisan reconciliation bill right now — I want us to legislate,” said Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska), who cast a decisive vote in the first package. “Let’s be legislators here. Reconciliation is, yes, it’s a tool for us, but it’s a partisan tool and look at how divided we are right now. … That’s not the way to go.”</p> 
<p>Any attempt at partisan legislation will be complicated by the fact that Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/donald-trump-epstein-vote-00654761?nid=0000018f-3124-de07-a98f-3be4d1400000&amp;nname=politico-toplines&amp;nrid=1a9f354b-c3a1-4374-8b80-6845d7848ff4" target="_blank">increasingly willing to break from Trump</a>. (Case in point: Georgia GOP Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene.)</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson, for his part, acknowledged a lesson that could be crucial for the president to grasp: Today’s enemy could be tomorrow’s indispensable ally.</p> 
<p>“I work on unity in the party, and my encouragement of everybody is to get together,” Johnson said. “We’ve got to do all that in order to deliver for the people.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House floor action:</b> The House is expected to vote Wednesday to repeal a provision in the shutdown-ending deal that could allow eight GOP senators to collect hundreds of thousands of dollars in compensation for having their electronic records seized during the Biden administration. And while there’s bipartisan support in both chambers to roll back the provision, Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who secured the language, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/thune-phone-records-payout-jack-smith-00658393" target="_blank">is standing by it</a>.</p> 
<p><b>— Notable Wednesday hearings:</b> Paragon Health Institute’s Brian Blase, one of the fiercest critics of extending the enhanced ACA subsidies, will testify at a 10 a.m. Senate Finance hearing on rising health care costs. There’s also a 10 a.m. House Administration hearing on congressional insider trading, which is happening as pressure builds for House GOP leadership to take up a bipartisan bill banning the practice.</p> 
<p><b>— What’s next for appropriations: </b>Talks are set to ramp up on the other nine spending bills that weren’t included in last week’s shutdown-ending minibus deal. House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) has meetings teed up Wednesday morning to huddle with his subcommittee chairs, then with all House Republican appropriators.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Hailey Fuchs and Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump’s Capitol Hill dreams are at odds with GOP reality</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591</link>
      <description>Passing major new Republican priorities would have been a tall order even before President Trump went to war inside his own party.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9a18-d49b-af9f-befccc410000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f8/2a/64b26cc6488f8ddbcc7cb7f8ceed/u-s-congress-39680.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Scalise and Johnson are laying the groundwork for a last big policy push.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f8/2a/64b26cc6488f8ddbcc7cb7f8ceed/u-s-congress-39680.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House’s dream of clinching major new Republican victories on Capitol Hill before the midterms is crashing into the reality of a bitterly divided Congress.</p> 
<p>Tackling major GOP priorities on the economy and health care was already going to be a heavy lift: There are deep divisions among Republicans about their strategy ahead of the end-of-year expiration of some Affordable Care Act subsidies, and President Donald Trump is showing little appetite to cut a deal with Democrats.</p> 
<p>Trump’s top political aide raised the possibility Tuesday of pursuing another go-it-alone bill, a sequel to the sweeping tax-focused megabill the GOP passed this summer, but going down that road would require building almost complete unity among congressional Republicans.</p> 
<p>And that would have been a tall order even before Trump went to war inside his own party this past week, effectively excommunicating longtime ally Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.) over her criticism of his policies, as well as her support for the release of Justice Department records related to the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>The rift comes amid other signs that Republicans in and out of Washington are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/donald-trump-epstein-vote-00654761" target="_blank">growing less willing to follow Trump’s lead</a>, whether on congressional redistricting or overhauling the Senate’s rules. And, with Trump already <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115570813586755288" target="_blank">sketching out red lines</a> on health care, skepticism is growing inside the GOP about burning months of political capital in an election year without a clear path forward.</p> 
<p>Asked this week about the ugly standoff between Greene and Trump, Speaker Mike Johnson acknowledged a fact of political life that Trump has often struggled to grasp: Today’s enemy could be tomorrow’s indispensable ally.</p> 
<p>“I work on unity in the party, and my encouragement of everybody is to get together,” Johnson said. “We've got to do all that in order to deliver for the people.”</p> 
<p>Johnson’s peacemaker stance comes as House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-gop-leaders-pitch-members-on-unaffordable-care-act-00656362" target="_blank">privately plot a health care overhaul</a>, with GOP leaders pitching their members on policy options during a closed-door conference meeting Tuesday. One slide shared by House Majority Leader Steve Scalise during the meeting knocked the expiring Obamacare subsidies, calling them part of the “Unaffordable Care Act.”</p> 
<p>Around the same time, White House deputy chief of staff James Blair <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/white-house-health-bill-tariffs-00655917" target="_blank">at a Bloomberg News event</a> sketched out a major “affordability” bill that could include $2,000 checks that Trump has pitched as tariff “dividends” as well as health care legislation along the lines of what House Republicans are discussing.</p> 
<p>Those ideas are not likely to get Democratic buy-in — especially with less than a year before the midterms. That means the GOP would have to explore party-line approaches to passing any policy agenda. But Senate Republicans have spurned Trump’s demands that they eliminate the filibuster that requires bipartisan buy-in for most legislation, leaving the convoluted reconciliation process, which was used to pass this summer’s megabill, as their only viable choice.</p> 
<p>Talk of another reconciliation bill has been hanging around Hill GOP circles for months, ever since House leaders dangled the promise of a second bite at party-line legislation to conservative hard-liners earlier this year in exchange for their votes to pass the “big, beautiful bill.”</p> 
<p>But <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/05/second-megabill-doubts-republicans-00545855" target="_blank">that push appeared to fizzle</a> earlier this fall. And just two weeks ago, during a meeting with Senate Republicans, Trump himself expressed skepticism about how much another reconciliation bill could accomplish. Some Republicans still want to try and revive the idea for the spring, but they are facing a hard sell with many members who remember the political trauma their party suffered amid attempts to repeal and replace Obamacare in 2017.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said in an interview that she did not want to pursue a GOP-only health care bill, arguing that it would undermine efforts to work with Democrats on other issues like funding the government </p> 
<p>“I don’t want another one-sided, partisan reconciliation bill right now — I want us to legislate,” Murkowski said. “Let’s be legislators here. Reconciliation is, yes, it’s a tool for us, but it’s a partisan tool and look at how divided we are right now. … That’s not the way to go.”</p> 
<p>Republicans have barely any room for error if they are going to launch another party-line policy bill. Murkowski, notably, was a decisive vote in getting the first GOP megabill through the Senate over the summer — after helping to sink the 2017 partisan health care bill.</p> 
<p>To get another reconciliation bill passed now, Republicans would need to lean on their most vulnerable members during a time in the election cycle when party leaders typically become shy about making their front-liners take politically tough votes that could negatively ricochet in swing districts.</p> 
<p>Retiring Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), who voted against the reconciliation bill in July, left the door open to pursuing a new party-line bill. But underscoring the headache waiting for GOP leaders and the administration, he floated using it to at least partially address some of what he called the “problematic” policies from the first Republican megabill.</p> 
<p>He also voiced a concern that has taken root with many of his House and GOP Senate colleagues — that if they are going to make a second run at reconciliation, they need to be unified at the outset about the nature of the end product rather than figuring it out along the way.</p> 
<p>“It could go sideways real quick if the scope changes much, so we’d have to have a lot of agreement up front to make sure it was going to be successful,” he said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Inside the closed-door conference meeting across the Capitol Tuesday morning, GOP leaders <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-gop-leaders-pitch-members-on-unaffordable-care-act-00656362" target="_blank">got pushback</a> to their ambitious health care agenda from Rep. Nathaniel Moran (R-Texas), who asked why they had waited until just weeks before the expiration deadline for the Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>House Republicans, Moran countered in the meeting, should have been working on alternatives months ago, according to four people granted anonymity to share the private exchange.</p> 
<p>GOP leadership aides and senior Republicans on Capitol Hill say they have been waiting for months for Trump to outline what he wants on health care. But the president only started weighing in publicly on policy options in recent days.</p> 
<p>The president on Tuesday warned that the only thing he would support would be a bill that sends “THE MONEY DIRECTLY BACK TO THE PEOPLE,” adding that Congress should “not waste your time and energy on anything else” and “GET IT DONE, NOW.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) added that Trump’s proposal — to essentially restructure the subsidies to give them directly to Americans — was a “welcome discussion … but we’re not going to get that done before Dec. 31. That’s unlikely.”</p> 
<p>Asked about Trump’s comments, Senate Majority Leader John Thune didn’t close the door Tuesday night to the chances lawmakers could reach a bipartisan health care deal, but he said that would be up to what Democrats would be willing to accept. They have been cool to the health savings account ideas favored by the GOP.</p> 
<p>“We’ve got members who are very interested in addressing the affordability of health care,” Thune added. “The question is, what’s the best way to do it.”</p> 
<p>Senate Budget Committee Republicans are keen to advance a budget resolution that would unlock the filibuster-skirting power of a second reconciliation bill, but they are tentatively looking at early next year to do that. And they are getting pushback from their colleagues behind the scenes.</p> 
<p>When Sen. John Kennedy of Louisiana pitched fellow Senate Republicans during a caucus lunch about using the fast-track procedure to pass a health care plan, a colleague pointed out that many of the GOP’s favorite policies wouldn’t comply with the strict rules governing the budget reconciliation process, according to an attendee who was granted anonymity to describe the private discussion.</p> 
<p>Kennedy acknowledged in an interview he can’t guarantee a bill will ever make it to the floor, but he suggested there was a pent-up feeling among some Republicans that Congress, despite being in GOP hands, has little to show for their majority.</p> 
<p>“That’s the problem — nothing’s happened. We’re not doing anything. I think some of that was reflected in the [off-year] elections” earlier this month, Kennedy said.</p> 
<p>“Everybody says, what about the One Big Beautiful Bill? That was yesterday — I mean what have we done since then?” he continued. “We haven’t done anything for months, and a lot of people — you are talking to one — are sick of it.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thune denies Johnson’s demand for Epstein bill changes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/johnson-thune-epstein-files-gop-00658475</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-99de-df0f-abfa-f9fef55a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 21:20:24 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said he voted for the Jeffrey Epstein disclosure bill Tuesday based on his hope that the Senate would make changes he’s been demanding. Senate Majority Leader John Thune shot that down.</p> 
<p>Thune said Tuesday evening that, while he had talked with the speaker about the bill, he and Senate GOP legal counsel decided the legislation was “sufficient.” The Senate effectively <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764" target="_blank">approved the legislation</a> by unanimous consent mere hours after House passage Tuesday afternoon without provisions sought by Johnson, including additional victim and whistleblower name protections.</p> 
<p>"I talked with the speaker a bit, and we've been in consultation obviously with the White House on this for some time,” Thune told reporters. “The conclusion was when it came out of the House 427-1 that, you know, it was going to pass in the Senate.”</p> 
<p>Thune’s refusal to amend the bill was just the latest setback Johnson has faced in the Epstein saga, where the Louisiana Republican saw a rank-and-file member of his own party, Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), pull off a stunning legislative end-run despite the speaker’s months-long opposition campaign.</p> 
<p>Johnson said after House passage Tuesday that he would “insist upon” changes.</p> 
<p>“I talked to John Thune over the weekend. I just texted him. We’re going to get together. We’ll talk about this,” Johnson told reporters as he left the floor. “There’s an easy way to amend the legislation to make sure that we don’t do permanent damage to the justice system. And I’m going to insist upon that.”</p> 
<p>Asked if he would press Trump to veto the bill if the Senate didn’t amend it, Johnson said he would “cross that bridge” if necessary. He also raised “national security” concerns about the bill Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Thune said Senate Republican lawyers examined the legislation and determined it could go forward without being amended.</p> 
<p>“Our lawyers obviously had looked closely at some of the issues and had concluded that the bill I think was, you know, sufficient to accomplish what needed to be done here, and that is to get the information out there as quickly as possible,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>Earlier this week, Johnson told reporters he had received “some comfort” from the Senate that the chamber would make the changes. But Thune never publicly indicated he expected the Senate to revise the bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/senate-pass-epstein-thune-00657429" target="_blank">and even warned earlier Tuesday</a> that changes were unlikely.</p> 
<p>The only short-lived whiff of resistance that appeared in the Senate Tuesday came from Sen. Markwayne Mullin (R-Okla.), who appeared to raise concerns at the last minute but did not block the effort.</p> 
<p>“We were trying to see if we needed to change language to protect the victims,” Mullin said to reporters.</p> 
<p>Shortly before Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer sought unanimous consent to greenlight the bill, Mullin said that there had been a “conversation” with the administration about what the Oklahoma Republican characterized as “technical changes,” which ultimately didn't get made.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plaskett narrowly escapes censure over her Epstein texts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-escapes-censure-vote-epstein-texts-00658334</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9993-d51c-a39e-bd9b8c1a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 21:11:09 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House voted 209-214 Tuesday night against formally reprimanding Del. Stacey Plaskett for communicating with the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a 2019 Oversight Committee hearing.</p> 
<p>Three House Republicans — Reps. Don Bacon of Nebraska, Lance Gooden of Texas and Dave Joyce of Ohio — voted with all Democrats against the measure. Three Republicans voted present: Reps. Andrew Garbarino of New York, Dan Meuser of Pennsylvania and Jay Obernolte of California.</p> 
<p>Plaskett drew scrutiny after documents released from the Epstein estate revealed her texts with him. She’s denied wrongdoing, saying on the House floor Tuesday that Epstein was a constituent, that her contact was limited to information-gathering and that it was not public information at the time that Epstein had been under federal investigation.</p> 
<p>“I know how to question individuals. I know how to seek information. I have sought information from confidential informants, from murderers, from other individuals because I want the truth,” she said on the House floor.</p> 
<p>Republicans contend Plaskett’s contact with Epstein was more substantive and shaped her questioning during the hearing, which Plaskett denies.</p> 
<p>“Standing against a convicted predator's influence in our proceedings is not partisan. It's basic decency,” said Rep. Ralph Norman (R-S.C.), who brought the measure to the House floor through a fast-track process bypassing committees and Hill leadership.</p> 
<p>But the measure rejected Tuesday by the House would have also removed Plaskett from the House Intelligence Committee, a step too far for some lawmakers. She would have been the latest House Democrats to be removed from a committee position by Hill Republicans after Republicans voted last Congress to remove Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) from the House Foreign Affairs Committee for her past comments on Israel.</p> 
<p>The failed vote to reprimand Plaskett comes on the same day the House voted almost unanimously to force the Department of Justice to release more files about its case against Epstein. The controversy has roiled Congress and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/mtg-speaks-on-epstein-00656279" target="_blank">split the MAGA base</a> for months.</p> 
<p>In retaliation for the move against Plaskett, Democrats introduced a measure to censure Rep. Cory Mills (R-Fla.) and to remove him from the House Armed Services Committee. He’s faced a spate of ethical issues including an since-withdrawn allegation of assault and an ongoing legal dispute over a previous relationship. But that measure is likely to be withdrawn now that the Plaskett effort has failed.</p> 
<p>The failure of the Plaskett measure prompted an outcry from conservative Republicans who had pushed for it, with some accusing leaders of cutting deals to avoid a vote on the Mills resolution. </p> 
<p>"They’re brokering back end deals to avoid bringing forward justice in both Democrat and Republican chambers," said Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.). "So it’s literally covering up public corruption."</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senators rage against phone data payout measure won by Thune</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/thune-phone-records-payout-jack-smith-00658393</link>
      <description>Senate Republicans are expected to debate the issue during their weekly lunch Wednesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-99b2-df0f-abfa-f9fa01b20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 20:20:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9a/ba/4fdf4fe6447cabc97f629bdde98f/u-s-congress-54663.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks with reporters outside his office at the U.S. Capitol on Nov. 10, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9a/ba/4fdf4fe6447cabc97f629bdde98f/u-s-congress-54663.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House plans to vote Wednesday to <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6019" target="_blank">repeal a provision</a> that could award eight GOP senators hundreds of thousands of dollars for having their phone records seized without their knowledge during a Biden-era probe. Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who secured the measure, is standing his ground.</p> 
<p>"The House is going to do what they are going to do with it,” he told reporters Tuesday night. “It doesn't apply to them.”</p> 
<p>But many senators from both parties are eager to roll back the legislative language they didn’t know <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/john-thune-government-funding-phone-records-seizure-00646094" target="_blank">Thune secretly negotiated</a>with Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer in the government funding package that ended the longest shutdown in history last week. Republicans could revolt if leadership doesn’t give them a vote to overturn it.</p> 
<p>In interviews Tuesday with nearly a dozen lawmakers, confusion, frustration and anger ran rampant about what has quickly become branded as a politically toxic, taxpayer-funded windfall for a select few. Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) went so far as to quip there could be “some stabbings” at the Senate GOP’s weekly lunch Wednesday when the topic will inevitably get discussed.</p> 
<p>“Whoever put this in had an obligation to tell us about it, and they didn’t,” said Kennedy. “There's something called trust and good faith around here.”</p> 
<p>Even Schumer conceded the widely unpopular language should ultimately be scrapped.</p> 
<p>“The bottom line is, Thune wanted the provision and we wanted to make sure that at least Democratic senators were protected from [Attorney General Pam] Bondi and others who might go after them,” he said Tuesday. “But I'd be for repealing all of it and I hope that happens,” he told reporters.</p> 
<p>It’s not clear whether it’s too late to reverse course in the Senate.</p> 
<p>The provision at issue, which President Donald Trump signed into law last week, would award senators $500,000 or more if they discover their electronic records were seized without notification.</p> 
<p>In seeking to attach it to the funding bill, Thune was directly responding to furor from several Senate Republicans eager for retribution against former special counsel Jack Smith, who obtained the phone records for at least eight Republican senators during his investigation into Trump’s efforts to overturn the results of the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>Thune in an interview acknowledged that members would indeed discuss the issue at lunch Wednesday but reiterated that he personally was not having second thoughts about including the measure in the funding deal.</p> 
<p>“It’s designed to protect United States senators,” Thune said. “We have a number of people who are interested in making sure that that sort of thing has a consequence if that kind of weaponization of the government along the lines of what Jack Smith did is ever employed again in the future.”</p> 
<p>Senate Commerce Chair Ted Cruz (R-Texas), who claims he was targeted by the Smith probe, praised Thune for including the language. Senate Budget Chair Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), who is confirmed to have had his records subpoenaed during the Smith investigation, has said he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/senate-republicans-phones-sue-jack-smith-00651463" target="_blank">plans to take advantage</a> of the provision to make it “so painful” for those involved.</p> 
<p>Some Senate Republicans admitted they hope the language is preserved. Sen. Eric Schmitt (R-Mo.) said he wanted the provision expanded to let a broader range of parties sue to show “how corrupt Jack Smith is.”</p> 
<p>It’s far from certain disgruntled lawmakers would make it easy for Thune to move a standalone bill to revoke the provision, even if he decides he wants to — they could insist on controversial amendments or make the voting process drawn-out and disruptive. Nor is it clear Republicans would allow the provision to be stripped in a subsequent government funding bill.</p> 
<p>There's far less hand-wringing in the House, where members were criticizing the language before they even voted on the Senate-passed funding bill last Thursday.</p> 
<p>The House Wednesday evening is expected to easily pass a bill to repeal the payout provision with support from Speaker Mike Johnson and House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan, who is working to get Smith to sit for a transcribed interview before his committee.</p> 
<p>In the Senate, several lawmakers signaled Tuesday night they were anxious to distance themselves from the new policy and wanted to follow the House’s lead.</p> 
<p>"I’m going to support repealing it,” said Sen. Markwayne Mullin (R-Okla.), the chair of the legislative branch appropriations subcommittee.</p> 
<p>He added he was not alerted about the language until after he already voted for the funding package last week and that he later received an “apologetic” call from GOP leadership over how the matter was handled. Thune confirmed that he had spoken to Mullin and that the Oklahoma Republican was not aware of the provision’s drafting.</p> 
<p>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine), chair of the Senate Appropriations Committee, said she was likewise in the dark in advance of the vote.</p> 
<p>“That was something that the leaders put into the bill, and I played no role in that whatsoever,” she told reporters.</p> 
<p>Democrats made clear they would continue to pummel Republicans if Thune failed to take action.</p> 
<p>Sen. Martin Heinrich (D-N.M.), the ranking member on the legislative branch appropriations subcommittee, said he was “furious” with leadership and has since introduced a bill to pare back the provision.</p> 
<p>Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.), another senior appropriator, said in an interview his party was “going to make every effort to try to reverse that pretty serious mistake.”</p> 
<p>“I guess there's an argument that it offers some future protection, but that's not what the provision is about,” he said. “The provision is about a cash payout to Republican senators, plain and simple.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
