<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 19:35:53 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Serious investigation or ‘clown show’? Clintons’ closed testimonies on Epstein leave room for disagreement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/27/clintons-depositions-epstein-trump-00805449</link>
      <description>Democrats say the depositions pave the way for slapping Trump with a subpoena. Republicans say they point to his exoneration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-a191-d2db-adfe-b3b956760000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 19:35:53 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5e/da/28f3cad84b3da16cc8f4466507a8/main-billclintondeposition.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Claudine Hellmuth/POLITICO (source images via AP and Department of Justice)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.BillClintonDeposition.jpg</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5e/da/28f3cad84b3da16cc8f4466507a8/main-billclintondeposition.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Maya Kaufman, Gelila Negesse and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Maya Kaufman, Gelila Negesse and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>CHAPPAQUA, New York — As House Republicans and Democrats embarked on two days of depositions with Bill and Hillary Clinton, both sides professed a seriousness of purpose to find answers that could aid their investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>They left with completely different versions of what transpired behind closed doors.</p> 
<p>Republicans said President Donald Trump was now "exonerated." Democrats said Trump was no such thing and called the event an “unserious clown show.” And amid dueling news conferences and social media posts throughout Thursday and Friday, the public is now left with starkly divergent narratives in a congressional probe that shows few signs of ending anytime soon.</p> 
<p>The split screen underscores the politically fraught nature of the House investigation, which is unfolding as the electorate clamors for <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/house-oversight-congress-epstein-accountability-results-00799731" target="_blank"><u>someone to be held accountable</u></a> for the years that the sex trafficking operation of Epstein and his co-conspirator, Ghislaine Maxwell, went unchecked.</p> 
<p>The House Oversight and Government Reform Committee spent hours grilling both Clintons — the former secretary of State on Thursday and the former president on Friday — about Epstein and Maxwell, in compliance with a pair of subpoenas issued by the panel as part of its long-running Epstein investigation.</p> 
<p>Republican and Democratic committee members took turns <a href="https://x.com/RepSuhas/status/2027475610084257809" target="_blank"><u>chiding</u></a> <a href="https://x.com/GOPoversight/status/2027476939879948672" target="_blank"><u>each other</u></a> for their characterizations of the Clintons’ testimonies, while also selectively leaking comments from inside the room to support their respective party lines.</p> 
<p>Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) said that Bill Clinton told the committee that Trump “never said anything to me to make me think he was involved” with Epstein and left Republicans confident there was no reason now to depose the president.</p> 
<p>“From all the evidence I’ve seen, he’s been exonerated for a long time,” Comer said of Trump during a news conference Friday.</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia of California, the top Democrat on the committee, said repeatedly the former president’s deposition Friday sets a precedent for Trump to testify under oath, and that Comer’s remarks were not an “accurate description” of Bill Clinton’s testimony.</p> 
<p>Democrats said Bill Clinton’s deposition raised additional questions about Trump and Epstein’s falling out. Trump has long said he kicked Epstein out of his club, Mar-a-Lago in Florida, years before Epstein’s 2019 arrest on sex trafficking charges, because he “stole people that worked for me,” while the White House has said Epstein was banned “for being a creep.”</p> 
<p>Neither of the Clintons have been accused of misconduct in connection with Epstein, nor has Trump.</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton has maintained he was an acquaintance of Epstein’s and traveled on his plane several times internationally, while Secret Service details were present, but stopped communicating with him at least a decade before his arrest in 2019 on federal sex trafficking charges.</p> 
<p>Behind closed doors, Bill Clinton testified that Trump told him he and Epstein had “great times together," according to a person in the room who was granted anonymity to describe the private deposition.</p> 
<p>Democratic Rep. Maxwell Frost said Bill Clinton testified that Trump told him the falling out with Epstein was over a land dispute.</p> 
<p>“He’s been caught in multiple lies as it relates to his relationship with Jeffrey Epstein,” Frost said, referring to Trump.</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton’s office did not immediately return a request for comment. The White House referred back to an earlier statement from press secretary Karoline Leavitt, who said, “the President has always remained consistent in that he kicked Jeffrey Epstein out of his club at Mar-a-Lago because frankly, Jeffrey Epstein was a creep.”</p> 
<p>The Republican-led committee is expected to release videos of the proceedings as soon as this weekend. Democrats on the committee requested full, unedited versions to be made public, with each side promising their version of events will then be vindicated.</p> 
<p>Republicans are under increasing public pressure to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/house-oversight-congress-epstein-accountability-results-00799731" target="_blank"><u>have something to show for their investigation</u></a> and are eager to find a win in the Clintons’ testimony.</p> 
<p>Comer said Friday his panel would call in additional witnesses as part of the ongoing probe, saying lawmakers had refrained from naming any of these individuals before the Clintons’ depositions. He suggested names could be announced before the depositions of the co-executors of Epstein’s estate, which will take place in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>"I didn't want to do anything that jeopardized losing them,” he told reporters Friday, referring to the Clintons.</p> 
<p>As lawmakers left the deposition site in Chappaqua, it also appeared likely the panel would soon subpoena Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick, who has faced calls to resign over revelations in the Justice Department’s materials about the extent of his relationship with Epstein. Rep Nancy Mace of South Carolina, a Republican on the Oversight panel, said she was on board.</p> 
<p>Lutnick recently acknowledged that he visited Epstein’s island in 2012 with his family, after he previously claimed their relationship ended before Epstein was convicted in 2008 of soliciting a prostitute. Lutnick has not been accused of wrongdoing in connection with Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>“We have a lot of questions about anyone who spent time with Epstein post-conviction,” Comer told reporters when asked about calling in Lutnick to testify.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Oversight chair: Bill Clinton punts question to committee on whether Trump should testify in Epstein probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/comer-bill-clinton-punts-on-whether-trump-should-testify-00804180</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-a0a8-d731-a3fd-eebd3df10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 14:58:29 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gelila Negesse and Maya Kaufman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gelila Negesse and Maya Kaufman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former President Bill Clinton told members of the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee that it’s “for you to decide” whether to call up current President Donald Trump to testify in the panel’s Jeffrey Epstein investigation, Chair James Comer told reporters Friday.</p> 
<p>“[He] went on to say that, ‘President Trump has never said anything to me to make me think he was involved and he met with Epstein,’” Comer, a Kentucky Republican, recalled Clinton telling the committee during his deposition.</p> 
<p>“I know there’s a lot of curiosity about President Trump,” Comer continued. “I thought that was an interesting thing that President Clinton said.”</p> 
<p>But Rep. Robert Garcia of California, the top Democrat on the Oversight Committee, said in a subsequent news conference during a break in the deposition proceedings that Comer’s remarks were not an “accurate description” of Clinton’s testimony.</p> 
<p>Garcia declined to share more details, accusing Republicans of breaking the rules with their disclosures about what was being discussed inside the room. But he reiterated that Trump should be subpoenaed in the panel’s Epstein probe.</p> 
<p>Rep. Maxwell Frost (D-Fla.) said that he now, in fact, had “new questions” about Trump’s alleged falling out with Epstein. Trump has said the two men fell out years before Epstein’s 2019 arrest and that he had no part in Epstein’s criminal activities. Trump also has not been charged with any crimes.</p> 
<p>Clinton has maintained he was an acquaintance of Epstein’s but stopped communicating with him at least a decade before the late financier’s arrest in 2019 on federal sex trafficking charges.</p> 
<p>Former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton, during her testimony before the committee Thursday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/youll-have-to-ask-my-husband-house-republicans-say-hillary-clinton-punted-questions-on-epstein-00802742" target="_blank">denied ever meeting Epstein</a> and said she had no knowledge of his or Ghislaine Maxwell’s crimes.</p> 
<p>Neither of the Clintons have been accused of wrongdoing.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FEMA taps billions for disasters, warning Democrats of ‘dire’ shutdown impact</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/disaster-aid-wanes-00804052</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-a033-d21a-af9e-b8371b930000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 13:56:27 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Thomas Frank and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Thomas Frank and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Trump administration spent more than half of the balance in the nation’s disaster relief fund this week, pointing to that dwindling aid as means to pressure Democrats into yielding in Department of Homeland Security funding negotiations.</p> 
<p>A FEMA spokesperson said Friday that the agency sent out more than $5 billion this week for recovery projects, including for disasters “that happened more than 15 years ago.” The withdrawal substantially shrinks cash in the disaster coffer that held $9.6 billion as of last week and appears to contradict Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem’s weekend announcement that FEMA “is scaling back to bare-minimum, life-saving operations only.”</p> 
<p>Accusing Democrats of “playing political games” with disaster aid amid the DHS shutdown, the FEMA spokesperson warned of “dire consequences” as the disaster relief fund “is being rapidly depleted.”</p> 
<p>It has been almost two weeks since DHS funding lapsed, and still top lawmakers and the White House are trading offers on policies to curtail the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement tactics, which Democrats are demanding as a condition of voting to fully restore agency operations.</p> 
<p>Republicans delivered a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/white-house-dhs-funding-offer-00803919" target="_blank">private counteroffer</a> late Thursday, 10 days after Democrats on Capitol Hill sent their last proposal. A White House official granted anonymity to discuss the closed-door negotiations also cited diminished disaster relief Friday, challenging Democrats to “make a move … before more Americans are harmed.”</p> 
<p>Some Democrats on Capitol Hill have offered plans to fund FEMA and other non-immigration agencies at DHS amid the negotiations over immigration enforcement policy. But top Republicans have rejected that idea.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bill Clinton says in opening statement he had ‘no idea’ about Epstein’s crimes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/bill-clintons-opening-statement-00803977</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-a01c-d21a-af9e-b81cd4a10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 12:25:15 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Maya Kaufman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Maya Kaufman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bill Clinton plans to testify that he did nothing wrong and had “no idea” about the crimes Jeffrey Epstein was committing — nor did he see anything that “ever gave me pause” — according to his prepared opening statement to the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee.</p> 
<p>“As someone who grew up in a home with domestic abuse, not only would I not have flown on his plane if I had any inkling of what he was doing — I would have turned him in myself and led the call for justice for his crimes, not sweetheart deals,” the former president said in his statement, which he <a href="https://x.com/BillClinton/status/2027424128559452573" target="_blank">posted on X</a>.</p> 
<p>The prepared remarks also lambasted the Republican-led committee for demanding testimony from his wife, former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton, who spent over six hours answering questions Thursday during her own deposition.</p> 
<p>She testified that she does not recall meeting Epstein and denied any knowledge of his sex trafficking offenses with longtime co-conspirator Ghislaine Maxwell.</p> 
<p>“Whether you subpoenaed 10 people or 10,000, including her was simply not right,” he said in the statement.</p> 
<p>In contrast to Hillary Clinton’s <a href="https://x.com/hillaryclinton/status/2027053057100693779?s=46" target="_blank">opening statement</a>, which referenced Epstein and Maxwell’s “criminal activities,” Bill Clinton’s statement makes no mention of Maxwell.</p> 
<p>The former president said he is in Chappaqua testifying in compliance with a congressional subpoena because “no person is above the law, even Presidents — especially Presidents.”</p> 
<p>He continued, “I hope that by being here today, we can bring ourselves a little further away from the brink and back to being a country where we can disagree with one another civilly–where the search for truth and justice outweighs the partisan urge to score points and create spectacle.”</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton has maintained he was an acquaintance of Epstein’s but stopped communicating with him at least a decade before the late financier’s arrest in 2019 on federal sex trafficking charges. Neither he nor Hillary Clinton has been accused of wrongdoing.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-27T15:21:45-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump administration delivers latest DHS funding offer</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/white-house-dhs-funding-offer-00803919</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-a013-d2db-adfe-b2bbca2a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 12:10:27 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Alex Gangitano</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Alex Gangitano</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House made a new Homeland Security funding proposal to congressional Democrats late Thursday as a partial shutdown of the sprawling department enters its third week.</p> 
<p>The two sides have struggled to make progress since the funding lapse began Feb. 14, with the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/shutdown-talks-make-little-progress-as-dhs-bill-stalls-in-senate-00796857" target="_blank">Senate failing Monday</a> to advance legislation that would restore the flow of cash to agencies dealing with matters ranging from immigration enforcement to airport security to cyber infrastructure.</p> 
<p>“Democrats need to make a move to end the shutdown before more Americans are harmed by a lack of funding for critical services like disaster relief,” a White House official said, describing the latest proposal as a “serious counter offer.”</p> 
<p>A joint statement from spokespeople for Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> and House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> said the two Democrats “received the White House’s counteroffer and are reviewing it closely." </p> 
<p>"Democrats remain committed to keep fighting for real reforms to rein in ICE and stop the violence,” the statement added.</p> 
<p>No congressional action is expected until the middle of next week at the earliest, with the Senate out of town until Monday and the House not voting until Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The White House official’s warning about disaster relief comes after President Donald Trump pointed to a recent snowstorm that clobbered parts of the Northeast in urging Democrats to end the partial shutdown during his State of the Union speech. FEMA officials said earlier this month that the main federal disaster fund “has sufficient balances to continue emergency response activities for the foreseeable future,” but expected new disbursements could drain it quickly.</p> 
<p>Democrats have vowed to block DHS funding until they get changes to Trump’s immigration enforcement tactics after federal agents killed two people in January in Minneapolis. Enforcement agencies like ICE and Border Patrol, however, have been largely unaffected by the shutdown due to funding put in place last year by the party-line GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Democrats haven’t yet weighed in on the latest White House offer. But Schumer said this week that Republicans have not meaningfully changed their position as talks have continued.</p> 
<p>“They're just trying to pass paper back and forth with no real changes,” he told reporters.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats say they have the votes to subpoena Lutnick in Epstein probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/dems-will-force-lutnick-subpoena-vote-00803881</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9ff7-d21a-af9e-9ff7fd850000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 11:45:21 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats on the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee have the votes to force Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick to testify before their panel about his relationship with convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) told reporters Friday.</p> 
<p>“I believe we will have the votes to subpoena him,” Khanna said outside a performing arts center in Chappaqua, New York, where Oversight members were poised to begin their deposition of former President Bill Clinton.</p> 
<p>Rep. Nancy Mace (R-S.C.) also said Friday that she would ask for Lutnick’s appearance before the panel as part of its Epstein investigation, after materials released by the Justice Department revealed the extent of the former Cantor Fitzgerald CEO’s relationship with the disgraced financier.</p> 
<p>Lutnick <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/howard-lutnick-trumps-dealmaker-tensions-00798716" target="_blank">recently acknowledged</a> that he took a trip to Epstein’s island in 2012 with his family, after he claimed that their relationship had ended after Epstein had been convicted of soliciting a prostitute. He has not been accused of wrongdoing in connection with Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>The Commerce Department did not immediately return a request for comment.</p> 
<p>It is the latest development in the Oversight Committee Democrats’ campaign to control the trajectory of the panel’s Epstein probe, even as they lack subpoena power as the minority party. The subpoena for the Justice Department’s Epstein files ultimately came from several Republicans joining with Democrats to support the measure.</p> 
<p>“We’re going to continue to, you know, ask questions of everyone … that shows up in photos on the island and things like that,” House Oversight Chair James Comer told reporters Friday in Chappaqua.</p> 
<p>The Kentucky Republican also suggested the public would be curious to hear what Hillary Clinton said about Lutnick.</p> 
<p>“I think it’ll be interesting what Hillary Clinton said about Howard Lutnick,” Comer said, before Mace interjected: “And how she said it.”</p> 
<p>Democrats are pushing for the unedited film footage of Thursday’s deposition with Hillary Clinton to be released quickly; Comer said he expected the video to be made public as soon as feasible. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bill Clinton takes his turn in House Oversight's hot seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/bill-clintons-turn-to-testify-00803870</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9fee-d731-a3fd-ffff315b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 11:31:54 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gelila Negesse and Maya Kaufman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gelila Negesse and Maya Kaufman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Members of the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee are gearing up to spend hours today grilling former President Bill Clinton about his relationship with the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein and longtime co-conspirator, Ghislaine Maxwell.</p> 
<p>It comes on the heels of former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton’s six-hour-plus deposition Thursday, in compliance with a subpoena issued by the panel as part of its long-running Epstein investigation.</p> 
<p>Committee Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) said they plan to highlight emails released by the Department of Justice about Epstein and Maxwell's involvement with the Clinton Global Initiative and the Clinton Foundation and photographs that show the former president with unidentified women.</p> 
<p>Comer was flanked by Republican Reps. Eric Burlison of Missouri, John McGuire of Virginia, Anna Paulina Luna of Florida, Glenn Grothman of Wisconsin, as well as South Carolina Reps. Nancy Mace and William Timmons.</p> 
<p>“No one's accusing anyone of any wrongdoing, but I think the American people have a lot of questions, and our House Oversight Committee is committed to getting answers,” Comer said during a news conference before the deposition, adding that Hillary Clinton at several points the day before punted questions to her husband.</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton has maintained he was an acquaintance of Epstein’s but stopped communicating with him at least a decade before the late financier’s arrest in 2019 on federal sex trafficking charges. His spokesperson Angel Ureña said on social media in 2019 that Bill Clinton traveled on Epstein’s plane four times internationally in 2002 and 2003, adding that Secret Service details were present “on every leg of the trip.”</p> 
<p>Hillary Clinton, during her testimony, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/youll-have-to-ask-my-husband-house-republicans-say-hillary-clinton-punted-questions-on-epstein-00802742" target="_blank">denied ever meeting Epstein</a> and said she had no knowledge of his or Maxwell’s crimes. Neither of the Clintons have been accused of wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>“I think it is fair to say that the vast majority of people who had contact with [Epstein] before his criminal pleas in ‘08 were like most people,” she told reporters Thursday. “They did not know what he was doing, and I think that that is exactly what my husband will testify to tomorrow.”</p> 
<p>Republicans at their Friday morning news conference said they were unconvinced, citing an email from Epstein saying the former secretary of State “looks better in person.” Mace claimed Hillary Clinton was “screaming” during the deposition.</p> 
<p>“She was unhinged, and I hope that President Clinton is less unhinged today than his wife was yesterday,” Mace told reporters.</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia of California, the top Democrat on the committee, called that an unfair characterization.</p> 
<p>Garcia and other Democratic members of the committee — Reps. Yassamin Ansari of Arizona, Wesley Bell of Missouri and Maxwell Frost of Florida, as well as Virginia Reps. Suhas Subramanyam and James Walkinshaw — each took turns speaking to the press before Bill Clinton’s deposition. They decried Republicans’ lines of questioning during Hillary Clinton’s testimony, saying it underscored the need for President Donald Trump to come before the committee, too.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), who helped lead the charge to force the Justice Department to release the Epstein files, said Friday that Bill Clinton’s historic deposition sets a new standard for Oversight investigations overriding the so-called Trump rule, referring to the current president’s defiance of a congressional subpoena of the committee investigating the Jan. 6, 2021 attacks on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>“Now we have the Clinton rule, which is: The presidents and their families have to testify when Congress issues a subpoena,” Khanna said. “And that means that Donald Trump needs to come before our committee and explain what he knew about Epstein and explain why we have not had a full release of the documents.”</p> 
<p>Trump has maintained he had a falling out with Epstein years before his 2019 arrest and had no part in Epstein’s criminal activities.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Democrats’ affordability agenda TBD</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/27/congress/democrats-affordability-midterm-agenda-plan-00803234</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9d1b-d21a-af9e-9d1fb9070000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Democrats are hoping to solidify their legislative agenda on affordability as midterm campaigning starts to heat up. So far, they don’t know what’s in it.</p> 
<p>But lawmakers have gathered in Leesburg, Virginia for their annual policy retreat these past few days to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/house-democrats-retreat-midterms-agenda-00802548" target="_blank">try and hammer out the details</a>.</p> 
<p>“We know it’s not enough to just lay out the issues and what the problems are,” House Minority Whip Katherine Clark (D-Mass.) told reporters. “Our goal is to have simple solutions that we can put out and lay out that vision — that if you give Democrats the gavels back, this is exactly what we’re going to do.”</p> 
<p>So far, that message has centered on reversing President Donald Trump’s policies. Rep. Suzan DelBene (D-Wash.), chair of House Democrats’ campaign arm, said undoing the administration’s aggressive new tariffs is one of the top priorities Democratic candidates should communicate this fall.</p> 
<p>Democrats also pledge to revive Obamacare health insurance subsidies that lapsed last year and reverse cuts to federal safety-net programs Republicans made in last year’s megabill.</p> 
<p>They’re less set, however, on what their platform should be beyond simply opposing the policies of the party in power. Outside of Trump-related rollbacks, Democrats are discussing evergreen proposals such as expanding the child tax credit and increasing the federal minimum wage.</p> 
<p>The New Democrat Coalition — the largest ideological group in the caucus composed of more centrist members — laid out an affordability agenda with more robust proposals, addressing matters like broadband connectivity and data center construction. The group is hoping it catches Democratic leaders’ attention, said Vice Chair Nikki Budzinski (D-Ill.) in an interview: “We want our agenda to be what comes top of mind for them.”</p> 
<p>In the Senate, having a specific affordability agenda could be especially critical for Democrats’ uphill battle to flip the chamber.</p> 
<p>“I feel very strongly that if Democrats do not put forward a positive affirmative message and vision of what we wanna do — what we will do when we’re in power, what our value proposition is to the American people — it’s hard to win elections,” Sen. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/podcasts/the-conversation" target="_blank">told POLITICO on “The Conversation</a>.” “I think that was part of why we lost in this last presidential.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we're watching: </i></b></p> 
<p>Former President Bill Clinton will sit Friday for a deposition on Jeffrey Epstein in front of House Oversight Committee members in Chappaqua, New York. It comes a day after former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/youll-have-to-ask-my-husband-house-republicans-say-hillary-clinton-punted-questions-on-epstein-00802742" target="_blank">testified for nearly six hours</a> in front of the panel and appeared to offer little new or relevant information for its investigation into the late convicted sex offender. </p> 
<p><i>Dasha Burns, Maya Kaufman, Gelila Negesse and Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘You'll have to ask my husband:’ House Republicans say Hillary Clinton punted questions on Epstein</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/youll-have-to-ask-my-husband-house-republicans-say-hillary-clinton-punted-questions-on-epstein-00802742</link>
      <description>The former secretary of State testified for roughly six hours, paving the way for Friday’s scheduled grilling of former President Bill Clinton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9c53-d0f8-adde-fe5bfe8b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 18:51:26 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/3e/5c/09aa4d284e27b7f9cd9d94520f0e/main-hillaryclintondeposition.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Claudine Hellmuth/POLITICO (source images via Getty and Department of Justice)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.HillaryClintonDeposition.jpg</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/3e/5c/09aa4d284e27b7f9cd9d94520f0e/main-hillaryclintondeposition.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Maya Kaufman, Gelila Negesse and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Maya Kaufman, Gelila Negesse and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>CHAPPAQUA, New York — Hillary Clinton appeared to offer little new or relevant information during her closed-door testimony Thursday for a House investigation into Jeffrey Epstein, according to Republicans who questioned her for hours — raising the stakes for them to pry revelations out of Bill Clinton when he sits for his deposition Friday.</p> 
<p>The former secretary of State testified for roughly six hours under oath, fielding questions from members of the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee about any involvement Epstein, the late financier and convicted sex offender, and longtime co-conspirator Ghislaine Maxwell, might have had with the Clinton Global Initiative.</p> 
<p>Hillary Clinton reiterated that she did not recall ever meeting Epstein and that she only knew Maxwell “casually as an acquaintance.” She denied knowing anything about Epstein and Maxwell’s sex trafficking offenses before the accusations went public. In fact, she repeatedly punted questions to her husband, the former president.</p> 
<p>“I don't know how many times I had to say I did not know Jeffrey Epstein. I never went to his island, I never went to his homes, I never went to his offices,” she told reporters after the deposition. “So it's on the record numerous times.”</p> 
<p>She also complained that Republicans’ questions were “repetitive,” noting how lawmakers frequently veered off topic — asking about UFOs and the <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/story/epstein-files-pizzagate?srsltid=AfmBOop0CgVZxPUNnRXZQ7uaUmwRPOHbIBdfDfR8pgSZ_bwF6BfZDd1t" target="_blank"><u>“Pizzagate” conspiracy theory </u></a>that circulated among some conservatives during the 2016 U.S. presidential election, when she was the Democratic nominee.</p> 
<p><b>“</b>They asked literally the same questions over and over again, which didn't seem to me to be very productive,” she said.</p> 
<p>Democratic lawmakers said that proves Republicans are engaged in a political fishing expedition — Rep. Yassamin Ansari (D-Ariz.) earlier in the day called the proceedings a “clown show” — but Republican members of the committee are using the nonresponses to tee up Bill Clinton’s forthcoming deposition Friday morning.</p> 
<p>“The number of times that she said, ‘I don't know, you'll have to ask my husband,’ was more than a dozen,” Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) told reporters after Hillary Clinton’s deposition concluded Thursday.</p> 
<p>Republican Rep. Scott Perry (R-Pa.) also told reporters that any specific questions about the Clinton Global Initiative and the relationship the Clintons might have had with Epstein and Maxwell, who is currently in prison, could only be answered by Bill Clinton.</p> 
<p>Neither of the Clintons have been accused of misconduct. Bill Clinton has maintained he was an acquaintance of Epstein’s but stopped communicating with him at least a decade before his arrest in 2019 on federal sex trafficking charges.</p> 
<p>His spokesperson Angel Ureña also posted on social media in 2019 that Bill Clinton traveled on Epstein’s plane four times internationally in 2002 and 2003, though Secret Service details were present “on every leg of the trip.”</p> 
<p>But Republicans are eager to make Bill Clinton <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/trump-world-takes-shots-at-favorite-boogeyman-bill-clinton-in-epstein-file-dump-00701780" target="_blank"><u>their bogeyman</u></a>, seizing on images of him posing with Epstein and unidentified women that are part of the files released by the Justice Department, either in response to the law passed by Congress or the subpoena issued in August by the Oversight Committee.</p> 
<p>GOP members of the Oversight panel are also facing increasing pressure to escalate their Epstein investigation, which so far has spurred no prosecutions in the U.S. — in stark contrast to all the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/epstein-europe-america-fallout-00769506" target="_blank"><u>heads rolling across the Atlantic</u></a>. The global fallout includes the recent arrests in Britain of Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, and ex-ambassador to the U.S. Peter Mandelson, not on allegations of sex crimes but rather on suspicions of misconduct in public office.</p> 
<p>The committee’s focus on the Clintons, however, is fueling accusations from Democrats that the GOP is deflecting from President Donald Trump’s own ties to the convicted sex offender — especially after <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/24/nx-s1-5723968/epstein-files-trump-accusation-maxwell" target="_blank"><u>news</u></a> <a href="https://sollenbergerrc.substack.com/p/fbi-interviewed-trump-accuser-epstein" target="_blank"><u>reports</u></a> this week found the DOJ may have withheld FBI case records of allegations that Trump allegedly sexually abused a minor.</p> 
<p>Trump has maintained he had a falling out with Epstein years before his 2019 arrest and had no part in Epstein’s criminal activities.</p> 
<p>Speaking to reporters multiple times during breaks in Hillary Clinton’s deposition, Comer stated that the president has already answered “hundred if not thousands of questions” about his relationship with Epstein.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/24/nx-s1-5723968/epstein-files-trump-accusation-maxwell" target="_blank"><u>told NPR</u></a> any files that were not published are privileged, duplicates or related to an ongoing investigation.</p> 
<p>Democrats remain unimpressed.</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia of California, the top Democrat on the House Oversight Committee, appeared to suggest Thursday that Democrats would attempt to subpoena Trump next year for information, should their party reclaim the House majority in the midterms.</p> 
<p>“This committee has now set a new precedent about talking to presidents and former presidents,” Garcia told reporters. “And we’re demanding immediately that we ask President Trump to testify in front of our committee and be deposed in front of oversight Republicans and Democrats.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Democrats assemble outside Washington in search of a midterm agenda</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/house-democrats-retreat-midterms-agenda-00802548</link>
      <description>“We can't be just anti-Trump,” said Rep. Debbie Dingell.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9c35-d0f8-adde-fe7f87b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 18:12:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d5/76/7580c35b47948082ceae33eefe74/u-s-congress-43576.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Top House Democrats are formulating a new campaign agenda, much as they did ahead of their 2006 and 2018 midterm sweeps.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d5/76/7580c35b47948082ceae33eefe74/u-s-congress-43576.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>LEESBURG, Virginia — House Democrats say they’re intent on putting a legislative agenda behind their <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/affordability-affordability-affordability-democrats-new-winning-formula-00637023" target="_blank">midterm affordability message</a>. They don't know yet what's going to be on it.</p> 
<p>But they have gathered at a resort outside Washington to spitball some options for putting specifics behind their pledge to address Americans’ rising costs of living, with sessions devoted to utilities, housing, groceries and the “care economy.”</p> 
<p>“We know it's not enough to just lay out the issues and what the problems are,” said House Minority Whip <a>Katherine Clark</a>. “Our goal is to have simple solutions that we can put out and lay out that vision, that if you give Democrats the gavels back, this is exactly what we're going to do.”</p> 
<p>A few Democratic evergreens have started to emerge as consensus proposals — such as expanding the child tax credit and increasing the federal minimum wage. But by and large, the policies that most unify Democrats are simply reversing what President Donald Trump and congressional Republicans have already done.</p> 
<p>That includes things like ending Trump’s global tariff campaign and reviving the Obamacare health insurance subsidies that lapsed this year amid Republican opposition, as well as reversing cuts to federal safety-net programs made in last year’s GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198811" data-person-id="198811">Suzan DelBene</a> (D-Wash.), chair of the House Democrats’ campaign arm, said reversing the Trump tariffs is the one of the top priorities Democrats should communicate as they seek election this fall.</p> 
<p>“He's raised prices on people all across the country without the authority to do so,” DelBene told reporters. “But it has had an incredible impact on families all across the country and they’re doubling down on it.”</p> 
<p>The effort to assemble a campaign agenda represents a reprise of prior efforts from a party out of power to put some specifics behind their election-year messaging. Republicans set the modern standard with their 1994 “Contract With America,” but Democrats did much the same 12 years later with their “<a href="https://www.cnn.com/2006/POLITICS/07/27/campaign.2006/" target="_blank">Six for ’06</a>” agenda and again in 2018 with “<a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2017/07/24/democrats-congress-economics-2018-240864" target="_blank">A Better Deal</a>.”</p> 
<p>In each of those cases, the insurgent party claimed dozens of seats and retook the majority.</p> 
<p>This time, Democrats could have a tougher path, thanks in part to the effects of partisan gerrymandering putting fewer seats in play. Many in the party are also dubious that focusing only on an unpopular president will be enough to guarantee midterm victory.</p> 
<p>“We can't be just anti-Trump. We have to have an agenda,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/152934" data-person-id="152934">Debbie Dingell</a> (D-Mich.), who described this week’s retreat as the place that “lets every Democrat have a voice in inputting what we will be rolling out this year.”</p> 
<p>The problem for Democrats is likely to be the sheer number of voices wanting input, as well as the diversity of policy prescriptions being proposed.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/411928" data-person-id="411928">Maxwell Frost</a> (D-Fla.), a co-chair of the Democratic Policy and Communications Committee, said that Democrats, should they win the majority, would aim to move a comprehensive housing package “that will help make safe, stable, affordable housing a fundamental American right for everyone.”</p> 
<p>But he said the details of that proposal are as yet undefined. Complicating the issue is that a bipartisan housing bill passed the House earlier this month and will get Senate consideration next week. Trump could sign a bill in the coming months, defusing the issue.</p> 
<p>“We don’t have specifics because it’s part of what this conference is for,” Frost said Thursday, pointing to the need to expand homeownership, lower rental costs and address a “crisis” in the homeowners insurance market.</p> 
<p>The New Democrat Coalition — a large group of free-market-oriented members — put forward one of the more robust packages of policy proposals seen at the retreat, addressing matters such as broadband connectivity and data center construction. The group’s leaders are hoping to develop their own agenda that battleground Democrats can campaign on.</p> 
<p>“Leadership is working through how they're narrowing their focus,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/413257" data-person-id="413257">Nikki Budzinski</a> (D-Ill.), a New Democrats vice chair, said in an interview. “We want our agenda to be what comes top of mind for them.”</p> 
<p>The Democratic Women’s Caucus highlighted the need to address costs facing American families, particularly those having to care for both their children and their aging parents — a message that former Vice President Kamala Harris put at the center of her 2024 presidential campaign with limited success.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/182891" data-person-id="182891">Suzanne Bonamici</a> (D-Ore.) said in an interview she was not worried that the message might fall flat again.</p> 
<p>“This is an issue that's affecting not just kids, not just families,” she said. “It's affecting businesses in the economy. So I'm not concerned that the message won't get through.”</p> 
<p>To be sure, the chances that any of the Democratic proposals would quickly become law are thin. Even if Democrats retake the House, Trump will still be president for another two years and the Senate could still be controlled by Republicans.</p> 
<p>But Democrats are mindful that the ideas they put forward now could get real momentum if their party wins the presidency in 2028.</p> 
<p>Back in Washington Thursday, Democratic senators joined in the effort with a Capitol Hill roundtable focused on spiking food costs.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers and leaders of advocacy groups who appeared at the event emphasized the need to enforce antitrust laws and maintain competitive markets.</p> 
<p>Basel Musharbash, managing attorney at the Antimonopoly Counsel, suggested Democrats push legislation to break up dominant firms in critical industries such as meatpacking, fertilizers and grocery sales, as well as to increase funding for antitrust enforcement agencies.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats demand fast turnaround of unedited transcript of Hillary Clinton’s deposition</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/dems-hillary-clinton-deposition-demands-00801922</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9ba7-d647-addc-bbe74ddf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 15:37:10 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Maya Kaufman and Gelila Negesse</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Maya Kaufman and Gelila Negesse</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic lawmakers involved in deposing Hillary Clinton as part of a House investigation into Jeffrey Epstein want the Republican majority to release a full, unedited transcript of the interview within 24 hours, citing the limited transparency of the closed-door proceeding.</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia of California, the top Democrat on the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee, made the demand during a news conference Thursday afternoon outside the Chappaqua Performing Arts Center, where the former secretary of State has been testifying for hours. Former President Bill Clinton will testify Friday.</p> 
<p>He was joined at the microphones by Democratic Rep. Yassamin Ansari of Arizona, Rep. Wesley Bell of Missouri and Reps. Suhas Subramanyam and James Walkinshaw, both of Virginia.</p> 
<p>The likelihood of the committee being able to publish the transcript that quickly is highly unlikely. The court reporter needs to send the transcript back to the panel after a few days, and Clinton's legal team must then review it before it can be published, said an Oversight aide who requested anonymity to describe private committee operations.</p> 
<p>But the committee Democrats said the transcript’s immediate release was warranted because Hillary Clinton’s request to testify publicly — instead of behind closed doors — was denied. Oversight Republicans told reporters earlier Thursday they plan to release a video of the proceedings as soon as it is approved.</p> 
<p>Garcia also said that Hillary Clinton has so far answered all questions and has not pleaded the Fifth Amendment — and offered no information that’s been helpful to the committee investigation.</p> 
<p>Hillary Clinton has repeatedly denied any knowledge of the criminal activities of Epstein and Ghislaine Maxwell, his convicted co-conspirator, and said she did not recall ever meeting Epstein.</p> 
<p>“We are sitting through an incredibly unserious clown show of a deposition where members of Congress and the Republican Party are more concerned about getting their photo opp of Secretary Clinton than actually getting to the truth and holding anyone accountable,” Ansari told reporters.</p> 
<p>“We have not learned one new thing,” Bell added.</p> 
<p><i>Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bernie Moreno eyes possible run for NRSC chair</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/bernie-moreno-nrsc-chair-00801431</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9b1a-d0f8-adde-fb5ad0470000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 13:20:59 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ohio Sen. Bernie Moreno is eyeing a bid to head the Senate GOP's campaign arm for the 2028 cycle, according to two Republican senators granted anonymity to disclose private conversations.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Moreno declined to comment on Moreno’s interest in leading the National Republican Senatorial Committee.</p> 
<p>While Moreno hasn’t officially thrown his hat into the ring, he has discussed the matter with colleagues, according to the two GOP senators. And his likely bid is already getting public support.</p> 
<p>“He's a machine. He is always working. He’s an incredible fundraiser,” said Sen. Jim Banks (R-Ind.) about why he would back Moreno for the role.</p> 
<p>Two other GOP senators predicted that the job is likely Moreno’s if he wants it, given that there normally isn't a contest for the top campaign spot. But it's possible he could have competition if he jumps in. </p> 
<p>During a recent lunch, a member of leadership made a quip about well-connected Sen. Pete Ricketts of Nebraska potentially leading the NRSC during the 2028 cycle, according to one of the senators.</p> 
<p>But Moreno would also bring a network of relationships to the role: He is well-liked within the Senate GOP Conference, is close with the White House and President Donald Trump, built a donor network in his pricey 2024 battle to unseat Democratic Sen. Sherrod Brown, and has been a prolific fundraiser for the NRSC, which is now chaired by South Carolina Sen. Tim Scott.</p> 
<p>Despite being not quite 14 months into his Senate career, Moreno has taken on prominent roles within the conference recently, including as one of the lead negotiators in recent health care talks. Moreno is viewed by his colleagues as ambitious and smart, with Majority Leader John Thune and other senior Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/bernie-moreno-obamacare-talks-00719585" target="_blank">praising him over the past year</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hillary Clinton accuses Oversight Republicans of ‘political theater’ in opening statement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/hillary-clintons-opening-statement-00800903</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9adc-d0f8-adde-fadec8370000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 11:54:33 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Maya Kaufman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Maya Kaufman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In her prepared opening statement to the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee Thursday, Hillary Clinton suggested the panel’s monthslong Jeffrey Epstein investigation is “partisan political theater” — not a quest for truth, transparency or accountability.</p> 
<p>The former secretary of State’s statement slams the committee for not asking President Donald Trump under oath about his appearances in the Epstein files or demanding testimony from Florida and New York prosecutors about Epstein’s infamous “<a href="https://www.miamiherald.com/news/local/article220097825.html" target="_blank">sweetheart deal</a>” in 2008 that allowed him to dodge federal sex trafficking charges and plead guilty to lesser state charges.</p> 
<p>“Instead, you have compelled me to testify, fully aware that I have no knowledge that would assist your investigation, in order to distract attention from President Trump’s actions and to cover them up despite legitimate calls for answers,” Clinton said, according to her opening statement to the Oversight panel, which she <a href="https://x.com/hillaryclinton/status/2027053057100693779?s=46" target="_blank">posted on X</a>.</p> 
<p>“This institutional failure is designed to protect one political party and one public official, rather than to seek truth and justice for the victims and survivors, as well as the public who also want to get to the bottom of this matter,” Clinton continued. “My heart breaks for the survivors. And I am furious on their behalf.”</p> 
<p>In a sworn declaration to the panel Jan. 13, Clinton denied any knowledge of the criminal activities of Epstein and Ghislaine Maxwell, his convicted co-conspirator, and said she did not recall ever meeting Epstein.</p> 
<p>Clinton is testifying Thursday behind closed doors in Chappaqua, New York, but Oversight Republicans told reporters they plan to release a video of the proceedings as soon as it is approved. Her husband, former President Bill Clinton, will testify Friday under the same circumstances.</p> 
<p>The Clintons are not accused of any wrongdoing and have denied knowledge of any sex offenses by Epstein and Maxwell, who is now serving a 20-year prison sentence. Bill Clinton has acknowledged flying on Epstein’s plane on several occasions but has said he never visited Epstein’s private island.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans not ruling out a subpoena for Lutnick in Epstein investigation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/panel-still-eying-lutnick-for-epstein-testimony-00800838</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9ad4-d3b5-addf-fad4903f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 11:45:16 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Oversight Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260072" data-person-id="260072">James Comer</a> is not ruling out slapping Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick with a subpoena to testify as part of the panel’s investigation into the convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“That’s very possible,” the Kentucky Republican told reporters Thursday morning as members of the committee headed inside a performing arts center in Chappaqua, New York, for daylong grilling of Hillary Clinton.</p> 
<p>The former secretary of State <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/house-oversight-congress-epstein-accountability-results-00799731" target="_blank">is testifying</a> about <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/hillary-clinton-deposition-terms-00800272" target="_blank">interactions she may have had with Epstein</a> or his associate Ghislaine Maxwell, who is now serving 20-years in prison for her part in the late financier’s sex trafficking scheme.</p> 
<p>“I think it’s a good possibility that his name will arise in some questioning today,” Comer added.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/282851" data-person-id="282851">Nancy Mace</a> (R-S.C.) said she also intended to ask Clinton about Lutnick.</p> 
<p>Lutnick <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/main-wh-lutnick-00774844" target="_blank">had maintained that his relationship with Epstein</a> ended in 2005, but newly released materials from the Justice Department revealed they continued to have ties following Epstein’s conviction on soliciting a minor for prostitution in 2008. The files also show that Lutnick and his family had lunch on Epstein’s private island in 2012.</p> 
<p>The Commerce secretary has not, however, been accused of wrongdoing in connection with Epstein’s crimes. The Commerce Department did not immediately return a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Comer also said Thursday morning his panel was “looking into” <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/24/nx-s1-5723968/epstein-files-trump-accusation-maxwell" target="_blank">reporting from NPR</a> that the Justice Department has sought to obscure information that could be damaging to President Donald Trump, including that he allegedly sexually assaulted a minor, as part of its release of the Epstein files in compliance with the law Congress passed in November.</p> 
<p>“We don’t know the answer to that,” Comer said when asked about the missing DOJ records around the allegation against Trump. “We know what the administration says. We’re still looking to get a definitive answer on that.”</p> 
<p>Trump has not been charged with any crimes in connection with Epstein and has maintained that the two had a falling out years before his 2019 arrest.</p> 
<p>Reached for comment Thursday, the White House referred questions to the Justice Department about the implementation of the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_4405?q=Epstein+Files+Transparency+Act" target="_blank">Epstein Files Transparency Act</a>, the law which compelled the administration to release materials in the Epstein case.</p> 
<p>The White House also pointed to an earlier DOJ press release around the rollout of the Epstein materials, which stated that the production “may include fake or falsely submitted images, documents or videos, as everything that was sent to the FBI by the public was included in the production that is responsive to the Act.”</p> 
<p>“Some of the documents contain untrue and sensationalist claims against President Trump that were submitted to the FBI right before the 2020 election,” the statement continued. “To be clear, the claims are unfounded and false, and if they have a shred of credibility, they certainly would have been weaponized against President Trump already.”</p> 
<p>A DOJ spokesperson also pointed to earlier statements insisting the department was reviewing materials flagged by the public and that no files had been deleted.</p> 
<p>“Should any document be found to have been improperly tagged in the review process and is responsive to the Act, the Department will of course publish it, consistent with the law,” <a href="https://x.com/DOJRR47/status/2026769082159112295?s=20" target="_blank">read one of the statements</a>.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department has accused Democrats of playing politics with the investigation, after Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/420280" data-person-id="420280">Robert Garcia</a> of California, the top Democrat on the Oversight panel, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/24/democrats-doj-epstein-files-trump-00795347" target="_blank">announced his team</a> had been looking into missing materials related to an allegation against Trump.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oversight Republicans tout bipartisan support for Hillary Clinton’s deposition</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/oversight-kicks-off-hillary-clinton-testimony-00800749</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9ac1-de8a-a1fc-fbc14a810000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 11:37:37 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gelila Negesse and Maya Kaufman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gelila Negesse and Maya Kaufman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican members of the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee emphasized the bipartisan demand for Hillary Clinton to share what she knows about Jeffrey Epstein and his longtime associate Ghislaine Maxwell, ahead of the former secretary of State’s closed-door deposition Thursday morning.</p> 
<p>Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260072" data-person-id="260072">James Comer</a> of Kentucky — flanked by Republican Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/356900" data-person-id="356900">Lauren Boebert</a> of Colorado, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192565" data-person-id="192565">Eric Burlison</a> of Missouri, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/300715" data-person-id="300715">Michael Cloud</a> of Texas, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/278925" data-person-id="278925">John McGuire</a> of Virginia and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> of Florida, alongside South Carolina Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/282851" data-person-id="282851">Nancy Mace</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/24817" data-person-id="24817">William Timmons</a> — told reporters in Chappaqua, New York, that they are focused on better understanding Epstein’s accumulation of wealth and social cachet.</p> 
<p>“This isn’t a partisan witch hunt,” said Comer. “This was a motion — a bipartisan motion, supported by the Democrats — to bring the Clintons in. So I don’t think it’s any type of being unfair in any way to the Clintons. They’ve never answered questions, unlike President Trump, who gets questioned every day by just about every one of you about his knowledge or involvement with Epstein.”</p> 
<p>Neither Hillary Clinton nor her husband — former President Bill Clinton, who will be deposed by the committee Friday — have been accused of any wrongdoing. They also have denied knowledge of any sex offenses by Epstein and Maxwell. </p> 
<p>Hillary Clinton, who has said she does not recall meeting Epstein, previously accused the Oversight panel of <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/czx47k34yqxo" target="_blank">trying to shift focus away</a> from President Donald Trump’s documented associations with Epstein. Bill Clinton has acknowledged flying on Epstein’s plane on several occasions but has said he never visited Epstein’s private island.</p> 
<p>Comer clarified that the panel is not accusing Hillary Clinton of wrongdoing but noted that emails released by the Department of Justice as part of its Epstein files disclosure showed that Epstein and Maxwell discussed support for the Clinton Foundation and Clinton Global Initiative.</p> 
<p>Democratic members of the Oversight panel, also addressing reporters Thursday morning, emphasized their interest in questioning anyone who appears to have close associations with Epstein but voiced concerns that their Republican colleagues are using the Clintons’ depositions for political gain.</p> 
<p>“Let’s get President Trump in front of our committee to answer the questions that are being asked across this country, from survivors, from those have been brutally attacked and raped — sometimes as children,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/420280" data-person-id="420280">Robert Garcia</a> of California, the panel’s top Democrat.</p> 
<p>He was joined by Democratic Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478829" data-person-id="478829">Yassamin Ansari</a> of Arizona and Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/80129" data-person-id="80129">Suhas Subramanyam</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/74912" data-person-id="74912">James Walkinshaw</a>, both of Virginia.</p> 
<p>Thursday's deposition marks one of the most high-profile moments to date in the committee’s Epstein probe, as lawmakers seek to demonstrate momentum in an investigation that has drawn intense public attention but has yet to produce criminal charges.</p> 
<p>For House Republicans, the testimony also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/house-oversight-congress-epstein-accountability-results-00799731" target="_blank">serves as a test</a> of how far the committee is willing — or able — to push an inquiry that has so far generated no prosecutions.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Oversight, Hillary Clinton agree on deposition terms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/hillary-clinton-deposition-terms-00800272</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9a76-d0f8-adde-fa7ee1fd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 10:04:04 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Maya Kaufman and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Maya Kaufman and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hillary Clinton’s testimony before members of the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee will focus on the federal government’s handling of the investigations into Jeffrey Epstein and his co-conspirator, Ghislaine Maxwell, as well as potential ethics violations by elected officials, according to a person granted anonymity to share details of the plans for the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/house-oversight-congress-epstein-accountability-results-00799731" target="_blank">closed-door deposition</a> in Chappaqua, New York.</p> 
<p>The former secretary of State will testify today, and her husband, former President Bill Clinton, will be deposed Friday.</p> 
<p>Among the terms for Hillary Clinton’s agreement to comply with a congressional subpoena and participate in the panel’s Epstein investigation, she will agree to engage in questions about Epstein and Maxwell’s efforts to exploit their connections to powerful figures — such as the Clintons — to protect themselves from accountability for their alleged sex trafficking crimes, the person said.</p> 
<p>The Oversight panel has also agreed to discuss the government’s mishandling of the Epstein case, which began in Florida long after Bill Clinton left office.</p> 
<p>Notably, the list of agreed-upon issues does not include unrelated topics that have long been a fixation among Republicans, such as Hillary Clinton’s handling of the 2012 Benghazi attack while she was secretary of State or her use of a private email server for official communications. She was dogged by both issues as she ran for president in 2016 against Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Neither Bill nor Hillary Clinton has been accused of wrongdoing in connection with Epstein. Hillary Clinton has maintained she has no memory of meeting Epstein, while Bill Clinton has admitted to using Epstein’s plane on several occasions but has maintained he never visited his island.</p> 
<p>Both have said they had no knowledge of his crimes.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP bets on immigration fight, not big bills</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/26/congress/trump-immigration-midterms-gop-legislation-agenda-00799871</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9850-d3b5-addf-f8d44c510000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republicans are betting that Donald Trump just handed them a political lifeline on immigration. But when it comes to demands for legislative action, the president’s big speech this week gave Congress little to do.</p> 
<p><b>— Reframing the immigration fight:&nbsp;</b>The National Republican Congressional Committee huddled Wednesday to strategize how to best capitalize on the State of the Union moment when Trump asked lawmakers to stand if they agree “the first duty of the American government is to protect American citizens, not illegal aliens,” according to one person granted anonymity to discuss a private meeting.</p> 
<p>How the party deploys to underscore Trump’s maneuver could be critical for GOP candidates. Many of them quickly amplified the clip — which showed Democrats seated and expressionless following Trump’s rhetorical gambit — on social media.</p> 
<p>Republicans are underwater in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/poll-americans-trump-voters-affordability-crisis-00674747" target="_blank">polling on the economy</a> and immigration — two issues they used to own. But the made-for-TV immigration moment has given the GOP <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/26/trump-sotu-republicans-immigration-campaigns-00799449" target="_blank">fresh political ammunition</a> ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p><b>— Reality on the Hill:&nbsp;</b>Trump’s speech will have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/trump-sotu-congress-agenda-00799454" target="_blank">little effect on the congressional agenda</a> over the coming months.</p> 
<p>That’s giving Republicans the freedom to focus on what they want. The Senate is expected to tee up a bipartisan housing bill at the end of this week. And Majority Leader John Thune hinted Wednesday that other legislation, like an energy permitting overhaul or a possible AI bill, could also be on the chamber’s to-do list for the rest of this Congress.</p> 
<p>But Republicans also acknowledge there’s little on Trump’s wish list they can easily accomplish heading into the midterms with such thin majorities.</p> 
<p>“I’ve got effectively a zero-vote margin at the point that we are now,” Speaker Mike Johnson said. “So I’ve got to have near-unanimity among Republican priorities.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Clintons’ deposition:</b> Around 19 members of the House Oversight Committee will be in Chappaqua, New York, to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/house-oversight-congress-epstein-accountability-results-00799731" target="_blank">interview Hillary Clinton Thursday (and Bill Clinton Friday)</a> under oath and behind closed doors. It’s the latest, and perhaps highest profile, set of depositions to take place in the panel’s ongoing investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>The former president and secretary of State, appearing in compliance with congressional subpoenas, have denied wrongdoing and aren’t implicated in any illegal acts. Hillary Clinton has said she has no memory of meeting Epstein at all.</p> 
<p><b>— Democratic retreat:</b> House Democrats are heading into Day Two of their annual retreat. Thursday’s agenda features breakout sessions on the cost of housing, groceries, utilities and the care economy, as Democrats try to sharpen their affordability messaging in their quest to flip control of the House in November. Speakers include historians Ron Chernow and Heather Cox Richardson and Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee Chair Suzan DelBene.</p> 
<p><i>Alec Hernandez, Dasha Burns, Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Clintons are in the hot seat — and lawmakers are hungry for Epstein-related prosecutions</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/house-oversight-congress-epstein-accountability-results-00799731</link>
      <description>They face questions about what, if anything, they knew about Jeffrey Epstein's illegal activities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9740-d0f8-adde-ff5a45a60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 19:06:06 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/16/ae/945daa7e4b39aa9bc830de9e9562/u-s-congress-14404.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Oversight Committee Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) walks to speak with reporters after former President Bill Clinton did not appear for a deposition on Capitol Hill Jan. 13, 2026. Behind him, an image of Clinton in drag is seen.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/16/ae/945daa7e4b39aa9bc830de9e9562/u-s-congress-14404.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House members are eyeing a new phase in their monthslong investigation into Jeffrey Epstein: A race to produce results that match the stunning Epstein fallout across the globe and satisfy an electorate clamoring for accountability.</p> 
<p>This week’s interviews of Bill and Hillary Clinton — who are scheduled to testify to lawmakers under subpoena and behind closed doors about their relationships with Epstein and his convicted co-conspirator, Ghislaine Maxwell — could be a pivotal moment in this effort.</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton has maintained that he was an acquaintance of Epstein’s but stopped communicating with him at least a decade before his arrest in 2019, and he has not been accused of wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>His spokesperson Angel Ureña posted on social media in 2019 that the former president traveled on Epstein’s plane four times internationally in 2002 and 2003, but that Secret Service details were present "on every leg of the trip." Hillary Clinton has said she has no memory of meeting Epstein at all. A spokesperson for the Clintons did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>But the Clintons’ depositions before the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee come as the recent arrests in Britain of Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, and ex-ambassador to the U.S. Peter Mandelson, have only intensified the pressure on Congress to produce similarly dramatic impacts closer to home.</p> 
<p>That means both Clintons will be put under a microscope for any potential transgression, whether it relates to the late financier’s sex trafficking conviction or not.</p> 
<p>“Obviously, the committee wants to see some people be held accountable,” said Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) in an interview in advance of the high-profile depositions. The former president will testify Friday, and the former secretary of state Thursday, both in Chappaqua, New York.</p> 
<p>Roughly 19 committee members are expected to be on hand for the depositions, and Comer said he suspected questions to focus on what interactions the couple had with Epstein — in the White House or elsewhere.</p> 
<p>“I think what you're seeing in Britain is, the charges against Prince Andrew and the former ambassador weren't sex-related crimes. They were more with respect to treason and selling secrets and things like that,” he explained. “We were just fascinated how Epstein was able to surround himself with so many high-profile government figures, not just in the United States, but in other countries, so I think there will be a lot of questions.”</p> 
<p>Linking Bill or Hillary Clinton to any type of criminal charge would be a win for Republicans, who are facing growing pressure to take down any powerful person with ties to Epstein — even as President Donald Trump’s own connections to the late convicted sex offender present persistent questions and ongoing political liability. That’s especially true as the Justice Department faces criticism for its haphazard release of the Epstein files, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/24/democrats-doj-epstein-files-trump-00795347" target="_blank">allegations from Democrats</a> that the administration is covering up for the commander-in-chief.</p> 
<p>“The DOJ hasn’t released all the files … terabytes of data, millions of files,” said GOP Rep. Nancy Mace of South Carolina, a member of the Oversight panel. “We need to bring in witnesses, people that will actually give us information and tell us the truth. Because so far, you know, people aren’t being honest.”</p> 
<p>Countless public figures and elected officials have communicated with Epstein over the years, and many of those communications are not criminal in nature — even if there has been a reckoning for some of those individuals. Larry Summers, for instance, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/larry-summers-resigns-harvard-epstein-00798100" target="_blank">announced Wednesday</a> he would resign from Harvard University, an institution he once led, as a result of his association with Epstein highlighted in the files.</p> 
<p>That means that delivering accountability is not so simple, and lawmakers are fighting an uphill battle to put anyone behind bars in connection with Epstein. Obstacles include a key witness who won’t cooperate — Epstein’s imprisoned <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/maxwell-pleads-the-fifth-00771258" target="_blank">co-conspirator Maxwell</a>, who has invoked the Fifth Amendment — and the fact that records might show investigative targets mingling with Epstein but not engaging in specific illegal acts.</p> 
<p>“Most of our big investigations have ended with criminal referrals,” Comer said. “This is a complicated investigation. A lot of the major players have died.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, even Democrats, who have cast themselves as the champions of transparency in the Epstein saga, now appear willing to go hard in their questioning of Bill Clinton after the caucus was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/9-democrats-vote-to-hold-bill-clinton-in-contempt-of-congress-for-evading-epstein-testimony-00739940" target="_blank">initially divided</a> over whether the former first couple should be held in contempt for failing to appear for previously scheduled depositions.</p> 
<p>“Our job is to, regardless of how powerful the person with knowledge of this abuse and trafficking ring is, to find out what they know, who else is implicated, what they've seen, what they participated in,” said Rep. Emily Randall (D-Wash.), a member of the Oversight Committee. “We definitely are there to ask questions that will help us uncover more information. Not to throw softballs.”</p> 
<p>At the same time, Democrats are cognizant that the GOP sees an easy target in Bill Clinton, who is featured in multiple images released by the DOJ. None of those photos indicate illicit or illegal activities, but Republicans and the White House <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/trump-world-takes-shots-at-favorite-boogeyman-bill-clinton-in-epstein-file-dump-00701780" target="_blank">have used them</a> anyway to elevate the former president as an alternative boogeyman to Trump, who remains Democrats’ main target.</p> 
<p>Trump has also not been charged with any wrongdoing in connection with Epstein and has maintained his innocence.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think anybody should be spared,” said Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.), a member of the House Judiciary Committee, in an interview earlier this week. “But [Republicans are] going to have a hard time just pinning it on Bill Clinton, I think, because there’s just too many others. … The minute they go to Bill Clinton, they gotta go to Trump as well, because there’s really significant stuff about Trump in there.”</p> 
<p>The House Oversight investigation dates back to July, when Democrats and a handful of Republicans in a subcommittee hearing <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/23/congress/house-panel-votes-to-subpoena-epstein-files-00472015" target="_blank">voted to subpoena</a> the Justice Department for all of the materials in its Epstein investigation.</p> 
<p>That vote launched a formal probe that led to other subpoenas for individuals in Epstein’s orbit, along with the release of documents and images from the Epstein estate, including the now-infamous “birthday book” where Trump allegedly wrote Epstein a message accompanied by a lewd drawing.</p> 
<p>Reps. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) and Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) forced a House vote in November to compel the DOJ to release its complete Epstein archive, and the department has since presided over a staggered document dump that has been criticized by members of both parties as misleading and incomplete.</p> 
<p>But while several high-profile individuals have suffered reputational blows from their associations with Epstein laid bare in newly public documents, no arrests have been made in the U.S. as a direct result.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers remain eager to show that their work has still been effective, and that hunger has led to some missteps. For one, Rep. Jasmine Crockett (D-Texas) <a href="https://x.com/LeeMZeldin/status/1990993148244312175" target="_blank">publicly accused</a> EPA administrator Lee Zeldin of taking campaign money from a Jeffrey Epstein — but the former Republican congressmember actually received the money from a physician with the same name.</p> 
<p>And Khanna read aloud a number of names on the House floor that of men who were initially redacted from the DOJ files — some of which <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2026/feb/13/four-men-unredacted-epstein-files-no-ties-ro-khanna" target="_blank">reportedly had no apparent connection to Epstein</a>.</p> 
<p>In an interview this week, Khanna said Congress’ work must culminate in prosecutions for those involved in Epstein’s scheme.</p> 
<p>“We need to look at what Britain's doing, what France is doing, what Norway is doing, and have those kind of prosecutions here,” he said.</p> 
<p>“I just want to see prosecutions,” Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) also said in an interview.</p> 
<p>After the Clintons are deposed Thursday and Friday, the committee has scheduled testimony from two co-executors of Epstein’s estate. Earlier this month, the panel heard from billionaire businessman Les Wexner, a onetime client of Epstein whose fortune helped fuel Epstein’s wealth. The former CEO of Victoria’s Secret insisted he severed ties with Epstein around the time that authorities were investigating sex crimes allegations against the late financier and accused Epstein of stealing from and lying to him.</p> 
<p>While some members of the panel are clamoring to subpoena more witnesses, Comer suggested his committee’s strategy could now shift as the midterms approach and the 119th Congress comes to a close. The panel, he said, could soon turn to new questions — including some that have been the subject of conspiracy theories.</p> 
<p>“Was Jeffrey Epstein a spy? Was he an agent?” Comer said. “Was he trading secrets with the U.S. government, the Israeli government — you know, the Middle Eastern government?”</p> 
<p>“I'm trying to make sure the committee understands we've got to really focus on a timeline here,” Comer said. “It took six months to get the Clintons in.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump doesn’t give Congress much to do before the midterms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/25/trump-sotu-congress-agenda-00799454</link>
      <description>Tuesday’s State of the Union address is unlikely to make more than a ripple in the congressional agenda.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-971e-de8a-a1fc-ff5e8eaa0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 19:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a3/52/5aacd89c46cc99c744ca6d86d182/unlimiteduse-02-24-2026-sotu-0051.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Kent for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I've got effectively a zero-vote margin at the point that we are now," Speaker Mike Johnson said Wednesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a3/52/5aacd89c46cc99c744ca6d86d182/unlimiteduse-02-24-2026-sotu-0051.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump sketched out his vision Tuesday night of Republican governance heading into the midterms. Congress is barely in the picture.</p> 
<p>From a legislative perspective, Trump’s State of the Union address was notable for what it didn’t include. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/trump-state-of-the-union-address-2026/trump-talks-tariffs-00797151" target="_blank">gave Republicans a pass</a> on trying to revive his global tariff campaign after a major Supreme Court setback. He didn’t demand another party-line domestic policy bill before November, and he even skipped a jab at one of his favorite punching bags, the Senate filibuster.</p> 
<p>Instead, Trump used the bulk of the speech to lean into red-meat issues like illegal immigration and gender-affirming health care, while encouraging lawmakers to tackle a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/02/25/trumps-sotu-demands-for-congress-00797413" target="_blank">few relatively minor topics</a> — many of which have already been churning behind the scenes for months.</p> 
<p>“He wasn’t really pushing us to do anything we don’t [already] want to do,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198816" data-person-id="198816">Kevin Cramer</a> (R-N.D.) said.</p> 
<p>The upshot is that Trump’s prime-time address is unlikely to make more than a ripple in the congressional agenda over the coming months. It’s the reality, Republicans acknowledged Wednesday, of life in Washington right now: Despite its trifecta, the party’s legislative ambitions are being hemmed in by its barely-there majorities.</p> 
<p>“I think we know what the agenda items are,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/194184" data-person-id="194184">Ryan Mackenzie</a> (R-Pa.) said. “Accomplishing those is going to be hard with a small majority.”</p> 
<p>GOP leaders on Capitol Hill are vowing to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/house-tariff-votes-republicans-affordability-00777567" target="_blank">focus on pocketbook issues</a> heading into the midterms, as they try to convince skeptical voters the party is responding to lingering economic angst.</p> 
<p>The Senate, for example, is expected to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/house-approves-housing-bill-setting-stage-for-tough-senate-negotiations-00772552" target="_blank">tee up a bipartisan housing bill</a> at the end of this week, and Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> hinted Wednesday that other measures, such as an energy permitting overhaul, could be on the chamber’s to-do list for the rest of this Congress.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/40/8f/2a4f480c48a0ad467ec65706ac4d/u-s-congress-29605.jpg" alt="Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks alongside Sens. John Barrasso (R-Wyo.) and James Lankford (R-Okla.) during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol, on Feb. 25, 2026." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26056732029605" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks alongside Sens. John Barrasso (R-Wyo.) and James Lankford (R-Okla.) during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol, on Feb. 25, 2026."/><p>But Trump showed only passing concern about lawmakers’ anxieties Tuesday, sending the message that the economy was on the rebound — asserting that prices were falling just fine and that last year’s GOP megabill did quite enough to address any voter concerns.</p> 
<p>He mentioned “affordability” only to engage in a blame game — accusing Democrats of embracing that word “knowing full well that they caused and created the increased prices that all of our citizens had to endure.”</p> 
<p>Instead, Trump pressed lawmakers to “codify” a drug pricing plan his administration negotiated with some pharmaceutical manufacturers and rolled out a retirement savings program that largely builds on a bipartisan law signed by his predecessor, Joe Biden. He also weighed in on the housing proposal, urging members to limit home purchases by institutional investors.</p> 
<p>Those matters have already been percolating on Capitol Hill, with internal divisions among Republicans creating major obstacles in some cases.</p> 
<p>“On our side, obviously, they’re not unanimous,” Thune said about the housing and drug proposals. “There are a lot of these things that are not just that clear cut.”</p> 
<p>The situation in the House is even more tenuous. While the thin GOP majority there was able to eke through a partisan elections bill Trump highlighted Tuesday, they have had a harder time building support for another bill that earned a presidential endorsement: a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/trump-state-of-the-union-address-2026/trump-backs-congress-stock-trading-ban-00797162" target="_blank">ban on lawmaker stock-trading</a>.</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, while not ruling anything out, acknowledged his “small margin” will affect what items on Trump’s wishlist, if any, ultimately make it to the president’s desk. Republicans can currently lose just one vote on party-line matters, and one GOP lawmaker, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/338556" data-person-id="338556">Tony Gonzales</a> of Texas, is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/tony-gonzales-affair-allegations-00793653" target="_blank">facing pressure to resign</a> amid allegations of an affair with a subordinate who died by suicide.</p> 
<p>“I've got effectively a zero-vote margin at the point that we are now, so I've got to have near-unanimity among Republican priorities,” Johnson said. “I would like to say we could do some bipartisan things, but it'll be up to the Democrats.”</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189728" data-person-id="189728">Mike Haridopolos</a> (R-Fla.) characterized the House GOP as a “micromajority” Wednesday and questioned whether one of its members — Kentucky Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a>, who frequently breaks with Trump — even still <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2026/02/17/thomas-massie-epstein-files-trump-bondi-interview-00781625" target="_blank">qualified as a Republican</a>: “I don't know what party he belongs to, but it's not ours.”</p> 
<p>Trump did use his bully pulpit Tuesday to urge Senate Republicans to act on the House-passed elections bill, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499" target="_blank">SAVE America Act</a>, that would place new restrictions on the ability to vote. That included an apparent appeal to Thune, who was in the House chamber for the speech.</p> 
<p>But Trump didn’t push to skirt the 60-vote legislative hurdle by forcing Democrats to hold the floor in a so-called “<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/senate-filibuster-gop-save-act-00775393" target="_blank">talking filibuster</a>” to oppose the bill — as some conservatives personally lobbied Thune on the House floor Tuesday to do, the Senate leader acknowledged.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/da/58/f19c75f346a6912def93e3f058b7/unlimiteduse-02-24-2026-sotu-0021.jpg" alt="The U.S. Capitol building is seen ahead of the State of the Union address in Washington, on Feb. 24, 2026." data-portal-copyright="Alex Kent for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Alex Kent for POLITICO" data-title="The U.S. Capitol building is seen ahead of the State of the Union address in Washington, on Feb. 24, 2026."/><p>Thune said he has tentative plans to bring the bill to the floor sometime next month, so long as the Department of Homeland Security shutdown is resolved. But the lack of a sustained presidential push to upend existing filibuster rules makes it even more likely the legislation is likely to sputter out.</p> 
<p>Thune, who has repeatedly warned about the potential pitfalls of the talking filibuster approach, said Wednesday it was “a very real possibility” the bill could be brought up under the usual approach that would allow Democrats to quickly block it.</p> 
<p>The reality of Congress’ legislative morass isn’t stopping some Trump allies, who are either running for reelection or for another office, from trying to use his State of the Union speech as a springboard to action.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.), who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/lindsey-graham-dhs-immigration-sanctuary-cities-00766664" target="_blank">linked himself closely</a> to Trump, <a href="https://x.com/LindseyGrahamSC/status/2026765595912642746?s=20" target="_blank">said Wednesday</a> that Republicans “need to legislate with the same spirit as President Trump’s speech.” And GOP Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189182" data-person-id="189182">Andy Biggs</a>, who is running for governor of Arizona, touted his own legislation that he said aligns with Trump’s priorities.</p> 
<p>“I urge House Leadership to quickly move my bills that align with his priorities,” he said in a statement. “The time to act is now.”</p> 
<p>Some conservatives continue to urge Congress to pass another party-line policy bill under filibuster-skirting budget reconciliation rules to give the party a messaging boost before the midterms.</p> 
<p>But others who listened to Trump’s speech Tuesday weren’t nearly so inspired. One House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly quipped, “It was certainly light on details.”</p> 
<p>A GOP senator, also granted anonymity, summed up the congressional agenda for the foreseeable future in one word: “Slow.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-25T14:36:05-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump tells committee chairs he backs controversial spy law extension</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/25/congress/trump-section-702-renewal-00798337</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-960d-de8a-a1fc-ff4d4eea0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 13:27:30 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and John Sakellariadis</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and John Sakellariadis</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump wants Congress to sidestep internal debates and extend a key surveillance program — and he has made the demand directly to key Hill Republicans.</p> 
<p>At issue is the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/trump-section-702-clean-extension-00787007" target="_blank">foreign spy program known as Section 702</a>, which is set to lapse on April 20. Lawmakers in both parties want to put new restrictions to prevent the intelligence community from searching program data for Americans without a warrant.</p> 
<p>Trump has instead asked for a straight extension with no changes, according to Senate Intelligence Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198766" data-person-id="198766">Tom Cotton</a> and three other senior lawmakers who were granted anonymity to discuss the private request.</p> 
<p>“President Trump has requested a simple, clean extension and I support the commander-in-chief on this vital national-security decision,” Cotton (R-Ark.) said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Trump recently told Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, House Intelligence Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/148088" data-person-id="148088">Rick Crawford</a> (R-Ark.) and Judiciary Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51745" data-person-id="51745">Jim Jordan</a> (R-Ohio) that he wanted a clean extension, according to a congressional aide familiar with the discussion.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66846" data-person-id="66846">Jim Himes</a> (D-Conn.), the top Democrat on the House Intelligence Committee, said Crawford told him this week Trump wants a straight extension.</p> 
<p>“The chairman and a variety of other people have told me that the president is pushing [an] 18-month clean authorization,” Himes said.</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for the White House, Johnson, Crawford and Jordan didn’t immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Trump’s backing for a clean extension comes as top White House staffers have been privately lobbying for a clean extension of at least 18 months, including top domestic policy adviser Stephen Miller. Some intelligence community allies have privately floated going even longer — up to three years, according to one GOP lawmaker granted anonymity to discuss private discussions with the administration.</p> 
<p>Even with Trump’s private edict, a clean extension faces an uncertain path in the House, where a bipartisan coalition of privacy hawks have long demanded sweeping changes to the spy power. People familiar with the vote-counting effort don’t believe it can clear the two-thirds-majority bar for fast-track passage, and GOP lawmakers and senior aides are skeptical their party could unite behind a necessary procedural measure to put it on the floor.</p> 
<p>Himes argued the administration had a “very good story” to tell about how changes made to Section 702 two years ago had curbed privacy concerns with the program. Still, he acknowledged that while Trump’s vote of confidence could help rally Republicans, it could scare off some Democrats.</p> 
<p>“We now have a president who has shown disdain for the law, disdain for the Congress, and an awful lot of my Democrats are going to point that out and say, ‘Hey, I supported this when we actually had a president who supported the law — tell me again why I should support it now,’” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson: Gonzales allegations will ‘play out’ in primary next week</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/25/congress/speaker-watching-gonzales-primary-00797668</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9569-d0f8-adde-ff7b1f560000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 10:31:50 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said Wednesday he believes Rep. Tony Gonzales’ primary election, now six days away, will be a referendum on the serious sexual harassment allegations plaguing the Texas Republican.</p> 
<p>“I’ve said to him publicly and privately, he's got to address that directly and head on with his constituents,” Johnson told reporters. “There's a primary there in less than a week, these things will play out.”</p> 
<p>Gonzales has been accused of having an affair with a staffer and pressuring her for sexually explicit photos. That staffer later died by suicide.</p> 
<p>While Johnson and fellow House GOP leaders have not pulled their endorsement of Gonzales, several rank-and-file Republicans have called for their colleague’s resignation and many are unsure Gonzales can prevail against his challenger at this point.</p> 
<p>Gonzales told reporters Tuesday he was “not resigning” from Congress.</p> 
<p>On Wednesday morning, Johnson again called the allegations against Gonzales “alarming and detestable” and deflected when asked by reporters why he had not yet come down harder on the lawmaker.</p> 
<p>“How do you know I haven’t?” Johnson said.</p> 
<p>He added, “I don't usually go into detail on private conversations I've had with members, but I'll tell you that what I've said publicly is these are very serious allegations. He's denied much of it. We have to allow the due process here to play out, as always.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schumer defends Democrats who didn’t stand during SOTU</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/25/congress/schumer-defends-dems-00797528</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9536-d0f8-adde-ff7ec3140000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 09:38:22 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer defended Democrats for refusing to stand at the State of the Union Tuesday night when President Donald Trump implored both parties to rise if they believe the first duty of the government is to protect American citizens, not undocumented immigrants.</p> 
<p>“We agree we need to protect Americans,” Schumer told CNN on Wednesday. “He's not. By his reckless ICE agency in Minnesota, two Americans were killed. Americans are being pulled out of their cars and beaten. Americans' houses, the doors are being knocked down, you know, without a warrant.”</p> 
<p>Republicans were quick to capitalize on the moment — a visual of Trump gesturing to the Democrats still seated in the chamber while Republicans stood and clapped for well over a minute. They said it could haunt Democrats ahead of the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>“Unbelievable that Democrats would not stand to reaffirm the American government’s first duty is to American citizens, NOT illegal aliens,” <a href="https://x.com/SenRonJohnson/status/2026524187636990145" target="_blank">Wisconsin Sen. Ron Johnson wrote on X</a>.</p> 
<p>Schumer told CNN that it’s the president who is failing to live up to that ideal.</p> 
<p>“No other police department in America run by Americans has done what ICE has done,” he said. “So, yes, we want to protect Americans. He's not doing it. And that's why the American people are against what ICE is doing. So it was legitimate and right not to stand.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump’s SOTU demands for Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/25/congress/trump-sotu-demands-lawmakers-congress-immigration-00797464</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-937e-d0f8-adde-fb7ebe2d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump littered his record-breaking, nearly two-hour-long State of the Union address Tuesday night with dramatic tributes to American heroes, caustic attacks on congressional Democrats and a preview of his party’s midterm campaign pitch.</p> 
<p>But he also sprinkled in a handful of legislative demands that have uneven prospects at best on Capitol Hill. Here’s what caught our ears:</p> 
<p><b>— Targeting noncitizens:&nbsp;</b>Trump repeatedly railed against illegal immigration and pushed lawmakers to pass the SAVE America Act, the GOP bill that would tighten proof-of-citizenship standards for voting.</p> 
<p>“Why would anyone not want voter ID?” Trump said at one point. “One reason — they want to cheat.”</p> 
<p>But the bigger news might be what Trump didn’t mention: A hard-right push to use a “talking filibuster” to get the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/save-america-act-passes-house-00777405" target="_blank">House-passed bill</a> past Senate Democrats. In what was likely a big relief for Senate Majority Leader John Thune, the president didn’t mention the filibuster at all. </p> 
<p>Trump also called for passage of “<a href="https://x.com/WhiteHouse/status/2026493705394221485?s=20" target="_blank">Dalilah’s Law</a>,” which would bar states from granting driver’s licenses to undocumented immigrants.</p> 
<p><b>— Health care:</b> The president pressed Thune and Speaker Mike Johnson to take the most-favored-nation drug-pricing deals he’s recently struck with pharmaceutical companies and enact them into law.</p> 
<p>“I’m not sure it matters, because it’s going to be very hard for somebody that comes along after me to say, ‘Let’s raise drug prices by 700 or 800 percent,’” Trump said. “But John and Mike, if you don’t mind, codify it anyway.”</p> 
<p>But the provision faces big opposition from the prescription drug industry and its allies inside the GOP.</p> 
<p>Completely unmentioned? The expired Obamacare subsidies, which now seem like ancient history in Washington. Trump only briefly mentioned his “Great Health Care Plan” that would give money “directly to the people.”</p> 
<p><b>— Stock trading:&nbsp;</b>Trump drew bipartisan applause after endorsing a ban on stock trading by members of Congress. But getting a bill on Trump’s desk will be tough.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s leadership-blessed legislation to crack down on the practice is in limbo, without enough GOP support to put it up for a vote. Democrats are pushing for a more expansive stock trading bill, which would also apply to the president and vice president.</p> 
<p>Even if the House can pass something, the Senate is seen as even more unlikely to act.</p> 
<p><b>— Crime:&nbsp;</b>The president included a demand for lawmakers to pass “tough legislation to ensure violent repeat offenders are put behind bars and, more importantly, that they stay there.”</p> 
<p>That called back to Trump’s multiple comments last summer about <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/27/trump-comprehensive-crime-bill-dc-00531202" target="_blank">pursuing a sweeping crime bill</a>, which never materialized into legislation. Rekindling the effort in an election year would be iffy at best.</p> 
<p><b>— Housing:&nbsp;</b>Trump renewed his request for Congress to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/housing-deal-faces-new-hurdle-as-trump-pushes-investor-ban-00779021" target="_blank">limit large investors</a> from purchasing single-family homes as the GOP tries to address a growing housing affordability crisis — an idea that has bipartisan support.</p> 
<p>It comes as the House and Senate are working to reconcile competing legislative packages, and the White House push could help convince skeptical Republicans to include it in a final product.</p> 
<p>“We want homes for people, not for corporations,” Trump said.</p> 
<p><b>— Left unmentioned: </b>There’s one area where the president conspicuously said lawmakers are free to sit on their hands: “Congressional action will not be necessary,” Trump said, to impose new global tariffs to replace the levies struck down by the Supreme Court last week in what he called a “very unfortunate” ruling.</p> 
<p>And while Trump did discuss an expansion of a retirement savings program launched under former President Joe Biden, he did not call for new tax cuts or party-line economic measures to address rising prices — which he continued to blame on Democrats.</p> 
<p>“Their policies created the high prices,” he said. “Our policies are rapidly ending them. We are doing really well.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p>Lawmakers are set to grill two Trump nominees Wednesday morning who have come under fire for their records and financial ties.</p> 
<p><b>— Steve Pearce for BLM:</b> Steve Pearce’s appearance in front of the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee will be the former House Republican’s first opportunity to publicly push back against accusations from Democrats and conservation groups that he’s unfit to lead the Bureau of Land Management.</p> 
<p>The committee’s top Democrat, Sen. Martin Heinrich of New Mexico, and Sen. John Hickenlooper (D-Colo.) will almost certainly zero in on Pearce’s voting record. When Pearce was in Congress, he opposed BLM efforts to tighten rules on the oil and gas industry and supported selling some BLM and Forest Service lands.</p> 
<p>Pearce also reported that he earned as much as $1 million last year from a business often associated with oil and gas development.</p> 
<p><b>— Casey Means for ‘America’s top doctor’:</b> Over at the Senate HELP panel, all eyes will be on how hard Chair Bill Cassidy (R-La.) presses Casey Means, Trump’s pick to be U.S. surgeon general, over her stance on vaccines. Cassidy has repeatedly criticized Health and Human Services Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr.’s vaccine policy changes, and Means has previously condemned giving the hepatitis B shot to infants.</p> 
<p>There’s also bipartisan criticism over Means’ credentials. The wellness influencer and health-tech entrepreneur’s medical license is currently listed online as inactive, and she has promoted contested health practices such as consuming raw milk.</p> 
<p><i>Scott Streater, Nico Portuondo and Amanda Friedman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Here’s how to watch Trump’s State of the Union address</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/trump-state-of-the-union-address-2026/how-to-watch-what-time-00794726</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-918b-d0f8-adde-fbdb65900000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 20:08:37 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is set to descend on Capitol Hill for his annual State of the Union address on Tuesday, as his administration faces growing outcry over its nationwide immigration crackdown and declining support for several of his key policies.</p> 
<p>Trump’s high-stakes speech <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/21/a-high-stakes-state-of-the-union-just-got-even-harder-for-trump-00791753" target="_blank">comes just days</a> after the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trump-tariffs-supreme-court-ruling-00790687" target="_blank">dealt a crushing blow</a> to the centerpiece of his economic and foreign policy agenda, ruling his sweeping tariffs illegal. The president is also staring down brewing conflict abroad, with an immense military <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trumps-iran-buildup-risks-drowning-out-affordability-message-00788875" target="_blank">buildup in the Middle East</a> amid threats toward Iran, and an ongoing partial government shutdown impacting the Department of Homeland Security.</p> 
<p>Amid a stark backdrop — and just months before kicking off festivities for America’s 250th anniversary — Trump will be tasked with highlighting his administration’s biggest wins in his first year back in office and shoring up support with key voter blocs ahead of November’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>Here’s what you need to know before Trump delivers his highly anticipated address to Congress — and the nation:</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>How can I watch the speech?</b></span><br>Trump’s State of the Union speech is scheduled to begin at 9 p.m. Eastern on Tuesday. The address will be broadcast on major television networks and available to stream online, including on POLITICO’s website. You can follow our live coverage of the address here.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>What will Trump talk about?</b></span><br>Trump said Monday that his address is “going to be a long speech because we have so much to talk about,” hinting that his remarks will likely touch on the state of the economy. The White House has attempted to keep Trump on message about affordability ahead of this fall’s midterm elections, with the president <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-sotu-georgia-rally-00790155" target="_blank">offering a preview</a> of his possible remarks during a Thursday rally in Georgia.</p> 
<p>“They would say affordability, everybody would say, ‘Oh, Trump caused–,’ no, they cause– they caused the affordability problem,” Trump said at the rally. “And we’ve solved it. And we’re going still lower, but we’ve solved it.”</p> 
<p>Several Republicans told POLITICO they hope Trump will focus on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/trump-sotu-speech-tariffs-fallout-dhs-shutdown-00792608" target="_blank">highlighting economic issues</a>, <a href="https://www.eenews.net/articles/state-of-the-union-republicans-eager-for-trump-to-talk-energy/" target="_blank">American energy dominance</a> and the tax cuts passed in last year’s GOP megabill during his address.</p> 
<p>The president’s job approval has slid in recent months, with numerous polls <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/trump-state-of-the-union-polling-00793017" target="_blank">revealing widespread disapproval</a> of his handling of immigration and the economy — two issues that helped propel Trump back to a second term in the White House.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>Who is attending?</b></span><br>Lawmakers from both chambers of Congress, members of Trump’s family and several administration officials, including Cabinet secretaries and Vice President JD Vance, are expected to attend. Several personal guests of the president will also be at the Capitol, including Turning Point CEO Erika Kirk, widow of the late conservative influencer Charlie Kirk.</p> 
<p>Supreme Court justices are also invited to the State of the Union, although Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/donald-trump-tariff-supreme-court-reaction-00791245" target="_blank">sniped at several of the justices</a> who voted to strike down his tariffs last week, telling reporters Friday: “I couldn't care less if they come.”</p> 
<p>Members of Congress are each permitted to invite a guest to the address, and lawmakers frequently use the invite to draw attention to high-profile issues. Some Democrats — including House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries and Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer — have announced that they’ll bring survivors of convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein as their guests. Many Republicans are bringing guests who benefited from Trump’s One Big Beautiful Bill Act passed last year.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/squeeze-in-the-hockey-players-00794705" target="_blank">confirmed Tuesday</a> the U.S. men’s hockey team will attend Trump’s address, although the women’s team said it would not participate due to scheduling issues.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>Who won’t be there?</b></span><br>More than a dozen Democratic lawmakers have announced that they won’t attend Trump’s State of the Union, with several choosing to attend <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/democrats-trump-state-of-the-union-boycott-00786370" target="_blank">a counterprogramming rally</a> on the National Mall instead.</p> 
<p>The event, dubbed the “People’s State of the Union,” will feature lawmakers who also skipped Trump’s inaugurations, including Sens. Ed Markey (D-Mass.) and Chris Murphy (D-Conn.) and Reps. Greg Casar (D-Texas) and Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.).</p> 
<p>Jeffries advised Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/trump-state-of-the-union-shutdown-00781266" target="_blank">during a private leadership meeting</a> earlier this month that members of his caucus should either attend alternative programming or sit in “silent defiance” of Trump’s speech, hoping to avoid the image of Democratic hecklers during last year’s address.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers from both parties are also facing weather-related delays in traveling back to Washington after a winter storm led the House to cancel Monday votes.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>Who is giving the Democratic response?</b></span><br>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger is set to deliver the official Democratic rebuttal to Trump’s address Tuesday night.</p> 
<p>Spanberger, a former CIA officer who served in the House from 2019-2025, defeated GOP nominee Winsome Earle-Sears to flip the Virginia governor’s mansion blue in November. Democrats widely <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/affordability-affordability-affordability-democrats-new-winning-formula-00637023" target="_blank">lauded her campaign</a> for its focus on affordability.</p> 
<p>Spanberger <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/spanberger-state-of-the-union-dems-00789425" target="_blank">hinted last week</a> that her response will likely center on those issues, writing in a statement that “Virginians and Americans across the country are contending with rising costs, chaos in their communities, and a real fear of what each day might bring.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Alex Padilla (D-Calif.) — California’s first Latino senator and the son of Mexican immigrants — will deliver the Democratic response in Spanish.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shutdown talks make little progress as DHS bill stalls in Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/shutdown-talks-make-little-progress-as-dhs-bill-stalls-in-senate-00796857</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91f2-d0f8-adde-fbfa4f010000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 18:19:40 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats blocked a Department of Homeland Security funding for a second time Tuesday, underscoring a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/shutdown-stalemate-deepens-as-white-house-dems-dig-in-on-dhs-funding-00789614" target="_blank">shutdown stalemate</a> now in its second week.</p> 
<p>Senators voted 50-45 to advance a House-passed DHS bill in their first action on funding for the department since a partial government shutdown started Feb. 14. The bill needed 60 votes to move forward.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump will use part of his State of the Union speech Tuesday evening to encourage Democrats to reopen the Department of Homeland Security, White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Tuesday. But with lawmakers just returning to Washington from a weeklong recess, the talks appear to have almost entirely stalled.</p> 
<p>“We've heard crickets from them, nothing,” Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> told reporters Tuesday. “They're not negotiating. They're just trying to pass paper back and forth with no real changes.”</p> 
<p>There’s currently no meeting scheduled between congressional leaders and Trump to talk about the funding fight, which disproportionately impacts nonimmigration agencies such as TSA and the Coast Guard. With talks going slowly, there’s no expectation that a deal to end the partial shutdown is reached this week, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the private negotiations.</p> 
<p>Democrats have vowed to oppose DHS funding until they get changes to Trump’s immigration enforcement tactics after federal agents killed two U.S. citizens in Minneapolis. Democrats have outlined more than a dozen changes that they want, including banning masks for federal agents, requiring them to obtain judicial warrants to search private property and requiring independent investigations of agent misconduct.</p> 
<p>Despite the partial shutdown, Trump’s immigration agencies have funding under the party-line megabill Republicans passed last year. But Democrats believe they have public opinion on their side due to the political backlash over Trump’s immigration tactics, which have also sparked unease among some Republican lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Democrats gave their latest counteroffer to the White House last week. Asked about a possible White House response, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said in an interview Tuesday that the talks are now more “informal,” with the parties “just kind of going back and forth and trying to hit the landing spot.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-24T19:03:45-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Ahead of SOTU, Dems demand Trump make Iran plans public</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/ahead-sotu-dems-demand-trump-iran-plans-public-00796594</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91be-d3b5-addf-f1fe43930000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:33:44 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Joe Gould</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Joe Gould</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As President Donald Trump prepared to deliver his State of the Union Address Tuesday night, top Democratic lawmakers emerged from a classified briefing on Iran and urged him to explain how he will resolve the standoff over Tehran’s nuclear program. </p> 
<p>The briefing, which Secretary of State Marco Rubio delivered to House and Senate leadership, as well as the top members of the House and Senate Intelligence Committees, comes as the administration weighs potential military action against Iran.</p> 
<p>Though Trump hasn’t indicated he has made a final decision, he has ordered a huge expansion of U.S. military forces in the Middle East and warned of “really bad things” if a deal isn’t reached with Tehran on its nuclear enrichment program.</p> 
<p>“Look, this is serious, and the administration has to make its case to the American people,” Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said after the briefing. </p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> afterward questioned the need for military action, pointing to Trump’s past claims that he had destroyed Tehran’s nuclear program during Operation Midnight Hammer this past summer.</p> 
<p>“Part of the concern that I’ve articulated, and will continue to do so, is that the president made the representation that Iran’s nuclear program was completely and totally obliterated last year as a result of actions that the administration has taken,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>“And so if that, in fact, was true, what is the urgency as of this moment? That’s an open question, and the American people need a real explanation,” he added.</p> 
<p>Senate Intelligence Vice Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66837" data-person-id="66837">Mark Warner</a> (D-Va.) called it was “a serious moment” for the Middle East and America. He noted that some of the sailors in the administration’s military buildup are from his state.</p> 
<p>“I think it is incumbent upon the president to make the case of what our country's goals are, what our country's interests are, and how we're going to protect American interests in the region,” he said. “Maybe we'll hear that tonight, but if we don't hear it tonight, we need to hear it very, very soon.”</p> 
<p>On the other side of the aisle, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said “consultation” with Congress “needs to happen” on Iran.</p> 
<p>But he said it was unclear what decisions the administration has made on military action.</p> 
<p>“There are multiple issues with regard to Iran, one of which is the nuclear program; The other is the ballistic missile program,” Thune said. “It is a dangerous country, and very volatile, as you know, right now.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No. 2 House Democrat won’t attend State of the Union</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/katherine-clark-skip-sotu-00796596</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91b8-de8a-a1fc-f9f8e53e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:19:27 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Minority Whip Katherine Clark said she will be skipping President Donald Trump’s State of the Union speech Tuesday, becoming the most senior Democrat to boycott the annual address.</p> 
<p>“I will be hearing from the people of my district about their personal experiences with skyrocketing costs, new barriers to health care, dismantled Social Security services, and brutal cuts to medical research,” the No. 2 House Democrat said in a statement.</p> 
<p>The Massachusetts lawmaker pointed to the fatal shootings of U.S. citizens in Minnesota last month as a stalemate over Homeland Security funding heads into a second week. She also said Trump is “standing in the way of truth” in citing the DOJ’s handling of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries and Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer have said they plan to attend Trump’s address. Jeffries has encouraged members to either sit in silent defiance or attend alternative programming as dozens of rank-and-file members have announced plans to skip the speech.</p> 
<p>“Donald Trump’s presidency has been one broken promise after another, and the people of this country and the Commonwealth deserve so much better,” Clark said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalise, committee chairs huddle with White House officials on GOP agenda</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/scalise-committee-chairs-huddle-with-white-house-officials-on-gop-agenda-00796589</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91b4-d3b5-addf-f1f416ee0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:11:13 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise held a dinner Monday night with Republican committee chairs and senior White House officials to discuss the GOP legislative agenda ahead of the midterms, according to five people granted anonymity to share details of the private event.</p> 
<p>White House deputy chief of staff for legislative affairs James Blair was in attendance at the dinner, held at a Capitol Hill restaurant, alongside the administration’s legislative affairs director James Braid and top House liaison, Jeff Freeland, according to the people.</p> 
<p>Blair and White House officials discussed key affordability policy areas they feel are especially salient in a midterm election year, including housing. They also raised health care and economic issues — topics Trump plans to hit on in his State of the Union address Tuesday night.</p> 
<p>But notably, the people with knowledge of the meeting said the group did not discuss pursuing these priorities through another party-line budget reconciliation package.</p> 
<p>Scalise said in an interview Tuesday afternoon he organized the dinner to coordinate with the White House and invited the chairs to share details of the legislation they plan to work on for the rest of the year.</p> 
<p>White House officials also gave a rough overview of what to expect from Trump’s State of the Union speech, Scalise continued.</p> 
<p>Blair and other White House representatives said the president will laud American greatness ahead of the country’s upcoming 250th birthday, according to Scalise. Trump will also talk about “the mess he inherited from Biden,” including high inflation and rampant illegal border crossings.</p> 
<p>Trump will give examples of how he’s working with his Republican majority in Congress to fix a lot of those problems, but “also make clear that the work’s not done,” Scalise said. </p> 
<p>He added that Trump's speech also will preview “what we need to do in the next few months” ahead of the midterms.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-24T18:10:34-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democrats to probe DOJ’s alleged withholding of Epstein files on Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/24/democrats-doj-epstein-files-trump-00795347</link>
      <description>Republicans are accusing their colleagues across the aisle of launching a “witch hunt.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-90c1-d0f8-adde-fadbb3330000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 15:35:11 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/cf/8e/e31d11f64453856343b8855d0f7b/epstein-congress-clintons-05916.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Ranking member Rep. Robert Garcia, D-Calif., speaks during a House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform markup business meeting about finding former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Rodham Clinton in contempt of Congress, Wednesday Jan. 21, 2026, on Capitol Hill in Washington. (AP Photo/Jacquelyn Martin)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/cf/8e/e31d11f64453856343b8855d0f7b/epstein-congress-clintons-05916.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats on the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee are investigating whether the Justice Department purposefully withheld materials in its release of the Jeffrey Epstein files that included sexual assault allegations against President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia (D-Calif.), the ranking member of the panel, said in a statement Tuesday that such an act by DOJ would violate the law Congress passed in November, which required the administration to publicly release all files in its possession related to the federal case against Epstein, a convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>Garcia also said it also would run afoul of the subpoenas the Oversight Committee separately transmitted to DOJ last summer as part of<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/02/house-releases-first-trove-of-epstein-files-00540467" target="_blank"><u> its own Epstein investigation</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“For the last few weeks, Oversight Democrats have been investigating the FBI’s handling of allegations from 2019 of sexual assault on a minor made against President Donald Trump by a survivor,” Garcia said <a href="https://x.com/OversightDems/status/2026326604335522245" target="_blank"><u>in the statement</u></a>. “Oversight Democrats can confirm that the DOJ appears to have illegally withheld FBI interviews with this survivor who accused President Trump of heinous crimes.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the White House did not immediately provide comment to POLITICO regarding whether the administration is withholding incriminating materials.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department, <a href="https://x.com/dojrr47/status/2026366459375497413?s=46" target="_blank">on social media</a>, called on Oversight Democrats to "stop misleading the public while manufacturing outrage from their radical anti-Trump base," asserting that "NOTHING has been deleted."</p> 
<p>"If files are temporarily pulled for victim redactions or to redact Personally Identifiable Information, then those documents are promptly restored online and are publicly available," the DOJ X post continued. "ALL responsive documents have been produced unless a document falls within one of the following categories: duplicates, privileged, or part of an ongoing federal investigation."</p> 
<p>Trump has denied wrongdoing in relation to the Epstein allegations, and no evidence has suggested that Trump took part in Epstein’s trafficking operation. Many of the materials released by the Justice Department also lack substantiation or context.</p> 
<p>Congressional investigators identified missing materials after matching public files with case files listed in the evidence manifest provided to the legal team of Ghislaine Maxwell, Epstein’s co-conspirator who is currently serving a 20-year prison sentence, said Sara Guerrero, a spokesperson for Oversight Democrats.</p> 
<p>One of those files include an allegation from a redacted individual that Trump sexually assaulted a minor. The accusation appears in <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2010/EFTA01660622.pdf" target="_blank"><u>a slide deck presentation</u></a> featuring a list of powerful men who had been at one point connected to Epstein, including Trump.</p> 
<p>In that slide deck, a person, whose name has been redacted but was estimated to be between 13 and 15 years old at the time of the alleged incident sometime in the 1980s, accuses Trump of forcing her head down to his penis, then reacting violently when she resisted.</p> 
<p>An investigative <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/24/nx-s1-5723968/epstein-files-trump-accusation-maxwell" target="_blank"><u>report by NPR</u></a>, published Tuesday, found that DOJ withheld “what appears to be more than 50 pages of FBI interviews, and notes from conversations with a woman who accused Trump of sexual abuse decades ago when she was a minor.” The report also notes that DOJ “removed some documents from the public database where accusations against Jeffrey Epstein also mention Trump.”</p> 
<p>POLITICO did not independently verify the NPR findings.</p> 
<p>Garcia said he viewed unredacted files on a DOJ computer Monday, per privileges afforded to members of Congress.</p> 
<p>“Covering up direct evidence of a potential assault by the President of the United States is the most serious possible crime in this White House cover up,” he added.</p> 
<p>The Democrats’ probe, which will lack subpoena power given the party’s minority status, comes as party operatives see political advantage in drawing attention to DOJ’s handling of the Epstein files, alleging the administration is working to hide information that could be damaging to the president and not making enough efforts to bring justice to Epstein's accusers, a charge that the DOJ denies.</p> 
<p>Separately, two House Democrats are asking deputy attorney general Todd Blanche to appoint a special counsel to investigate whether the nation’s top prosecutor, Pam Bondi, lied to Congress during her recent testimony before the House Judiciary Committee regarding Trump’s involvement with Epstein.</p> 
<p>At that hearing earlier this month, Bondi said there is “no evidence” in the Epstein documents made public by her department that shows Trump committed a crime. In a letter to Blanche, Reps. Dan Goldman of New York and Ted Lieu of California pointed to the unsubstantiated claim in the Epstein documents that Trump allegedly forced himself on the young girl.</p> 
<p>Lieu accused Bondi of lying to Congress during the hearing about whether Trump was accused of committing crimes in the Epstein files, without specifying details. Bondi responded, “don’t you ever accuse me of a crime.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for House Oversight Republicans, in a statement, accused Democrats of “playing politics instead of seeking justice for survivors.”</p> 
<p>“In the course of their witch hunt, they’ve cherry-picked and doctored documents to mislead the public and released images with no context to create a false narrative,” she continued<b>.&nbsp;</b></p> 
<p>She also noted Democrats have “refused to condemn their own colleague,” Del. Stacey Plaskett (D-V.I.), who was found to have been<a href="https://www.notus.org/congress/stacey-plaskett-virgin-islands-epstein-emails-document-release" target="_blank"><u> a close associate of Epstein,</u></a> texting and speaking on the phone with him and trying to set up a visit to his private island.</p> 
<p>All Democrats voted against a Republican-led resolution in November that would have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-epstein-defense-00657798" target="_blank"><u>formally reprimanded Plaskett</u></a> and kicked her off the House Intelligence Committee.</p> 
<p>“Democrats have no credibility on this issue,” the spokesperson said.</p> 
<p>Plaskett has not been found guilty of wrongdoing and <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-98dd-df0f-abfa-f9ff4bbc0000" target="_blank"><u>has described Epstein</u></a> as her former “constituent.” </p> 
<p>“The partisan attack on the congresswoman is a pathetic and deliberate distortion of the facts," a Plaskett spokesperson said in a statement. "The Congresswoman has never visited Jeffrey Epstein’s island and has been clear in condemning his abhorrent behavior and has a long history of fighting against the sexual exploitation of women. It is imperative that we do not allow politically motivated distractions to pull the focus away from the actual bad actors who perpetrated and enabled these crimes.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-24T17:28:11-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Judges plead with Congress for control of crumbling courthouses</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/congress-pressed-on-courthouses-00795767</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9143-d3b5-addf-f1c7b1e00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 15:09:39 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Josh Gerstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Josh Gerstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The infrastructure of the nation’s federal courthouses is crumbling, plagued by collapsing ceilings, malfunctioning elevators and contaminated water supplies, a top representative for the federal judiciary declared in <a href="https://www.uscourts.gov/sites/default/files/document/judiciary-real-property-authority-legislative-package.pdf" target="_blank">an unusual plea</a> to Congress on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>“Federal courthouses are in crisis. Without immediate action, the problems will continue to worsen,” Judge Robert J. Conrad Jr., director of the Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts, said in a letter to lawmakers. “Action is needed now to reverse a downward spiral of critical-system failures, long-term underfunding of repairs, security risks, and climbing costs.”</p> 
<p>Conrad urged lawmakers to address the problem by giving the courts the power to build and operate their courthouses — tasks now handled by the General Services Administration.</p> 
<p>While judges have groused for decades about neglect by their government landlord, complaints about GSA reached a fever pitch last year after haphazard moves by President Donald Trump’s Department of Government Efficiency initiative radically downsized the agency and targeted some courthouses for sale without any input from the judges who work there.</p> 
<p>The urgent missive the judiciary sent to Congress on Tuesday doesn’t make direct mention of DOGE, but it notes that GSA eliminated almost half its staff in recent months, creating security and safety risks by leaving no one on site at many courthouses to address hazards and urgent repairs. Legislation the judges are backing would gradually transition existing courthouses from GSA to a new Judiciary Buildings Service.</p> 
<p>GSA spokesperson Marianne Copenhaver said in a statement that the agency disputes the suggestion that courthouses are in "crisis." </p> 
<p>“While aging federal buildings present well-known challenges, [the judiciary’s] narrative omits critical context regarding our lack of access to GSA's Federal Building Fund to address delinquent maintenance," she added. "The American taxpayer is best served by the Judiciary focusing on the rule of law while GSA continues to focus on the federal real estate portfolio."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
