<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 21:48:40 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>House Democrats think Pam Bondi just helped them in the midterms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-judiciary-epstein-trump-00777293</link>
      <description>Tensions flared between Democrats and the Attorney General during a House Judiciary Committee hearing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4ef1-d0f8-adde-fefbedc70001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 19:17:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/88/21/eb64ddd74c0fbbb4fa8eeeca05f6/congress-bondi-55791.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Attorney General Pam Bondi testifies before a House Judiciary Committee oversight hearing on Capitol Hill in Washington, Wednesday, Feb. 11, 2026, in Washington, as Jeffrey Epstein survivors, stand left. (AP Photo/Tom Brenner)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/88/21/eb64ddd74c0fbbb4fa8eeeca05f6/congress-bondi-55791.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats walked into the House Judiciary Committee hearing with Attorney General Pam Bondi Wednesday expecting her to be nonresponsive and combative. They walked out with what they believe to be a more compelling argument for winning back the majority.</p> 
<p>For four hours, the nation’s top law enforcement officer largely refused to answer questions from Democrats about the Justice Department’s handling of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>In some moments, Bondi deflected queries by asking members if they cared about crimes or violence in their districts, flipping through a massive binder of research Rep. Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) derided as her “burn book.”</p> 
<p>In others, she responded by lashing out at committee members in personal terms, at one point calling Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the panel’s top Democrat, a “washed-up, loser lawyer — not even a lawyer.”</p> 
<p>“If we had the power, we would subpoena her, and we would require her to answer our questions,” Raskin, a former constitutional law professor, told reporters following the hearing. “So that is the importance of who's going to be in control in Congress after the 2026 elections because we would like the subpoena power, so we don't see this kind of phenomenal disrespect of Congress.”</p> 
<p>Even if Democrats reclaim the gavel of the House Judiciary Committee, Bondi could still drag her feet. And her aggressive posture in attacking lawmakers during a regular oversight hearing of the DOJ — the purported purpose of Wednesday’s proceedings — suggests she will not cooperate easily.</p> 
<p>“The questions I’ve asked … are not trick questions, they’re not gotcha questions, they’re actually basic questions about how the Department of Justice functions,” said Rep. Joe Neguse (D-Colo.), who said the hearing lacked “some modicum of resembling something that has typically been fairly conventional: an oversight hearing of the Department of Justice.”</p> 
<p>The only relevant, new information that Bondi provided to lawmakers was in response to a question from a Republican, Rep. Chip Roy of Texas, who asked <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/doj-epstein-investigations-00776455" target="_blank"><u>whether people would be indicted</u></a> for ties to Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>Bondi said vaguely, “We have pending investigations in our office.” It was not clear whether she was referring to investigations into prominent Democratic officials, which had come after a directive from President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Still, Democrats think Bondi’s hostile performance throughout the hearing will help their cause in the midterms as they make a case for a return to normalcy. At times, even House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan had to interrupt to ensure lawmakers could ask their questions.</p> 
<p>"I can't believe that the Attorney General of the United States of America would appear before hundreds of millions of Americans this way and then have a book of insults that she's ready to lob at members of Congress ... we've got to get back to the America that we had before they dragged us down into the mud like this,” Raskin said following the hearing.</p> 
<p>Rep. Steve Cohen (D-Tenn.), a member of the Judiciary panel, also said the events Wednesday boost Democrats’ case in the midterm elections.</p> 
<p>“She did an excellent job in appealing to Donald Trump, and it was [for] … one person audience: Donald Trump,” said Cohen, adding that the hearing “gave the public some information about what the Justice Department's not doing correctly.”</p> 
<p>In many ways, Bondi played directly into Democrats’ hands, and not only by trash-talking lawmakers whose questions she didn’t want to answer — similar to the maneuver she deployed when <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/07/congress/bondi-goes-after-schiff-00596375" target="_blank"><u>testifying before the Senate Judiciary Committee</u></a> back in October.</p> 
<p>Democrats coordinated with the victims of Epstein’s abuse so that roughly ten could sit in the hearing room behind Bondi. Lawmakers offered her the opportunity to engage with them directly and apologize for the department’s conduct or meet with the victims.</p> 
<p>Bondi, in her opening remarks, said she was “deeply sorry for what any victim … has been through” but otherwise refused to take the bait. At one point, when Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/dems-challenge-bondi-on-epstein-00775809" target="_blank"><u>asked Bondi to apologize to the victims</u></a> for what the Justice Department has put them through, Bondi declined: “I’m not going to get in the gutter for her theatrics.”</p> 
<p>Democrats also headed into Wednesday’s high-profile hearing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-house-judiciary-tesitmony-00775441" target="_blank"><u>prepared to draw a contrast</u></a> between their interest in asking hard questions about events that have captured the public’s attention — namely justice for Epstein’s victims and accountability for any potential accomplices — and Republicans’ more politically accommodating approach.</p> 
<p>Jordan said on Wednesday evening he thought Bondi “handled herself very well” and expected Democrats to be aggressive. At one point, Rep. Dan Goldman (D-N.Y.) yelled at Bondi to be “quiet” as he fought to be heard, while Rep. Chuy Garcia (D-Ill.) called her “one of the worst” attorneys generals “in our history.”</p> 
<p>“I think it went great — I mean, the bottom line is … under the leadership of the Attorney General and the president, crime is down,” Jordan said.</p> 
<p>The only <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/massie-vs-bondi-00775966" target="_blank"><u>Republican who challenged Bondi</u></a> was Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky, who led the charge to release the Epstein files in DOJ’s possession and picked enough fights with Trump that the president and his allies are now seeking to oust him in a primary.</p> 
<p>Accusing Bondi of failing to comply with the law he shepherded through Congress with sloppy redactions — or lack thereof — of both victims and the name of one powerful man in the Epstein files, Bondi called Massie a “failed politician” and a “hypocrite.”</p> 
<p>Massie, in an interview Wednesday evening, said it took Bondi “a long time to find my insult card.”</p> 
<p>“I think she was crashing the whole time,” he said. “There was no effort really to answer any of the difficult questions.”</p> 
<p>Asked about being the only Republican to ask a tough question at the hearing, Massie replied, “Nobody wants to get on the bad side of Trump … That’ll change once we get past our primaries.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House passes GOP elections overhaul</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/save-america-act-passes-house-00777405</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4f12-de8a-a1fc-ff523bba0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 18:44:56 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House passed a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499" target="_blank">major GOP elections overhaul</a> Wednesday after intense pressure from President Donald Trump, tech mogul Elon Musk and hard-right influencers. But the legislation still has no clear path forward in the Senate, where Republicans privately acknowledge there is not enough GOP support to skirt a Democratic filibuster as Trump is demanding.</p> 
<p>The SAVE America Act, an updated version of a bill tightening voter registration standards that the House passed last year, was approved on a 218-213 vote. One Democrat, Rep. Henry Cuellar of Texas, voted for it — down from the four who backed the earlier effort.</p> 
<p>Conservative hard-liners wanted the bill attached to a massive government funding package this month, threatening to extend a four-day partial government shutdown until Trump intervened and ordered House Republicans to pass the bill without it.</p> 
<p>The legislation would trigger major changes to how Americans vote, including requiring voters to present proof of citizenship to register, eliminating mail-only registrations, and requiring photo ID in every state for the first time. It would also require states to take new steps to remove noncitizens from existing voter rolls.</p> 
<p>The GOP’s hope is that the focus on election integrity and Trump’s false claims that the 2020 election was “rigged” will help drive turnout among MAGA voters when Trump isn’t on the ballot this November, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy. The vote is also meant to satisfy the president’s demands for a voting crackdown as he mulls bigger overhauls many Republicans oppose, like “federalizing” America’s election system and ending mail voting.</p> 
<p>But the House vote hands a hot potato to Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who has ruled out changing Senate rules to weaken the 60-voter supermajority threshold to pass the bill and has reacted coolly to suggestions a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/senate-filibuster-gop-save-act-00775393" target="_blank">“talking filibuster” approach could work instead</a>.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders deployed a procedural feint, using a Senate-passed shell bill to try to fast-track consideration in the other chamber — part of the Trump-backed push to try to force a reckoning on the filibuster.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) poured cold water on House Republicans' celebratory mood this week.</p> 
<p>Even before the House vote Wednesday, Murkowski announced she would oppose it — lambasting the bill as “federal overreach.” Her move sparked an onslaught of recriminations from House Republicans, who are still pushing Thune and Speaker Mike Johnson to find a way to send the bill to Trump’s desk.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bondi dodges questions about Lutnick’s connections with Epstein</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/pam-bondi-howard-lutnick-00776491</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e46-d3b5-addf-eec634520000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 15:04:11 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Josh Gerstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Josh Gerstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi gave no direct answer Wednesday when pressed by Rep. Becca Balint (D-Vt.) on whether the Justice Department has made any effort to question Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick about his interactions with Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“Secretary Lutnick has addressed those ties himself,” Bondi replied.</p> 
<p>Lutnick said on a podcast last year that he was disgusted by Epstein’s conduct and vowed in 2005 to never to be in the same room with him again. However, documents the Justice Department released last month show continued interactions between the two men in the ensuing years.</p> 
<p>In addition, Lutnick acknowledged at a Senate hearing Tuesday that he and his family traveled in 2012 to the Caribbean island Epstein owned. Lutnick <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/lutnick-grilled-over-epstein-links-at-commerce-appropriations-hearing-00773002" target="_blank">described a lunch with the financier</a>, who pleaded guilty in 2008 to soliciting a minor for prostitution in Florida and who died by suicide in 2019 in a New York jail while awaiting trial on federal sex-trafficking charges.</p> 
<p>Lutnick, despite the latest revelations, has faced <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/main-wh-lutnick-00774844" target="_blank">few recriminations from Trump world</a> over his connections with the late financier.</p> 
<p>As Balint demanded that Bondi explain whether prosecutors or the FBI have talked with Lutnick or other Trump administration officials who had “ties” with Epstein, the attorney general challenged the lawmaker’s terminology.</p> 
<p>“What does ‘ties’ mean?” Bondi replied. “Can you define that? Can you define ‘ties’?"</p> 
<p>“I think Americans would be shocked to learn that you are not interested in talking with these officials who have ties to Jeffrey Epstein,” Balint replied as the attorney general tried to change the subject to the shooting of a Border Patrol agent in Vermont last month. “We now know that Lutnick went to Epstein's island in 2012. How was that not a dealbreaker for the president?” the Democratic lawmaker asked.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bondi says DOJ is investigating possible Epstein conspirators</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/doj-epstein-investigations-00776455</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e30-d3b5-addf-eef43f4f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 15:03:06 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Erica Orden</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Erica Orden</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi said Wednesday her department is actively probing individuals who might have conspired with convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“We have pending investigations in our office," she said during her testimony before the House Judiciary Committee, when asked by Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) if people would be indicted for ties to Epstein's crimes.</p> 
<p>It was not clear if Bondi was referring to work by the U.S. Attorney's Office in the Southern District of New York, where Bondi has directed U.S. Attorney Jay Clayton to oversee investigations into connections between Epstein and prominent Democrats. </p> 
<p>But members of both parties are clamoring for justice for Epstein's victims, with many lawmakers counting on the release of the DOJ's Epstein files to reveal more information about who should be implicated in wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Republicans have repeatedly suggested former President Bill Clinton should be further scrutinized, pointing to his long-standing relationship with Epstein as captured in photos Bondi's agency made public in compliance with the law Congress passed last fall. Democrats, meanwhile, continue to scrutinize Trump's relationship with the disgraced financier. </p> 
<p>Neither man has been accused of wrongdoing in connection with Epstein's crimes.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rep. Jason Crow asks Pirro to preserve evidence related to failed indictment</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/rep-jason-crow-asks-pirro-to-preserve-evidence-related-to-failed-indictment-00776376</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e1e-d3b5-addf-eede3ce50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 14:19:05 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) on Wednesday demanded U.S. Attorney for the District of Columbia Jeanine Pirro preserve all evidence related to her unsuccessful effort to bring charges against him and five other Democratic lawmakers.</p> 
<p>The request comes a day after Pirro’s office <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/lawmakers-military-orders-grand-jury-indictment-00775504" target="_blank"><u>failed to obtain a criminal indictment</u></a> against the lawmakers for putting out a video last year urging military personnel not to carry out illegal orders.</p> 
<p>In a letter sent Wednesday to Pirro’s office, Abbe Lowell, Crow’s attorney, called the effort to indict Crow and the other Democrats involved in the video “a breathtaking and unprecedented level of prosecutorial overreach and misuse of power.” Lowell, who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/27/trump-retribution-lawyer-abbe-lowell-lisa-cook-00529290" target="_blank"><u>represented a wide swath of President Donald Trump’s enemies</u></a> in the last year, also put Pirro and other federal prosecutors “on notice” of the possible legal ramifications for failing to preserve evidence in the case or taking further action to pursue the case.</p> 
<p>“Donald Trump’s abuse of America’s justice system is chilling and indefensible,” Lowell wrote <a href="https://www.politico.com/document/crow-lowell-pirro-letter" target="_blank">in the letter</a>. “What’s perhaps most surprising is not that your effort to secure a grand jury indictment failed, but that you even tried. Americans are paying attention to your gross abuses of power and demanding accountability."</p> 
<p>Pirro's office did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Pirro and other prosecutors in the Trump administration have on several occasions struggled to secure indictments against several of the president’s political foes, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/letitia-james-indictment-third-charge-00697148" target="_blank"><u>New York Attorney General Letitia James</u></a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/james-comey-case-lindsey-halligan-hearing-00659479" target="_blank"><u>former FBI Director James Comey</u></a>. A grand jury rejecting indictments is an exceedingly rare outcome in federal cases, as they are tasked only with determining whether the Justice Department has brought a plausible case, although the Trump administration has faced an unusual number of failures in liberal areas like New York and the D.C. area.</p> 
<p>Sens. Mark Kelly of Arizona and Elissa Slotkin of Michigan, whom federal prosecutors also attempted to indict in relation to the video, decried the move from Pirro’s office at a Wednesday press conference, with Kelly, calling it an effort “to abuse power in order to silence and intimidate anyone who disagrees with them.”</p> 
<p>“The baseless and absurd allegations by Donald Trump, followed by your carrying out of the President’s political retribution campaign has already gone too far, and are evidence of yet another abuse of power directed at those who dare speak out and criticize this Administration,” Lowell wrote in the letter, which was <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/jason-crow-letter-jeanine-pirro-illegal-orders-video-records-lawsuit/" target="_blank"><u>first reported by CBS News</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Trump, in the wake of the video’s release in November 2025, repeatedly called for the lawmakers to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank"><u>face arrest and trial</u></a> for what he called “SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR, punishable by DEATH!” The president later clarified that he was “not threatening death” against the Democrats.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson says he has urged Florida Republican to stay in Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/neal-dunn-resignation-johnson-00776216</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e11-de8a-a1fc-ff517add0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 13:59:40 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> says he has asked retiring Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259506" data-person-id="259506">Neal Dunn</a> to serve out his term amid concerns the Florida Republican might resign early.</p> 
<p>An early exit from Dunn, 72, would deal Johnson another massive blow as he tries to maintain his narrow majority. Currently, Republicans can afford to lose no more than one GOP vote on party-line measures, though they are expected to pick up a vote in a March special election.</p> 
<p>Senior House Republicans believe Dunn intends to step down in the coming months despite an effort to get him to stay, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the private discussions.</p> 
<p>“Neal Dunn is a beloved member of Congress and a great man, and you know, he's informed us he's <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/neal-dunn-florida-retirement-00724395" target="_blank">not going to run for reelection</a>," Johnson told reporters Wednesday. As for what Dunn does beyond that, he added, "I'm not sure — you need to ask him about it. But I've encouraged him to stay and be a part of this, and I think he wants to do that.”</p> 
<p>Dunn, who represents a heavily Republican seat in northern Florida, declined to discuss his intentions in an interview Wednesday: "No comment," he said. </p> 
<p>Dunn has worn a mask on the House floor at times in recent weeks, and some of his colleagues said they believe his health is a factor in his decision. Asked about those concerns, Dunn replied, "Don't I look good?"</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massie becomes first Republican to spar with Bondi during House Judiciary hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/massie-vs-bondi-00775966</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4dc6-de8a-a1fc-fdc617370000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 12:57:34 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Thomas Massie was the first and so far only Republican to spar with Attorney General Pam Bondi during her hearing Wednesday before the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>The Kentucky lawmaker asked Bondi about redactions in the Jeffrey Epstein files that failed to comply with the law Massie helped shepherd to passage last year. He pointed to instances where the names of victims are not shielded but the name of Les Wexner, a businessman and client of the convicted sex offender, is blacked out.</p> 
<p>“Who’s responsible?" Massie asked. "Are you able to track who in the organization made this massive failure and released the victims’ names?"</p> 
<p>Bondi replied that Massie, who has become a vocal critic of President Donald Trump, was a "failed politician" and a "hypocrite."</p> 
<p>“Within 40 minutes, Wexner’s name was added back in,” Bondi said.</p> 
<p>“Within 40 minutes of me catching you red-handed,” Massie responded.</p> 
<p>Bondi then accused Massie of having “Trump derangement syndrome" and refusing to press for justice for Epstein's victims during previous administrations.</p> 
<p>“This is bigger than Watergate,” Massie told Bondi. “This cover-up spans decades, and you are responsible for this portion of it.”</p> 
<p>Wexner has said he severed ties with Epstein in the aughts, around the time of an earlier investigation against the late financier and when Wexner realized that Epstein has illicitly taken money from him.</p> 
<p>“The Assistant U.S. Attorney told Mr. Wexner’s legal counsel in 2019 that Mr. Wexner was being viewed as source of information about Epstein and was not a target in any respect," a legal representative for Wexner said in a recent statement. "Mr. Wexner cooperated fully by providing background information on Epstein and was never contacted again.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP senators rail at FDA after closed-door briefing on abortion drug</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/bitter-pills-00775740</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d3e-d0f8-adde-ff7e39600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:57:18 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Senate Republicans emerged disappointed from a closed-door briefing Tuesday with FDA Commissioner Marty Makary, saying the agency is not taking a safety review of the abortion pill mifepristone seriously and calling for congressional action to curb access to the drug.</p> 
<p>Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said in an interview Makary failed to give a timeline for completion of the review, explain what the audit will involve and disclose whether it was even underway.</p> 
<p>“I think that this safety study is a dead end,” Hawley said. “I just think that FDA is not serious about it. I don't think that they're proceeding with any sense of urgency whatsoever. If they're really proceeding at all. I frankly, can't tell.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Bill Cassidy (R-La.), the chair of the Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee who organized the briefing for select GOP senators, in a statement also blasted “the lack of progress on HHS and FDA’s promised safety study on these dangerous drugs” as “disappointing,” and complained the review was “moving too slowly.”</p> 
<p>It's not clear what comes next. Republicans have previously tried and failed to impose restrictions on mifepristone, which is used in more than two-thirds of abortions, through government funding legislation. Hawley said he has not yet decided whether to attempt to place guardrails on the drug as part of the next appropriations process or introduce a standalone bill, but that he will roll out his plans in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p><br>“I don't have confidence [the FDA review] is going to amount to anything,” he said. “My view is Congress now needs to get involved.”</p> 
<p><br>Reached for comment, HHS spokesperson Andrew Nixon referred POLITICO to a<a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/questions-and-answers-mifepristone-medical-termination-pregnancy-through-ten-weeks-gestation" target="_blank">&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/questions-and-answers-mifepristone-medical-termination-pregnancy-through-ten-weeks-gestation" target="_blank">previous agency statement</a> asserting the FDA “is taking care to do this study properly and in the right way.”</p> 
<p>“We are planning to complete the study as soon as possible while ensuring we are not cutting any corners from a scientific research standpoint,” the statement reads, adding that such reviews “often take approximately a year or more to conduct.”</p> 
<p>Conservative anger with the Trump administration has boiled over in recent months over its decision to leave in place Biden-era rules that<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/01/03/justice-department-postal-abortion-drugs-00076274" target="_blank">&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/01/03/justice-department-postal-abortion-drugs-00076274" target="_blank">expanded access to abortion pills via mail</a> and telemedicine, and for approving a new generic version of the drug. Administration officials took narrower steps in January to roll back access to mifepristone at retail pharmacies, but the anti-abortion movement and its allies in Congress are pressuring the FDA to abolish telemedicine prescription of the pills or ban them altogether.</p> 
<p>At the same time, several GOP states are suing the agency, including Cassidy’s Louisiana and Hawley’s Missouri. The administration has tried to rebuff these lawsuits, asking judges to wait until FDA’s ongoing study is completed before issuing a ruling. Anti-abortion activists, tired of waiting, have threatened to withhold resources from the GOP in the upcoming midterm elections if they don’t see action on the drugs.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dems challenge Pam Bondi to address Epstein's victims at House Judiciary hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/dems-challenge-bondi-on-epstein-00775809</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d50-d647-addc-efd783a70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:53:05 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are challenging Attorney General Pam Bondi to address the victims of Jeffrey Epstein, who are seated behind her during a House Judiciary Committee oversight hearing of the Justice Department.</p> 
<p>The panel's top Democrat, Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, used his opening remarks to introduce Bondi to Epstein's victims, setting the tone for the tough questions she's expected to face for her handling of the case against the convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>“To promote justice for the people, you’ve got to listen to the victims, like the women seated behind you today,” said Raskin. “Those are just some of the hundreds of survivors of Jeffrey Epstein's global sex trafficking ring who are demanding that the truth be told and are demanding accountability for the abusers who trafficked and raped them.”</p> 
<p>Raskin added that Bondi had not yet met with those victims.</p> 
<p>In her own opening remarks, Bondi defended her handling of the Epstein files and maintained that if victims’ names were inadvertently released, her department has moved swiftly to correct those mistakes.</p> 
<p>She opted to directly address the victims seated behind her.</p> 
<p>“I’m a career prosecutor and despite what the ranking member said, I have spent my entire career fighting for victims, and I will continue to do so," Bondi said. "I am deeply sorry for what any victim, any victim, has been through, especially as a result of that monster.”</p> 
<p>She added that the FBI was waiting to hear from those with information.</p> 
<p>But when asked by Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) to turn around and directly address the victims and apologize for what the Justice Department has put them through, Bondi refused.</p> 
<p>"I am not going to get in the gutter for her theatrics," Bondi said of Jayapal.</p> 
<p>Jayapal also asked the Epstein victims seated in the hearing room to stand and raise their hands if they have not been able to meet with the Justice Department to share their stories. Everyone did.</p> 
<p>Bondi has faced criticism for months for reneging on her commitment to bring transparency in the Epstein case, starting with when <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/25/lawmakers-pressure-pam-bondi-release-epstein[…]ref_fark&amp;utm_content=link&amp;utm_medium=website&amp;utm_source=fark" target="_blank">she told Fox News</a>last year that Epstein-related materials were “on [her] desk right now to review" but then in July announced no such files would be released.</p> 
<p>Since Congress passed legislation compelling the Justice Department to release the Epstein files in their near-entirety, the administration has blown past statutory deadlines to do so. A bipartisan group of lawmakers has complained in recent days that some redactions were overly broad, while other materials appeared to jeopardize the privacy of Epstein’s victims.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tillis pans ‘political lawfare’ after grand jury declines to indict Democratic lawmakers</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/tillis-on-lawfare-00775810</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d52-d0f8-adde-ff5a9b510000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:31:50 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican Sen. Thom Tillis slammed the Justice Department’s push to criminally charge Democratic lawmakers who last November urged military servicemembers to disobey illegal orders in a video, calling it “political lawfare” in a post on X on Wednesday.</p> 
<p>A Washington, D.C., <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/lawmakers-military-orders-grand-jury-indictment-00775504" target="_blank">grand jury on Tuesday declined to</a> indict the six lawmakers, who include battleground state Sens. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.) and Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.). It marked another instance of U.S. Attorney Jeanine Pirro failing to clinch a high-profile federal indictment since taking over as the top prosecutor in D.C.</p> 
<p>“Political lawfare waged by either side undermines America's criminal justice system, which is the gold standard of the world,” <a href="https://x.com/SenThomTillis/status/2021577817868095796" target="_blank">Tillis wrote</a>. “Thankfully in this instance, a jury saw the attempted indictments for what they really were. Political lawfare is not normal, not acceptable, and needs to stop.”</p> 
<p>The White House referred POLITICO to the Department of Justice, which did not immediately respond to a request for comment on the North Carolina Republican’s social media post.</p> 
<p>Kelly and Slotkin were joined in the video by Pennsylvania Democratic Reps. Chris Deluzio and Chrissy Houlahan, and also Reps. Jason Crow of Colorado and Maggie Goodlander of New Hampshire.</p> 
<p>“Like us, you all swore an oath to protect and defend this Constitution,” they said. “Right now, the threats to our Constitution aren’t just coming from abroad, but from right here at home. Our laws are clear, you can refuse illegal orders.”</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">Truth Social spree that followed</a>, President Donald Trump called for the lawmakers to face trial for “seditious behavior” and reshared a post that advocated for hanging the Democrats.</p> 
<p>The two-term senator has been a thorn in Trump’s side even before he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/29/thom-tillis-retires-00432045" target="_blank">declared he wouldn’t seek reelection last June</a>. Tillis <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/28/congress/donald-trump-threatens-thom-tillis-00431472" target="_blank">voted against the Big Beautiful Bill</a>, Trump's signature domestic policy package, last year after expressing major concerns with its effects on Medicaid. He’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/blogs/politico-press/2026/01/30/full-transcript-sen-thom-tillis-on-the-conversation-with-dasha-burns-00757104" target="_blank">called for the sacking</a> of Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem and White House deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller. And he’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/greenland-trump-republicans-congress-00732945" target="_blank">called for greater congressional cooperation</a> in the wake of Trump’s ambitions to expand into Greenland.</p> 
<p>This isn’t the first time Pirro has struggled to persuade a grand jury to indict subjects who draw the ire of the Trump administration. After a panel last August declined to grant a felony indictment against a former DOJ employee who threw a hoagie at a federal officer in Washington, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/31/pirro-washington-crime-sandwich-thrower-00538780" target="_blank">she lamented that DC residents</a> “were so used to crime” and “don’t even care about whether or not the law is violated” in an interview with Fox News.</p> 
<p>“My office has been instructed to move for the highest crime possible, consistent with the law, the statute, and the evidence. And in that one case, in that particular article, we were on point,” she said. “But the grand jurors don’t take it so seriously. They’re like, ‘Ah, you know, whatever.’”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>US debt forecast to hit $64T in a decade as Trump policies widen deficit  </title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/us-debt-forecast-to-hit-64t-in-a-decade-as-trump-policies-widen-deficit-00775726</link>
      <description>Congress’ nonpartisan scorekeeper predicts that the annual deficit will grow to $3.1 trillion by 2036.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d19-d3b5-addf-eddd7fa30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:00:22 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a7/d1/ab32a83f41ef81a799606189abd1/u-s-congress-88781.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>The U.S. Capitol building is seen Jan. 12, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a7/d1/ab32a83f41ef81a799606189abd1/u-s-congress-88781.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The U.S. national debt is on track to reach $64 trillion within a decade as the federal government continues its trend of red-ink balances under President Donald Trump and Republican control of Congress.</p> 
<p>The Congressional Budget Office released its <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-4d22-d3b5-addf-ede6923c0000" target="_blank">marquee report</a> Wednesday on the U.S. fiscal outlook, estimating that the tax and spending package Republicans enacted last summer — along with Trump’s immigration policies — will increase deficits by trillions of dollars over the next decade. That budget gap would essentially cancel out the roughly $3 trillion in deficit reduction Trump’s tariffs are expected to produce.</p> 
<p>Congress’ nonpartisan scorekeeper predicts that the U.S. will run a $1.9 trillion deficit during the current fiscal year as the national debt currently exceeds $38 trillion. The annual deficit is then forecast to grow to $3.1 trillion by 2036.</p> 
<p>Growing interest costs and spending on safety-net programs drives the expanding gap between how much money flows into federal coffers each year and how much is doled out.</p> 
<p>Debt compared to economic output is also on track to soar in the coming years. CBO predicts that federal debt held by the public will rise from 101 percent of gross domestic product this year to 120 percent in a decade, exceeding the previous high of 106 percent of GDP in 1946.</p> 
<p>As the CBO <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/12/cbo-economic-growth-estimate-trump-00560730" target="_blank">predicted last summer</a>, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/house-passes-gop-megabill-00438206" target="_blank">Republican megabill Trump signed into law in July</a> will help boost economic growth this year. But that will be partially offset by the economic effects of Trump’s tariffs and increased immigration enforcement.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: House set to rebuke Trump’s tariffs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/house-votes-trump-tariffs-resolution-canada-00775520</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4b4e-d3b5-addf-ebce31e10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House is set to rebuke Donald Trump’s signature economic policy Wednesday following Speaker Mike Johnson’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/gop-revolt-sinks-effort-to-block-votes-on-trumps-tariffs-00775107" target="_blank">failure late last night</a> to contain GOP unrest over the administration’s trade war.</p> 
<p>The chamber will vote on a resolution offered by Democratic Rep. Gregory Meeks (N.Y.) to overturn the president’s Canadian tariffs. It comes after GOP Reps. Kevin Kiley of California, Don Bacon of Nebraska and Thomas Massie of Kentucky sided with Democrats to tank a procedural rule, which contained a provision GOP leaders have relied upon for months to prevent members from voting to undermine Trump’s trade agenda.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think that the House should be limiting the authority of members and enlarging the power of leadership at the expense of our members,” Kiley told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>Now the House will vote Wednesday afternoon on the Meeks resolution. And thanks to a combination of Johnson’s razor-thin majority, Democratic unity and expected Republican defections, that measure is expected to be approved — it’s only a question of, by how much.</p> 
<p>Besides Kiley, Bacon and Massie, keep an eye on Republican Reps. Dan Newhouse (Wash.) and Zach Nunn (Iowa), who held out on voting for the rule Tuesday night before eventually folding. Newhouse in particular was subject to a full-court press on the House floor from House Majority Leader Steve Scalise and Majority Whip Tom Emmer. Reps. Tom McClintock (R-Calif.) and Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) have also been uneasy about the tariffs.</p> 
<p>No longer held back, Democrats can and likely will continue to force votes on other resolutions to overturn Trump’s tariffs on goods from Mexico and Brazil, following the example of senators who have successfully voted across party lines to curb the administration’s trade activities.</p> 
<p>“What we want to show is that really this should be a bipartisan issue,” Meeks told reporters Tuesday. “The American people are watching to see what we do in this issue.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— DHS negotiations: </b>Senate Majority Leader John Thune took the first procedural step Tuesday toward allowing the Senate to vote on another DHS funding punt. But Democratic support will be necessary to get a continuing resolution for the agency over the finish line. A DHS shutdown at the end of the week is near certain, with no deal in sight.</p> 
<p><b>— Schumer seeks Venezuela probe: </b>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer and Sen. Adam Schiff (D-Calif.) are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/schumer-pressure-trump-venezuela-oil-fund-00775358" target="_blank">rolling out legislation Wednesday</a> that would direct the Government Accountability Office to investigate the Trump administration’s handling of proceedings from Venezuelan oil sales. Their bill, shared first with POLITICO, would require GAO to launch the audit within 30 days and report its findings to Congress within 90 days of completion.</p> 
<p><b>— Bondi in the hot seat: </b>Attorney General Pam Bondi will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-house-judiciary-tesitmony-00775441" target="_blank">testify before the House Judiciary Committee</a> Wednesday as the Department of Justice faces scrutiny over its handling of the Jeffrey Epstein files, prosecution of former Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro and response to the fatal shootings by federal agents of two U.S. citizens in Minnesota.</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor, James Bikales and Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump keeps driving online fundraising — for both parties</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/political-donations-trump-fundraising-00774862</link>
      <description>The GOP president is dominating his own party’s online fundraising and proving a major driver for Democrats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4993-d3b5-addf-e9d75cb70001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f3/17/05cb869f497d9f77436aa363ef2b/main-piper-onlinefundraising-illustration.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Jade Cuevas/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images and iStock)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Donald Trump continues to best Republicans' best online fundraiser, even as he is constitutionally barred from running for office again.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f3/17/05cb869f497d9f77436aa363ef2b/main-piper-onlinefundraising-illustration.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump still raises far more money online than any other GOP figure.</p> 
<p>Democrats get major fundraising boosts when they clash with him.</p> 
<p>And the Democratic money machine continues to churn — a sign of hope for a party seeking to regroup from brutal losses the year prior.</p> 
<p>Those are among the key patterns that appeared in a POLITICO analysis of online fundraising across 2025, as both parties began to gear up for highly competitive midterms.</p> 
<p>The sweeping POLITICO analysis of data from ActBlue and WinRed — the primary fundraising platforms for each party — revealed how Trump, who is constitutionally barred from seeking reelection, is still at the center of the GOP’s digital and financial universe. And while Democrats continue to debate how much they should focus on opposing Trump in their broader campaign messaging, the data shows just how strongly the GOP president motivates liberal donors.</p> 
<p>Major surges in online Democratic fundraising were fueled by members of the party standing up to — or being attacked by — the president. Democratic candidates’ biggest fundraising days on ActBlue were all driven by conflict with Trump, with those days accounting for millions of dollars raised from tens of thousands of donors giving online for the first time this cycle.</p> 
<p>Among Republicans, Trump’s own joint fundraising committee, Trump National Committee, continued to raise the most money out of anyone on WinRed in 2025, bringing more over the course of the year than the next two biggest GOP groups combined. Trump’s political operation accounted for more than 1 in 5 total dollars raised federally through WinRed last year.<br></p><p>ActBlue and WinRed report all donations made to federal campaigns and committees through their platforms, providing a detailed picture of small-dollar giving. The platforms are so dominant that they include the vast majority, though not all, of online donations for both parties.</p> 
<p>The data provides insight not only into who raised the most but the specific moments that drove donors to give.</p> 
<p>Leading the way was Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/211545" data-person-id="211545">Cory Booker</a> (D-N.J.), who saw a massive surge in donations when he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/01/cory-booker-record-breaking-senate-speech-00265142" target="_blank">broke records with a 25-hour quasi-filibuster speech</a> protesting the Trump administration’s policies.</p> 
<p>Booker’s campaign committee received nearly 92,000 donations totaling $2.5 million on ActBlue on April 2, the day after his speech finished. It was the highest single-day total for any federal committee on the platform in 2025. For roughly a third of those donors, it was their first donation of the year on ActBlue.</p> 
<p>The New Jersey senator was not the only Democrat to get a donation boost off of standing up to Trump. California Gov. Gavin Newsom’s joint fundraising committee saw a massive surge in donations in early June after he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/11/california-national-guard-deployment-lawsuit-00400503" target="_blank">sued the Trump administration</a> to block the deployment of the National Guard to Los Angeles and Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/09/donald-trump-on-arresting-gavin-newsom-id-do-it-00394530" target="_blank">suggested arresting</a> the governor. The group, Campaign for Democracy, recorded more than 47,000 donations on June 11, for a total of $1.3 million.</p> 
<p>That was the start of a three-day surge that accounted for nearly one-third of all online donations to the Newsom joint fundraising committee in 2025.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/163882" data-person-id="163882">Mark Kelly</a> (D-Ariz.) saw nearly 43,000 donations for a total of nearly $1.3 million to his campaign committee Nov. 25 after Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894" target="_blank">ordered the Pentagon to investigate</a> whether a video that featured Kelly and others advising troops not to follow illegal orders was itself unlawful. Roughly 1 in 5 donations on the platform that day went to Kelly’s campaign.</p> 
<p>Kelly then remained the top fundraiser nearly every day for three weeks after that, bringing in donations from about 278,000 unique donors in November and December. That surge set Kelly apart from other Democratic figures last year for both its intensity and duration. The POLITICO analysis found that more than three-quarters of donors in that time period had not given to Kelly previously in the year. For 1 in 5 of his donors, it was the first time they’d given to any Democrat through ActBlue in the entire year.</p> 
<p>Kelly’s strong preexisting brand helped him leverage the attack from Trump into a fundraising bonanza, said Mike Nellis, a democratic digital strategist and founder of the firm Authentic.</p> 
<p>“You can raise a ton of money by just opposing Trump,” Nellis said. “But if you want to elevate yourself into that stratosphere of becoming a household name that people believe in, with Democratic donors who are going to give you $5, $10, $25, over and over and over, you’ve got to go a little bit deeper.”</p> 
<p>Democrats’ dream of flipping the Senate also fueled massive contributions. A handful of Senate candidates — Roy Cooper in North Carolina, Sherrod Brown in Ohio, Janet Mills in Maine and both James Talarico and Jasmine Crockett in Texas — were the top Democratic online fundraisers when they launched their respective campaigns.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/34364" data-person-id="34364">Jon Ossoff</a> (D-Ga.), the only incumbent Democratic senator seeking reelection in a state Trump won in 2024, brought in $32.5 million through ActBlue in 2025, more than any other candidate on the platform. Democrats running in competitive Senate races this year were consistently among the top overall fundraisers on ActBlue, as was the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee itself.</p> 
<p>The online fundraising landscape for Democrats looking to take back the House was more muddled, with the top fundraising numbers coming more often from progressive stars than candidates in competitive races.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/304452" data-person-id="304452">Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez</a> (D-N.Y.), long a fundraising powerhouse, raised $22.8 million on ActBlue in 2025, the most of any House Democrat, followed by House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>, who raised just shy of $11 million through his campaign and joint fundraising committee, then Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/482861" data-person-id="482861">Eugene Vindman</a> (D-Va.) and Eileen Laubacher, one of the Democrats seeking to challenge Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/356900" data-person-id="356900">Lauren Boebert</a> (R-Colo.) in a heavily Republican district.</p> 
<p>Those House candidates reflect a few of the different ways that virality can help online fundraising. More than 400,000 donors gave to Ocasio-Cortez’s campaign more than once in 2025, reflecting her strength with returning donors. Laubacher’s numbers reflect how running in a district represented by a high-profile Republican can attract Democratic donors — even as she still has to get through a primary to face Boebert.</p> 
<p>But vulnerable Democratic House incumbents and candidates running in some of the most competitive battlegrounds were not represented among those with the best online fundraising numbers — a challenge for party strategists as they fight for the resources to flip the House.</p> 
<p>“The things that work to raise money from small donors are the opposite of the things that work to beat MAGA,” said Liam Kerr, co-founder of the centrist Democratic group WelcomePAC.</p> 
<p>At the same time, Kerr said that there was enough variety in the candidates who put up strong online fundraising numbers to suggest that more moderate candidates can make inroads.</p> 
<p>Donors give, Kerr said, because they want to “feel like they're part of something.” If candidates in key races can start to capture the attention of donors across the country, then, he said, “the base of the raged donor class would start to shift to what they thought could beat Trump.”</p> 
<p><i>Methodology: Donations and monetary totals are based on ActBlue and WinRed receipts, not reports from campaigns. Donations that were later refunded are still included in the totals.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Dems think they have the upper hand at Pam Bondi’s big Hill hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-house-judiciary-tesitmony-00775441</link>
      <description>The attorney general could have to answer for the Trump administration’s handling of immigration enforcement, military action in Venezuela and the Epstein files.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4a9c-d647-addc-ebdfd5b70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0e/ff/a2f449dc487d9d6701f7d71f067d/u-s-congress-88677.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Attorney General Pam Bondi testifies before the Senate Judiciary Committee on Capitol Hill, Oct. 7, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0e/ff/a2f449dc487d9d6701f7d71f067d/u-s-congress-88677.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi will testify Wednesday before the House Judiciary Committee amid a barrage of controversies that would ordinarily portend a dicey bipartisan grilling.</p> 
<p>The nation’s top law enforcement officer is being scrutinized for the Justice Department’s handling of the Jeffrey Epstein investigation, with files being released well past the statutory deadline and redactions appearing to defy the law’s requirements.</p> 
<p>Bondi’s department is overseeing the prosecution of former Venezuela President Nicolás Maduro, who was forcibly removed from his country by U.S. troops in an operation that has prompted a flurry of legal questions. Her agency is also being pressured to investigate and bring charges against the federal agents who fatally shot two U.S. citizens in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“It’s very hard to narrow down all of the lawlessness and gross abuse of power that this Department of Justice has engaged in in just one year,” said Rep. Dan Goldman (D-N.Y.), a member of the committee, in an interview. “She’s been trying to avoid us, but she can't avoid us any longer.”</p> 
<p>But other than Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), who said he plans to pepper Bondi over the Epstein saga, Republicans on the panel don’t appear to be clamoring to challenge Bondi on any of it.</p> 
<p>Asked his priorities for the hearing, House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan in an interview said he wanted to hear about the newly appointed senior DOJ official focused on fraud, the now-defunct investigation into President Donald Trump and “the good work they've done on just regularly prosecuting bad guys.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Glenn Grothman (R-Wis.) said he intends to ask Bondi about efforts to overhaul election law, while Rep. Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.) suggested he would question her about the department’s work to protect what he called “the rights of parents.”</p> 
<p>“It’ll be fun,” Kiley added.</p> 
<p>It’s not unusual for Cabinet officials to confront a hospitable audience when the majority shares the party affiliation of the administration in power, but Democrats think the stack of high-profile dramas encircling Bondi could give them a unique opportunity — namely by drawing out the GOP’s anticipated silence on the hot-button issues and the attorney general’s expected refusal to engage in Democratic questioning.</p> 
<p>“The Department of Justice has been found to be lying by federal courts across the land — they have withheld evidence, they have misled the court, they've shown spectacular disrespect for the rule of law and the integrity of the courts,” said Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, in an interview. “So, I think as little respect as they have for the courts, they probably have less for Congress.”</p> 
<p>But, Raskin said, Democrats plan “to engage in some exchanges that will spotlight some of the worst depredations of the Trump Justice Department, and we hope the mobilization of public opinion will allow us to make some progress in some areas.”</p> 
<p>He told reporters that Democrats will ask about the DOJ’s process for releasing the Epstein files that “produced such flawed results” in its production of the materials.</p> 
<p>Democrats also say they’re ready for Bondi to deflect member questions by personally attacking lawmakers.</p> 
<p>When she appeared before the Senate Judiciary Committee in October, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/07/congress/bondi-goes-after-schiff-00596375" target="_blank">she told Sen. Adam Schiff (D-Calif.)</a> to “apologize” for trying to impeach Trump and accused Sen. Dick Durbin of being unwilling “<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/07/congress/pam-bondi-spars-with-dick-durbin-00596234" target="_blank">to protect your citizens</a>” when the Illinois Democrat asked about National Guard deployment to his state.</p> 
<p>She also punted a question on Epstein back to Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse (D-R.I.) over campaign donations of which there is no record with the Federal Election Commission, then levied a bizarre charge that he had pushed legislation that would subsidize his wife’s company.</p> 
<p>“We've all noticed that at prior hearings, when she's afraid to answer a question, she attacks the members of Congress,” Rep. Ted Lieu of California, a member of House Democratic leadership who also sits on the Judiciary Committee, said in an interview. “So if she starts doing that, you know she's afraid to answer a question, and she's engaged in a cover-up, so the American people will be able to see what she does on Wednesday.”</p> 
<p>Bondi could go after Rep. Eric Swalwell (D-Calif.), a longtime vocal foe of the Trump administration who is now running for governor and has drawn past scrutiny for an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/12/10/pelosi-swalwell-chinese-spy-444308" target="_blank">alleged connection</a> to a suspected Chinese spy. House Republicans removed him from the Intelligence Committee, but the Ethics Committee abandoned its investigation into the matter in 2023.</p> 
<p>It’s possible Republicans on the House Judiciary Committee offer veiled criticism of the Justice Department’s immigration policies following the violent confrontations in Minnesota. House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/ice-todd-lyons-dhs-funding-hearing-00774309" target="_blank">said at a hearing</a> with some of the Trump administration’s top immigration officials Tuesday that “when officials or elected leaders rush to conclusions about law enforcement or their fellow Americans, public trust suffers.”</p> 
<p>But most of the Republicans who sit on the House Judiciary dais are staunch Trump loyalists unlikely to be out of lockstep with Bondi. Massie, who Trump is now trying to primary out of office after multiple defections, could be the sole exception.</p> 
<p>“It probably wouldn’t surprise you or her that it’s probably going to be Epstein-focused,” Massie said of his plans for questioning Bondi. But he wouldn’t offer any previews: “I don’t want her to know.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Here's where — and when — a DHS shutdown would cause pain for the public</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499</link>
      <description>Immigration and border security agencies wouldn’t as affected in a funding lapse as other parts of the department.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4ab0-d0f8-adde-fafaec2a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/af/01/f9a850184d2ca3d20c735aedb33f/u-s-congress-37856.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem could find creative ways to lessen the pain of a shutdown.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/af/01/f9a850184d2ca3d20c735aedb33f/u-s-congress-37856.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Maggie Miller</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Maggie Miller</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There’s nothing like the ire of constituents to motivate lawmakers to end a government shutdown. But it could take weeks for the public to start noticing the funding lapse set to hit DHS on Saturday if Congress doesn’t act.</p> 
<p>TSA airport screeners, for instance, wouldn't miss full paychecks until March, and billions of dollars remain in the FEMA coffers used for immediate response to disasters like hurricanes, tornadoes and floods.</p> 
<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem could find creative ways to lessen the pain of a shutdown. That could include bankrolling paychecks for DHS law enforcement personnel and active-duty members of the Coast Guard by tapping money from the tax and spending package Republicans enacted last summer, as the agency did during the shutdown last fall.</p> 
<p>This could decrease pressure on lawmakers to fund DHS amid negotiations over a crackdown on the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement tactics. Congress doesn’t have forever, though, before the pain starts to kick in across the department.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Immigration and border security</h5> 
<p>The Trump administration's immigration and border security operations are at the heart of the partisan dispute that could spark a shutdown. Compared to other parts of the agency, though, the federal government’s three immigration-focused agencies aren’t as affected by funding lapses.</p> 
<p>About 40 percent of funding for Immigration and Customs Enforcement, Customs and Border Protection and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services is untouched by a lapse. That’s because the agencies receive a combination of mandatory funds, revenue from fees and billions of dollars from the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_1" target="_blank">GOP megabill</a> Trump signed into law in 2025.</p> 
<p>Of the three, CBP relies most on the cash Congress provides each year in the regular government funding bills. But the agency received $65 billion from the party-line legislation Republicans cleared last summer, in addition to the $75 billion the law included for ICE.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">TSA</h5> 
<p>When airport security screeners start missing pay, many stop showing up to work, causing TSA lines to grow at hubs throughout the country. In prior shutdowns, that started happening about a month in.</p> 
<p>This time, screeners would begin missing full paychecks in mid-March, likely spurring longer waits during the peak of spring break travel.</p> 
<p>While DHS paid air marshals during the historic government shutdown last fall, that didn’t cover checks for the TSA screeners who keep people and their baggage moving through U.S. airports.</p> 
<p>One factor that could motivate TSA agents to show up to work anyway is the $10,000 bonuses DHS officials gave to screeners who demonstrated “exemplary service” after the funding lapse that ran through October and into November.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">FEMA</h5> 
<p>FEMA has about $7 billion left in its disaster relief fund, a sum likely to buoy the agency for at least a month or two. While most of the agency’s disaster aid work continues during a government shutdown, though, FEMA would have to start restricting its reimbursements to states.</p> 
<p>During past funding lapses, FEMA deemed roughly 85 percent of its 25,000 employees “essential,” meaning they had to continue coming to work without pay, and it continued processing disaster aid applications from individuals.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Coast Guard</h5> 
<p>The Coast Guard’s work alongside the military in missions abroad would continue during a funding lapse. But the service could have to halt some work including family support services and efforts to buy new cutters.</p> 
<p>During the record-setting shutdown late last year, DHS dipped into a $10 billion pot of money from the GOP megabill to pay about 68,000 workers, including some law enforcement personnel and active duty members of the Coast Guard, to the tune of about $1 billion each pay period.</p> 
<p>If DHS shuts down again, department officials could do the same for several months before exhausting the account, which was replenished after the government reopened in mid-November.</p> 
<p>Coast Guard contractors and employees who are not active duty were not paid during the fall shutdown, however. And contractors are not guaranteed back pay, even though all federal employees, whether furloughed or not, are eligible for back pay after a shutdown under a law enacted in the wake of the funding lapse that ended in 2019.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Cybersecurity</h5> 
<p>The Trump administration has previously designated only about a third of federal workers as essential at the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency during a government shutdown.</p> 
<p>That limits the workforce that scans and protects U.S. networks from cyber incursions. It also hinders CISA’s ability to help state and local officials defend against cyber threats and assist other agencies with security patches.</p> 
<p>Even before Congress let any federal funding lapse in recent months, the Trump administration had already considerably downsized the agency. Around a third of its employees were either <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/05/cisa-layoffs-hundreds-deferred-resignation-offers-00346299" target="_blank">laid off</a><a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/05/top-cisa-leaders-to-depart-this-week-as-the-cyber-agency-continues-to-shrink-00371297" target="_blank">or quit</a> over the last year, then dozens were permanently shifted to other DHS agencies during the shutdown that ended in November.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Secret Service</h5> 
<p>Most of the Secret Service’s workforce is kept on during a shutdown, sometimes including employees in charge of recruitment, training and communications. But personnel who do jobs in offices like human resources and finance are typically furloughed.</p> 
<p>After Trump was shot at a campaign rally in 2024, the Secret Service significantly elevated the level of security it provides to the more than 40 people the agency is tasked with protecting, among them former presidents. During a government shutdown, the agency is more selective about how it spends money to safeguard those people.</p> 
<p>Like other DHS agencies, the Secret Service also got money from the GOP’s 2025 tax and spending package that can be used during a funding lapse. That included almost $1.2 billion to cover a wide range of expenses such as training facility costs, technology and bonuses.</p> 
<p><i>Thomas Frank, Paroma Soni, Leo Shane III and Andres Picon contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filibuster fight comes full circle as GOP faces internal pressure on elections bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/senate-filibuster-gop-save-act-00775393</link>
      <description>Sen. Mike Lee and other hard-liners want to pursue the “talking filibuster.” Their colleagues are skeptical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4a38-d0f8-adde-fa7a441b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:30:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/54/c1/b62b6dd54b68830aea65790b522e/u-s-congress-31702.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mike Lee (R-Utah) has been at the front of the push for the SAVE America Act.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/54/c1/b62b6dd54b68830aea65790b522e/u-s-congress-31702.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans are facing a full-circle moment on the filibuster.</p> 
<p>Four years ago, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/01/19/democrats-senate-rules-change-527366" target="_blank">GOP stood united</a> against a failed attempt by Democrats to sidestep the chamber’s 60-vote supermajority requirement and pass a voting-rights bill demanded by their party base. Now — with their own trifecta and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499?can_id=71597c61003cabad9b09c8444aa14487&amp;email_referrer=email_3092311&amp;email_subject=bumping-this-sign-and-send-a-letter-to-your-members-of-congress-opposing-the-save-act-which-would-impose-significant-new-documentation-requirements-when-registering-to-vote&amp;link_id=1&amp;source=email-sign-and-send-a-letter-to-your-members-of-congress-opposing-the-save-act-which-would-impose-significant-new-documentation-requirements-when-registering-to-vote" target="_blank">their own elections bill</a> at issue — Republicans are under pressure to do much the same.</p> 
<p>The shoe-on-the-other-foot moment is being fueled by a cadre of hard-right senators arguing forcefully for tactics once embraced by Senate progressives. Many Democrats, meanwhile, are keeping silent and watching as the GOP undergoes similar internal turmoil to what they had experienced in the majority.</p> 
<p>Only a few, like Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska), have acknowledged the irony of the moment — noting in a statement Tuesday that the push for the <a href="https://x.com/lisamurkowski/status/2021245420303782254?s=20" target="_blank">GOP elections bill</a> looks a lot like what Democrats had previously attempted.</p> 
<p>“Once again, I do not support these efforts,” she said in a statement. “Ensuring public trust in our elections is at the core of our democracy, but federal overreach is not how we achieve this.”</p> 
<p>But the dial on the intraparty pressure cooker is set to ratchet up Wednesday, when House Republicans are expected to pass the SAVE America Act and send it to the Senate. Backed by an Elon Musk-driven public pressure campaign, the conservative hard-liners are working overtime to bend their GOP colleagues toward allowing a “talking filibuster” — a strategy they believe will ultimately allow the Senate to act on a simple-majority basis.</p> 
<p>Much as Democrats said their voting-rights legislation dealt with existential issues of democracy that necessitated an exception to the filibuster, GOP Sen. Mike Lee of Utah and his allies argue SAVE America is essential to securing elections — including the upcoming midterms — from a purported surge of noncitizen voting.</p> 
<p>The bill would mandate voters present proof of citizenship, such as a passport or birth certificate, to register and would require photo ID to vote in every state, among other changes, and has garnered strong backing from President Donald Trump. The push to make Democrats hold the floor indefinitely if they want to block it has picked up support from many of Trump’s GOP allies in the Senate.</p> 
<p>“I’m a fan of the talking filibuster … especially as Democrats have proven more and more obstructionist,” Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said.</p> 
<p>Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas) said forcing a talking filibuster is “exactly what we should do” and that he’s “making the case vigorously” for it.</p> 
<p>But many other Senate Republicans are wary of any step that further waters down the 60-vote margin after both parties have already diluted it over the past decade. Once a majority makes an exception for one bill, Republicans argue it will effectively mark the beginning of the end for the legislative filibuster — something many of them see as a bulwark against big-government Democratic policies, not an obstacle to GOP priorities.</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said he was not eager to rejoin a battle that has resulted in party-line confirmations of presidential nominees after a series of partisan escalations involving the so-called “nuclear option.”</p> 
<p>Tillis said he did not see a substantial difference between those sorts of rules changes and instead by trying to force Democrats into a talking filibuster, which GOP proponents suggest would not require going nuclear. Both, he said, have the “same fundamental message.”</p> 
<p>Lee has been urging his legion of X followers to reach out to his GOP colleagues, seeking to build public pressure on them to support the voting bill even if it means throwing them into a filibuster fight they don’t want.</p> 
<p>He also gave a presentation on his talking filibuster proposal during a closed-door GOP lunch Tuesday, and the topic is expected to come up again Wednesday when Senate Republicans hold a private retreat on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, a band of ultraconservatives in the House, led by Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), is trying to focus pressure on Senate Majority Leader John Thune. Luna told reporters last week that she had received “assurances” that the Senate would allow a talking filibuster for the voting bill — something Thune denied.</p> 
<p>The multifront push has sparked frustration among Senate Republicans, according to two people granted anonymity to speak candidly, who warned that trying to put words in Thune and other GOP senators' mouths was only undermining her cause.</p> 
<p>A GOP senator who granted anonymity to disclose private discussions said that while Lee gave a good presentation during Tuesday’s lunch, “a lot of people in the room are sick of Mike Lee fundraising off of it.”</p> 
<p>“It’s a political spectacle,” the senator added. “It’s never going to happen. It doesn’t work.”</p> 
<p>Republican senators have raised concerns that pursuing a talking filibuster strategy would require either eating up potentially weeks of floor time with no guarantee of success or pursuing strategies that would require procedural votes that would essentially require 50 GOP lawmakers to sidestep recent Senate precedent — a hurdle they wouldn’t be able to clear.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Lee did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Republicans have been privately circulating op-eds <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/bench-memos/the-talking-filibuster-quagmire/" target="_blank">detailing the procedural headaches</a> they could invite upon themselves if they backed Lee’s idea. And they’ve warned that opening up the floor to unlimited amendments could set the stage for Democrats to hijack any bill and turn it into a health care bill or tariff bill or any other proposal they could get a majority to support.</p> 
<p>Many GOP senators aside from Tillis, who is retiring, are starting to speak out against the idea — including Sen. John Curtis of Utah, <a href="https://x.com/SenJohnCurtis/status/2019088376066957731?s=20" target="_blank">who said that</a> “for those concerned in the House, I also oppose skirting around the filibuster.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Kevin Cramer of North Dakota predicted that it wouldn’t go anywhere and summed up his own position as “not interested.”</p> 
<p>One Democrat who has closely studied the issue, Sen. Jeff Merkley of Oregon, said he relished the idea of a “talking filibuster.” During the Biden-era debates over voting legislation, he put forward a <a href="https://www.merkley.senate.gov/jeff-merkley-circulates-talking-filibuster-reform-proposal/" target="_blank">proposal of his own</a> — albeit with rules changes that would ultimately allow debate to end.</p> 
<p>“If they’re operating within the existing rules and looking to have an extended debate where they maintain a quorum and go day and night … I say thumbs up,” Merkley said.</p> 
<p>Thune has vowed to put the SAVE America Act up for a Senate vote at some point after it comes over from the House, and he said he was open to discussions about getting it passed. But he reiterated Tuesday that changing the 60-vote filibuster through a party-line vote is an idea “that doesn’t have a future.”</p> 
<p>Asked later if he knew how a “talking filibuster” could work without a prolonged floor battle — something the South Dakota Republican warned could derail other GOP priorities — Thune started laughing.</p> 
<p>“No, I don’t,” Thune said. “It takes you back over 100 years. So, unlimited debate and unlimited amendments. … Nobody knows.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Leo Shane III contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-11T21:48:40-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Dan Osborn cancels fundraiser after co-host’s Epstein link surfaces</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/dan-osborn-dana-chasin-fundraiser-00775138</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-49c6-d3b5-addf-e9c666030000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:04:52 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Lippman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Lippman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nebraska Senate candidate Dan Osborn abruptly canceled a <a href="https://www.politico.com/osborn_invite" target="_blank">Tuesday fundraiser</a> that was set to be co-hosted by a Democratic operative who was mentioned in the recently released Jeffrey Epstein files as allegedly transporting young girls for the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>Dana Chasin — a Rockefeller heir who advised Hillary Clinton’s 2016 presidential campaign as well as former Sens. Tim Johnson (D-S.D.) and Jon Tester (D-Mont.) — was listed on an invitation for the Washington event benefiting Osborn, who is running against GOP Sen. Pete Ricketts as an independent.</p> 
<p>His name <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2012/EFTA02731721.pdf" target="_blank">appears in a March 2024 email</a> sent to a Justice Department attorney by Jeanne Christensen, a lawyer representing a young unnamed woman who alleged Chasin flew her on a private plane to Epstein’s Manhattan townhouse for sex with powerful men. The email, which details allegations of sexual abuse, also mentions a second flight with Chasin but does not make a direct accusation against him.</p> 
<p>In a statement sent Wednesday, after publication, Chasin said that “nothing pertaining to me in the March 2024 email” was true.</p> 
<p>He said he had never met Epstein, Ghislaine Maxwell or other prominent men mentioned in the emails or had any relationship with them.</p> 
<p>“Furthermore, I have never owned or rented a prop plane, or any plane for that matter,” he said in an email. “I stand with the victims of Jeffrey Epstein and their pursuit of justice and accountability.”</p> 
<p>Christensen did not respond to an email seeking comment. A spokesperson for her firm, Wigdor, declined to comment.</p> 
<p>POLITICO asked the Osborn campaign Tuesday afternoon whether it was aware of Chasin’s name surfacing in the files. “This event has been cancelled,” a spokesperson replied.</p> 
<p>“Anyone who hurt kids or engaged in other illegal activity needs to be arrested and prosecuted,” the statement continued. The spokesperson did not respond to a question about what vetting had been done of the co-hosts in advance of the event.</p> 
<p>Chasin has donated more than $2 million to Democrats since the 1990s, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/receipts/individual-contributions/?contributor_name=chasin+dana&amp;max_date=12%2F31%2F2026" target="_blank">according to federal records</a>. An invitation to the fundraiser listed tickets from $250 to $3,500.</p> 
<p>Chasin donated $3,300 to Osborn’s 2024 failed Senate campaign, the records indicate. The campaign said in an email “a donation has already been made by the Osborn campaign to a nonprofit organization in Nebraska whose mission is to end child abuse and trafficking that is the equivalent to the amount donated by this individual.”</p> 
<p>In recent weeks, Osborn has made numerous posts on X calling for justice to be served for Epstein’s victims.</p> 
<p>“There is a small, powerful group of ELITES who think they can do anything they want on this earth,” he <a href="https://x.com/osbornforne/status/2020873083704230393?s=20" target="_blank">posted Monday</a>. “They think they are deserving. They think they are exceptional.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-10T16:19:25-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House Dem identifies ‘wealthy, powerful men’ DOJ redacted in Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/ro-khanna-names-names-00774551</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-491b-d647-addc-ebdf5eda0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:56:17 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Ro Khanna took to the House floor Tuesday and read aloud the names of six “wealthy, powerful men” whose names were originally redacted in the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>It comes after Khanna (D-Calif.) and Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) emerged from reviewing unredacted materials related to the late convicted sex offender and demanded that the Justice Department reveal these individuals’ identities to the public if their redactions did not fall under the terms established by Congress..</p> 
<p>The lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/reps-question-epstein-file-redactions-00772399" target="_blank">threatened to expose</a> the men if DOJ did not cooperate, taking advantage of the Constitution’s Speech or Debate Clause that under certain circumstances can shield members of Congress from litigation. DOJ ultimately complied with some of their requests, Massie announced in <a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/2021235321942217085" target="_blank">social media posts</a> Tuesday morning.</p> 
<p>Khanna, however, wasn’t satisfied to stop there.</p> 
<p>“Why did it take Thomas Massie and me going to the Justice Department to get these six men’s identities to become public?” he asked from the House floor. “And if we found six men that they were hiding in two hours, imagine how many men they are covering up for in those 3 million files.”</p> 
<p>Khanna accused the Trump administration of continuing to violate the law he and Massie helped shepherd through Congress in November that placed limits on DOJ redactions of the documents.</p> 
<p>It’s not immediately clear who some of the individuals are, but Khanna identified Leslie Wexner as the billionaire former owner of Victoria’s Secret and other retail companies, and Sultan Ahmed bin Sulayem as the chief executive officer of DP World. </p> 
<p>“The Assistant U.S. Attorney told Mr. Wexner’s legal counsel in 2019 that Mr. Wexner was being viewed as source of information about Epstein and was not a target in any respect," a legal representative for Wexner said in a statement. "Mr. Wexner cooperated fully by providing background information on Epstein and was never contacted again.”</p> 
<p>A representative for bin Sulayem did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Other names include Salvatore Nuara, Zurab Mikeladze, Leonic Leonov, and Nicola Caputo, who could not be reached for comment.</p> 
<p>Khanna did not provide evidence of wrongdoing against any of them. </p> 
<p>Massie<a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/2021327147403706470" target="_blank">in a social media</a>post Tuesday afternoon, also said that while "Appearing in the Epstein files does not prove guilt ... Leslie Wexner was designated as a coconspirator of Epstein for 'child sex trafficking' in a 2019 FBI document and the Sultan’s email address was used to send correspondence about the 'torture video.' Four other men and their pictures appear in a list with Epstein, Maxwell, two known victims, and several women."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rule vote postponed amid tariff backlash</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/rule-vote-postponed-amid-tariff-backlash-00773687</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-488f-d0f8-adde-fadf5d7e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 12:20:03 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House leaders are postponing their latest effort to block votes on President Donald Trump’s tariffs until 8:30 p.m. amid internal GOP backlash.</p> 
<p>House Republican leaders are attempting to use a procedural measure to block any resolutions related to Trump’s tariffs until the end of July, restarting a moratorium on such votes that expired on January 31. But they face <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/johnson-tariff-vote-ban-00773143" target="_blank">significant internal opposition</a> from a band of tariff-skeptical Republicans, led by Reps. Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Rep. Kevin Kiley of California.</p> 
<p>Several Republican lawmakers have expressed discomfort with a tariff regime that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/poll-affordability-cost-of-living-00678076" target="_blank">polling shows is broadly unpopular</a>, even with parts of the GOP base, as Americans continue to grapple with high costs for everyday goods.</p> 
<p>House leaders have side-stepped the controversy since last March, when they first used a procedural measure to block efforts to force a vote on the national emergency Trump used to implement the tariffs. The move has guarded members from a controversial vote ahead of a crucial midterm election and has protected the president from clear vote of Congressional disapproval as his administration attempts to strike agreements with major trading partners.</p> 
<p>If Republicans fail to pass the new procedural block, Democrats are aiming to force a vote on Trump’s 25 percent tariff on Canadian goods as early as Wednesday, with votes on the president’s global tariffs and tariffs on Brazil and Mexico to follow.</p> 
<p>The Senate has already disapproved of the tariffs four times.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jeffries slams Republican DHS offer as 'woefully inadequate'</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/jeffries-slams-republican-dhs-offer-as-woefully-inadequate-00773372</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4845-d3b5-addf-e8c52eb10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 10:58:11 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> said Tuesday a GOP counterproposal on Department of Homeland Security funding is “woefully inadequate” and shows the White House “is clearly not open to” several key Democratic demands.</p> 
<p>Speaking four days ahead of a DHS shutdown deadline, Jeffries said the Republican offer did not satisfactorily address a need for judicial warrants, detention center standards, independent investigations and excessive-force standards. Asked about whether the Trump administration would support a prohibition on masks for federal agents, Jeffries said, “That’s an open question.”</p> 
<p>“They don't appear to be open to ... ensuring that ICE agents are identifiable in a manner consistent with every other law enforcement agency in the country,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>Also speaking Tuesday morning, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said he believed there was still room for compromise, with support from at least seven Senate Democrats needed for any shutdown-averting stopgap measure.</p> 
<p>"There are things I think on probably both sides that are non-negotiables," he said. "But I do think there are a number of things in the range of common ground."</p> 
<p>Speaking on the Senate floor, Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> struck a more cautious tone than Jeffries, saying Democrats "need to see more from Republicans very soon."</p> 
<p>"What Democrats propose is the definition of common sense," he said. "We simply want ICE to follow the same standards that most law enforcement agencies across America already follow."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson says it's full steam ahead on tariff vote ban</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/johnson-tariff-vote-ban-00773143</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-482d-d3b5-addf-e8edcc6c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 10:33:07 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said in an interview Tuesday he will push ahead an afternoon vote to ban challenges to President Donald Trump’s global tariffs over committed internal GOP opposition.</p> 
<p>Language tucked into a procedural measure would forestall votes on privileged resolutions of disapproval through July 31, reviving a ban that expired Jan. 31 as Democrats plan to push fresh tariff votes as soon as Wednesday. But Johnson is facing growing GOP backlash to the move from a band of tariff-skeptical House Republicans. </p> 
<p>Two of them, Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260571" data-person-id="260571">Kevin Kiley</a> of California and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> of Kentucky, told POLITICO they will oppose the rule — enough to tank the procedural vote if all Democrats vote against it as expected. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/276525" data-person-id="276525">Victoria Spartz</a> (R-Ind.) also said she is a "no" on the procedural vote, though she is known to change her mind on the floor.</p> 
<p>Inside a closed-door conference meeting Tuesday morning, Johnson told House Republicans he was going ahead with the vote, arguing to members that they needed to wait until the Supreme Court rules on Trump's tariff powers, according to three people in the room granted anonymity to describe the private meeting. That ruling could comes as late as the end of June.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> declined to say if GOP leaders would have the vote to adopt the blockade language, telling a POLITICO reporter to "ask the whip questions about vote coalitions."</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maxine Waters is the newest target in Democrats’ intergenerational war</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/maxine-waters-newest-target-democrats-intergenerational-00772858</link>
      <description>Waters has been in Congress for 35 years, but Myla Rahman says the district needs fresh representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4564-d0f8-adde-ff7e39da0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ba/9a1a456b49338dd68b87fe59d88d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2198970159">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Anna Moneymaker/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Financial Services ranking member Maxine Waters has opposed GOP-led crypto legislation, in part over concerns about the Trump family's digital assets business ventures.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ba/9a1a456b49338dd68b87fe59d88d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2198970159" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Melanie Mason</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Melanie Mason</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>LOS ANGELES — Rep. Maxine Waters, an institution of Los Angeles Democratic politics, is facing an upstart challenger from her party seeking to capitalize on the national wave of generational change-seekers.</p> 
<p>Myla Rahman, a nonprofit executive, hopes to turn Waters’ 35 years in Congress — and 50 years overall as an elected official — against her, arguing the 87-year-old incumbent has lost touch with her district.</p> 
<p>“The community has said that they’d like new energy, a new perspective,” said Rahman in an interview. “And the reality is, the average age is 36 years old in the district. The average person is a renter in the district. So we've got a lot of issues that are relatable to my life experience.”</p> 
<p>Waters is the rare member of Congress to be both a local icon and a national meme. She gained near-celebrity status in President Donald Trump’s first term as “Auntie Maxine” who regularly lobbed acerbic barbs at the president and his administration. She has maintained an electoral lock on her South Los Angeles district, normally winning with more than 70 or 80 percent of the vote.</p> 
<p>That commanding presence has deterred any serious challenge against Waters in decades. But Rahman is aiming to tap into Democrats’ party-wide discontent over their graying representation, spurred on by President Joe Biden’s initial decision to run for reelection in 2024 despite concerns about his advanced age and mental acuity.</p> 
<p>In California, long-serving Democratic incumbents like Reps. Brad Sherman and Mike Thompson are facing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/16/democrats-generational-challenges-california-00565027" target="_blank"><u>insurgent campaigns</u></a> from younger opponents. The generational rift is also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/congressional-black-caucus-2026-midterms-00741618" target="_blank"><u>roiling the Congressional Black Caucus</u></a>, whose members are facing challenges from younger Black politicians who argue the old guard is not fighting hard enough for the current political moment.</p> 
<p>Rahman, who is 53, pointedly noted Waters has been her representative since she moved into the district at age 6. She said her differences from the congressmember are stylistic, not ideological, and that she considers herself “more energetic, younger, more relatable in terms of the experiences that people face in the district.”</p> 
<p>Rahman said she is especially focused on affordable health care after surviving two occurrences of breast cancer. She received her diagnosis the second time just as she was elected city clerk in Carson and stepped down from the role one day after winning because of her health. She is now cancer-free.</p> 
<p>Waters’ seniority in Congress has made her a powerful force on the Hill; she is currently the top-ranking Democrat on the House Financial Services committee and is in position to become its chair if the Democrats win control in the midterm elections.</p> 
<p>But Waters is not particularly flush in campaign cash, perhaps because she has so rarely faced a serious challenge. She raised roughly $430,000 in 2025 and started the year with less than $150,000 cash on hand.</p> 
<p>Rahman initially sought a state legislative seat in 2026 and raised less than $35,000 for her Assembly campaign, most of which she donated herself. But she said she’s “very confident” she’d be competitive fundraising for a congressional seat. She’s hired veteran Democratic consultant Mike Trujillo to work on the campaign.</p> 
<p>After working as a high-level staffer for Los Angeles-area legislators, Rahman said she’s well aware her decision to go up against a pillar of the city’s political scene will stir some outrage.</p> 
<p>“I'm sure I'll get a lot of calls. I’m waiting for ‘how dare you? The audacity of you, who do you think you are,’” she said. “And what I can say is that there's a choice, and this is a democracy. That's why we have elections, and the voters can decide.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Democrats demand more from GOP on DHS</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/democrats-white-house-dhs-proposal-shutdown-00772903</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-45eb-d0f8-adde-fffba9370000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Do we have a negotiation or a stalemate?</p> 
<p>The answer to that question will determine whether the Department of Homeland Security shuts down in just four days, and Tuesday morning, it’s not entirely clear which way things are headed.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders Chuck Schumer and Hakeem Jeffries panned a White House counterproposal sent to them Monday evening as too light on details for how to rein in President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p><b>— Dems vs. White House:</b> “The initial GOP response is both incomplete and insufficient in terms of addressing the concerns Americans have about ICE’s lawless conduct,” the leaders said in a statement. “Democrats await additional detail and text.”</p> 
<p>That’s far from a “hell no,” but expect to hear more later Tuesday morning on where Democrats stand after Jeffries and Schumer meet with their respective caucuses.</p> 
<p>Neither side is saying exactly what the GOP counter to the 10-point Democratic offer entails, but White House allies made clear Monday that one key Democratic demand — requiring federal law enforcement officials to obtain judicial warrants before entering private property — is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/09/a-complete-non-starter-white-house-draws-red-lines-in-dhs-funding-talks-as-shutdown-looms-00772302" target="_blank">dead on arrival</a>. </p> 
<p>Other Democratic asks — including a mask prohibition, ID display requirements and limits on places where agents can operate — would need major concessions from Democrats to make them palatable for the administration, several people close to the White House said.</p> 
<p>But the trading of offers is giving GOP leaders optimism that a deal is possible. Senate Majority Leader John Thune said he’ll probably get the ball rolling on a continuing resolution Tuesday to give negotiators more time to strike a deal.</p> 
<p>—<b> About that CR:</b> Whether a stopgap can pass depends almost entirely on the tenor of DHS talks come Thursday, when senators are hoping to leave town.</p> 
<p>Republicans need at least seven votes from Senate Democrats to prevent a DHS shutdown, and some Senate Democrats continue to signal they could be convinced — if there’s a bona fide negotiation.</p> 
<p>“It depends on whether we’re making progress or not,” Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) told reporters Monday. “We’ve got some time. Hopefully people will be working to try and get something done.”</p> 
<p>Also undecided is how long a short-term DHS funding punt might run. GOP appropriators want at least two weeks, but the exact length “will have to be negotiated,” Thune said.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— A high-stakes rule vote: </b>House GOP leaders will attempt to adopt a rule Tuesday that includes language to block votes on President Donald Trump’s global tariffs through July after Democrats threatened to move as soon as Wednesday to overturn the president’s levies on Canada.</p> 
<p>It could get hairy: Under the current member math, as few as two GOP defections could block adoption of the rule. Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) is a no. Keep an eye on Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.), Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.) and Tom McClintock (R-Calif.).</p> 
<p><b>— SAVE America Act inches forward: </b>The House will consider the SAVE America Act in Rules on Tuesday despite the uncertain future in the Senate for the GOP elections overhaul. It’s on track to hit the House floor Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The four Democrats who supported a version of the bill in April — Reps. Henry Cuellar of Texas, Ed Case of Hawaii, Marie Gluesenkamp Perez of Washington and Jared Golden of Maine — have so far been mum on whether they will support the updated measure. Jeffries said House Democrats will discuss the measure Tuesday morning.</p> 
<p><b>— DHS officials take the stand: </b>House Homeland Security Committee members will question DHS officials Tuesday morning for the first time since last month’s fatal shootings of Renée Good and Alex Pretti sparked bipartisan backlash against the Trump administration. </p> 
<p>Acting director for ICE Todd Lyons, Customs and Border Protection Commissioner Rodney Scott and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services Director Joseph Edlow will testify.</p> 
<p>While Democrats are expected to give the officials a fierce grilling, some Republicans will also likely push them for more clarity on ICE operations.</p> 
<p><i>Myah Ward, Alex Gangitano, Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson moves to again block House from voting on Trump tariffs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/johnson-moves-to-again-block-house-from-voting-on-trump-tariffs-00772559</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-44fa-de8a-a1fc-fdfa2b9b0005</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:37:47 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said Monday he is moving forward with a plan to revive a prohibition on House votes to overturn President Donald Trump's global tariffs.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters he believes he will have the votes to include the block in a procedural measure set for House consideration Tuesday. The House Rules Committee <a href="https://rules.house.gov/sites/evo-subsites/rules.house.gov/files/documents/rule_hr2189hr261hr3617.pdf" target="_blank">approved legislation Monday</a> that would prevent any further tariff votes through July 31.</p> 
<p>The move comes after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/16/congress/house-again-votes-to-surrender-tariff-powers-to-trump-00566975" target="_blank">previous blockade imposed by GOP leaders</a> expired — and House Democrats threatened to force a vote as soon as Wednesday that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/house-vote-canada-tariffs-00772224" target="_blank">effectively cancel Trump's tariffs on Canada</a>.</p> 
<p>But it is far from clear that Johnson will actually have the necessary votes. A band of House Republicans are already pushing back on the plans, with a group of at least six tariff-skeptical GOP members discussing the matter on the floor Monday night. With united Democratic opposition expected, nays from as few as two Republicans could derail the effort.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House approves housing bill, setting stage for tough Senate negotiations</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/house-approves-housing-bill-setting-stage-for-tough-senate-negotiations-00772552</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-44eb-d3b5-addf-e4ef08510005</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:20:30 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Cassandra Dumay</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cassandra Dumay</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House on Monday night passed its bipartisan <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/house-financial-services-introduces-bipartisan-housing-package-00688305" target="_blank">housing package</a> aimed at increasing home supply and affordability, setting up an uncertain effort to merge the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6644" target="_blank">measure</a> with a Senate housing bill.</p> 
<p>House lawmakers approved by a vote of 390-9 the <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/02/house-republicans-eye-next-week-for-housing-bill-vote-00761249#:~:text=Housing%20in%20the%2021st%20Century%20Act" target="_blank">Housing in the 21st Century Act</a> under suspension of the rules, a fast-track procedure for non-controversial legislation. The bill includes provisions to modernize local development and rural housing programs, expand manufactured and affordable housing, protect borrowers and those utilizing federal housing programs and enhance oversight of housing providers. The package also contained a recently added section aimed at increasing community bank lending.</p> 
<p>Congress must now work to get a unified bill to the president’s desk. The Senate passed its own bipartisan housing affordability package in October, which was supported by the White House. Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) — who spearheaded the House bill with ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51664" data-person-id="51664">Maxine Waters</a> (D-Calif.) — told reporters Monday he plans to negotiate with the administration as well as his counterparts on the Senate Banking Committee to get a final version which both chambers and the White House can support.</p> 
<p>“We wanted to get [the housing bill and other committee priorities] through the House so that we could work with the Senate to find packages that the President could sign into law, long before the very active summer campaign season,” Hill said. “So I would hope that we could work over the spring and find a way to have a bicameral, bipartisan set of bills.”</p> 
<p>Hill has previously said the Senate bill, the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2651" target="_blank">ROAD to Housing Act</a>, contained a number of provisions that House Republicans would likely not support. Although the House and Senate bills share many similarities, the Senate measure includes a number of grant programs that would expand federal spending.</p> 
<p>But Senate Banking ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> (D-Mass.) said that she still wants the House to take up the Senate bill, setting the stage for a potential clash. Support from Senate Democrats will likely be necessary to get housing legislation through the upper chamber.</p> 
<p>“ROAD to Housing is a Jenga tower. Adding or taking things away risks losing the unanimous coalition that we have built in the Senate,” Warren said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Warren also signaled that she disapproved of the new section added to the House legislation, which would ease regulation on community banks — reflecting Hill’s <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/hill-barr-introduce-community-banking-package-00715479?site=pro&amp;prod=alert&amp;prodname=alertmail&amp;linktype=headline&amp;source=email" target="_blank">“Make Community Banking Great Again” agenda</a>.</p> 
<p>“House Republicans should not hold housing relief hostage to push forward several bank deregulatory bills that will make our community banks more fragile,” Warren said in a statement before Monday’s House vote.</p> 
<p><i>Katherine Hapgood contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers don't rule out exposing redacted names of powerful men in Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/reps-question-epstein-file-redactions-00772399</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-44bb-d0f8-adde-fefb06f50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:41:27 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reps. Ro Khanna and Thomas Massie are challenging the Justice Department for redacting the names of six men in the publicly released materials related to the convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein — and they could take matters into their own hands to reveal their identities.</p> 
<p>These omissions, the two lawmakers argued Monday evening outside the Justice Department, could go beyond the scope of redactions that are permitted under the legislation they championed — and which President Donald Trump signed into law in November — to compel the full release of Epstein files within DOJ’s possession.</p> 
<p>And while they declined to share the names with reporters Monday, Massie, a Kentucky Republican, didn’t rule out taking steps to do so in the coming days. He told reporters he should “probably” broadcast the identity of the shielded individuals “from the floor or in a committee hearing,” where his remarks would be protected from lawsuits through the Speech and Debate Clause.</p> 
<p>“What we’re after is the men who Jeffrey Epstein trafficked women to,” said Massie, adding he would give DOJ officials the opportunity to “correct their mistakes” and reverse the redactions on their own before reading the names of the six men on the chamber floor or from a committee dais.</p> 
<p>Massie said at least one of the men was a U.S. citizen, another was a foreigner and the nationalities of others were unclear. He suggested authorities were investigating at least one of them.</p> 
<p>“There are six men, some of them with their photographs, that have been redacted, and there's no explanation why those people were redacted,” Khanna, a California Democrat, told reporters. “That’s really concerning.”</p> 
<p>Khanna and Massie were at a DOJ office building Monday to peruse the unredacted Epstein files, a privilege being afforded to members of Congress following the files' public release. The lawmakers scrutinized the unscrubbed materials on closely held computers — though Massie complained he was unable to view some documents that have since been taken down from the Justice Department website after being posted publicly.</p> 
<p>Khanna suggested that some materials may have been redacted before the Justice Department review — potentially by the FBI — complicating the process for complete transparency.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, also viewed the unredacted materials earlier in the day Monday. He said there were about four computers for lawmakers’ use and viewers can only take written notes on what they see.</p> 
<p>“We didn't want to see any redactions of the names of co-conspirators, accomplices, enablers, abusers, rapists, simply to spare them potential embarrassment, political sensitivity or disgrace of some kind,” Raskin told reporters. “And yet nonetheless, the Epstein … documents that were released are filled with redactions of names and information about people who clearly are not victims and may fall into that other category.”</p> 
<p>He pointed to the redaction of Les Wexner’s identity as an example. Wexner, the former CEO of Victoria’s Secret, was an Epstein client and has a deposition scheduled before the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee later this month.</p> 
<p>Raskin also said he saw one redacted document, a message from Epstein’s legal team regarding Trump. He recalled the note mentioned that Trump had identified Epstein as a guest, but not a member, of Mar-a-Lago.</p> 
<p>“That was redacted for some indeterminate, inscrutable reason,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House vote on Canada tariffs coming as soon as Wednesday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/house-vote-canada-tariffs-00772224</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4482-d3b5-addf-e4c62af80006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 17:28:02 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Desrochers and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Desrochers and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Democrats are aiming to force a vote on President Donald Trump’s Canada tariffs as early as Wednesday.</p> 
<p>House Democrats still need to meet and decide when to offer the resolution, but it is likely to come Wednesday, according to two staffers granted anonymity to discuss private plans.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/51521" target="_blank">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.) <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HJRES_72?q=H.J.Res.72" target="_blank">introduced the resolution</a> last March, but House Republican leaders <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/03/11/congress/house-republicans-move-to-block-vote-on-trumps-tariffs-00223947" target="_blank">blocked a vote on the measure and any others</a> disapproving of Trump’s emergency powers to impose tariffs. That block <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/16/congress/house-again-votes-to-surrender-tariff-powers-to-trump-00566975" target="_blank">expired in January</a>, after a group of Republicans pushed leadership to allow tariff votes.</p> 
<p>One of those lawmakers, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/6d3990d9-4e46-4bc9-a299-af8b3dad90fd" target="_blank">Don Bacon</a> (R-Neb.), said he is inclined to vote to end the tariffs on Canada.</p> 
<p>“We have a trade agreement with them, and I don’t like how the White House has treated our neighbor and ally,” Bacon said Monday in an interview.</p> 
<p>If it is offered, it would force a difficult vote for Republican lawmakers, who have faced sustained pressure from businesses in their districts over the costs and disruptions the tariffs have produced.</p> 
<p>The Senate has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/29/congress/senate-votes-to-block-trumps-tariffs-on-canada-for-a-second-time-00629068" target="_blank">voted twice</a> to block Trump from imposing tariffs on Canada, first in April and then again in October. Four Republican Senators voted with the Democrats each time: <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/aa48154b-408e-4868-a88a-e4c2151d6492" target="_blank">Mitch McConnell</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/4b1312cc-ee28-4ef7-aeac-bd4f852ca121" target="_blank">Rand Paul</a> of Kentucky, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/6c1b2696-bcf8-42e0-8d5f-b4d513a17758" target="_blank">Susan Collins</a> of Maine, and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/a5094dbc-f9c4-455a-875d-d56a1b3f0abd" target="_blank">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska.</p> 
<p>The votes are largely symbolic — even if Congress disapproves of Trump’s national emergency, the president is likely to veto it, and it would require a two-thirds vote from both chambers to overturn his veto.</p> 
<p>Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/01/trump-tariffs-canada-mexico-00201953" target="_blank">used his emergency powers</a> to impose a 25 percent tariff on goods from Canada, Mexico and China in February, accusing the three countries of failing to prevent undocumented migrants and fentanyl from flowing into the U.S.</p> 
<p>The administration exempted the majority of Canadian goods from those tariffs, however, if they comply with the existing U.S.-Mexico-Canada free trade agreement.</p> 
<p><i>Doug Palmer contributed to this article.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-09T15:29:36-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Howard Lutnick faces bipartisan calls to resign over latest Epstein revelations</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/howard-lutnick-epstein-resignation-00771261</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-432e-d3b5-addf-e3ee29e90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:15:16 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick is facing bipartisan calls to resign after he appeared in a recent batch of files linked to convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51608" data-person-id="51608">Adam Schiff</a> (D-Calif.) accused Lutnick in a statement Monday of having “lied” about the extent of his connection to Epstein. Lutnick has sought to downplay their relationship, saying in a podcast appearance last year he vowed in 2005 to never again be in the same room as Epstein.</p> 
<p>But files recently released by the Justice Department <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/epstein-europe-america-fallout-00769506" target="_blank">suggest he continued his interactions with Epstein</a>, including planning a visit several years later to Epstein’s Caribbean island.</p> 
<p>“Lutnick’s lies about his business dealings with a convicted child sex offender, raise serious concerns about his judgement and ethics,” Schiff said. “Lutnick has no business being our Commerce Secretary, and he should resign immediately.”</p> 
<p>Asked about the scrunity, White House spokesperson Kush Desai did not respond directly but said President Donald Trump "has assembled the best and most transformative cabinet in modern history." </p> 
<p>"The entire Trump administration, including Secretary Lutnick and the Department of Commerce, remains focused on delivering for the American people,” he said.</p> 
<p>House Oversight Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260072" data-person-id="260072">James Comer</a> (R-Ky.), who is leading an investigation into Epstein and has already subpoenaed multiple associates, did not rule out issuing one for Lutnick. But he said the panel's outstanding subpoenas take priority for now.</p> 
<p>"We're interested in talking to anyone that might have any information that would help us get justice for the survivorship," he told reporters Monday.</p> 
<p>Schiff is joining a bipartisan chorus of House members who have called in recent days for Lutnick to either resign or be fired — neither of which appears to be on the precipice of happening.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.) <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/02/08/politics/massie-howard-lutnick-epstein-files" target="_blank">told CNN</a> during an interview that aired over the weekend that Lutnick should “make life easier on the president, frankly, and just resign.” House Democrats, including top Oversight Committee member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/420280" data-person-id="420280">Robert Garcia</a>, have also called on Lutnick to go.</p> 
<p>“It’s now clear that Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick has been lying about his relationship with Epstein,” the Californian posted on X. “Lutnick must resign or be fired. And he must answer our questions.”</p> 
<p><i>Hailey Fuchs and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ghislaine Maxwell pleads the Fifth in House Oversight Epstein investigation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/maxwell-pleads-the-fifth-00771258</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-431e-d3b5-addf-e3def70a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:12:25 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The congressional investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein hit its latest snag Monday morning when Epstein’s longtime associate, Ghislaine Maxwell, declined to answer questions in a sworn deposition.</p> 
<p>Maxwell, now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in Epstein’s sex trafficking scheme, invoked her Fifth Amendment right over video from a prison camp in Texas, months after she had been subpoenaed by the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee.</p> 
<p>In a copy of Maxwell's lawyer’s opening statement obtained by POLITICO, David Oscar Markus reiterated that grant of clemency would facilitate her testimony — a power only President Donald Trump can bestow. He has not ruled out issuing a pardon.</p> 
<p>“Only she can provide the complete account. Some may not like what they hear, but the truth matters,” according to Markus’ prepared remarks. “For example, both President Trump and President Clinton are innocent of any wrongdoing. Ms. Maxwell alone can explain why, and the public is entitled to that explanation.”</p> 
<p>He also noted some of Maxwell’s legal proceedings were still ongoing.</p> 
<p>Democrats accused Maxwell of using the deposition as part of a campaign for clemency from Trump, while House Oversight Chair James Comer told reporters he did not believe Maxwell should be granted clemency.</p> 
<p>“Unfortunately, she had an opportunity today to answer questions that every American has — questions that would be very important in this investigation — and she chose to invoke her Fifth Amendment right,” the Kentucky Republican said. </p> 
<p>Rank-and-file members of the panel who shuffled into the deposition room Monday morning for Maxwell's questioning included Reps. Andy Biggs (R-Ariz.), who is running for governor, and Raja Krishnamoorthi (D-Il.), who is running for Senate.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) said he intended to view the unredacted Epstein files from the Justice Department on Monday afternoon. He also noted he would be joined by Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), with whom Khanna led the effort to force a floor vote on the release of the files.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Republicans prepare DHS punt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/dhs-shutdown-funding-bill-continuing-resolution-00771028</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-40a4-d0f8-adde-fafe543b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With fewer than five days to go before a DHS shutdown, Senate Democrats have put bill text for full-year funding on the table. But another punt is probably still the best-case scenario, and it’s by no means guaranteed.</p> 
<p><b>— What Democrats are pitching: </b>The draft legislation Democrats sent Republicans on Sunday would codify the immigration enforcement guardrails outlined by Democratic leaders last week, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss the plans. They include new judicial warrant requirements and limits on masking by federal agents.</p> 
<p><b>— Republicans review and prepare for CR: </b>While getting bill text is generally a good thing for the process, after Republicans complained publicly into the weekend about the lack of specifics from Democrats, it hasn’t changed the endgame for this week. Republicans and the White House view some of the ideas as possible areas for negotiation, but it’s just highly unlikely all sides agree to a full-year DHS revamp by Friday at midnight.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans expect to begin taking procedural steps Monday to set up consideration of a DHS funding patch. Senate aides still hope there’s a way to prevent a DHS shutdown, and progress on negotiations could dictate how easy it is to get bipartisan buy-in for another CR. Most Democrats will be reluctant to punt.</p> 
<p><b>— Shutdown still looks likely: </b>Unless the Senate does the unexpected and clears a new CR for DHS by Wednesday, there probably won’t be enough time for the House to follow suit before the shutdown deadline. House GOP leaders have no plans to cancel next week’s recess absent clearer proof of progress in the Senate, meaning a DHS shutdown could take even longer to resolve.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Ghislaine</b> <b>Maxwell deposition: </b>The House Oversight Committee<b>&nbsp;</b>will depose Jeffrey Epstein co-conspirator Ghislaine Maxwell virtually at 10 a.m. Monday. Maxwell is expected to invoke the Fifth Amendment and be uncooperative with questioning. House Judiciary ranking member Jamie Raskin (D-Md.) will be reviewing unredacted Epstein files, according to a spokesperson. Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) will review the files as well. </p> 
<p><b>— House moves on housing package: </b>The House is expected to swiftly pass a sweeping, bipartisan housing supply bill from the Financial Services Committee on Monday afternoon. After that, it’s unclear how the House and Senate will come together on one of the country’s most urgent cost-of-living problems.</p> 
<p>— <b>D.C. tax bill advances:</b> Senate Republicans are expected to act early this week to pass a measure that would force the District of Columbia to implement GOP tax cuts. The bill, which the House <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/house-passes-measure-to-force-d-c-s-hand-on-tax-cuts-00766206" target="_blank">passed along party lines</a> last week, would block a November D.C. budget law that tossed aside tax provisions from last year’s “Big, Beautiful Bill.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Hailey Fuchs and Cassandra Dumay contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
