<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 18:48:13 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>GOP moves to let Obamacare subsidies expire as Trump promises ‘money to the people’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/gop-obamacare-subsidies-expire-00684115</link>
      <description>As the president rails against insurance companies, other Republicans say allowing a subsidy lapse is “not acceptable.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-057e-d889-a1df-fd7ee5020000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 18:48:13 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/bd/0d/ca815173435fbf64d6e6a285d522/u-s-congress-11758.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Speaker Mike Johnson is scrambling to cobble together health legislation after promising a House vote this month.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bd/0d/ca815173435fbf64d6e6a285d522/u-s-congress-11758.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican leaders on Capitol Hill are moving decisively away from extending key Obamacare tax credits that help more than 20 million Americans pay for health insurance — following direct cues from President Donald Trump while also stoking ire among many in the GOP who fear severe political repercussions.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/donald-trump-full-interview-transcript-00681693" target="_blank">Monday interview with POLITICO</a>, Trump refused to endorse a continuation of the expiring subsidies, even as his administration faces mounting pressure to address rising costs for Americans. He instead laid out his own vision for health care: “I want to give the money to the people, not to the insurance companies.”</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans now plan to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/senate-republican-heath-vote-00683250" target="_blank">offer a proposal for a vote Thursday</a> that would let the subsidies expire and instead encourage the use of health savings accounts. That abrupt shift in strategy is in turn putting new pressure on House GOP leaders to come up with their own health plan, according to four people who attended a closed-door meeting with Speaker Mike Johnson and senior Republicans Tuesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>Yet after months of pressure from competing factions, lawmakers inside the meeting didn’t reach a conclusion and Johnson is <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/johnson-house-gop-health-care-plan-00676661" target="_blank">still trying to figure out</a> what that plan should be. House GOP staff Tuesday were prepping a health care framework to give Republicans something to vote on next week before they leave Washington for the holidays — one that, for now, does not include an extension of the enhanced Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>For many Republicans facing tough reelection races and even some in deep-red areas with a high reliance on the tax credits, following Trump’s one-sentence policy prescription would harm Americans and make for political disaster as the Dec. 31 expiration of the tax credits looms.</p> 
<p>“We can agree that the current construct is flawed, but that letting them expire is not acceptable,” Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) said in an interview Tuesday. “That doesn’t work.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick is pushing a competing proposal that would extend the tax credits for two years while imposing an income cap and other eligibility restrictions. Fitzpatrick’s bill also includes new HSA provisions and a bipartisan package aimed at lowering drug costs, but he said it was unrealistic for GOP leaders to completely replace the subsidy framework in a matter of weeks.</p> 
<p>“They can just dig themselves into an ideological corner all day long — it’s not fixing the problem,” Fitzpatrick added. “We can’t live in this fantasy land.”</p> 
<p>But Johnson appears determined to cobble together a health care framework that will not include even a short-term extension of the subsidies, which <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/aca-marketplace-premium-payments-would-more-than-double-on-average-next-year-if-enhanced-premium-tax-credits-expire/" target="_blank">can cut premiums</a> for many families by $1,000 a year or more. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2025/12/08/gop-struggles-on-affordability-message-00680485" target="_blank">blindsided members of his own leadership circle</a> and senior Republicans who have been involved in health care policy work when he announced last week his intentions to unveil a GOP health plan early this week and hold a vote before year's end.</p> 
<p>“What health care plan?” said one of the senior Republicans who has been involved in the talks and was granted anonymity to share a candid reaction to Johnson’s pledge.</p> 
<p>Turning Johnson’s promise into legislation has been difficult. As of Tuesday evening, the House GOP framework centered on an expansion of health savings accounts and funding for cost-sharing reductions — a type of Obamacare subsidy meant to reduce out-of-pocket health costs, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the deliberations.</p> 
<p>While the plan does not currently include a temporary subsidy extension, some senior House Republicans say it might still be on the table — including Rep. Lisa McClain of Michigan, the No. 4 GOP leader, who said she believed it was still an option as she left the health care meeting Tuesday.</p> 
<p>It’s also still to be determined whether the plan will be offered up as a suite of individual bills or packaged together. But the goal is for GOP lawmakers to have “something” to vote on before the end of next week, according to one of the senior House Republicans involved in the talks — even if there is no time left for the Senate to pass it before the subsidies lapse.</p> 
<p>GOP members will be briefed on the talks during their closed-door conference meeting Wednesday morning, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal planning. They will not be presented with a formal plan, they said.</p> 
<p>The health care sprint also comes as Johnson faces down growing displeasure inside the GOP over his leadership style, where he has repeatedly sought to bulldoze internal dissent and march in lockstep with Trump. In this case, Johnson has so far sided with the bulk of his conference who want to see the Obamacare subsidies expire — even though some Trump aides have counseled that an extension would be politically prudent.</p> 
<p>The White House was on the cusp of endorsing a two-year continuation of the subsidies just before Thanksgiving, but top Republicans on the Hill were not fully consulted first and moved to quash the idea — to the horror of many in the rank-and-file who favor an extension.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think leadership understands just how upset people are,” said one House Republican who among several granted anonymity to speak frankly about internal conversations. “People are getting desperate.”</p> 
<p>In fact, according to six other House GOP lawmakers and senior aides with direct knowledge, enough Republicans could sign a discharge petition that would sidestep Johnson and force a vote on extending the expiring subsidies. One of those House Republicans said they would be willing to support a discharge of Fitzpatrick’s legislation, which largely mirrors the White House trial balloon, or another bill from Rep. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.) and is waiting to see details of what Johnson proposes as an alternative.</p> 
<p>“We shall see,” the lawmaker said.</p> 
<p>Some in the GOP who support an extension have floated a short-term patch until Jan. 30 in order to buy some more time to come up with a deal. Many Republicans in the White House and on Capitol Hill believe that once the tax credits expire, there could be a chance to work out a wider health care deal next month that could tackle issues such as HSAs and drug prices.</p> 
<p>While that argument has its merits on paper, people involved in the talks say a short-term punt wouldn’t make much sense for people trying to buy health insurance for the entire year and could create major logistical hassles.</p> 
<p>One of the many problems is the White House itself isn’t providing any clear guidance amid all the internal divisions. The Trump administration itself has been and still is deeply divided about allowing the Obamacare tax credits to lapse, according to two administration officials and three senior House Republicans involved in the conversations.</p> 
<p>“It depends on who you ask,” said a senior House Republican about the White House’s views on health care.</p> 
<p>One White House official said Tuesday that “policy teams are looking at a lot of different avenues” and that “three weeks is actually a lot of time for a lot of stuff to come together.” However, both the House and Senate are set to adjourn for the holidays at the end of next week.</p> 
<p>The Senate plan now set for a vote Thursday, from Sens. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana and Mike Crapo of Idaho, quickly won support inside the GOP this week amid fears that the party would look hapless if they did not put up an alternative to Democrats’ plan to extend the subsidies for three years.</p> 
<p>But there are still plenty of lawmakers who are anxious about voting to upend the health care system with the deadline looming and no signals from the White House on what Trump would accept.</p> 
<p>"There's just not enough time to do a comprehensive bill," one House Republican said, adding that the expiring subsidies will be “a problem for everyone” in the GOP.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Cheyenne Haslett and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-09T16:09:13-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Senate Republicans set to put Cassidy-Crapo health proposal up for a vote Thursday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/senate-republican-heath-vote-00683250</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-049c-d533-a99b-04fc70140003</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:38:15 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans will offer a <a href="http://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3386" target="_blank">health care plan</a> for a vote Thursday alongside a Democratic proposal to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies, capping off days of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/senate-republicans-obamacare-health-00682318" target="_blank">furious behind-the-scenes debates</a>.</p> 
<p>The decision announced Tuesday by Senate Majority Leader John Thune is a U-turn from just a day prior, when GOP leadership appeared likely to skip a vote on a Republican alternative to the Democrats’ proposal, which would continue the expiring subsidies for three years.</p> 
<p>But that strategy sparked grumbling from various corners of the GOP conference, who believed they should put up their own plan to illustrate that their party has health care ideas, even if some Republican senators ultimately aren't supportive. The matter was discussed at a closed-door GOP policy lunch Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Some corners of the conference were caught off guard by the expectation that there wouldn't be a vote, especially as Democrats hammer them over health care, according to two people granted anonymity to speak candidly about the reason for the shift.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans ultimately agreed to vote on a proposal from Sens. Mike Crapo of Idaho and Bill Cassidy of Louisiana, who chair the Finance and HELP committees respectively. Their bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/cassidy-crapo-unveil-alternative-to-obamacare-subsidies-00682315" target="_blank">expands health savings accounts and includes funding</a> for Americans to spend on health expenses but does not extend the Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>“Our members decided that we’re going to vote on a Crapo-Cassidy proposal,” Thune told reporters.</p> 
<p>That fits in with a rough framework supported by President Donald Trump, who declined to commit to extending the subsidies in a Monday interview with POLITICO. “I want to give the money to the people, not to the insurance companies,” he said.</p> 
<p>But a White House official, granted anonymity to discuss the administration’s thinking, said that there was not a preferred plan among the several currently floating around Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Neither the Crapo-Cassidy plan nor the Democratic proposal will get the 60 votes needed to advance Thursday. And it's far from clear if the Republican proposal will win the backing of all 53 GOP senators.</p> 
<p>Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.), who has his own competing proposals, said he’s “still looking at” the Crapo-Cassidy bill, for instance.</p> 
<p>Republicans have struggled perennially for years to unite around a health care plan. Thune acknowledged Tuesday that most, but potentially not all, of the conference would back the bill.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said some in her party “still have questions about implementation” of the Cassidy-Cassidy plan, though she said it was good Republicans were putting something forward.</p> 
<p>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) said Tuesday after the lunch that she was still reviewing the legislation.</p> 
<p>“There are many good provisions in that plan that I think would be helpful to driving down health care costs,” Collins said.</p> 
<p>Collins and Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/gop-senators-circulate-health-care-plans-ahead-of-thursday-vote-00680645" target="_blank">proposed a two-year extension</a> of the expiring Affordable Care Act credits with new eligibility restrictions such as income caps and minimum premium payments. If the enhanced subsidies expire, the tax credits will revert back to their original, pre-Covid levels.</p> 
<p>Other GOP senators could try to pass or set up votes this week on their own competing bills by seeking unanimous consent, according to their colleagues.</p> 
<p><i>Cheyenne Haslett and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brad Lander set to challenge Rep. Dan Goldman from the left</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/brad-lander-set-to-challenge-rep-dan-goldman-from-the-left-00682619</link>
      <description>The city comptroller and former mayoral candidate will have the endorsement of Zohran Mamdani, two people tell POLITICO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-038e-dea0-a7df-0bdff6c40001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:20:56 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4f/a1/7245c2624d1f8a0fde3179278fac/ice-protests-new-york-15327.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Olga Fedorova/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Brad Lander, the progressive New York City city comptroller, is set to launch his primary challenge to Rep. Dan Goldman.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4f/a1/7245c2624d1f8a0fde3179278fac/ice-protests-new-york-15327.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Emily Ngo</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Emily Ngo</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NEW YORK — Brooklyn progressive Brad Lander is planning to launch his bid for Congress as soon as Wednesday, challenging Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/320509" data-person-id="320509">Dan Goldman</a> from the political left in a district that went big for Zohran Mamdani, three people familiar with his preparations told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>The city comptroller is expected to open his campaign with a pivotal endorsement from Mamdani, the democratic socialist mayor-elect’s first formal nod since his November election win upended the Democratic landscape. Lander has also sought support from progressive Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51605" data-person-id="51605">Bernie Sanders</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a>, according to two people close to Lander.</p> 
<p>Lander shot his campaign launch video, with some scenes from his Park Slope community, two people with knowledge of his operations said. And he is interviewing for the Working Families Party endorsement, four more people confirmed to POLITICO. The people looped into Lander’s plans were granted anonymity to protect a sensitive rollout process.</p> 
<p>Lander’s entry will mark New York progressives’ boldest salvo yet in primaries to unseat more mainstream party members on the heels of Mamdani’s ascension to the helm of the country’s largest city. The fiscal wonk and Israel critic is a favorite of left-leaning voters in the liberal congressional district, which encompasses lower Manhattan and northwest Brooklyn and overlaps Lander’s former City Council district.</p> 
<p>“These are urgent times when ICE agents are abducting our neighbors, Donald Trump is stealing money from New York City’s bank account. I think people are looking for leaders who will put their bodies on the line,” Lander told reporters Friday after <a href="https://www.nydailynews.com/2025/12/05/comptroller-brad-lander-pleads-not-guilty-in-ice-protest-as-he-mulls-run-for-congress/" target="_blank">pleading not guilty</a> to trespassing and related charges tied to <a href="https://x.com/emilyngo/status/1968769479623557346?s=20" target="_blank">his September sit-in protesting</a> the detention of migrants at 26 Federal Plaza. He said Friday he had not made a decision on running for Congress but was seriously considering it.</p> 
<p>Lander's team did not immediately comment on his plans Tuesday when contacted by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>Mamdani defeated Andrew Cuomo in Goldman’s 10th Congressional District by 23 points in the June mayoral primary. In that same contest, Lander placed third in the district, just a quarter of a percentage point behind Cuomo, the moderate former governor. Lander helped clear the democratic socialist’s path to the nomination <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/13/mamdani-lander-cross-endorsing-mayor-00405357" target="_blank">with a cross-endorsement deal</a> that many in the progressive movement <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/02/brad-lander-is-riding-a-wave-of-good-will-00436553" target="_blank">lauded as a sacrifice</a> for the cause. While Lander is a progressive and Working Families Party darling, he is not a member of the Democratic Socialists of America.</p> 
<p>Goldman — a Manhattan Democrat, second-term House member and former prosecutor — was lead counsel in President Donald Trump’s first impeachment process. While Goldman is a scion of the Levi Strauss empire and a staunch defender of Israel, he has championed progressive policies as co-sponsor of Medicare for All and Green New Deal legislation. The incumbent has advocated <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/12/05/mamdanis-volunteer-army-reassembles-00678203?nname=new-york-playbook&amp;nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b74f0000&amp;nrid=0000014f-8906-d780-a9ef-9d7e2a4c0000#:~:text=Rep.%20Dan%20Goldman-,TAX%20MYSELF%3A,-Rep.%20Dan%20Goldman" target="_blank">for taxing the ultra-wealthy</a> — including himself — and criticized settler violence in the West Bank. Both Goldman and Lander are Jewish.</p> 
<p>Lander and Goldman are aligned in the resistance against Trump’s ramped-up deportation agenda and have <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/10/01/what-the-shutdown-means-for-new-york-00589342?nname=new-york-playbook&amp;nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b74f0000&amp;nrid=0000014f-8906-d780-a9ef-9d7e2a4c0000#:~:text=Wong/Getty%20Images-,PRESSURE%20ON%20ICE%3A,-Rep.%20Dan%20Goldman" target="_blank">even worked in tandem.</a> Both Democrats are a frequent presence at 26 Federal Plaza, the lower Manhattan administrative building where migrants have been detained by masked federal agents as they attend immigration court hearings.</p> 
<p>“These are nonviolent, noncriminal people, often escaping terrible conditions in their country, seeking refuge here, and now, they are being yanked away from their families, detained and deported,” Goldman told reporters Monday as he and Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/193043" data-person-id="193043">Adriano Espaillat</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51659" data-person-id="51659">Nydia Velázquez</a> unveiled legislation to protect migrants from arrest as they attend their court dates and follow pathways to legal status.</p> 
<p>At least two other progressive Democrats are considering a bid for Congress in the district. City Council Member Alexa Avilés, chair of the council’s Immigration Committee and a democratic socialist, and former Assemblymember Yuh-Line Niou, who came in second place to Goldman in the 2022 primary for the district, also appealed to the Manhattan and Brooklyn chapters of the Working Families Party for their support. Goldman did as well.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: What Trump told POLITICO about health care</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/09/congress/president-trump-health-care-obamacare-00682436</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0173-dc13-a39b-3bff436e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>TRUMP’S TAKE ON HEALTH TALKS —</b> President Donald Trump in an exclusive interview with POLITICO's Dasha Burns was noncommittal on the fate of Obamacare subsidies set to lapse at the end of the month, the latest sign that Republicans will let them expire.</p> 
<p>Pressed on whether he would intervene and ask Congress to extend the tax credits, Trump said, “I don’t know. I’m going to have to see.” He instead touted his rough vision for a health care revamp.</p> 
<p>“I want to give the people better health insurance for less money,” he said. “The people will get the money and they’re going to buy the health insurance that they want.”</p> 
<p>Watch the interview and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/trump-dasha-burns-interview-europe-immigration-ukraine-00682016" target="_blank">read a rundown</a> of the newsiest bits on Latin America, the economy, the Supreme Court and Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.). “She was a loyal person until I wasn’t able to answer her phone calls,” he said.</p> 
<p><b>SENATE GOP SEARCHES FOR UNITY —</b> With just two days until Democrats get a vote on their proposal to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies, Republican senators <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/senate-republicans-obamacare-health-00682318" target="_blank">have yet to coalesce behind an alternative</a> to put up alongside it.</p> 
<p>“What signal would that send if Republicans say, ‘Yeah, we’re going to say no to the Democrats’ plan, but we’re not going to offer anything?’” Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said. “The message that will send is, good luck to the American people, and we don’t really care.”</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are expected to discuss their options at a closed-door lunch Tuesday afternoon and make a decision about which direction to take.</p> 
<p><b>— The competing proposals:</b> Factions of the conference are either ready to extend enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies or replace them with new frameworks.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune on Monday praised a proposal by Sens. Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) and Bill Cassidy (R-La.) expanding the use of health savings accounts and directing funding toward them — without extending the tax credits. Thune took steps Monday night to make the bill available for a vote later this week, as Republicans try to keep options on the table. But he didn’t commit to putting it up for a vote Thursday.</p> 
<p>Sens. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) and Susan Collins (R-Maine) proposed a two-year subsidy extension with new income caps and other eligibility restrictions — a plan that won some Democratic interest from Illinois Sen. Dick Durbin, the No. 2 party leader.</p> 
<p><b>— The path ahead: </b>The Democratic proposal is likely to fail Thursday even though a handful of Republicans haven’t said yet how they will vote. Hawley, for instance, said Monday “everything is on the table.”</p> 
<p>But Thune is suggesting there will be further bipartisan negotiations afterward. There’s hope on both sides of the aisle that failure could spark new momentum as some lawmakers start eyeing Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cutoff to land a health care deal.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— NDAA hits Rules: </b>The House plans to vote on the National Defense Authorization Act Wednesday afternoon — assuming it gets through the Rules Committee Tuesday evening. House Democrats could support the defense policy bill after House Armed Services ranking member Adam Smith (D-Wash.) signaled he’s on board. That means the biggest issue for Republicans likely won’t be final passage, but instead the rule vote Wednesday if some in the GOP choose to tank the party-line vote.</p> 
<p><b>— Digital trade legislation: </b>Sen. Todd Young (R-Ind.) is introducing a bipartisan bill Tuesday that would empower the president to negotiate and enforce digital trade agreements — but also give Congress the opportunity to review and block those agreements. The move signals potential renewed interest from Congress in addressing the taxation of digital goods.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Mia McCarthy and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-08T23:25:20-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Why Senate Republicans aren't uniting behind a health care plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/senate-republicans-obamacare-health-00682318</link>
      <description>Voting on any alternative to Democrats' Obamacare extension is likely to highlight the divisions in the GOP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-00ba-d77a-a99f-09fe1e300000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 20:32:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/88/78/d79427e848daa2801ef8c856799d/u-s-congress-70222.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I don’t think they’re serious about wanting to do a deal yet," Thune said about Democrats Monday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/88/78/d79427e848daa2801ef8c856799d/u-s-congress-70222.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/gop-senators-circulate-health-care-plans-ahead-of-thursday-vote-00680645" target="_blank">no shortage of health care plans</a>. The challenge is getting all 53 of them to rally behind one.</p> 
<p>Three days before a high-profile vote on a Democratic proposal to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies, GOP senators are nowhere near coalescing behind any single alternative that could be put up alongside it. Instead, Republican leaders appear happy allowing their members to freelance, even as Democrats and some in their own ranks fume at the lack of clear direction.</p> 
<p>For Republicans, the risk of proceeding Thursday with a side-by-side vote is clear. While Democrats say they will have their entire 47-member caucus behind the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3385" target="_blank">three-year extension</a>, any GOP plan right now is likely to fall well short of complete unity — and highlight the divisions in their party.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> called the upcoming vote on Democrats’ plan “a political messaging exercise,” one he agreed to last month as part of a deal to end the 47-day government shutdown. He didn’t commit to putting up a GOP counteroffer for a vote.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think they’re serious about wanting to do a deal yet, so I think that may be what this week is about,” Thune told reporters Monday. “But we’ll see from there if there is a genuine interest in trying to do something.”</p> 
<p>GOP senators are expected to further discuss their options at a closed-door lunch Tuesday and make a final decision about their posture. But, according to three Republican aides granted anonymity to comment on internal conference dynamics, leaders are not currently expected to offer an alternative for a vote Thursday.</p> 
<p>One of the aides said Republicans will be prepared to make the case they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/06/obamacare-plans-schumer-trump-congress-00679712" target="_blank">have plenty of ideas</a> and are ready to talk with Democrats once they move off a proposal that won’t get the 60 votes needed to advance.</p> 
<p>But some Republicans want their leaders to put some concrete alternatives forward as more than 20 million Americans face the loss of enhanced Obamacare tax credits that were implemented as a Covid relief measure under President Joe Biden in 2021 and later extended through 2025. Without them, many families could see premiums rise by $1,000 a year or more.</p> 
<p>“What signal would that send if Republicans say, ‘Yeah, we’re going to say no to the Democrats’ plan, but we’re not going to offer anything?’” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.) said. “The message that will send is, good luck to the American people, and we don’t really care.”</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said in an interview that simply standing aside while Democrats vote to extend the subsidies would be “a big mistake.”</p> 
<p>“A lot of my colleagues, I think, will be very upset if we don't put something up,” he said.</p> 
<p>But there are multiple competing proposals that are favored by subsets of the Senate GOP. Some of them include shorter extensions of the expiring subsidies. Others seek to replace them with new frameworks, generally involving giving Americans cash in the form of health savings accounts to help underwrite premiums and other costs.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.) is among those pushing for a clean break from the Affordable Care Act subsidy framework that reflects “what we believe in” as free-market-oriented Republicans. “I always think it's good to have an alternative,” he said in an interview.</p> 
<p>But Thune praised another <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3386" target="_blank">proposal</a> being circulated by Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> of Idaho and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana, who chair the health-oriented Finance and HELP committees, respectively.</p> 
<p>Their proposal, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/cassidy-crapo-unveil-alternative-to-obamacare-subsidies-00682315" target="_blank">released Monday</a>, would expand the use of health savings accounts and direct funding toward them without extending the enhanced Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>Cassidy said Monday that it is a “leadership decision” if his proposal gets a vote Thursday. Thune took steps Monday night to make the bill available for a vote later this week, as Republicans try to keep options on the table ahead of Tuesday’s lunch.</p> 
<p>But Thune also acknowledged some of his members have other ideas centered on extending the enhanced subsidies with a new income cap and other eligibility restrictions. Republican Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> of Ohio and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> of Maine, for instance, propose to extend the expiring subsidies for two years with income cap restrictions and minimum premium payments.</p> 
<p>That proposal won some Democratic interest Monday from Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.), the No. 2 party leader, who called it “encouraging” and “in the ballpark” of a workable solution — though he cautioned he hadn’t seen the details.</p> 
<p>“It's not crazy,” Durbin said. “Let’s have a conversation.”</p> 
<p>The Senate GOP is straining to formulate a path forward as House Republicans race to come up with their own plan in hopes of putting some health care legislation up for a vote next week before lawmakers break for the holidays — and the enhanced subsidies expire, returning them to the original levels as passed in the 2010 Affordable Care Act.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders still need to make key decisions, including if they try to assemble one bill or put up a suite of bills for members to pick and choose from. But they, too, are under pressure from a slice of members to embrace an extension of the subsidies — even as most in the party are happy to see them expire.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump hasn't put forward his own framework, which could have helped rally the disparate factions of his party on Capitol Hill. And Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> hammered Republicans Monday, saying that they “have no plan.”</p> 
<p>“The question Republicans face this week is very simple: Will they support our bill and lower people’s premiums or will they block our bill and send premiums through the roof?” Schumer said from the Senate floor Monday.</p> 
<p>While the Democratic proposal is expected to fall well short of the necessary 60 votes, a handful of Republicans haven’t said yet how they will vote. Hawley, for instance, said Monday “everything is on the table.”</p> 
<p>“What I’m not going to do is do nothing,” he said.</p> 
<p>It's likely Thursday’s vote won't be the last word on health care this Congress. Thune left the door open to further bipartisan negotiations, and there’s some hope on both sides of the aisle that a failed vote — or votes — could in fact lend new momentum to the talks. Lawmakers are increasingly eyeing Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cutoff to land a health care deal.</p> 
<p>But getting to that point will require Democrats to compromise and Republicans to get together behind a plan of some kind. Asked Monday if his ranks were united or divided on health care, Thune acknowledged reality for a party that has struggled on the issue for decades.</p> 
<p>“I think we have people in different camps, as you would expect,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this article misstated the average premium increase for households losing enhanced subsidies. It is about $1,000 a year.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Texas Rep. Marc Veasey to drop his reelection bid</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/texas-rep-marc-veasey-to-drop-his-reelection-bid-00682223</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0068-da6e-a9bf-acffdf160000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 19:15:38 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Marc Veasey is set to drop his House bid in a Dallas-area seat and will instead run for Tarrant County judge, according to a person familiar with the situation granted anonymity.</p> 
<p>It’s the latest reshuffle brought on by the Texas GOP’s gerrymander, which could yield the party as many as five additional seats in next year’s midterms. Veasey’s north Texas district was redrawn to favor Republicans.</p> 
<p>Veasey had been expected to run for the seat being vacated by Democratic Rep. Jasmine Crockett, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/crockett-announces-texas-senate-bid-00680505" target="_blank"><u>launched her Senate campaign</u></a> on Monday after former Rep. Colin Allred dropped out of that race. Punchbowl News first reported Veasey’s decision.</p> 
<p>Allred’s decision to bow out of the Senate race and instead run for a seat in the House sets up yet another primary battle between the former NFL linebacker and Rep. Julie Johnson (D-Texas) in the state’s newly redrawn 33rd Congressional District. Johnson succeeded Allred after he left the House for his first Senate bid in 2024.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP leaders plan Wednesday NDAA vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/house-gop-leaders-plan-wednesday-ndaa-vote-00681502</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-ffea-d750-a99a-ffefc9c10004</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 16:44:50 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders are planning to pass the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_1071" target="_blank">annual defense policy bill</a> late Wednesday afternoon, according to three people granted anonymity to comment on the scheduling ahead of an official announcement.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders unveiled <a href="https://docs.house.gov/billsthisweek/20251208/RCP_xml[2].pdf" target="_blank">text of the 3,086-page bill</a> Sunday evening and are already facing public pushback from hard-line conservatives over the inclusion of Ukraine funding, the omission of a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/french-hill-at-odds-with-warren-scott-waters-over-ndaa-provisions-00663438" target="_blank">Federal Reserve digital currency ban</a> and other issues.</p> 
<p>While Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> can likely count on support from some Democrats on the final vote, he first must keep his own party together on a procedural vote expected earlier Wednesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>To build unity, House GOP leaders are touting a variety of conservative wins in the final bill, including provisions taking aim at diversity and equity programs in the ranks. They also are declaring victory on measures that crack down on U.S. investment in China and repeal decades-old Middle East war powers authorizations.</p> 
<p>But some conservatives could be turned off by leaders’ decision to drop some social policy riders as well as the inclusion of language that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/07/compromise-defense-bill-trump-europe-troop-withdrawals-00680407" target="_blank">restricts Trump from significantly reducing</a> U.S. troop levels in Europe.</p> 
<p><i>Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeSantis: Trump’s AI order ‘can’t preempt’ states from taking action</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/desantis-trump-ai-order-states-action-00681301</link>
      <description>As President Donald Trump eyes a federal top-down AI “rulebook," the GOP governor maintained it should be up to Congress, not the president, to establish such a sweeping policy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-ffb7-d4a2-afde-fff760490006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 16:17:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c4/16/00f24dcd4807944d946885dafc4f/trump-immigration-51865.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Evan Vucci/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>DeSantis, a fierce AI skeptic, is pushing Florida to enact a slate of AI protections for residents during the upcoming legislative session and has the backing of state lawmakers.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c4/16/00f24dcd4807944d946885dafc4f/trump-immigration-51865.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Atterbury</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Atterbury</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>TALLAHASSEE, Florida — Gov. Ron DeSantis cast doubt Monday on the Trump administration’s ability to restrict states like Florida from regulating artificial intelligence, with new federal guidelines expected soon.</p> 
<p>DeSantis, a fierce AI skeptic, is pushing Florida to enact a slate of AI protections for residents during the upcoming legislative session and has the backing of state lawmakers, who are holding several hearings on the topic this week. But as President Donald Trump eyes a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/trump-says-ai-executive-order-limiting-state-rules-coming-this-week-00680557?utm_medium=bluesky&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank">federal top-down AI “rulebook”</a> that could stymie Florida’s efforts, the GOP governor maintained it should be up to Congress, not the president, to establish such a sweeping policy. </p> 
<p>“An executive order doesn’t/can’t preempt state legislative action,” DeSantis posted on <a href="https://x.com/RonDeSantis/status/1998101450442895531" target="_blank">social media</a> Monday. “Congress could, theoretically, preempt states through legislation.”</p> 
<p>“The problem is that Congress hasn’t proposed any coherent regulatory scheme but instead just wanted to block states from doing anything for 10 years, which would be an AI amnesty," DeSantis continued. "I doubt Congress has the votes to pass this because it is so unpopular with the public." </p> 
<p>Trump’s hardline insistence on the federal government crafting AI regulations instead of states puts the president in a unique position with DeSantis, one of the loudest voices calling for states to take action. While the relationship between DeSantis and Trump has been strained at times, the governor has avoided direct criticism of the president and has largely been apprehensive of Congress proposing a lengthy moratorium blocking local AI laws.</p> 
<p>The president’s promise of an AI executive order coming down this week, though, could put a damper on possible moves sought by DeSantis and other state leaders.</p> 
<p>Florida lawmakers have introduced several bills to rein in AI, such as requiring insurance claim denials to come from a “qualified human,” and are likely to file more by the time session begins in January. DeSantis, for his part, wants a “bill of rights” stuffed with AI protections for consumers and residents, like preventing utility companies from up-charging residents when tech companies build massive data centers.</p> 
<p>With Trump’s AI action looming, state legislative leaders are currently taking a wait-and-see approach on how it could ultimately restrict them.</p> 
<p>“I haven't read the executive order, so I don't know,” state Senate President Ben Albritton (R-Wauchula) told reporters Monday. “I don't know the answer to the question, not until I see what it is specifically that the president comes out with and where that relates to what our authorities are.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republican Bruce Blakeman planning to enter race for New York governor</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/republican-bruce-blakeman-planning-to-enter-race-for-new-york-governor-00681465</link>
      <description>His campaign would complicate Rep. Elise Stefanik’s path. Trump praises both.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-ffbf-d77a-a99e-ffff10210001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 16:13:15 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9e/56/788a15db4276829e214255f78895/ap25035860352763.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Yuki Iwamura/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman plans to run for New York governor, setting up a primary with Rep. Elise Stefanik and pitting two allies of President Donald Trump against each other.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9e/56/788a15db4276829e214255f78895/ap25035860352763.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nick Reisman, Emily Ngo and Bill Mahoney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nick Reisman, Emily Ngo and Bill Mahoney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman is preparing to enter the race for New York governor as soon as Tuesday, according to two people with direct knowledge of his plans.</p> 
<p>Blakeman’s decision to seek the Republican nomination is a major snag in Rep. Elise Stefanik’s efforts to secure GOP backing in her challenge to Democratic Gov. Kathy Hochul, who is running for a second full term next year.</p> 
<p>The looming primary has the makings of a battle royale between two ardent supporters of President Donald Trump — a generational fight pitting an ascendent woman in the Republican Party against a stalwart GOP officeholder who has been on the periphery of the Empire State’s political scene for decades.</p> 
<p>Blakeman, who last month won reelection in the suburbs east of New York City, has said Trump has not discouraged him from seeking statewide office. The president offered no preference Monday when reporters asked about Blakeman and Stefanik, appearing to signal that he doesn’t mind them competing.</p> 
<p>“He’s great and she’s great,” Trump said at the White House. “They’re both great people.”</p> 
<p>Hochul more overtly welcomed the competition.</p> 
<p>“If there’s a Republican primary, it makes it much more entertaining for me,” Hochul said about Blakeman’s launch. “Let them go at it. Let’s see how they out-MAGA each other.”</p> 
<p>Hochul has reason to be reassured. Republican Lee Zeldin competed in a four-candidate primary in 2022 and eventually came within 6 points of unseating her. Some New York Republicans grumble that Zeldin lost time he could have used to focus on Hochul and was drained of resources as a result.</p> 
<p>The people who spoke with POLITICO about Blakeman’s announcement were granted anonymity to discuss the sensitive matter. A Blakeman spokesperson declined to comment on the pending launch.</p> 
<p>The county executive has downplayed the problems a primary would pose.</p> 
<p>“You gotta be sharp. You gotta be on your game if you want to win this,” he said when he was beginning to explore his bid. “There’s not a large margin of error for Republicans. So I think it sharpens both candidates if there is a primary in many circumstances as long as you can keep it from not degrading into namecalling and things of that nature, which I would never do.”</p> 
<p>Hochul, who faces her own primary challenge against Lt. Gov. Antonio Delgado, led Stefanik 52 percent to 27 percent in <a href="https://sri.siena.edu/2025/09/16/hochul-approval-favorability-ratings-up-a-little-favorability-best-since-jan-24-majority-hochul-works-hard-demonstrates-honesty-integrity-plurality-gets-things-done-provides-dec/?_gl=1*7cmts4*_ga*MjAyMDI4ODQzNC4xNzQ0MDYzODQ1*_ga_XN3VDZ9ZYZ*czE3NjUxNjQ1Mzkkbzg0JGcwJHQxNzY1MTY0NTM5JGo2MCRsMCRoMA.." target="_blank"><u>a Siena University poll last month</u></a>. In their bid to defeat the governor, Republicans plan to leverage New York City mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani’s ascendance to City Hall — tying the moderate Hochul to the 34-year-old democratic socialist who is unpopular in the suburban counties.</p> 
<p>The suburbs will be key to Blakeman’s campaign.</p> 
<p>While he’s not well known statewide, the Nassau County executive hails from vote-rich Long Island, which has trended toward Republicans in recent elections. He identifies <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/11/19/gops-2026-abortion-conundrum-00658469" target="_blank"><u>as a “pro-choice Republican”</u></a> — a position that stands to complicate his ability to win over GOP voters in a closed party primary. Republicans, though, are hungry to win after being shut out of statewide office in New York for the last 20 years, and a less rigid stance on abortion rights may win over moderate voters.</p> 
<p>Blakeman is also a Trump-allied Republican <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/07/19/bruce-blakeman-trump-00169768" target="_blank"><u>who revels in culture wars</u></a> and has twice won a purple county where registered Democrats outnumber Republicans. Nassau County is home to two critical House battlegrounds, and Republicans are eager to flip the seats held by Reps. Tom Suozzi and Laura Gillen in an effort to retain the majority in Washington.</p> 
<p>“Even before the election, a lot of community leaders, business leaders, political leaders asked me if I would get into the race because they feel that I would have the best chance to beat Kathy Hochul because of my attraction to crossover Democrats and independent voters,” <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/11/11/blakeman-tests-the-waters-00646111" target="_blank"><u>Blakeman said</u></a> last month after he won reelection.</p> 
<p>He has taken a conservative line on trans athletes, masking in public and is eager to have local law enforcement coordinate with federal immigration enforcement efforts.</p> 
<p>He also enjoys a warm relationship with The New York Post, the influential conservative tabloid owned by Rupert Murdoch. Blakeman this year announced the Post would become the “official newspaper” of Nassau County.</p> 
<p>But Blakeman will face an immediate fundraising crunch. Stefanik, an aggressive fundraiser, formally entered the race for governor in November, but she has been effectively a candidate since the summer after Rep. Mike Lawler bowed out to run for reelection in his swing House seat. Stefanik has made early inroads with Republicans statewide, funding an effort to boost the party’s local-level candidates in the November elections.</p> 
<p>Trump likely will loom large in the race. Democrats are poised to tether the president to whoever emerges as the GOP nominee. And Trump’s May endorsement of Lawler’s House reelection bid almost certainly influenced the Hudson Valley Republican’s decision to forgo a gubernatorial run. If Trump decides to favor Stefanik or Blakeman, it is almost certain to have an impact on whether one or the other remains in the running.</p> 
<p>“I spoke to President Trump on election night. He congratulated me,” Blakeman said in November. “I told him I wanted to sit down and talk to him. And he said he was willing to sit down and talk about it. He didn’t discourage me.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-08T15:36:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Senate Judiciary plans hearings around Jack Smith probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/senate-judiciary-plans-smith-hearings-00681147</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-ff86-d750-a99a-ff8724080000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 15:00:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate Judiciary Committee will hold hearings in early 2026 surrounding former special counsel Jack Smith’s investigation into President Donald Trump — culminating in a hearing later in the year<b>&nbsp;</b>where Smith will testify in person before the panel.</p> 
<p>“Arctic Frost was a runaway train that swept up information from hundreds of innocent people simply because of their political affiliation,” Senate Judiciary Chair Chuck Grassley said in a statement, shared first with POLITICO. “Congress and the American people want answers, and sunshine is the best disinfectant.”</p> 
<p>The Iowa Republican continued, “The Senate Judiciary Committee is leading this investigation to find out exactly what went wrong, so that bad actors can be held accountable and this sort of political witch hunt never happens again.”</p> 
<p>The announcement follows news that Smith requested Republican lawmakers’ phone records as part of his probe into Trump’s efforts to subvert the results of the 2020 election. The revelations enraged GOP senators, who argued Smith’s investigation amounted to a weaponization of the Justice Department and have been clamoring for hearings.</p> 
<p>Four Senate Judiciary subcommittees are expected host hearings beginning in January focusing on how telecommunications companies responded to Smith’s subpoenas for lawmakers’ data; legal issues presented by those subpoenas; how judges handled non-disclosure orders for Smith’s subpoenas; and the use of government resources for the probe.</p> 
<p>Among those who could be chairing the subcommittee hearings will be Sens. Marsha Blackburn (R-Tenn.) and Josh Hawley (R-Mo.), who were among the senators singled out by Smith. Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas) is another subcommittee chair expected to oversee a hearing who claims to have been subject to a subpoena.</p> 
<p>It’s not clear when Smith will testify before a full Senate Judiciary Committee hearing, but he is scheduled to testify across the Capitol next Wednesday behind closed doors to staff investigators with the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio), who is leading that effort, had his phone data requested by the Biden Justice Department prior to Smith joining the investigations into 2020 election interference and Trump's handling of classified documents.</p> 
<p>“Jack remains ready and willing to discuss his work as Special Counsel, and we're happy the American people will have the opportunity to hear directly from him about his investigation into President Trump’s alleged retention of classified documents and efforts to overturn the 2020 election," Peter Koski, an attorney for Smith, said in a statement Monday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP struggles on affordability message</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/08/congress/republicans-affordability-2026-midterms-health-care-vote-00680489</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-fc72-d0a4-a1be-ffff65a60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate is set to vote Thursday on whether to extend Obamacare health insurance subsidies that expire in 23 days. How Republicans will engage remains up in the air, as the party struggles more broadly to reach consensus on a range of “affordability” issues.</p> 
<p>Here’s where things stand heading into the big vote.</p> 
<p><b>The Senate GOP’s missing plan —</b> Senate Democrats are poised to get a vote on a three-year extension of Affordable Care Act tax credits — a bill that will likely fail. Republicans are leaning against holding a separate vote on their own alternative as they face internal divisions over what to put forward. The decision isn’t final, and some Republicans could try to advance proposals via unanimous consent.</p> 
<p><b>Mysterious House action — </b>Speaker Mike Johnson surprised a number of Republicans last Thursday when he <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/johnson-house-gop-health-care-plan-00676661" target="_blank">said he planned to roll out a health care framework</a> in time to present to his conference by early this week. The House GOP strategy is expected to be a major topic of discussion during a retreat of committee staff directors and leadership staff that wraps tonight in Boston. The House Republican plan is likely to encompass bills that committees have been working on to boost health care options beyond the ACA — not an extension of Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p><b>The big picture on the GOP and affordability — </b>Republicans’ struggle over how to address the expiring ACA subsidies — a lapse that would raise health premiums for millions of Americans — is representative of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/republicans-affordability-congress-00679545" target="_blank">broader GOP floundering</a> over how to decisively respond to cost-of-living concerns ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>Beyond health care, the Trump administration’s proposal to distribute $2,000 rebate checks has gotten a lukewarm response on the Hill, and intraparty sparring has weighed on other smaller bills to address things like housing costs and student debt. Top Republicans acknowledge they haven’t done enough to sell the economic benefits of the “one big, beautiful bill,” and internal divisions threaten any attempt to follow up on it.</p> 
<p>Just this weekend, congressional leaders released a compromise version of the annual National Defense Authorization Act without housing legislation sought by Senate Banking Chair Tim Scott (R-S.C.) and ranking member Elizabeth Warren (D-Mass.), after House Financial Services Chair French Hill (R-Ark.) and other key House Republicans objected.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump himself has recently called the emphasis on affordability a “hoax” perpetrated by Democrats, even as 37 percent of those who voted for him last year say the cost of living in the U.S. is the worst they can remember it being, according to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/poll-americans-trump-voters-affordability-crisis-00674747?orgid=756&amp;uniquet=vjmpEOsQvIeM0oJsD61kEg&amp;utm_att1=" target="_blank">a new POLITICO Poll</a>.</p> 
<p>“We haven’t probably messaged as effectively as we should,” Senate Majority Leader John Thune said in an interview. “I think we’ll have lots of opportunities now that we’re getting into an election year to talk about the things we’ve done and how they are going to lead to things being more affordable for the American people, probably starting with tax relief next year.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— NDAA on track for House vote this week: </b>Compromise NDAA <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-fc11-d0a4-a1be-ffdd6f110000" target="_blank">text is out</a> and House GOP leaders are targeting a floor vote <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/07/compromise-defense-bill-trump-europe-troop-withdrawals-00680407" target="_blank">Thursday or Friday</a>. The first stop is a Rules Committee hearing, which could come as early as Tuesday.</p> 
<p><b>— Government funding action: </b>House GOP leaders are eyeing putting at least one appropriations bill if not two on the floor next week, right before they leave for the holiday recess. One senior House Republican says Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) and other appropriators are expected to lean on leadership in the coming days.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Benjamin Guggenheim, Meredith Lee Hill, Jasper Goodman, Connor O’Brien and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans have an affordability problem. They can’t agree on how to fix it.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/republicans-affordability-congress-00679545</link>
      <description>Top GOP leaders in Congress are keeping expectations low for major new economic legislation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-f0db-d5ec-adbe-f5ff3a6b000b</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/2f/b2/ba2ce1ea4867b335f500a31e77f6/u-s-congress-47476.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“Health care, as it currently is, is too expensive for everybody,” said Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.), who is pitching a plan to make more medical expenses tax-deductible.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2f/b2/ba2ce1ea4867b335f500a31e77f6/u-s-congress-47476.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Jasper Goodman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Jasper Goodman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republicans want to put the economy at the center of their midterm message as they seek to protect their majorities in Congress. But as cost-of-living concerns mount across the political spectrum, the GOP is struggling to act decisively to address them.</p> 
<p>Already top Republicans acknowledge they haven’t done enough to sell the “one big, beautiful bill,” the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/house-passes-gop-megabill-00438206" target="_blank">party-line centerpiece</a> of their economic agenda they enacted over the summer. Now internal divisions and the need for bipartisan support in the Senate are threatening any attempt to follow up on it.</p> 
<p>The GOP is struggling to coalesce behind a health care plan that would prevent Obamacare premium hikes set to kick in next month and efforts to rein in President Donald Trump’s tariffs have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/15/congress/house-gop-to-extend-block-on-tariff-votes-00565091" target="_blank">run aground in the House</a>. Meanwhile, the administration’s proposal to distribute $2,000 rebate checks has gotten a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/republicans-in-congress-lukewarm-to-the-idea-of-tariff-rebate-checks-00650747" target="_blank">lukewarm response on Capitol Hill</a> and the fate of other smaller bills to address things like housing prices and student debt have sparked intraparty sparring.</p> 
<p>“The cost of living is a legitimate issue — I think it was one of the main reasons President Trump was elected. I think it’s still an issue,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said in an interview, urging Republicans to pursue another party-line bill before the midterms in response.</p> 
<p>While many in the GOP — including Trump — continue to lay blame for their economic problems with former President Joe Biden, there are clear warning signs for Republicans. Forty-six percent of respondents in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/poll-americans-trump-voters-affordability-crisis-00674747" target="_blank">recent POLITICO Poll</a> said the cost of living is the worst they can remember it being.</p> 
<p>That includes 37 percent of those who voted for Trump in 2024, and about a quarter of Trump voters say he is either fully or mainly responsible for the current state of the economy.</p> 
<p>Yet top GOP leaders in Congress are keeping expectations low for major new economic legislation. Instead, they are betting on having an easier time addressing affordability questions next month, when new programs enacted as part of the megabill start impacting voters — like no taxes on some tips and overtime income.</p> 
<p>“We haven’t probably messaged as effectively as we should,” Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said in an interview, when asked about the party’s economic case. “I think we’ll have lots of opportunities now that we’re getting into an election year to talk about the things we’ve done and how they are going to lead to things being more affordable for the American people, probably starting with tax relief next year.”</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> also argued voters have not fully felt the impact of the megabill “because it takes a while for it to be implemented.” But he predicted that by mid-2026, “there’s going to be boats rising in the economy, this is going to be a very different situation before we go into the election cycle.”</p> 
<p>“Republicans are dialed in like a laser, with laser focus on the cost of living and affordability,” he added, while forecasting more to come: “They are going to see this agenda going forward — our affordability agenda.”</p> 
<p>But there are reasons to doubt an impending turnaround. Some of these same leaders argued this summer, as they strained to pass the megabill, that Americans would feel the economic benefits in a big way by late fall. That never materialized, with Republicans instead bogged down in a monthslong fight over releasing files related to Jeffrey Epstein and a lengthy government shutdown. Trump himself has recently taken to calling the emphasis on affordability a “hoax” <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook-pm/2025/11/14/trump-plays-the-blame-game-on-epstein-affordability-00652024" target="_blank">perpetrated by Democrats</a>.</p> 
<p>Democrats are gearing up to hammer the GOP on the issue, and some of them are hearing some familiar echoes in the promises of a rapid turnaround just around the corner. Democrats said much the same thing after their party passed their own major party-line bills as inflation rose under Biden.</p> 
<p>“They are in a bubble from Donald Trump on down,” Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> told reporters last week. “Donald Trump says there’s no affordability crisis — what kind of world is he living in?”</p> 
<p>Kennedy isn’t the only one talking up the idea of doing a second party-line bill using the budget reconciliation process to overcome a Democratic filibuster in the Senate. The Republican Study Committee, a large bloc of House conservatives, is pushing such a bill aimed at addressing affordability and other issues, and Senate Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) is vowing to plow forward in laying the groundwork for another reconciliation measure.</p> 
<p>But Johnson and Thune have treaded lightly on the prospects for second such bill, which <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">faces uphill odds</a> with the GOP divided on the policy particulars and the midterms drawing closer by the day. Instead attention is being drawn to smaller-bore efforts.</p> 
<p>Tony Fabrizio, a top Trump pollster, also urged <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/tony-fabrizio-health-drug-prices-00674841" target="_blank">members of the RSC last week</a> to tackle high prices for prescription drugs and housing — warning members in a closed-door meeting that affordability concerns were a key reason a House special election in Tennessee was so close.</p> 
<p>But even a push to attach a bipartisan housing package to the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_3838" target="_blank">annual defense policy bill</a> sparked an intraparty turf war, pitting Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> (R-S.C.) and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> (D-Mass.), the panel’s ranking member, against House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.).</p> 
<p>Scott said in an interview last week the housing measure is “a great sign that we are looking for ways to address the challenges that we see in real America” and that passing it now would put lawmakers “on the same page as President Trump and the White House.”</p> 
<p>But Hill, who plans to advance a separate housing package through his committee later this month, told senators that parts of the Senate bill are unacceptable to most House Republicans and need to be left out of the Pentagon bill.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196030" data-person-id="196030">Mike Flood</a> (R-Neb.), who is spearheading the House package, said last week he would be “amenable to something that has provisions the House wants and the Senate wants.” Thune, asked if the Senate housing provision would get in the defense bill, crossed his fingers.</p> 
<p>But no agreement could be reached over the weekend, and the House released defense bill text Sunday night that did not include the housing provisions.</p> 
<p>Other lawmakers are itching to show that the party is addressing other affordability concerns, even if those efforts face an uncertain path to becoming law. </p> 
<p>House GOP leaders, for instance, are trying to move long-delayed permitting reform legislation over the floor in the coming weeks, arguing that reducing red tape for energy and other projects would lower the cost of living. And Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> (R-Fla.) told reporters Thursday there could soon be a bipartisan effort to force a <a href="https://moskowitz.house.gov/posts/federal-student-loan-interest-rates" target="_blank">bill capping student loan interest</a> at 2 percent to the House floor.</p> 
<p>“That’s a hint for next week,” she said, when asked if she or a colleague would pursue a discharge petition aimed at sidestepping House GOP leaders who have opposed other forms of student loan relief.</p> 
<p>House and Senate Republicans, meanwhile, are having a furious behind-the-scenes debate about how to show they are trying to address health care costs ahead of the end-of-year expiration of Obamacare subsidies used by more than 20 million Americans.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151837" data-person-id="151837">John Hoeven</a> (R-N.D.) acknowledged “there’s a lot more to do” on affordability beyond this year’s megabill on health care and more: “Obviously, medical inflation is very high.”</p> 
<p>But GOP leaders in both chambers are scrambling to figure out what pieces of a health care overhaul to put forward — and getting an earful from competing factions within their own party. It’s possible Senate Republicans this week won’t put a consensus GOP alternative up for a vote alongside the three-year extension Democrats want.</p> 
<p>A plethora of rank-and-file options are under development, with Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) and Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) backing a two-year extension of the subsidies with new eligibility restrictions, Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.) wanting to provide more flexibility for health savings accounts and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.) proposing to make it <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/hawley-pitches-new-health-care-tax-plan-00674123" target="_blank">easier to deduct medical expenses</a> on their income taxes.</p> 
<p>“It’s a disaster,” Hawley said. “Health care, as it currently is, is too expensive for everybody.”</p> 
<p><i>Katherine Hapgood and Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cassidy projects optimism on winning bipartisan support for his health care plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/07/bill-cassidy-health-care-senate-00679856</link>
      <description>GOP Sen. Bill Cassidy, who chairs the Senate’s health committee, said he planned to present leadership with his plan as soon as Sunday evening.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-f99f-d0a4-a1be-fbdf2b080000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 12:17:01 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/51/c5/fb86758b43959e17b8a1501b8a29/u-s-congress-39867.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Bill Cassidy (R-La.) walks to a Senate Republican Conference luncheon at the U.S. Capitol on Wednesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/51/c5/fb86758b43959e17b8a1501b8a29/u-s-congress-39867.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy </a>(R-La.) said he planned to present Republican leadership with his health care plan as soon as Sunday night, predicting that the divisive proposal to put money directly in Americans’ health savings accounts could clear the 60-vote threshold needed to pass in the Senate.</p> 
<p>“We're working to deliver to Leader Thune and Speaker Johnson a plan, which I think could get 60 votes, which gives the American people the power, and they can choose a lower premium and an HSA,” he said in an interview on “Fox News Sunday” with host Shannon Bream. “We're working on that. And I'll give them a piece of paper probably by e-mail tonight."</p> 
<p>Cassidy is pushing for congressional leadership to advance his health care plan, which encourages Americans enrolled in Obamacare to switch to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/cassidy-fund-hsas-trump-aca-subsidies-00655213" target="_blank">lower-premium, bronze-level plans</a> with the hope that they would be able to afford higher out-of-pocket health care costs with new funding in their HSAs.</p> 
<p>But the proposal faces skepticism from Democrats and health policy experts, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/cassidys-obamacare-plan-will-not-lower-skyrocketing-premiums-democrats-and-policy-experts-say-00660894" target="_blank">caution that it would do too little</a> to help consumers facing skyrocketing premiums — merely shifting who they'd pay when — as health care subsidies are set to expire at the end of the year if Congress doesn’t work out a deal to extend them.</p> 
<p>Cassidy, who chairs the Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee, acknowledged: “You can't fix everything by January 1, 2026” but said the decision about whether or not to extend health care subsidies to some extent while lawmakers debate a more sprawling overhaul of Obamacare is ultimately “a political decision.”</p> 
<p>Cassidy said he’d been talking to Democrats about his proposal and that there was “absolute interest” in bipartisan cooperation.</p> 
<p>“We may disagree on the threshold. … But if we can get to a framework where they give the American people a choice, they can stay with the policy they have with a $6,000 deductible or they can go to another policy with a lower premium and money in a health savings account for them to purchase that which they do, the rest is just political decisions," he told Bream.</p> 
<p>House Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> was set to huddle with Republican leaders on the Hill this weekend as he races to finalize a plan ahead of Tuesday’s GOP conference meeting.</p> 
<p>Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/johnson-house-gop-health-care-plan-00676661" target="_blank">told POLITICO last week</a> he hopes to schedule a vote on a health care package before the end of the year, but House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> was noncommittal on a timeline.</p> 
<p>House leaders are considering pulling from <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/06/obamacare-plans-schumer-trump-congress-00679712" target="_blank">an array of GOP proposals</a>, including a bipartisan pitch for a one-year extension of the subsidies led by Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260077" data-person-id="260077">Josh Gottheimer</a> (D-N.J.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.) and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635" target="_blank">a two-year extension plan</a> pushed by Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.).</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump, who has voiced support for Cassidy’s health savings account plan, has opted <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/trump-health-care-congress-00675170" target="_blank">not to wade into the details</a> of what should be included in a health care package.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The government’s top watchdog is retiring — but the Trump probes continue</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/07/gene-dodaro-gao-trump-impoundment-00679550</link>
      <description>The comptroller general is wrapping up his term after an unprecedented year checking the Trump administration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-f13c-d5ec-adbe-f5bfbf9f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/45/9e/18547ec347ea8a179bf905895e17/2025-1205-gene-dodaro-francis-1-5.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Gene Dodaro, U.S. comptroller general and head of the Government Accountability Office, poses for a portrait in his office at GAO headquarters in Washington, D.C., Dec. 5, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/45/9e/18547ec347ea8a179bf905895e17/2025-1205-gene-dodaro-francis-1-5.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Gene Dodaro started his career at what is now the Government Accountability Office in 1973, as then-President Richard Nixon was battling Congress for control of federal cash.</p> 
<p>More than a half-century later, Dodaro runs that watchdog agency amid another epic clash between Capitol Hill and the White House over President Donald Trump’s funding moves. Now, with his 15-year term as comptroller general coming to an end in late December, he’s getting ready to retire.</p> 
<p>“I’m going into witness protection,” Dodaro, 74, said in a recent interview of his upcoming departure from the independent office with a workforce of more than 3,000.</p> 
<p>He meant it as a joke. But Dodaro’s agency, which is tasked with auditing federal programs and helping lawmakers fulfill their constitutional duties, has been under an unprecedented level of scrutiny this year as conservative lawmakers and the White House publicly challenge GAO’s objectivity and seek to undermine its influence.</p> 
<p>Adding to the pressure on Dodaro, the Supreme Court this fall <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/26/supreme-court-foreign-aid-impoundment-ruling-00583052" target="_blank"><u>appeared to endorse the view</u></a> that only the comptroller general has the authority to sue the Trump administration for flouting impoundment law — not the groups losing out on federal cash.</p> 
<p>Dodaro has declined to take such legal action, despite the urging of some lawmakers, including Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins. “People are already suing in many cases,” he reasoned, adding that the court’s decision “surprised” him and that he won’t be “cajoled” into suing.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see what we need to do. But we need to be prudent and make sure that — when we do it — we’re in the strongest possible position to prevail,” he added.</p> 
<p>Following the Supreme Court’s opinion, Collins said in a brief interview that it “goes without saying” this dynamic underscores the need for the lawmakers involved in the selection process to find a strong candidate to succeed Dodaro.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/33/79/8abb075347808744f8974667b4e7/scotus-07019.jpg" alt="The U.S. Supreme Court building is seen in Washington, Nov. 4, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="The U.S. Supreme Court building is seen in Washington, Nov. 4, 2025."/><p>Dodaro’s last day is Dec. 29, at which point he will hand-pick an acting comptroller general to take the reins of the agency until the Senate confirms a permanent replacement. A panel of 10 lawmakers seated on a bipartisan commission is supposed to suggest candidates for Trump to nominate.</p> 
<p>Whoever succeeds Dodaro will have to direct ongoing probes into Trump’s funding moves. To date, the agency has issued 11 opinions — five concluding the administration illegally withheld money, two citing some wrongdoing. Dozens are ongoing.</p> 
<p>“The worst thing for GAO is to look like you have an agenda. That’s what concerns me about allegations like we’re against the current president’s agenda. We’re not,” he said. “Our job, and most of what we’re doing, is in response to actions they’ve taken. It’s not things we’re bringing up out of nowhere.”</p> 
<p>Because the Office of Management and Budget has stonewalled GAO’s requests for information, the agency is forced to rely on evidence in the many lawsuits against the administration, Dodaro said.</p> 
<p>Moreover, the GAO head said he has never spoken to Trump’s budget chief, Russ Vought. Multiple attempts to make contact during the first Trump administration were unsuccessful, he added.</p> 
<p>“His public comments have led me to believe that wouldn’t be a successful approach here,” Dodaro said of Vought, who on social media this spring accused the office of taking a “partisan role in the first-term impeachment hoax,” a reference to GAO’s conclusion that Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/01/16/white-house-violated-the-law-by-freezing-ukraine-aid-gao-says-099682" target="_blank"><u>illegally withheld aid to Ukraine</u></a> in 2019.</p> 
<p>The past 11 months have been politically difficult for Dodaro in other ways. Earlier this year, top Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/27/gop-declares-war-on-gao-00369762" target="_blank"><u>derided GAO</u></a> for not blessing Senate GOP efforts to skirt filibuster rules to overturn state waivers issued under former President Joe Biden for pollution standards — and ignored the agency’s conclusion to boot.</p> 
<p>Dodaro fended off Elon Musk’s attempt to send a downsizing team to GAO as part of the president’s now-disbanded Department of Government Efficiency initiative, before House Republicans proposed cutting the agency’s budget in half for the current fiscal year.</p> 
<p>It’s not the first time the comptroller general has irked a party in power. During the Biden administration, GAO delivered its first-ever estimate of fraud in the federal government, pegging losses at between $233 billion and $521 billion dollars a year.</p> 
<p>“OMB wasn’t happy,” Dodaro recalled.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/af/df/39faac444722be58c6978b664edd/2025-1205-gene-dodaro-francis-1-1.jpg" alt="Gene Dodaro, U.S. comptroller general and head of the Government Accountability Office, poses for a portrait in his office at GAO headquarters in Washington, Dec. 5, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Gene Dodaro, U.S. comptroller general and head of the Government Accountability Office, poses for a portrait in his office at GAO headquarters in Washington, Dec. 5, 2025."/><p>Dodaro’s agency doesn’t always disappoint Republicans. Just last week, GOP lawmakers cheered a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/03/watchdog-fraudulent-obamacare-subsidies-00675085" target="_blank"><u>new GAO report</u></a> reinforcing their arguments about fraud in the Obamacare insurance marketplace. To investigate this claim, GAO set up 24 fake accounts; 22 successfully enrolled in plans. It ended up costing the federal government thousands of dollars a month.</p> 
<p>And Congress has averted several crises as a direct result of the watchdog’s warnings. That includes action to replace crucial weather satellites before they fail and to buoy the federal insurance program designed to protect Americans whose pension benefits are at risk.</p> 
<p>“GAO is incredibly valuable … the ability for Congress to ask a hard question and ask them to chase it,” said Sen. James Lankford (R-Okla.), who added that Dodaro has for years aided him in a running effort to compel federal agencies to identify and describe each program they oversee.</p> 
<p>Dodaro also started a partnership with experts at the National Academy of Sciences and launched an international effort to help developing countries run audit offices.</p> 
<p>Sen. Gary Peters (D-Mich.), who is supposed to serve on the commission to recommend candidates for a Senate-confirmed comptroller general, said lawmakers “won't find anybody as experienced and as knowledgeable” as Dodaro. “The integrity and professionalism he brought to the job, I thought, was exceptional.”</p> 
<p>Dodaro attributes any praise to decades of relationship maintenance, including with top Trump administration officials who used to be members of Congress and senators who formerly served in the House.</p> 
<p>“I try to pull out all the stops on my Italian charm,” he joked. “We’re not only in the auditing business. We’re in the relationship business.”</p> 
<p>The next comptroller general could be anyone, and it could be a long time before that person is seated. Dodaro is the only Senate-confirmed GAO chief who was picked from inside the agency, and he held the position in an acting capacity for more than two years before then-President Barack Obama nominated him upon the recommendation of lawmakers. The Senate confirmed him by unanimous consent in 2010.</p> 
<p>“If it can be done quickly, that’s fine. If it can’t, then they need to take their time to get the right person in the job, because it’s 15 years,” Dodaro said of the selection process for his successor.</p> 
<p>“I have great confidence in the people at GAO … and I have confidence in the Congress to take their responsibility seriously and pick someone. This is their person — to serve them.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pardoned Democrat Henry Cuellar wants GOP to probe his prosecutors</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/05/henry-cuellar-pardon-investigation-00679552</link>
      <description>The Texas lawmaker said in an interview he'd be willing to cooperate with a House Judiciary "weaponization" probe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-f0ea-d0a4-a1be-fbff0f660000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 19:40:52 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/86/77/463cb58b4bb1ac805c7a915ca975/u-s-congress-77382.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Henry Cuellar (D-Texas) departs a meeting on Capitol Hill Dec. 3, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/86/77/463cb58b4bb1ac805c7a915ca975/u-s-congress-77382.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just-pardoned Democratic Rep. Henry Cuellar is encouraging his Republican colleagues to investigate the prosecutors who charged him and his wife with bribery.</p> 
<p>“I really think what they did was wrong,” Cuellar said in an interview Friday, adding that he has spoken to people in the House who are investigating prosecutors under former President Joe Biden. He said he plans to share information with them about his case.</p> 
<p>Any such probe would represent a remarkable scrambling of partisan battle lines over the Justice Department. But it would be just the latest such jumble involving Cuellar, a self-proclaimed conservative Democrat who was an outlier in his party even before he faced corruption charges — and was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/henry-cuellar-trump-pardon-00674210" target="_blank">suddenly pardoned Wednesday</a> by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>The investigation Cuellar referred to appears to be an ongoing probe of DOJ "weaponization" led by House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio).</p> 
<p>Cuellar ran into Jordan shortly after Trump announced the pardon of Cuellar and his wife Wednesday, according to a person granted anonymity to describe the private conversation. Cuellar encouraged Jordan to request records from the Justice Department on his prosecution, and Jordan expressed openness to the idea, the person said.</p> 
<p>“Based on what’s there, I definitely feel that there was misconduct by the prosecutors," Cuellar said Friday. "So we’ll get more in details later on, but I certainly am convinced that this was weaponization.”</p> 
<p>Jordan spokesperson Russell Dye declined to comment.</p> 
<p>Cuellar and his wife were <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/05/03/congress/cuellar-indicted-00155977" target="_blank">charged in 2024 with accepting $600,000 in bribes</a> from foreign entities, including an oil and gas company owned by the government of Azerbaijan. Cuellar has said he and his wife were innocent of the charges.</p> 
<p>In the Truth Social post announcing the pardon Wednesday, Trump blamed Biden for using “the FBI and DOJ to ‘take out’ a member of his own party” after Cuellar criticized Biden’s immigration policies.</p> 
<p>Jordan has spearheaded investigations of Biden-era probes of Trump, leading a select subcommittee on the "Weaponization of the Federal Government." He has recently ramped up the efforts, most recently subpoenaing former special counsel Jack Smith and accusing Smith’s team of<b>&nbsp;</b>"prosecutorial misconduct and constitutional abuses" in their investigations of Trump.</p> 
<p>Cuellar reiterated in the interview that despite his criticism for his own party and his willingness to cooperate with a polarizing GOP probe, he has no plans to switch parties. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/henry-cuellar-pardon-reelection-party-00674518" target="_blank">filed for reelection as a Democrat</a> soon after he was pardoned Wednesday.</p> 
<p>"I was a Democrat, and I'm still a Democrat," he said.</p> 
<p>Cuellar also said in the interview that neither he nor his family members had hired representatives to speak to the White House on his behalf — even as former lawyers and advisers to Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/25/binance-zhao-pardon-lobby-00621788" target="_blank">have reported receiving significant sums to seek pardons</a> on behalf of accused and convicted criminals. </p> 
<p>Trump in Wednesday's Truth Social post included a letter Cuellar's daughters wrote to the president criticizing the prosecution as politically motivated and pleading for clemency.</p> 
<p>Cuellar said he found out about the pardon Wednesday when asked by a reporter about Trump’s announcement.</p> 
<p>“My daughters ... saw their mom and dad go through a very difficult time and, on their own, they wrote a letter to the president,” he said. “Apparently the president read it and made a decision.”</p> 
<p><i>Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Supreme Court gave Trump a big redistricting win. But the fight is just getting started.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/05/trump-redistricting-fight-indiana-pressure-00678789</link>
      <description>Trump and his allies are heaping pressure on holdout Republicans in Indiana, while Democrats eye gains elsewhere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-efc7-df92-a59a-ffef69f30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 14:21:18 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/41/35/0025345a40909bb562df0ad29593/img-1399.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Adam Wren/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>The focus now shifts to Indianapolis, where the Donald Trump's allies are heaping pressure on GOP holdouts in the state Senate who are resisting the president's demands to draw new lines that could net Republicans additional congressional seats.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/41/35/0025345a40909bb562df0ad29593/img-1399.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy, Adam Wren and Kyle Cheney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy, Adam Wren and Kyle Cheney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>INDIANAPOLIS — Republicans scored a major win in the redistricting fight when the Supreme Court reinstated Texas’ newly drawn congressional map on Thursday. But President Donald Trump and his allies are staring down a brewing rebellion in the Indiana Statehouse that could derail their momentum.</p> 
<p>The high court decided in an apparent 6-3 vote to block <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/supreme-court-texas-house-map-00678075" target="_blank">a lower court ruling that deemed the Texas map a likely illegal race-based gerrymander</a>. In doing so, the court’s conservative majority helped Republicans avert a nightmare scenario in which Trump’s redistricting push ultimately cost the party seats leading into the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>The focus now shifts to Indianapolis, where the president’s allies are heaping pressure on GOP holdouts in the state Senate who are resisting Trump’s demands to draw new lines there that could net Republicans additional congressional seats.</p> 
<p>In the state Capitol, as members of the state House debated final passage of a map supporters argue would all but guarantee an entirely Republican congressional delegation — from the current 7-2 split favoring the GOP — Turning Point USA held a sparsely attended rally to pressure Indiana Senate Republicans to do the same, over chants of “9-0.”</p> 
<p>“This is now the national make-or-break issue of the year,” said Brett Galaszewski of Turning Point Action, adding that Indiana “is the center of the political universe.” Gov. Mike Braun and Lt. Gov. Micah Beckwith both addressed the crowd as they faced cheers, boos and shouts of “cheaters” from counterprotesters.</p> 
<p>Earlier Friday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/05/trump-allied-pacs-target-indiana-republicans-blocking-redistricting-push-00678520" target="_blank">Turning Point Action announced</a> that it, along with Trump-aligned super PACs, would spend in excess of eight figures to primary Indiana Republicans through 2028 if they opposed the new map. And Club for Growth President David McIntosh issued a “FINAL WARNING” to Indiana Senate President Pro Tem Rodric Bray, writing, “failure to get this done means you and any other opposition will be defeated and removed from office in your next election.”</p> 
<p>All of it was designed to amp up pressure on reluctant Indiana Senate Republicans, who are expected to convene Monday to consider the new map. It’s unclear whether pro-redistricting allies have flipped any senators since they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/11/21/redistricting-indiana-resistance-00663698" target="_blank">stalemated 19-19</a>last month on a vote that was a close proxy for gerrymandering. The map passed the state House easily on Friday.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ef/39/6e172f8043fe87923f14288b92a3/img-1417.jpg" alt="The fight over the new lines across the country is expected to carry into the new year." data-portal-copyright="Adam Wren/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="The fight over the new lines across the country is expected to carry into the new year."/><p>For now, Republicans have an edge across the six states that have seen a redraw. The GOP has nine more favorable seats across four states — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/23/texas-passes-congressional-map-gerrymander-00519116" target="_blank">Texas</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/31/ohio-redistricting-gerrymander-new-map-00631254" target="_blank">Ohio</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/12/missouri-map-redistricting-midterms-00557990" target="_blank">Missouri</a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/22/north-carolina-new-house-district-gop-gerrymander-00618225" target="_blank">North Carolina</a> — while Democrats have five more blue-leaning <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/prop50-newsom-strategy-00630313" target="_blank">seats in California</a>, and an additional <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/11/utah-judge-denies-gop-passed-congressional-map-00646183?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=substack" target="_blank">court-ordered likely pickup in Utah</a>.</p> 
<p>The fight over the new lines across the country is expected to carry into the new year. Privately, Democrats were not shocked by the Texas ruling, long assuming the conservative Supreme Court was going to allow the Texas map to stand. With the Texas maps in place, Democrats involved in the nationwide battle anticipate they'll ultimately start the midterm cycle down a handful of seats, but the exact number isn't clear.</p> 
<p>Republicans see another key pickup opportunity in Florida, where party redistricting proponents think they could extract another three to five seats ahead of the midterm elections.</p> 
<p>But while the state Legislature officially kicked off the mid-decade battle in the state on Thursday, Gov. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/florida-house-barrels-ahead-on-redistricting-despite-desantis-proposed-timeline-00677841" target="_blank">Ron DeSantis and the Florida House lawmaker in charge of redistricting</a> are at odds over how quickly to do it. And the state’s prospective redraw faces another roadblock: Florida’s anti-gerrymandering standards, which hold that a new district cannot be drawn for partisan gain.</p> 
<p>Democrats, meanwhile, are homing in on Virginia. Five of the state’s 11 House seats are held by Republicans, who were trounced in a November election that bestowed on Virginia a Democratic governor, attorney general and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/virginia-house-of-delegates-winner-00636533" target="_blank">a big Statehouse majority</a>. Democrats there already kicked off <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/23/virginia-house-redistricting-democrats-00620430" target="_blank">a surprise redraw process</a> right before the election. Now, Virginia House of Delegates Speaker Don Scott is teasing a major redraw early next year.</p> 
<p>"10-1 is not out of the realm to be able to draw the maps in a succinct and community-based way," <a href="https://x.com/kkondik/status/1996315465702867116" target="_blank">he said this week</a>. “We’re gonna take a look at it. We have to.”</p> 
<p>In Missouri, Democrats are looking to challenge a map the GOP-controlled Legislature passed in September, leaving the state with just one blue district. They <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/missouri-redistricting-gerrymander-fight-00675360" target="_blank">face a Thursday deadline to submit over 100,000 signatures</a> that could trigger a referendum and temporarily block the new lines from being implemented, along with a complicated web of legal battles around the referendum process.</p> 
<p>The Department of Justice, meanwhile, is going ahead with its lawsuit to challenge California’s new congressional map, even after Attorney General Pam Bondi <a href="https://x.com/AGPamBondi/status/1996729831355044296" target="_blank">celebrated the Supreme Court’s decision</a> to greenlight Texas’ newly gerrymandered House map.</p> 
<p>But the high court’s blessing of Texas’ Republican-friendly redrawn map came with a few Easter eggs that suggested how some of the other percolating redistricting battles are likely to play out. Most notably, three of the court’s conservative justices — Samuel Alito, Clarence Thomas and Neil Gorsuch — concluded that California’s redrawn districts were “indisputably” crafted for partisan advantage.</p> 
<p>It’s unclear precisely how the justices’ decision will influence the broader national clash over mid-decade redistricting for 2026. Had the justices struck down Texas’ map, it may have increased pressure on other GOP-led states like Indiana and Florida to redraw their own boundaries to help give the party a better chance at retaining the House. On the other hand, the ruling’s clear blessing of mid-decade redistricting for partisan gain could ensure that it becomes a routine weapon in the arsenal of political warfare.</p> 
<p>But conservative justices’ signaling on California’s map bodes poorly for the Trump administration, with the DOJ and California Gov. Gavin Newsom trading barbs following the decision.</p> 
<p>“So you gonna drop your lawsuit against us right, Pam?” <a href="https://x.com/GovPressOffice/status/1996743357893415087" target="_blank">Newsom’s office asked on X Thursday night</a>.</p> 
<p>“Not a chance, Gavin — we will stop your DEI districts for 2026,” <a href="https://x.com/TheJusticeDept/status/1996763717393055933" target="_blank">the Justice Department wrote</a> back.</p> 
<p><i>Adam Wren reported from Indianapolis, and Gregory Svirnovskiy and Kyle Cheney reported from Washington. Andrew Howard contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson scrambles to pass Pentagon bill as GOP ranks seethe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/mike-johnson-ndaa-pentagon-bill-00677847</link>
      <description>The must-pass legislation will test Johnson’s ability to command and cajole his conference.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-eb92-d889-af9b-ffbbfbb20001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 17:56:32 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7a/17/2569c8ea44ac8dc834ba2ffc4719/u-s-congress-05534.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson (R-La.) speaks with reporters as he departs a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 3, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7a/17/2569c8ea44ac8dc834ba2ffc4719/u-s-congress-05534.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans spent this week venting about <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" target="_blank" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, questioning the speaker’s hold on his tenuous House majority. Next week, he has to prove he’s capable of governing.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_3838" target="_blank">annual Pentagon policy bill</a> is due on the floor just in time to test Johnson’s ability to command and cajole his conference with must-pass legislation at stake. Already GOP leaders have had to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/03/ndaa-delays-defense-bill-00676098" target="_blank">delay release of bill text</a> as they deal with a host of 11th-hour intraparty flare-ups that show just how hard it will be for the speaker to lead ahead of next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>Johnson is already <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-feud-00674030" target="_blank">bruised from a high-profile fight</a> with Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227481" target="_blank" data-person-id="227481">Elise Stefanik</a> (R-N.Y.), a member of the GOP leadership team, over a surveillance provision she wanted attached to the sprawling defense package. She got her way after publicly accusing the speaker of lying and sandbagging conservatives.</p> 
<p>Other deeply divisive issues remain, ranging from cryptocurrency policy to in vitro fertilization, that could threaten to further splinter the House GOP and imperil the typically <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_1071" target="_blank">bipartisan Pentagon bill</a>. The brouhaha threatens to complicate Johnson’s effort to hammer out a still-brewing Republican health care plan he’s promised to unveil by early next week.</p> 
<p>“I think there's a lot of members that are frustrated that we're not doing the things that we said that we were going to do,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189831" target="_blank" data-person-id="189831">Greg Steube</a> (R-Fla.) when asked about Johnson’s leadership. “His response to that would be, we only have a [three] vote majority, but I think if you govern conservatively, Republicans will show up and vote for it.”</p> 
<p>Steube, a member of the House Intelligence Committee, said he was “not happy” that Johnson initially excluded Stefanik’s legislation allowing for congressional notification of counterintelligence probes concerning candidates for federal office — part of an annual intelligence authorization legislation that, he said, included “a lot of conservative reforms.” The speaker argued he didn’t know about the measure and that Stefanik’s accusations were “false.”</p> 
<p>Top GOP leaders are scrambling to douse the remaining fires and release text of the massive bill as early as Saturday, but it could slip into Sunday, according to four people granted anonymity to comment on internal planning. The negotiations are complicated, they say, because the final product must not only pass the GOP-controlled House but also withstand a possible Senate filibuster — meaning it needs to have Democratic buy-in.</p> 
<p>“Getting an agreement right now between Republicans and Democrats in the House and Senate's not easy,” Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" target="_blank" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said. “But we're getting close, and we want to get it done.”</p> 
<p>Johnson played down the internal turmoil Thursday, saying Republicans “are exactly on the trajectory of where we've always planned to be.”</p> 
<p>“Steady at the wheel, everybody,” he said. “It’s going to be fine.”</p> 
<p>But the pending fights over the Pentagon bill — or the National Defense Authorization Act, as it is formally known — serve as a mini-preview for the turmoil Johnson is likely to face for the remainder of the 119th Congress as he tries to tackle health care, government funding and other flashpoints.</p> 
<p>For instance, he is risking a showdown with conservative hard-liners if the final package doesn’t include a provision they favor that would ban the Federal Reserve from issuing a digital currency. Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/16/congress/house-advances-crypto-defense-spending-bills-following-standoff-00459201" target="_blank">promised House Freedom Caucus members</a> he would include the provision in the defense bill amid a toxic intra-GOP row during the House’s shambolic “crypto week” this summer.</p> 
<p>If the so-called central bank digital currency ban is missing, “it is a big deal,” said one House conservative who, like others quoted for this story, was granted anonymity to speak frankly about conference dynamics.</p> 
<p>The fate of that provision is currently tied up in talks over another matter — one that highlights how Johnson is facing pressure from another influential corner of the House GOP: his committee chairs.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders are taking steps to add a scaled-down version of a Senate housing proposal to the package. But Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" target="_blank" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) opposes the move and wants to advance a slate of House housing bills through his committee later this month.</p> 
<p>Johnson and Hill, normally low-key operators, had an intense conversation on the House floor Wednesday night as House and Senate GOP leaders went back-and-forth, including at the White House’s behest, over how to add some housing affordability measures to the defense bill.</p> 
<p>“French is very logical and measured, but he's very stern in what he believes and what he wants,” said a senior House Republican.</p> 
<p>Johnson, a staunch social conservative, is also facing pressure from women and others in the House to not strip out a measure expanding coverage for in vitro fertilization and other fertility services for military families under DOD’s Tricare health system. He’s also caught between big business and China hawks — two major GOP blocs — on whether to add in new restrictions on U.S. investments in China. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192213" target="_blank" data-person-id="192213">John Moolenaar</a> (R-Mich.), who chairs a select committee on China, said he was hopeful the provision would make it in but pointed to opposition from the “financial community.”</p> 
<p>The NDAA is “a train that comes around once a year,” he added. “We're hoping to include it.”</p> 
<p><i>Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump endorses identical twin of retiring Rep. Troy Nehls to fill his seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/trump-endorses-trever-nehls-00677128</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-eac9-d516-affe-fefddfc80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 14:43:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Thursday endorsed Trever Nehls, the identical twin of retiring GOP Rep. Troy Nehls, to fill the Texas seat being vacated by his brother.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115662373086221699" target="_blank">post on Truth Social</a>, Trump lauded Troy Nehls for his congressional career, which he spent as a reliable MAGA ally, and praised his brother for his support of the military, veterans and “LAW AND ORDER,” commending their entire family as “fierce advocates” for the MAGA movement.</p> 
<p>“In Congress, Trever will work hard to Keep our now very Secure Border, SECURE, Stop Migrant Crime, Grow our Economy, Cut Taxes and Regulations, Promote MADE IN THE U.S.A., Advance American Energy DOMINANCE, Champion Election Integrity, and Defend our always under siege Second Amendment,” he wrote in the post.</p> 
<p>The retiring Nehls has demonstrated <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/22/trump-honors-still-in-office-republican-bills-00244107" target="_blank">staunch loyalty</a> to the president throughout his time in Congress, and the endorsement adds early momentum to his brother’s bid for the seat.</p> 
<p>The lawmaker <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/29/texas-lawmaker-nehls-00670795?experience_id=EXYF89KVT5UQ&amp;is_login_link=true&amp;template_id=OTJIR2CRKUD6&amp;variant_id=OTV632IE7RALS" target="_blank">announced last week</a> that he’d be retiring from Congress at the end of his third term representing a southwestern swath of Houston. The departure dealt <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/texas-house-republicans-power-fading-00676389" target="_blank">yet another blow</a> to Texas’ GOP congressional delegation after five other members announced their retirements. Republicans are banking on the state’s redistricting plan to shore up their majority with another five red seats.</p> 
<p>Shortly after Troy Nehls announced his retirement, his brother announced on social media that he’d be stepping up to the plate to succeed him.</p> 
<p>“District 22 needs a Representative who will follow in Troy’s footsteps and stand shoulder-to-shoulder with President Trump to defend our conservative values, secure the border, protect our families, and oppose the reckless and radical agenda that Democrats continue to press upon the American people,” he wrote. “I’m ready to take up that fight.”</p> 
<p>This isn’t the first time he has followed in his brother’s footsteps. Trever Nehls also succeeded his twin as constable of Fort Bend County in 2013. He later won the Republican nomination to succeed him as the county’s sheriff in 2020 but later lost by 5 points in the general election.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-04T16:30:41-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump nominations package hits stumbling block in Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/senate-nominations-package-delay-00677016</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-eab5-d516-affe-fef5836c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 14:16:09 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans hit a temporary stumbling block in their latest effort to confirm dozens of President Donald Trump’s nominees.</p> 
<p>Democrats blocked Republicans from successfully taking an initial step toward confirming a <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6931de041765462b59f5a053&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNo1yEEKgDAMBMAXtWsFD_obldAWSiJmtT5fL96GKeThC9B7j7tpPsU9Zrux1daQ0swS_oeLrpTw2drFaoppHEB5-AK0Nhow&amp;@OriginalLink=www.congress.gov" target="_blank"><u>package of more than 80 nominations</u></a> because one of the picks doesn't qualify to be included: Sara Bailey's nomination to be the director of national drug control policy is a senior-level pick requiring individual consideration under the new rules <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6931de041765462b59f5a053&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoNyUkOgCAMAMAXlSJKXH5DsEESpISCfF8Oc5qntSIX4hhDFU6xRc_K84spfgS93K6RoNHGoj5xWdBzDpVEUCjPg8BlIoHcfSJXwQUXM2ht7bGv2w96OyDz&amp;@OriginalLink=www.politico.com" target="_blank"><u>Republicans themselves drafted earlier this year</u></a> for multinominee confirmation votes.</p> 
<p>Sen. Michael Bennet (D-Colo.), who challenged whether the package could get passed with a simple majority if Bailey’s nomination stayed included, said in a statement that “I just blocked 88 Trump nominees from confirmation.”</p> 
<p>He added, “I will not allow unqualified nominees, this White House, or the President to undermine the rule of law and our national security.”</p> 
<p>Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-eb39-d516-affe-fffd152d0000" target="_blank"><u>re-filed the resolution Thursday afternoon</u></a> with additional nominees, bringing the list to 97 nominations and teeing up a vote next week. That will also pave the way for another series of votes on confirming the nominees, which currently include 13 U.S. attorney designees and dozens of sub-Cabinet appointments.</p> 
<p>A Senate GOP aide, granted anonymity to speak candidly, said that the additional nominees will put the Senate on track to confirm 420 nominees. </p> 
<p>“Until Senator Bennet spoke up, we were on track to confirm less than 410. Our sincere thank you to master strategist Michael Bennet," the GOP aide added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson races to finalize elusive GOP health care plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/johnson-house-gop-health-care-plan-00676661</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-ea3d-da2c-af9f-fb7d7bb90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 11:43:26 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> is racing to finalize a Republican health care plan in time to present it to his conference at their weekly meeting Tuesday, but his team still needs to decide on major contours of the plan, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal conversations.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders are meeting Thursday to nail down what will go in the package, according to the three people. One major decision still to be made is whether to offer multiple individual bills for floor consideration or to assemble them into one piece of legislation. But top Republicans want to have a GOP alternative to vote on as Democrats hammer them over expiring Obamacare subsidies that will spike premiums for millions of Americans in the new year. </p> 
<p>If Johnson and fellow GOP leaders don’t make decisions about the way forward Thursday, one senior House Republican said, “it’s going to be bad.”</p> 
<p>The package is likely to be an assemblage of various GOP bills that have been working through House committees that are largely aimed at providing more options for health care coverage outside of the Affordable Care Act framework. One likely to be included would provide for "association health plans" allowing smaller businesses to join together to offer plans rather than going through ACA exchanges. Leaders are also likely to include options for expanding the use of health savings accounts, something President Donald Trump has endorsed but Democrats have generally opposed.</p> 
<p>It's also likely to include bipartisan legislation overhauling the role of pharmacy benefit managers and potentially other bills that could lower prescription drug prices — something Trump pollster Tony Fabrizio <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/tony-fabrizio-health-drug-prices-00674841" target="_blank">advised a group of House Republicans</a> to focus on as Democrats seize on the expiring tax credits.</p> 
<p>Johnson said in a brief interview that he and leaders plan to walk House Republicans through the health care plan through this weekend and then circulate the framework early next week. He also confirmed what GOP leaders have said in private — they want to vote on a health care package before the end of the year. But House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a>, who had been coordinating the health care deliberations, wouldn’t commit to that timeline shortly after Johnson spoke.</p> 
<p>Party leaders are facing massive pressure from GOP centrists who are assembling their own compromise plans to extend the expiring subsides with new eligibility requirements. But Johnson, Scalise and many House Republicans have no interest in continuing with the Obamacare framework.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.), who coauthored a new plan that would provide a one-year extension of the subsidies that has been endorsed by more than two dozen members in both parties, said "we need to act on this issue." </p> 
<p>"To do nothing is the wrong answer," she said.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick </a>(R-Pa.), who is assembling a separate compromise bill that would include a longer subsidy extension, said his party's leaders were not going down a path that will prevent a spike in American's health care costs.</p> 
<p>“Is it a Republican-only solution? That’s not a serious solution," he said. "The million-dollar question is, is it bipartisan or not?”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schumer announces health care plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/schumer-announces-health-care-plan-00676620</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-ea1e-da2c-af9f-fb7fa7f20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 11:08:22 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer officially unveiled <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3385" target="_blank">Democrats’ plan</a> for a health care vote next week, saying Thursday on the chamber floor his caucus will propose extending soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies for three years.</p> 
<p>“This is the bill, a clean three-year extension of ACA tax credits, that Democrats will bring to the floor of the Senate for a vote next Thursday, and every single Democrat will support it," Schumer said. "Republicans have one week to decide where they stand."</p> 
<p>The strategy aligns Senate Democrats with their counterparts in the House — and gives the party a message with which to hammer Republicans heading into next year's midterms. </p> 
<p>But the Democratic bill is guaranteed to fail. While many GOP senators say they would back a two-year extension, they’ve said income caps and other new restrictions would need to be added in order to garner sufficient Republican support.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are still mulling whether or not to put up a counterproposal on health care for a vote next week. They are likely to discuss the issue during their closed-door lunch Thursday afternoon.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Texas’ massive delegation is losing its sway</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/texas-house-delegation-influence-republican-retirements-00676395</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e7c1-da2c-af9f-ffe920ec0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thursday could determine whether the Lone Star State gets five more Republican-leaning seats next Congress. Yet the state’s Texas-sized influence is beginning to wane.</p> 
<p>The Texas GOP delegation is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/texas-house-republicans-power-fading-00676389" target="_blank">losing its clout</a> due to a combination of redistricting, retirements and bids for higher office.</p> 
<p>The group is on track to lose the seniority and committee gavels it once wielded to influence key decisions in the House. With six retirements looming and another five new GOP-leaning seats in the proposed map — the Supreme Court could decide as soon as Thursday whether to approve it — the state is looking at potentially 11 new members in a 30-member delegation.</p> 
<p>“There’s going to be a lot of introductory lunches, that’s for sure,” Rep. Jake Ellzey (R-Texas) told POLITICO, noting it’s going to be a “drastic change.”</p> 
<p>For decades, the GOP delegation was known for guarding its influence, holding weekly lunches to strategize, amassing seats on the influential steering committee that determines committee assignments and often voting as a bloc on key matters.</p> 
<p>But the fact that President Donald Trump started his aggressive redistricting campaign with Texas — and that it proceeded at all — reflects the state’s relative impotence in Trump’s Washington. Republicans wary of the effort eventually folded under pressure from the president, and since then, a fifth of the delegation has announced plans to leave.</p> 
<p>Those retirements include Budget Chair Jodey Arrington and Rep. Michael McCaul, the top Republican on two key committees for over a decade. At the start of Trump’s first term, Texas had seven gavels, including influential Armed Services, Financial Services and Ways and Means panels and three coveted Appropriations subcommittee chairs. Now, Texans hold only three committee gavels — including Arrington — and no Texans serve in the House GOP’s elected leadership.</p> 
<p>“We were powerful,” said Rep. Roger Williams (R-Texas), who chairs the House Small Business Committee, recounting what the delegation was like when he first arrived in 2013. “But that all cycles.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Van Epps seated: </b>Speaker Mike Johnson will swear in Rep.-elect Matt Van Epps (R-Tenn.) on the House floor at 9 a.m., giving the GOP a 220-213 majority.</p> 
<p><b>— Health care talks: </b>Reps. Josh Gottheimer (D-N.J.) and Jen Kiggans (R-Va.) plan to introduce a new framework at 9:30 a.m. to reduce health premiums as lawmakers scramble to figure out what to do about expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies. It includes a one-year extension of the subsidies with new guardrails to crack down on fraud and a menu of separate pay-for options — not in the form of subsidies — to keep premiums low.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats are expected to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/senate-democrats-obamacare-extension-00676149" target="_blank">propose a three-year extension</a> of the subsidies, which Senate Majority Leader John Thune said was “designed to fail.”</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA hurdles: </b>Final legislative text on the annual defense authorization bill was originally expected Thursday but has been delayed as GOP leaders work through <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/03/ndaa-delays-defense-bill-00676098" target="_blank">eleventh-hour intraparty issues</a> that could put its passage in jeopardy. Leaders are now aiming to unveil bill text by the end of the weekend.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Connor O’Brien and Joe Gould contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Texas exodus underscores the state’s fading relevance in the House GOP</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/texas-house-republicans-power-fading-00676389</link>
      <description>Not long ago, seven committee chairs hailed from the Lone Star State. Now its delegation is young, large and unsettled.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e757-db69-a9fb-e7771cca0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7d/0c/68146aad43b9815e57ad638f0139/house-of-representatives-00513.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“We were powerful,” said GOP Rep. Roger Williams, one of three remaining Texas committee chairs. “But that all cycles.”</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7d/0c/68146aad43b9815e57ad638f0139/house-of-representatives-00513.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Lone Star State is used to having a Texas-sized impact on the House Republican Conference. And, by the numbers, its influence should be larger than ever.</p> 
<p>If a bold redistricting plan pushed by President Donald Trump goes forward, Texas could have a massive 30-member GOP delegation come 2027. And yet by the measures of clout and seniority — the real markers of power inside the House — the state is clearly on the wane.</p> 
<p>Six members are retiring — some to pursue other political ambitions, others quitting cold turkey. Assuming the redistricting plan is approved — a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/supreme-court-texas-redistricting-case-00659035" target="_blank">Supreme Court ruling on the matter</a> could come as soon as Thursday — another five Republicans would be freshman back-benchers from a state that once racked up committee gavels.</p> 
<p>The turnover has left many in the already huge delegation unsettled and wondering how the state’s clout declined so precipitously. Rep. Pete Sessions, Texas’ longest-serving Republican, said in an interview that it’s “the biggest change of any redistricting period” he has been through in a nearly 30-year career.</p> 
<p>“The timing of this across the board has been difficult to get your hands around,” Sessions said. He noted the redistricting and other retirements will “add youth and opportunity to the Texas delegation but a lot of the inexperience and a lot of things that come at a time when my party needs a lot of teamwork and collegiality.”</p> 
<p>A younger colleague, Rep. Jake Ellzey, also said the delegation is facing a “drastic change” over the coming years: “There's going to be a lot of introductory lunches, that's for sure.”</p> 
<p>Already there has been a remarkable shift since the beginning of Trump’s first term, when Texans held sway over seven House committees — including the powerful Armed Services, Financial Services and Ways and Means panels — as well as three coveted Appropriations subcommittee chairs.</p> 
<p>The GOP delegation was known for zealously guarding its influence, holding weekly lunches to strategize, amassing seats on the influential steering committee that doles out committee assignments and often <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2018/07/24/texas-republicans-house-speaker-740361" target="_blank">voting as a bloc</a> on key matters.</p> 
<p>Today Texans hold only three committee gavels, all on relatively backwater panels, and just one Appropriations subcommittee chair. One of those chairs, Budget’s Jodey Arrington, is retiring. No Texans serve in the House GOP’s elected leadership.</p> 
<p>“We were powerful,” said Rep. Roger Williams, who chairs the House Small Business Committee, recounting what the delegation was like when he first arrived in 2013. “But that all cycles.”</p> 
<p>No single member approaches the influence of the most formidable Texan in recent House Republican history — former Majority Leader Tom DeLay, who was often said to be more powerful than the speaker he served with, Dennis Hastert.</p> 
<p>Rep. Michael McCaul, who announced his retirement plans in September, was the top Republican on two key committees for 12 years. In an interview, he remembered DeLay brokering power when he was first elected. “And there was a time when I was one of seven committee chairs from Texas, and we had the majority of the chairmanships,” McCaul added.</p> 
<p>There are still some pockets of ambition in the delegation’s ranks, including Rep. August Pfluger, who heads the 180-plus-member Republican Study Committee. Many Republicans expect Pfluger to vie for an elected leadership role in the next Congress.</p> 
<p>But the fact that the redistricting push proceeded at all reflects the state’s relative impotence in Trump’s Washington. The president used Texas as the tip of the spear in his aggressive campaign to rewrite congressional districts midway through the usual Census-driven cycle, and wary Republicans folded in the face of an unrelenting pressure campaign from Trump’s top political advisers.</p> 
<p>One Texas Republican relayed his surprise and frustration to a group of fellow House Republicans on the floor as the push unfolded.</p> 
<p>“What the hell did we do to deserve this?” he said, according to one of the Republicans present.</p> 
<p>Since then, a fifth of the delegation has announced plans to leave. McCaul <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/14/mccaul-texas-reelection-retire-challenge-term-00563169" target="_blank">announced his plans</a> to retire in September, as did Rep. <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/11/congress/morgan-luttrell-texas-retire-00557843" target="_blank">Morgan Luttrell</a>, a highly recruited former Navy SEAL. Arrington followed, and Rep. Chip Roy launched a campaign for state attorney general, while Rep. Wesley Hunt <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/06/wesley-hunt-texas-2026-senate-republican-primary-00594621" target="_blank">decided to take on</a> incumbent GOP Sen. John Cornyn.</p> 
<p>Last week, Rep. Troy Nehls made a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/29/texas-lawmaker-nehls-00670795?experience_id=EXYF89KVT5UQ&amp;is_login_link=true&amp;template_id=OTJIR2CRKUD6&amp;variant_id=OTV632IE7RALS" target="_blank">surprise announcement</a> that he would be retiring, and some Texas Republicans believe there could be at least one more in their ranks who could call it quits before the state’s Dec. 8 ballot qualifying deadline.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ronny Jackson, Trump’s former White House doctor, has spoken privately to other Republicans in the past about leaving for a possible administration job, but he has filed for reelection. A spokesperson said Jackson is "committed to strengthening the House Republican majority and supporting President Trump’s agenda in Congress."</p> 
<p>Even the Texas Republicans who are sticking around are showing signs of frustration in the House rank-and-file. Some conservatives in the ranks are privately expressing unease about the millions of Texans set to get hammered with higher health care costs before next year’s midterms and are concerned about Republicans’ lack of a counterattack as they get hammered by Democrats.</p> 
<p>Rep. Nathaniel Moran, who represents a deep-red east Texas district, stood up during a recent closed-door GOP conference meeting to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-gop-leaders-pitch-members-on-unaffordable-care-act-00656362" target="_blank">confront party leaders</a> on why they haven’t been working on a plan to address expiring Obamacare tax credits until just weeks before the year-end deadline.</p> 
<p>Moran said in an interview this week that Democrats were making headway against the GOP with what he called a “sound bite policy” on health care. “So I would like to see … Republicans come to the forefront” with more substantial plans, he said.</p> 
<p>Other senior Republicans note that the cohesion of the big delegations including Texas’ has withered under speakers Kevin McCarthy and now Mike Johnson, who have continued a trend of centralizing decisionmaking in the leadership suites. Younger members are not given enough senior mentorship, according to another senior Republican, and White House officials “run wild” across the Capitol forcing members to march in lockstep with Trump.</p> 
<p>For more than four decades, the Texas delegation has scheduled regular Thursday lunches in the Capitol during session weeks to build camaraderie and discuss strategy. But because Johnson often aims to wrap up House business by 10:30 a.m. Thursdays, Republicans note, members are often scattered to catch flights by lunchtime — including younger members who are most eager to get home.</p> 
<p>“Certainly that change of schedule has thrown into play the integrity of the ability of a delegation to meet and speak and gather their balance and equilibrium,” Sessions said.</p> 
<p>Members are generally shrugging off the retirements. Moran said “it's a natural cycle” to life in Congress while Arrington said in an interview that “Texans are more inclined to see it as a temporary calling to serve temporarily and go home.”</p> 
<p>“For some people, that's six years. For some, it's eight years, and for others, it's 10,” said Arrington, who is leaving after eight years even though he has the chance to continue at least one additional term as Budget chair if Republicans keep the majority.</p> 
<p>Those who choose to leave have different perspectives on the experience. Nehls and Luttrell have identical twins. Nehls is behind his brother Trever’s bid to replace him in the House, but Luttrell said he didn’t expect his twin brother Marcus, also a retired SEAL, to do the same.</p> 
<p>Asked if he would encourage him to consider it, Luttrell laughed: “No, I would never do that.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Democrats eye vote on 3-year Obamacare subsidy extension</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/senate-democrats-obamacare-extension-00676149</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e6a5-da2c-af9f-ffededeb0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:58:22 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats will propose a three-year extension of soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies for an expected floor vote next week, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss caucus strategy.</p> 
<p>Democrats get to decide what proposal the Senate votes on as part of a deal struck with Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> last month to end the government shutdown. The Senate is expected to hold that vote Dec. 11.</p> 
<p>The strategy likely helps Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> keep his caucus unified on the vote, and it aligns his caucus with House Democrats' plan to try to force a vote on a three-year extension through a discharge petition.</p> 
<p>But it will also limit any chance they would be able to peel off more than a couple of Republicans. Thune said in an interview Wednesday that pitching a clean three-year extension is “designed to fail.”</p> 
<p>To get a deal on the subsidies through the Senate, it would need 60 votes to advance. Some GOP senators, including <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> of Maine, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> of North Carolina, have backed a two-year extension but have acknowledged there would need to be income caps and other restrictions to pick up more GOP support. Whether or not to include abortion funding restrictions is also a major sticking point.</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for Schumer didn’t immediately respond to a question about the plan. Schumer declined to tip his hand earlier Wednesday when asked after a meeting with House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> if Senate Democrats would offer a three-year extension.</p> 
<p>“Stay tuned,” he told reporters.</p> 
<p>Some of his members want Democrats to put up a more sweeping health care proposal, while others have been discussing a potential compromise with Republicans that would extend the subsidies but with new restrictions.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans need to decide whether they will offer their own counterproposal for a vote next week. Senate Finance Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> and Senate HELP Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> talked through their ideas, along with other GOP senators, at a closed-door Tuesday lunch.</p> 
<p>Thune on Wednesday evening said they had not yet made a “final decision” on whether they would put a proposal up for a vote next week.</p> 
<p>“We’ll kind of see what the temperature of our members is,” Thune said.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House backing push to attach Senate housing package to must-pass defense bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/white-house-backing-push-attach-senate-housing-package-defense-bill-00674916</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e69c-dd9e-afba-fefd16b40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:49:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House is backing an effort to attach most of a Senate-approved housing package to a must-pass <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_1071" target="_blank">annual defense bill</a>, according to three people with knowledge of the matter who were granted anonymity to discuss private talks.</p> 
<p>The administration’s support could breathe new life into the push to include the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2651?q=road+to+housing" target="_blank">ROAD to Housing</a> package in the National Defense Authorization Act at the eleventh hour. Both Senate leaders are also backing the push, the people said.</p> 
<p>A White House official who was granted anonymity to relay the administration's position said: "We’re open to seeing this moving forward."</p> 
<p>The ROAD package, backed by Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" target="_blank" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> (R-S.C.) and ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" target="_blank" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> (D-Mass.), includes an array of legislation aimed at boosting housing supply. The Banking panel approved the measure unanimously in July.</p> 
<p>Scott and Warren have pushed to include most of the package in the NDAA, but House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" target="_blank" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) has pushed back. Hill said in a statement that “any housing package must have the buy-in from the House Financial Services Committee.”</p> 
<p>“Given our Conference has not seen any text, it’s unclear how we could support its inclusion in the NDAA,” he said.</p> 
<p>Hill spoke on the House floor with Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" target="_blank" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> (R-La.) Wednesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>Congressional GOP leaders are now considering whether to add a revised or scaled-down version of the Senate’s legislation to the Pentagon bill, but no final decisions have been made, according to two people with knowledge of the discussions.</p> 
<p>House Financial Services ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51664" target="_blank" data-person-id="51664">Maxine Waters</a> (D-Calif.) expressed support for the ROAD package during a committee hearing Wednesday morning, calling it a “common-sense legislative package that would chip away at the [housing] crisis.” But she told reporters later in the day that she doesn’t “know what’s in” the latest proposal.</p> 
<p>“I’m supportive of absolutely getting all of my people on the ROAD bill — their bills into the NDAA package,” she said, referring to the fact that many of the measures in the Senate's housing bill have companion bills in the House. “If they have worked that out, I’m happy. But I want to know what it is. And I want to know how many of my members are covered.”</p> 
<p>House Financial Services has not seen the latest text reflecting what the White House supports, according to a House Democratic aide with knowledge of the matter.</p> 
<p>Trump officials and the president's top political aides are trying to push harder on housing policy, as high home costs and mortgages weigh on voters.</p> 
<p>Top Trump pollster Tony Fabrizio spoke extensively about housing policy as a key area of potential focus for Republicans during a closed-door briefing with the Republican Study Committee Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The RSC itself is pushing housing as a key focus for a potential party-line bill the GOP could pass ahead of the midterms. Notably, Fabrizio encouraged House Republicans to work on advancing so-called portable mortgages, an idea some Trump officials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/experts-slam-pulte-trump-50-year-mortgage-idea-00645379" target="_blank">have been mulling</a>. That would allow homeowners to essentially take their mortgage rate with them when they move.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NDAA delays pile up as GOP leaders work through last-minute snags</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/03/ndaa-delays-defense-bill-00676098</link>
      <description>Text of the massive defense policy bill is no longer expected Thursday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e697-da2c-af9f-ffffcd2d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:44:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f5/08/415e6bc346d3a005c25dbf8e4e69/u-s-congress-27873.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson (R-La.) speaks with reporters as he departs a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 3, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f5/08/415e6bc346d3a005c25dbf8e4e69/u-s-congress-27873.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Joe Gould and Connor O'Brien</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Joe Gould and Connor O'Brien</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican leaders on Capitol Hill are scrambling to hammer out a host of complex, 11th-hour intraparty policy fights in the massive <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_1071" target="_blank">annual defense policy bill</a>, delaying the release of final legislative text beyond the expected date of Thursday, according to four people granted anonymity to discuss the internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>They are still pushing to release text of the sprawling bill by the end of the weekend, according to two of the people. But GOP leaders are going back and forth with White House officials about a raft of final issues, including <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/white-house-backing-push-to-attach-senate-housing-package-to-must-pass-defense-bill-00674916" target="_blank">Senate housing legislation</a> that the administration wants but a key House committee chair opposes.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump and his deputies are eager to address housing costs, and top Trump pollster Tony Fabrizio told a closed-door meeting of House Republicans earlier Wednesday that Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/tony-fabrizio-health-drug-prices-00674841" target="_blank">need to focus more on housing issues</a> ahead of next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>With White House officials digging in, congressional GOP leaders are now considering whether to add a revised or scaled down version of the Senate’s “ROAD to Housing” legislation to the Pentagon bill, but no final decisions have been made, according to the people. House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" target="_blank" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> has previously opposed the parts of the measure and said in a statement late Wednesday that “any housing package must have the buy-in” of his committee.</p> 
<p>“Given our Conference has not seen any text, it’s unclear how we could support its inclusion in the NDAA,” Hill said.</p> 
<p>Other issues GOP leaders are still working through include whether to add in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/china-investment-crackdown-in-flux-as-lawmakers-rush-to-finalize-defense-bill-00673705" target="_blank">new restrictions on U.S. investments in China</a>, as well as provisions that would expand coverage for in vitro fertilization and other fertility services for military families under the Defense Department’s Tricare health system.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders are reviewing the IVF expansion, which was included in both the House and Senate-passed defense bills. Pushed by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198768" target="_blank" data-person-id="198768">Tammy Duckworth</a> (D-Ill.), Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/369735" target="_blank" data-person-id="369735">Sara Jacobs</a> (D-Calif.) and others, the provision wasn’t included in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/12/04/congress/tammy-duckworth-ivf-donald-trump-00192544" target="_blank">last year’s defense bill</a> amid concerns about the practice from some conservatives.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" target="_blank" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said in a statement that he “has clearly and repeatedly stated he is supportive of access to IVF when sufficient pro-life protections are in place, and he will continue to be supportive when it is done responsibly and ethically.”</p> 
<p>The last-minute moves could weigh heavily on how easily Republican leaders can get the votes needed to pass the sprawling Pentagon bill, which the House aims to do next week.</p> 
<p>The annual National Defense Authorization Act typically passes with broad bipartisan support. Johnson won passage of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_3838" target="_blank">hard-right version of the defense bill</a> in September with just the support of a handful of Democrats, while the Senate cleared <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2296" target="_blank">its own version</a> with support from both parties.</p> 
<p>Bipartisan leaders of the House and Senate Armed Services committees made quick work of their negotiations on a compromise defense bill, which largely concluded before Thanksgiving.</p> 
<p>The legislation was then handed up to House and Senate leaders to hammer out what provisions that fall outside of Armed Services’ jurisdiction would be attached. Top lawmakers on those panels have cautioned against attaching unrelated issues that don’t have broad support and could tank the final bill.</p> 
<p>House and Senate leaders have already had to retreat on some fronts. Trump urged lawmakers to include a contentious moratorium on state regulations for artificial intelligence backed by House Majority Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" target="_blank" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> and other Republicans. But the effort foundered, and Scalise this week conceded the NDAA “wasn't the best place for this to fit.”</p> 
<p><i>Jasper Goodman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senior Johnson aide leaves for Holland &amp;amp; Knight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/johnson-aide-heads-to-k-street-00675871</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e670-da2c-af9f-ff7960e60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:04:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Chris Jaarda, who has spent the past two years as a senior policy adviser and counsel to House Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" target="_blank" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, has left the Hill to join Holland &amp; Knight as a partner in the firm’s lobbying practice.</p> 
<p>Jaarda’s portfolio in Johnson’s office spanned a variety of topics, including privacy, emerging technologies, foreign intelligence, homeland security and supply chain and production issues. His role also involved serving as a liaison between the speaker’s office and House panels such as the Energy &amp; Commerce Committee, Oversight Committee, Judiciary Committee and Homeland Security Committee. Jaarda said in an interview that he worked closely on seven of the 11 titles in this summer’s GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Now, he’ll advise the firm’s clients on their engagement at the state and federal levels as the Trump administration and statehouses begin to implement the law. (In August, Holland &amp; Knight hired Andrew Siracuse, another former Hill staffer who worked on the reconciliation bill under Texas GOP Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51170" target="_blank" data-person-id="51170">John Cornyn</a>.)</p> 
<p>Jaarda, who plans on registering to lobby, also has insights about key players on the Hill, especially as it pertains to the way Johnson has managed to navigate Republicans’ razor-thin House majority. “I think understanding that process, and what moves the needle on certain issues, hopefully will be very helpful” to the firm’s clients, he said.</p> 
<p>Jaarda earlier spent three years working for Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175665" target="_blank" data-person-id="175665">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Texas), including serving as Cruz’s deputy chief of staff for policy and legislative director. Before that, he did stints for former Rep. Ken Buck (R-Colo.), the Senate GOP Policy Committee and former Sen. John Ensign (R-Nev.), in addition to starting his own consulting firm.</p> 
<p>Jaarda is the latest House GOP leadership staffer to head downtown in the past year. Johnson’s policy director, Dan Ziegler, left the Hill in the spring to return to Williams &amp; Jensen. And a handful of top aides to House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" target="_blank" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a>, including his longtime chief of staff, have decamped for the private sector as well.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-03T16:20:16-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump pollster’s health care advice for Republicans: Pivot to drug prices</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/tony-fabrizio-health-drug-prices-00674841</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e5e2-db69-a9fb-e5e3a8500000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:25:07 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A top pollster for President Donald Trump advised a group of House Republicans on how to defend against Democrats’ attacks over expiring Obamacare tax credits: focus on reducing drug prices instead.</p> 
<p>Tony Fabrizio showed new polling to members of the Republican Study Committee in a closed-door meeting held a few blocks from the Capitol Wednesday. He argued the most effective way for Republicans to counter Democrats’ health care messaging is to change the subject and pivot to reducing drug prices in tandem with Trump.</p> 
<p>The presentation was described by a House Republican aide and two people in the room who were granted anonymity to discuss the closed-door event. Speaker Mike Johnson, an RSC member, attended the briefing. Fabrizio did not return a request for comment. </p> 
<p>Notably, the House GOP aide said Fabrizio did not recommend any extension of the insurance subsidies, something he has <a href="https://fabrizioward.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/pup-tcd-tax-credit-survey-memo.pdf" target="_blank">advocated for in the past</a>. The Trump administration has recently <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/trumps-cms-touts-12b-savings-from-medicare-drug-price-negotiations-00669231" target="_blank">refocused attention on drug pricing</a>, a topic the president tends to return to when Democrats try to hammer him on health care.</p> 
<p>Trump has tried to pressure House Republican leaders to address drug prices before, with little luck. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/johnson-not-a-big-fan-of-drug-policy-white-house-wants-for-trumps-megabill-00320974" target="_blank">wanted to add a most favored nation provision</a> to the GOP megabill in the final hours before its passage this summer, a policy opposed by the drug industry and GOP leaders themselves, along with some other Republicans. Speaker Mike Johnson said at the time he was "not a big fan" of the policy.</p> 
<p>Fabrizio also spoke extensively about housing as a key area of potential focus for Republicans as high home prices and interest rates weigh on voters. The RSC itself is pushing housing policy as a key focus for a potential party-line bill the GOP could pass ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>Notably, Fabrizio encouraged House Republicans to work on advancing so-called portable mortgages, an idea some Trump officials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/experts-slam-pulte-trump-50-year-mortgage-idea-00645379" target="_blank">have been mulling</a>. That would allow homeowners to essentially take their mortgage rate with them when they move.</p> 
<p>He also gave a postmortem rundown on the results from Tuesday’s Tennessee special election, where Republicans held onto the safe red seat albeit by a single-digit margin — raising concerns for the GOP ahead of next year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>Fabrizio argued it was a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/tennessee-election-republican-midterms-fallout-00674124" target="_blank">closer race than Republicans would have liked</a> because they weren’t talking enough about affordability issues facing voters. He told the group to “stay the course and talk about the realities of the economy,” one House Republican present said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stefanik says Johnson ‘certainly' wouldn’t be reelected speaker</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/stefanik-says-johnson-wouldnt-win-speaker-re-election-00674519</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e590-dd9e-afba-fdfd11010000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:13:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Elise Stefanik said Speaker Mike Johnson would lose an election to lead the House if a vote were suddenly called.</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-house-speaker-c41659cb?mod=Searchresults&amp;pos=1&amp;page=1" target="_blank">an interview with the Wall Street Journal</a> Tuesday night, the New York lawmaker said Johnson is an “ineffective leader” who is losing control of the Republican party.</p> 
<p>“He certainly wouldn’t have the votes to be speaker if there was a roll-call vote tomorrow,” said Stefanik, a close ally to President Donald Trump. “I believe that the majority of Republicans would vote for new leadership. It’s that widespread.”</p> 
<p>Johnson replaced former Rep. Kevin McCarthy to helm the lower chamber in 2023, accepting the speaker’s gavel after a historic series of multiple rounds of voting. He easily won reelection to the speakership earlier this year on a near-party-line vote.</p> 
<p>It’s not the first time Stefanik, who is running for governor, has criticized the speaker.</p> 
<p>Earlier this week, she <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-feud-00674030" target="_blank">accused Johnson</a> of blocking provisions to the National Defense Authorization Act that would notify Congress if the FBI begins investigating federal candidates.</p> 
<p>Johnson, she said Monday in <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995596731543671069" target="_blank">a post to X</a>, is “getting rolled by House Dems attempting to block my provision to require Congressional disclosure when the FBI opens counterintelligence investigations into presidential and federal candidates seeking office.”</p> 
<p>Still, Johnson appears to have the favor of Trump, who has been able to keep a lid on most GOP internal disputes this year and was credited with mediating the quarrel between Johnson and Stefanik.</p> 
<p>But <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/12/03/young-republicans-to-host-far-right-german-leader-after-leaked-chat-00674051" target="_blank">in an interview with Playbook</a>, Stefanik pointed out that between Trump and Johnson, “one has historic support among Republican voters, and one has catastrophic, plummeting support among Republican voters.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Democrats watching from the sidelines have cheered on the in-fighting with glee.</p> 
<p>“THE GIRLS ARE FIGHTING!” a <a href="https://mailchi.mp/dccc.org/the-girls-are-fighting-as-mike-johnson-and-elise-stefanik-brawl-online-mike-lawler-is-left-to-pick-his-favorite-party-boss?e=5f1378536e" target="_blank">Tuesday memo</a> from the DCCC highlighting the Stefanik-Johnson feud said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Henry Cuellar will seek reelection as a Democrat after Trump pardon</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/henry-cuellar-pardon-reelection-party-00674518</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e58c-dc85-abba-e7bf3c830000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:53:36 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Texas Rep. Henry Cuellar filed for reelection Wednesday as a Democrat and told reporters he had no intention to retire or switch parties hours after President Donald Trump announced pardons for him and his wife.</p> 
<p>“It came as a surprise,” Cuellar told a small group of reporters about the pardon. “I want to thank President Trump for this. … Now we clear the air. Nothing has changed, and we’re going to be ready to win re-election again.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s announcement of the pardons Wednesday morning immediately stoked speculation that the 11-term veteran might finally switch to the GOP after years of entreaties or simply retire — giving Republicans a much better chance to flip his competitive Rio Grande Valley seat.</p> 
<p>But Cuellar quickly assured a small group of senior Democrats that he would not switch parties, according to two people granted anonymity to describe the private conversations. He also filed reelection paperwork with Texas state officials Wednesday.</p> 
<p>“Nothing has changed — I'm a good old conservative Democrat,” Cuellar said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Trump claimed on Truth Social that Cuellar’s prosecution was the result of his speaking out against former President Joe Biden’s immigration policy. Cuellar and his wife Imelda were indicted last year on more than a dozen corruption charges including bribery.</p> 
<p>“Henry, I don’t know you, but you can sleep well tonight — Your nightmare is finally over!” Trump posted.</p> 
<p>The clemency for Cuellar comes as the president faces backlash for his use of the pardon power, including for officials in his own party. Trump has also railed for years about Biden’s alleged “weaponization” of law enforcement, and the Cuellar pardon could serve to show that his interest in that subject crosses party lines.</p> 
<p>But it stands to complicate the GOP’s longstanding effort to oust Cuellar from office. He is near the top of the party’s 2026 target list, and a top Republican recruit <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2025/12/02/webb-county-judge-tano-tijerina-congressional-run/" target="_blank">entered the race Tuesday</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump’s glowing praise of the Texas Democrat in his announcement of the pardon Wednesday — and Cuellar’s determination to seek reelection — shocked Republicans who have tried to defeat him for years.</p> 
<p>Rep. Pete Sessions, informed of the news, said Cuellar’s electoral intentions show “there was not a quid pro quo" with Trump over the pardon. But the veteran Texas Republican and former NRCC chair declined to opine further.</p> 
<p>“Very interesting,” he said. “Very interesting.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
