<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:55:52 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>No off-ramp in sight for DHS-fueled shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628</link>
      <description>Republicans are dangling options that would avoid having to change a massive spending bill. Democrats aren’t biting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fcf0-d1ea-a5df-fcf431d30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:55:52 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c9/02/7b3ffafc4e3ea5110a323ac21399/u-s-congress-53267.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Katie Britt (R-Ala.), who leads the Appropriations subcommittee dealing with DHS, said actions “within the purview of the administration” could address Democrats’ concerns.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c9/02/7b3ffafc4e3ea5110a323ac21399/u-s-congress-53267.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Washington is charging toward a partial government shutdown over President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda even as senators and the White House scramble to find an elusive off-ramp.</p> 
<p>Democrats, Republicans and the White House each say they want to avoid another costly lapse in government funding. But Saturday’s killing of a 37-year-old Minnesota man by federal agents has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">badly complicated the approach pattern</a> for a massive six-bill appropriations package that the Senate planned to approve this week.</p> 
<p>In the wake of the Minnesota shooting, Democrats want Republicans to join them in stripping out funding for the Department of Homeland Security from the sprawling package. Yet any changes would require further action in the House, which is out of town until Monday — after a shutdown would start at 12:01 a.m. Saturday.</p> 
<p>Republicans are dangling alternatives that would avoid having to change the massive bill, including potential executive actions or an agreement to pass a separate piece of legislation. But Democrats believe they have leverage as Americans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">recoil at Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement tactics</a> in Minnesota and elsewhere.</p> 
<p>The captured-on-video killing of Alex Pretti has sparked public unease even from Trump allies in Congress and fueled new questions about how the administration is enacting its agenda, putting intense pressure on Democrats to dig in and fight.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said Monday that the “responsibility to prevent a partial government shutdown” lies in the hands of Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and his fellow Senate Republicans. He called on them to agree to strip out and renegotiate the DHS bill while allowing the rest of the package — which would fund nearly three-quarters of annual agency spending — to be passed into law.</p> 
<p>As recently as Friday, enough senators were expected to help pass the full set of funding bills, which was negotiated over the course of months by bipartisan appropriators. Now, according to a person granted anonymity to disclose private discussions, Democrats are quickly “coalescing” around a number of changes they want to the DHS bill, which won only seven Democratic votes in the House.</p> 
<p>Those include requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, overruling a recently disclosed ICE memo asserting they are not required. Other potential Democratic amendments would mandate federal agents identify themselves, require DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations and limit the “mission creep of federal agencies.”</p> 
<p>Despite the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">concern that has emerged within the GOP ranks</a> after Saturday’s shooting, Republicans are moving forward with the six-bill package as currently drafted, taking a first step Monday to put it on the floor. Senators are expected to take an initial vote Thursday, when at least eight Democrats will be needed to leap a 60-vote hurdle.</p> 
<p>Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) told reporters Monday that she did not favor removing the DHS bill from the six-bill package but that there are ongoing discussions about “further reforms or procedural protections.”</p> 
<p>“My hope is that we’re not going to get to that point, that everyone would recognize that a government shutdown is extremely harmful and should be avoided,” Collins said when asked about the prospects for a partial shutdown.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a> (R-Ala.), who leads the Appropriations subcommittee dealing with DHS and met with Collins Monday, also told reporters the Senate should pass the funding package as is but that there could be actions taken “within the purview of the administration” to address Democrats’ concerns.</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers and aides held out hope that some of Trump’s moves Monday, which included sending border czar Tom Homan to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">oversee the Minnesota enforcement surge</a>, would soften the ground for a possible deal. Others were encouraged that lines of communications remained open between the parties early in the week.</p> 
<p>Republicans are facing their own internal pressures as they seek to avoid a shutdown. A group of conservatives, including Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah), is vowing to oppose any effort to strip out DHS funding. And because the Senate is locked in a time crunch with the Friday midnight deadline looming, any one senator can block an attempt to quickly amend the legislation.</p> 
<p>At the same time, there are some Democratic qualms about pushing agencies to the brink less than three months after ending a record 43-day shutdown fought over health care. Some are noting that ICE and Border Patrol will continue to be funded in any case through the GOP megabill enacted last year while other DHS agencies such as FEMA and TSA would be subject to the shutdown.</p> 
<p>But so far Democrats are insisting that Republicans agree to rewrite the bill. Democrats are skeptical that the administration can be trusted to take executive action or that standalone legislation reining in DHS would ever make it through the House.</p> 
<p>“My options are to do nothing or to recognize that two U.S. citizens were recently … executed by federal agents,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189136" data-person-id="189136">Ruben Gallego</a> (D-Ariz.) told reporters Monday. “We need to at least bring some level of pressure on DHS or on our Republican colleagues to explain to the American public why we are going to continue funding this without any changes.”</p> 
<p>Even sending an amended bill back to the House would carry the risk of an extended standoff. One senior House Republican granted anonymity said that would open a new "hellscape" in the funding talks, with the fractious GOP conference divided over the way forward.</p> 
<p>“Democrats already had a say in DHS funding during the bipartisan negotiations that occurred on each and every individual appropriations bill," said a House GOP aide granted anonymity to speak candidly about the dynamics. “If they renege on the agreement on any of these bipartisan bills, then it would open a bigger can of worms.”</p> 
<p>Privately, many Republicans on Capitol Hill believe that any off-ramp to be found before Friday night’s deadline will need to come from the White House, according to two people granted anonymity to disclose private thinking.</p> 
<p>But <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/white-house-backs-appropriations-package-with-dhs-funding-00746971" target="_blank">the administration said Monday</a> it wants to see the six-bill package passed as written — without the DHS funding separated out.</p> 
<p>“Policy discussions on immigration in Minnesota are happening,” White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said, adding that those talks “should not be at the expense of government funding for the American people.”</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson's leadership circle is still weighing options as the partial shutdown looms. While some Senate Democrats are calling on the House to cut its one-week break short and reconvene, there are no plans to bring the chamber back early, according to three people granted anonymity to comment on private planning.</p> 
<p>While GOP leaders plan for now to bring the House back next Monday as scheduled, some rank-and-file Republicans are wary that Johnson might re-run his strategy from the last shutdown and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/09/mike-johnson-shutdown-no-show-00601215" target="_blank">keep the House out even longer</a> in a bid to jam the Senate.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Susan Collins speaks with Noem about immigration enforcement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/susan-collins-speaks-with-noem-about-immigration-enforcement-00747915</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc6c-d452-a99b-fdfe0abf0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:28:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>GOP Sen. Susan Collins said she spoke Monday to embattled Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem after the administration launched an immigration enforcement campaign in her home state.</p> 
<p>Collins declined to divulge details of her conversation with Noem to reporters — though her office indicated earlier this month that the senator had reached out to DHS about ICE’s activities in Maine.</p> 
<p>Regarding the ICE presence there, Collins said in a statement last week that “people who are in this country legally should not be targets of ICE investigations,” while those who have “entered this country illegally and who have engaged in criminal activity …. could be subject to arrest and deportation.” </p> 
<p>She added, “People who are exercising the right to peacefully gather and protest their government should be careful not to interfere with law enforcement efforts while doing so.</p> 
<p>But the conversation comes at a critical moment. Federal agents shot and killed a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis over the weekend, prompting public outrage and sparking criticism from a growing number of Senate Republicans about the Trump administration’s handling of the situation. It’s the second such shooting to occur in the city since January began.</p> 
<p>Collins is also the chair of the Senate Appropriations Committee who helped negotiate legislation to fund several agencies — including DHS — through the end of September. That bipartisan package is now imperiled as Democrats now say they won’t vote to support any bill that funds DHS without significant guardrails in place to rein in immigration enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>DHS is among several agencies that would shut down after Jan. 30 unless lawmakers can reach some sort of compromise.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kristi Noem to testify before Senate Judiciary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc32-dabb-ad9f-fffff7b80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:35:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem will testify March 3 before the Senate Judiciary Committee, according to an aide for Chair Chuck Grassley.</p> 
<p>Grassley has been haggling for weeks to schedule Noem’s testimony as part of his panel’s regular oversight of DHS. But her high-profile appearance will likely be dominated by senators’ questions regarding the agency’s immigration enforcement tactics following two fatal shootings by federal agents in Minneapolis in the past month.</p> 
<p>Some GOP senators — including Sen. Thom Tillis of North Carolina, who is a member on the committee — have called for an independent investigation into the latest shooting over the weekend, while others have criticized initial comments from top administration officials that suggested the victim bore responsibility and not the officers involved.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rand Paul summons Trump immigration officials to testify after Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/rand-paul-dhs-hearing-minneapolis-00747012</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbef-d1ea-a5df-fbefeffb0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:14:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151828" data-person-id="151828">Rand Paul</a>, chair of the Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee, called on three top immigration enforcement officials to testify before his panel in the wake of Saturday’s killing of a Minneapolis man by federal agents.</p> 
<p>The Kentucky Republican <a href="https://x.com/SenRandPaul/status/2015868311825785113/photo/1" target="_blank">sent letters Monday</a> to Rodney Scott, the commissioner of Customs and Border Protection; Joseph Edlow, director of U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services; and Todd Lyons, who is serving as acting director of ICE, requesting that the three men testify at a Feb. 12 hearing.</p> 
<p>“As you know, the Department of Homeland Security has been provided an exceptional amount of funding to secure our borders and enforce our immigration laws,” Paul said in the letters to the administration officials. “Congress has an obligation to conduct oversight of those tax dollars and ensure the funding is used to accomplish the mission, provide proper support for our law enforcement, and, most importantly, protect the American people.”</p> 
<p>Paul’s letters don’t mention this weekend’s killing of 37-year-old Alex Pretti, which has sparked a wave of new scrutiny of the immigration enforcement actions in Minnesota ordered by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>But the hearing would be the first chance senators will have to question Trump administration officials’ over the shooting and the president’s broader immigration and Homeland Security agenda.</p> 
<p>Separately, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/52983" data-person-id="52983">Todd Young</a> (R-Ind.) joined the growing ranks of Republicans raising questions about the shooting, saying he supports a “full and transparent investigation into the tragic event in Minneapolis.”</p> 
<p>“Congress has requested testimony from ICE, CBP, and USCIS leaders in an open hearing, and they should testify soon,” said Young, who is not a member of Paul’s committee, in a statement to POLITICO. “Providing the American people with the full facts is an important part of maintaining public trust. We also need state and local officials to better cooperate with federal enforcement efforts.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House backs appropriations package with DHS funding</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/white-house-backs-appropriations-package-with-dhs-funding-00746971</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbe1-d452-a99b-fbff7a170000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:58:58 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House on Monday urged the Senate to pass the six-bill appropriations package to avert a partial government shutdown and signaled it doesn’t want Department of Homeland Security money separated out.</p> 
<p>“At this point, the White House supports the bipartisan work that was done to advance the bipartisan appropriations package and we want to see that passed,” press secretary Karoline Leavitt said at a White House briefing when asked if the administration would be willing to separate DHS funding.</p> 
<p>Leavitt said that “policy discussions on immigration in Minnesota are happening,” pointing to President Donald Trump’s call with Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz earlier Monday. She said the discussions “should not be at the expense of government funding for the American people.”</p> 
<p>The press secretary also pointed to the winter storms across the country and the effect a lapse in FEMA funding could have on the response effort.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer has pressed Republicans to rewrite the DHS funding legislation in the wake of the killing of Alex Pretti in Minnesota and signaled that the other five appropriations bills could move forward without it. Senate Republican leadership want to move forward all six bills, including DHS funding, and the first votes are expected Thursday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Hill Democrats want Kristi Noem out as DHS secretary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbb8-dabb-ad9f-fffde7210000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:37:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A growing number of Hill Democrats are calling for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem to step aside or be impeached following the shooting of a Minneapolis man by DHS agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>A House impeachment resolution targeting Noem now has <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HRES_996?q=H.Res.996" target="_blank">140 cosponsors</a>, nearly two-thirds of the Democratic Caucus, according to a spokesperson for Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/204795" data-person-id="204795">Robin Kelly</a> (D-Ill.), who authored the legislation. Dozens signed on over the weekend, including after a private caucus call Sunday in which a number of House Democrats spoke out for impeachment.</p> 
<p>Although impeaching President Donald Trump remains a highly divisive issue among Democrats, calling for Noem’s impeachment or resignation is fast becoming a mainstream position in the party.</p> 
<p>On the cosponsor list for Kelly's resolution are purple-district lawmakers such as Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422300" data-person-id="422300">Laura Gillen</a> (D-N.Y.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422519" data-person-id="422519">Greg Landsman</a> (D-Ohio), as well as members of the party leadership team including Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/152934" data-person-id="152934">Debbie Dingell</a> (D-Mich.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198811" data-person-id="198811">Suzan DelBene</a> (D-Wash.). </p> 
<p>Others in the party are calling for Noem's removal without mentioning the prospect of impeachment. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a>, for instance, declared in a Monday <a href="https://x.com/SenSchumer/status/2015840890112057442?s=20" target="_blank">social media post</a> that Noem "must be fired.” </p> 
<p>In a statement provided first to POLITICO, 15 House Democrats who are veterans said Noem should resign.</p> 
<p>“We call for an immediate stand down of ICE and CBP interior enforcement operations and demand the resignation of the Secretary of Homeland Security,” said the lawmakers, including California Democratic Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189606" data-person-id="189606">Ted Lieu</a>, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259485" data-person-id="259485">Salud Carbajal</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307601" data-person-id="307601">Gil Cisneros</a>. “Current leadership has failed to protect civil liberties, ensure accountability, or maintain the public trust.”</p> 
<p>With Republicans in control of the House floor, it could be difficult for Democrats to force the issue anytime soon. Absent a GOP groundswell, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> will be able to bottle up the measure indefinitely though Kelly could try to call up her impeachment legislation as a privileged matter, allowing it to bypass committees and move to a quick House vote.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suozzi: ‘I failed’ when voting to pass DHS funding bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-suozzi-dhs-funding-vote-00746598</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb59-d452-a99b-fbffc8740006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:29:47 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Tom Suozzi (D-N.Y.) on Monday said he regretted his vote last week for a funding bill for the Department of Homeland Security, amid intense backlash surrounding the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“I failed to view the DHS funding vote as a referendum on the illegal and immoral conduct of ICE in Minneapolis,” <a href="https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=1428888331927735&amp;id=100044197461606&amp;mibextid=wwXIfr&amp;rdid=39dD6MhX9Elb42eK#" target="_blank">he said in a statement</a>. “I hear the anger from my constituents, and I take responsibility for that. I have long been critical of ICE’s unlawful behavior and I must do a better job demonstrating that.”</p> 
<p>Suozzi was one of seven Democrats who crossed party lines to join Republicans in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402" target="_blank">narrowly passing the DHS funding bill</a> in a 220-207 vote. The bill funded agencies including FEMA and the Coast Guard — and ICE, keeping it funded at $10 billion for the fiscal year.</p> 
<p>Suozzi expressed his regret amid mounting tensions following federal immigration operations in Minnesota and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">killing of a second U.S. citizen protester</a>, 37-year-old ICU nurse Alex Pretti, on Saturday.</p> 
<p>“The senseless and tragic murder of Alex Pretti underscores what happens when untrained federal agents operate without accountability,” Suozzi said. “President Trump must immediately end ‘Operation Metro Surge’ and ICE’s occupation of Minneapolis that has sown chaos, led to tragedy, and undermined experienced local law enforcement.”</p> 
<p>Before the weekend killing, the DHS funding was slated to be part of a six-bill package that seemed likely to pass in the Senate. But Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said over the weekend that Democrats would not help <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">advance the current package</a> if it included the DHS funding — significantly raising the risk of a partial government shutdown at the end of the week.</p> 
<p>Rep. Laura Gillen (D-N.Y.), another one of the seven House Democrats who voted for the DHS package, called for DHS Secretary Kristi Noem’s impeachment following Pretti’s killing.</p> 
<p>“Another U.S. citizen has been killed at the hands of ICE and there must be accountability, which is why Secretary Noem must be impeached immediately,” Gillen <a href="https://gillen.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-gillen-urges-accountability-following-events-minnesota" target="_blank">said in a statement Sunday</a>. “Under her leadership, ICE has targeted U.S. citizens and children and killed Americans.”</p> 
<p>But Vicente Gonzalez (D-Texas), another member of the group of breakaway House Democrats, <a href="https://x.com/RepGonzalez/status/2015795510762787001" target="_blank">defended his vote in a video message Monday</a>, calling the footage out of Minnesota "appalling” but defending voting for the DHS funding.</p> 
<p>“ICE has all the resources they need that they got from that big ugly bill Republicans passed last year, that I voted against,” he said, adding he voted for funding for agencies like FEMA and the TSA.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T13:59:49-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans offer early support for Trump’s Minnesota pivot</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-homan-gop-support-00746206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb00-d1ea-a5df-fb8404090005</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:52:21 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Republicans on Capitol Hill expressed relief after President Donald Trump announced Monday he would send border czar Tom Homan to handle immigration enforcement in Minnesota after Department of Homeland Security agents shot and killed a second U.S. citizen there.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) said in an interview that the move was "a positive step to get the situation under control" while calling for a "full and transparent investigation" into the two Minneapolis shootings.</p> 
<p>"There needs to be greater coordination and cooperation between federal, state, and local officials — which is why sanctuary policies need to end and local officials must work with ICE so they can do their jobs without interference," he said. "It is paramount that we work to keep the public and law enforcement safe, while respecting the rights of everyone involved, including the right to peacefully protest."</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> <a href="https://x.com/LeaderJohnThune/status/2015841218182152505" target="_blank">called the move</a> a "positive development," while Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) also offered praise Monday, saying on X “we need a new set of eyes and someone with his experience to help turn around the problems of the moment and the future."</p> 
<p>“Tom is the right man to find a way to de-escalate the situation,” Graham added.</p> 
<p>A growing number of Hill Republicans have been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">pushing publicly and privately</a> for a lowering of the temperature, including from the federal government, after DHS agents shot and killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Saturday.</p> 
<p>GOP lawmakers largely view Homan as a more practical enforcer of Trump’s mass deportation plans as some grow increasingly wary of how Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem and Border Patrol commander Gregory Bovino are handling the campaign, according to six GOP lawmakers granted anonymity to discuss internal conversations.</p> 
<p>“There needed to be a change,” said one of the GOP lawmakers. But other at-risk Republicans have been wary to publicly embrace Homan, who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/16/tom-homan-50k-sting-operation-00611219" target="_blank">denied reports</a> that he took a $50,000 bribe from federal agents.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T13:25:07-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump says Justice Department is investigating Ilhan Omar</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/trump-justice-department-ilhan-omar-00746103</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fac6-d9a8-a7bf-fec66b6c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:30:55 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Monday said the Justice Department is investigating Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.).</p> 
<p>Trump made the <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115961647505369753" target="_blank">announcement on Truth Social</a>, writing: “the DOJ and Congress are looking at ‘Congresswoman’ Illhan Omar, who left Somalia with NOTHING, and is now reportedly worth more than 44 Million Dollars. Time will tell all.”</p> 
<p>It is the latest attack the president has levied at Omar, and the most recent instance of the president directing an investigation into his political rivals.</p> 
<p>Trump has previously said Omar <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/01/trump-ilhan-omar-somalia-00632599" target="_blank">should be jailed or deported to Somalia</a>, where she was born, though Omar has been a U.S. citizen since 2000. He has also linked Omar to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/29/us/fraud-minnesota-somali.html" target="_blank">government services fraud</a> investigations in Minnesota, accusing her of being “one of many scammers,” despite no clear evidence linking her to the cases.</p> 
<p>Tensions have only grown between the two as immigration officials continue to patrol the city of Minneapolis, which Omar represents.</p> 
<p>Omar on Monday appeared unperturbed by Trump's announcement. <a href="https://x.com/IlhanMN/status/2015818278728257569?s=20" target="_blank">In her own post on X</a>, Omar said Trump was "deflecting."</p> 
<p>"Sorry, Trump, your support is collapsing and you’re panicking," she wrote. "Right on cue, you’re deflecting from your failures with lies and conspiracy theories about me. Years of 'investigations' have found nothing. Get your goons out of Minnesota."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Omar's office said she has not received anything from DOJ about an investigation.</p> 
<p>Omar’s net worth skyrocketed in the last year, and House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) <a href="https://nypost.com/2026/01/24/us-news/house-gop-prepares-for-court-to-establish-how-ilhan-omar-her-husband-are-worth-up-to-30m/" target="_blank">recently told the New York Post</a> that he plans to launch an investigation into what caused the dramatic spike.</p> 
<p>According to <a href="https://disclosures-clerk.house.gov/public_disc/financial-pdfs/2024/10068415.pdf" target="_blank">financial disclosures filed last year</a>, Omar’s net worth principally increased due to her spouse — and not her work with the government. She disclosed her spouse having stakes worth collectively between $6 million and $30 million in a venture capital firm and a winery.</p> 
<p>Members of Congress’ and their spouses’ sources of income and assets are traditionally disclosed in broad ranges, not as a specific dollar amount.</p> 
<p>Omar has previously denied the allegations of anything untoward and has said Trump has <a href="https://x.com/ilhanmn/status/1995957774510162165?s=46" target="_blank">a “creepy” obsession</a> with her.</p> 
<p>Trump also announced Monday that he is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">sending border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis</a>. Residents have flooded the streets of the city this month, protesting the shootings of Renee Good, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/woman-killed-by-ice-agent-in-minneapolis-was-a-mother-of-3-poet-and-new-to-the-city-00715809" target="_blank">who was killed by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement officer</a> Jan. 7, and Alex Pretti, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">who was killed by a Border Patrol</a> agent Saturday.</p> 
<p>The Department of Justice did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: Due to an editing error, an earlier version of this report misstated the value of Omar's spouse's business partnerships.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Shutdown odds spike after Minnesota killing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/what-were-watching-00745892</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f841-dabb-ad9f-ffede4950000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The killing of Alex Pretti at the hands of federal agents is hitting hard on Capitol Hill, ratcheting up the odds of a partial government shutdown and spurring Republican lawmakers to make another break with the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Here’s the latest on how the fallout from the Minnesota shooting is playing out in Congress:</p> 
<p><b>— Shutdown looks likely: </b>The Senate is set to take its first vote on the last tranche of government funding bills Thursday, and things aren’t looking good.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer is insisting that Republicans work across the aisle to rewrite DHS funding legislation but also signaling that Democrats would be willing to help advance the other five pending appropriations bills in the meantime. Several Democrats who helped end the previous shutdown say they plan to vote against the funding bills unless there are changes to the ICE operation in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>At this stage, Senate GOP leadership expects to move forward as planned on the six-bill package including DHS. Republicans and the White House have reached out to Senate Democrats about how to proceed, but one Senate Democratic leadership aide granted anonymity said they haven’t raised “realistic solutions.” A number of rank-and-file Senate Republicans are speaking out against any attempt to “defund” DHS — and leadership would need buy-in from all 100 senators to quickly strip out the DHS bill. President Donald Trump is <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115958123338296139" target="_blank">now pushing Republicans</a> to pass a bill to “END Sanctuary Cities.”</p> 
<p>A couple key reminders: The pending funding bills include money for the departments of Defense, Health and Human Services and State, and account for more than 75 percent of federal discretionary spending.</p> 
<p>And don’t forget the House is out this week and wouldn’t be around to pass any revamped funding bills before Friday. The Senate won’t hold its first vote of the week until Tuesday afternoon because of the snow storm.</p> 
<p><b>— Trump faces nervous GOP: </b>A growing number of House and Senate Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">voicing public concerns</a> about the incident and calling for an investigation, as top administration officials defend the agents involved.</p> 
<p>Even close Trump allies are beginning to speak out. Sen. David McCormick (R-Pa.) <a href="https://x.com/SenMcCormickPA/status/2015562528114520255" target="_blank">said on X Sunday night</a> that he supports the Border Patrol and ICE but that he agrees <a href="https://x.com/NRA/status/2015227627464728661?s=20" target="_blank">with the NRA</a> about the need for a “full investigation.”</p> 
<p>House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) is calling for DHS officials to testify. House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) suggested to Fox News that Trump would want to “maybe go to another city” as Minnesota officials push back.</p> 
<p>Some Republicans have been privately warning administration officials and GOP leaders for months that Trump’s immigration crackdown is not going over well in some pockets of the country.</p> 
<p>“Many of us wonder if the administration has any clue as to how much this will hurt us legislatively and electorally this year,” said one House Republican.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How $16B in earmarks evaded conservative ire — and helped clinch a funding deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/earmarks-conservatives-government-funding-00745730</link>
      <description>Republican leaders have agreed to earmarks for thousands of pet projects in specific congressional districts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f6cd-d1ea-a5df-f6cda3d30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/dd/d3/c37e10b84e35b500d42b7d2e2afe/u-s-congress-22286.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Reps. Ralph Norman and Chip Roy confer during a House Rules Committee meeting at the U.S. Capitol on July 1, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/dd/d3/c37e10b84e35b500d42b7d2e2afe/u-s-congress-22286.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fiscal conservatives in Congress threatened for months to block government funding if GOP leaders didn’t shun earmarks. They succeeded in scrapping just one; the rest, almost $16 billion worth, are slated in the package the Senate needs to clear by Friday to avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p>Republican hard-liners on both sides of the Capitol have made things difficult this winter for their leadership, which has been scrambling to fund the government before cash runs out Friday for the vast majority of federal agencies. But they failed to significantly curtail the practice of directing federal dollars to specific projects back home.</p> 
<p>Republicans swore off earmarks for more than a decade in 2010 amid corruption scandals and demands from conservatives empowered by the rise of the Tea Party movement that has since receded. Then in 2021, Democrats brought back the practice after the party swept control of the White House and Congress, softening the return with a rebrand as “community project funding,” new rules to prevent abuse and a cap at 1 percent of funding.</p> 
<p>Now Republicans run Washington once again, and they’re overwhelmingly embracing the renaissance. As the Senate considers a nearly $1.3 trillion funding package this week loaded with thousands of earmarks for projects in specific congressional districts, fiscal hawks are acknowledging defeat.</p> 
<p>“When a majority of the United States House and a large chunk of the Senate seemingly want to advance earmarks, there's only so much you can do,” Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas), a member of the House Freedom Caucus, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>“I've long stated I think it's the currency of corruption, and we shouldn't do it,” he added. “But, you know, members like to do it.”</p> 
<p>Capitol Hill’s most vocal earmark proponents argue that, if not for the revival of earmarks, congressional leaders would not have succeeded in clinching bipartisan deals to fund the Pentagon and nondefense agencies with new budgets for the first time in almost two years.</p> 
<p>The multibill funding package has yet to reach President Donald Trump’s desk and is now <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank"><u>complicated by Democratic outrage</u></a> over ICE funding after a federal immigration enforcement agent fatally shot another U.S. citizen in Minnesota over the weekend. But lawmakers in both parties are already touting the cash they secured for local projects as they campaign for reelection nine months out from the midterms.</p> 
<p>“It's not worth being in Congress if you can't find ways to help your district,” Rep. Mike Flood said in an interview.</p> 
<p>The Nebraska Republican secured almost $30 million in projects for his district in the current slate of funding bills, including millions of dollars to repave roads, about $750,000 for police cruisers and $500,000 for improvements to a shelter for minors who would otherwise be in juvenile detention.</p> 
<p>Flood argues the inclusion of earmarks ultimately helped Republicans negotiate funding bills that keep federal spending mostly steady — a top priority of congressional fiscal hawks. “For all the things that people say are wrong with Congress, this process is working. And it's working well,” he said. “And we are bringing this in under budget.”</p> 
<p>This month members of the House Freedom Caucus threatened to tank a preliminary vote on spending bills if GOP leaders didn’t knock out at least some earmarks. They were able to kill only one: a $1 million earmark Democratic Rep. Ilhan Omar secured for a community organization in her Minnesota district, in part because the address listed for the group was that of a restaurant.</p> 
<p>House fiscal hawks made a final stand last week when they demanded, and received, a vote to nix hundreds of earmarks senators had worked to secure. That vote failed overwhelmingly, right before the House passed a funding package with a price tag of more than $1 trillion, with every earmark intact.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman, a member of the Freedom Caucus, said it was a “sad day” and called it “irredeemable” for a GOP-led Congress and White House to support the earmark-filled package. Norman said he now has no hope Republicans will ever do anything to get rid of earmarks.</p> 
<p>“I wish it was different,” he said.</p> 
<p>More than 70 House Republicans voted against killing the Senate earmarks. However, some hard-liners argue that it’s really the minority party driving the resurgence in a narrowly divided Congress.</p> 
<p>“You need Democratic votes, right? So let's not forget that,” said Rep. Scott Perry (R-Pa.), a former chair of the House Freedom Caucus. “I'm not here to apologize for, or validate, a bunch of garbage Republican earmarks. But we’d have a much better time at making sure those didn't prevail if we didn't need the Democrat votes.”</p> 
<p>In the Senate, where Democratic buy-in is necessary to overcome the filibuster, fiscal conservatives <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/senate-gop-conservatives-lee-johnson-scott-00703034" target="_blank">delayed action on funding bills</a> for more than a month following the end of the record-breaking government shutdown in November — in part due to their earmark concerns. Now that the final slate of funding bills is before the Senate, those same lawmakers are again demanding a vote to eliminate the pet projects.</p> 
<p>Last week Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.), a leader of that charge, noted that in 2021 the Senate Republican Conference voted unanimously to maintain their rule against earmarks, a nonbinding prohibition many <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/05/05/senate-republicans-earmarks-485373" target="_blank"><u>GOP senators were quick to flout</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“It’s time for Senate Republicans to follow our own rules. END ALL EARMARKS NOW!” <a href="https://x.com/SenRickScott/status/2014799358047216093?s=20" target="_blank"><u>Scott posted on social media</u></a>.</p> 
<p>The earmarks Congress has inserted in the new funding bills are the first of Trump’s presidency, since federal agencies have been running on stopgap funding patches for almost two years. Lawmakers in both parties see them as a way to protect their authority to dictate how federal money is spent as the Trump administration continues to shift and cancel billions of dollars in contravention of their wishes.</p> 
<p>“It restores the institutional faith in Congress' ability — albeit in a very small and minor way — to direct congressional spending and gets power back from any executive branch,” Tennessee Rep. Chuck Fleischmann, a senior Republican appropriator, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Many Republican lawmakers have been privately pressing GOP leaders to bring back earmarks for years, including as far back as 2016, when then-Speaker Paul Ryan <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2016/11/gop-lift-earmark-ban-231500" target="_blank"><u>halted a closed-door vote</u></a> on restoring the practice.</p> 
<p>At least under the old rules, earmarks were entwined with corruption. In the early 2000s, several lawmakers pled guilty to money laundering and bribery charges for abusing the practice. In the most high-profile of those cases, the late Rep. Randy “Duke” Cunningham (R-Calif.) admitted to accepting $2.4 million in bribes to secure earmarks.</p> 
<p>Now Congress has much tighter rules governing the process, including a prohibition on steering money to for-profit organizations. Senior members of the Appropriations Committees who want to avoid a repeat of infamous earmarks scandals also closely vet the requests, said House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.).</p> 
<p>“We scrub them pretty hard, and honestly the Democrats do, too,” he said.</p> 
<p>In a sign House Republicans are growing more comfortable with the practice, they are now discussing whether to expand earmarks in future funding bills to include education, health and labor projects, according to Rep. Robert Aderholt (R-Ala.), who chairs the panel in charge of that money. Only senators are currently allowed to specify projects for funding within those jurisdictions.</p> 
<p>“There's interest on both sides, as long as it's done in a way that doesn't make both sides feel uncomfortable,” Aderholt said. “Members want to have a little bit of say-so, because we do have the power of the purse.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-25T16:14:29-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans start raising concerns about Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707</link>
      <description>Most in the GOP are silent or backing the Trump administration, but a conspicuous few are speaking out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f675-dabb-ad9f-fffd94780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 13:44:59 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f5/bb/3089e2184b72b2a7d1e4df2758d0/u-s-congress-33546.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“ICE agents do not have carte blanche in carrying out their duties," Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said Sunday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f5/bb/3089e2184b72b2a7d1e4df2758d0/u-s-congress-33546.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A small but growing number of Republicans are raising public concerns about the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">killing Saturday of a 37-year-old Minnesota man</a> by federal agents.</p> 
<p>Hours after the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti on a Minneapolis street, one House GOP chair called for the top Immigration and Customs Enforcement leader and other Trump administration officials to publicly answer lawmakers’ questions. GOP Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> of North Carolina called for independent probes into the shooting, with <a href="https://x.com/SenBillCassidy/status/2015247523003162922" target="_blank">Cassidy arguing</a> the integrity of ICE and the Department of Homeland Security are “at stake.”</p> 
<p>Another House GOP chair appeared to suggest President Donald Trump should withdraw from Minneapolis and send the agents there to another city.</p> 
<p>"If I were President Trump, I would almost think about, OK, if the mayor and governor are going put our ICE officials in harm's way and there's a chance of losing more innocent lives, or whatever, then maybe go to another city and let the people of Minneapolis decide: Do we want to continue to have all of these illegals?” Oversight Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260072" data-person-id="260072">James Comer</a> (R-Ky.) said Sunday on Fox News, adding that he expected Minnesotans to “rebel against their leadership.”</p> 
<p>However gentle and equivocal the pushback might be, it is growing increasingly conspicuous as congressional Republicans privately discuss how to respond to Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement campaign ahead of the midterm elections. Some Republicans have been privately warning administration officials and GOP leaders for months that the operation is not going over well in some pockets of the country.</p> 
<p>“Many of us wonder if the administration has any clue as to how much this will hurt us legislatively and electorally this year,” said one House Republican granted anonymity to candidly discuss private reactions.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said Sunday “ICE agents do not have carte blanche in carrying out their duties.”</p> 
<p>“Lawfully carrying a firearm does not justify federal agents killing an American — especially, as video footage appears to show, after the victim had been disarmed,” she said.</p> 
<p>While some of those speaking out are retiring, <a href="https://x.com/SenThomTillis/status/2015435983316189686?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">like Tillis</a>, or known to be at odds with Trump, like Murkowski, not all fit that bill. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/306838" data-person-id="306838">Dusty Johnson</a>, who called Sunday for all parties to “deescalate,” is running in a June GOP primary to be South Dakota’s governor.</p> 
<p>"As with any officer-involved shooting, this demands a thorough investigation," <a href="https://x.com/RepDustyJohnson/status/2015468366773858419" target="_blank">he wrote on X</a>.</p> 
<p>After House Homeland Security Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/240947" data-person-id="240947">Andrew Garbarino</a> (R-N.Y.) called Saturday for ICE, Border Patrol and other DHS officials to <a href="https://homeland.house.gov/2026/01/24/chairman-garbarino-requests-ice-cbp-uscis-testimony-for-upcoming-oversight-hearing/" target="_blank">testify before his panel</a>, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/195413" data-person-id="195413">Michael Baumgartner</a> (R-Wash.) praised the move, saying it was important “the American people and Congress be given a better understanding of how immigration enforcement is being handled.”</p> 
<p>Still, most Hill Republicans have not weighed in publicly or are backing the Trump administration, which was quick to argue Pretti was a “domestic terrorist” intent on massacring federal agents. Eyewitness video shows no evidence he drew his weapon or otherwise threatened agents with deadly force before he was shot.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said in an interview with CBS’ “Face the Nation” Sunday that people are not allowed to carry a gun while committing another crime. "And interfering with law enforcement is a felony,” he added.</p> 
<p>"Peaceful protesters don’t have 9mm weapons with two extra magazines,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew</a> (R-N.J.) said on Fox News, referring to the concealed handgun Pretti had a permit to carry.</p> 
<p>The shooting and backlash from Democrats has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">upended a crucial government funding package</a> that the Senate was expected to pass this week. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said Saturday that Democrats won’t vote to advance <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">the legislation</a> so long as DHS funding is included, raising the likelihood of a partial shutdown at midnight Friday.</p> 
<p>He called on Republicans Sunday to pass the parts of the package funding other agencies while working with Democrats on "overhauling ICE and CBP to protect the public."</p> 
<p>"People should be safe from abuse by their own government," he said.</p> 
<p>Amid the uncertainty, some Republicans have privately fretted about the lack of guidance coming from the Trump administration about the shooting. Four GOP lawmakers and several GOP aides noted they had received many more updates from the administration about the weekend’s major winter storm than the situation in Minneapolis or immigration enforcement operations generally.</p> 
<p>Compounding the confusion, a DHS official sent an email alert with incorrect and contradictory information to congressional Republicans about three hours after the shooting Saturday, according to three people with direct knowledge of the message, which POLITICO obtained.</p> 
<p>The email described “the incident this morning between US Border Patrol officers and an illegal alien with a 9 mm semi-automatic handgun, who was wanted for violent assault.” But it linked to a DHS social media post that said federal agents were pursuing “an illegal alien wanted for violent assault” and then an “individual approached US Border Patrol officers with a 9 mm semi-automatic handgun,” referring to Pretti, who was a U.S. citizen.</p> 
<p>As Republicans wrangle with the shooting, Democrats are discussing internally how to mount a response — with senators strategizing over the funding bill and House leaders considering options including targeting Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem with sanctions.</p> 
<p>There’s a growing demand in the caucus to impeach Noem, with one purple-district Democrat who voted for DHS funding last week, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422300" data-person-id="422300">Laura Gillen</a> of New York, <a href="https://x.com/RepLauraGillen/status/2015460034537247216?s=20" target="_blank">publicly backing</a> the move shortly after a Sunday morning caucus call.</p> 
<p>Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz and state Attorney General Keith Ellison, both former House Democrats, briefed the lawmakers on the private call.</p> 
<p>Walz “sounded the alarm” over the “illegal” DHS activity in Minnesota, “and he urged everyone to unite and defend the integrity of the victims who are being smeared by the Trump administration,” said one House Democrat on the call who was granted anonymity because participants were encouraged not to leak its contents.</p> 
<p>“This is dark, unthinkable stuff, but I've never seen Democrats more militantly united,” the lawmaker added.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu and Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eleanor Holmes Norton won’t seek reelection as DC delegate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/eleanor-holmes-norton-retires-dc-delegate-00731986</link>
      <description>The 88-year-old Democrat had been facing mounting calls to step down.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c336-d22e-a1db-df37d7660000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 10:28:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a7/7c/46c635804d1e99e63f5fc2eab258/u-s-congress-06956.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Eleanor Holmes Norton's campaign on Sunday filed a termination notice with the Federal Election Commission.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a7/7c/46c635804d1e99e63f5fc2eab258/u-s-congress-06956.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Eleanor Holmes Norton, Washington’s nonvoting delegate to the House for more than three decades, will not seek a 19th term in office.</p> 
<p>Norton's campaign on Sunday <a href="https://docquery.fec.gov/cgi-bin/forms/C00244335/1935124/" target="_blank">filed a termination notice</a> with the Federal Election Commission, essentially signaling an end to her campaign. She can still file for reelection in the future. </p> 
<p>Norton's spokesperson did not respond to a request for comment. <a href="https://www.notus.org/2026-election/eleanor-holmes-norton-reelection-campaign-termination" target="_blank">NOTUS first reported</a> on the termination filing. </p> 
<p>Norton, 88, has faced mounting questions about her ability to serve in office as she retreated from most public appearances and showed unmistakable signs of frailty when she did speak.</p> 
<p>Her fitness came under particular scrutiny last summer when <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/13/eleanor-holmes-norton-trump-dc-00506273" target="_blank">she remained largely out of sight</a> as President Donald Trump announced a move to surge National Guard and federal law enforcement into Washington and take over its police department against the will of city leaders.</p> 
<p>While Norton insisted for months afterward she would in fact run again, reelection appeared increasingly untenable. Prominent Democratic strategist Donna Brazile, her former top aide, publicly called on her to retire, and Norton <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/08/congress/eleanor-holmes-norton-reelection-fundraising-00598060" target="_blank">raised scant funds</a> for her campaign.</p> 
<p>What is already a crowded field of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/18/robert-white-eleanor-holmes-norton-challenge-00571433" target="_blank">challengers to the longtime delegate</a> could balloon even further. The election is likely to be decided in the Democratic primary election in a city that hasn’t given a Republican presidential nominee more than 10 percent of the vote since 1988.</p> 
<p>Among the Democrats already vying to succeed her are D.C. Council members Brooke Pinto and Robert White, political strategist Kinney Zalesne and former Norton aide Trent Holbrook.</p> 
<p>One of only two people who have represented D.C. in Congress since the delegate position was established in 1970, Norton made her reputation as a civil rights activist and pioneering attorney for women’s rights. Elected to succeed Walter Fauntroy in 1990, she became known on Capitol Hill as a fierce defender of the city’s self-rule, helping to orchestrate a financial rescue for the city in the 1990s while fending off efforts by congressional Republicans to assert more control over the city.</p> 
<p>In the later decades of her career, she worked to build support for more autonomy for the city government and to secure congressional voting rights for D.C. residents. A bipartisan bid to secure D.C. a full House vote evaporated in 2009, and Norton turned to pushing statehood efforts.</p> 
<p>The House voted to support D.C. statehood in 2020 and 2021, but the effort has not otherwise advanced.</p> 
<p>Decades of improving conditions in the city had led to an increasingly hands-off approach from federal overseers. But that changed in recent years after a post-pandemic surge in crime and Trump’s reelection in 2024 — posing the greatest threat to the city’s autonomy since it was granted partial home rule in 1973.</p> 
<p>Norton was largely absent from the public eye during Trump’s takeover, issuing statements and news releases but not granting interviews or appearing alongside municipal leaders who railed against the Trump administration. When she has made speeches on Capitol Hill, she has read from prepared remarks with halting delivery and with aides close beside her.</p> 
<p>In an episode that raised further questions about her fitness for reelection, Norton was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/24/eleanor-holmes-norton-police-report-00622757" target="_blank">scammed out of thousands of dollars</a> by fraudsters last year. She was described as having “early stages of dementia” in an internal police report that also described a longtime aide as her caretaker with power of attorney.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump’s return supercharges lobbying revenues</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/trump-lobbying-revenues-00744357</link>
      <description>Firms with ties to the administration reaped windfalls, including one that saw a 350 percent revenue bump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f1d6-d1ea-a5df-f1d6d47d0009</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fc/36/936360274e5d827d807a87a23129/k-street-02405.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">J. Scott Applewhite/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>The K Street corridor is seen in northwest Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fc/36/936360274e5d827d807a87a23129/k-street-02405.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Caitlin Oprysko</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Caitlin Oprysko</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump’s second term is already delivering a massive payday for Washington’s top lobbying shops — especially those with close ties to the administration.</p> 
<p>According to disclosures filed this week, Trump's wide-ranging policy upheavals across trade, tax, health care, tech, defense and energy boosted the bottom lines of almost every one of K Street's biggest lobbying firms.</p> 
<p>Thirteen of the largest 20 firms by revenue reported growth of 10 percent or more compared to 2024. In total, they brought in nearly $824 million, up from $595 million during the final year of the Biden administration.</p> 
<p>Several reported their highest-ever annual revenues, including Ballard Partners, Brownstein Hyatt Farber Schreck, BGR Group, Akin Gump Strauss Hauer &amp; Feld and Holland &amp; Knight.</p> 
<p>"The real driver was that it's the most activity that we've seen from a first year of a new administration in a long time," said Holland &amp; Knight partner Paul Stimers, whose firm brought in $54.6 million in lobbying revenues last year.</p> 
<p>While federal lobbying spending <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/news/2025/02/federal-lobbying-set-new-record-in-2024/" target="_blank">has been climbing steadily</a> for the past decade — and the typical Year 1 of an administration also juices revenue — Trump's aggressive use of executive power and influence is supercharging the trend.</p> 
<p>“Every quarter it seems that there are more challenges and opportunities from the administration and Congress,” said Brownstein policy director Nadeam Elshami.</p> 
<p>Some of the firms that saw the most dramatic windfalls were those with close ties to Trump and top administration officials.</p> 
<p>Ballard Partners, which counts Attorney General Pam Bondi and White House chief of staff Susie Wiles among its alumni, signed more than 200 new clients after Trump's election. It led K Street last year with more than $88.3 million in lobbying fees — a 350 percent increase from 2024. </p> 
<p>In the fourth quarter alone, Ballard brought in more revenue than it did in all of 2024. (POLITICO’s parent company, Axel Springer, was a Ballard Partners client for less than two months last year.)</p> 
<p>Ballard contends that it's focused on long-term success, beyond its sharp rise last year and close ties to the current administration.</p> 
<p>“We remain doggedly committed to growing a fiercely bipartisan firm that is built to thrive in Washington’s dynamic political environment for decades to come,” said the firm's founder and president Brian Ballard, who credited his employees for the firm's growth.</p> 
<p>Brownstein, K Street's previous top earner and No. 2 for 2025, brought in $73.9 million in lobbying revenues last year, up from $67.9 million in 2024.</p> 
<p>Coming in third last year was BGR Group, which employed former Wisconsin Republican Rep. Sean Duffy before he became Trump's Secretary of Transportation. It also counts former Trump campaign adviser David Urban as a managing director. BGR reported $71.5 million in lobbying revenues last year, a 58 percent increase from 2024.</p> 
<p>Among the upstart lobbying firms that cashed in on Trump’s second term were Continental Strategy, which was launched in 2021 by former Trump diplomat and adviser Carlos Trujillo. Continental, which also employs a top former aide to Secretary of State Marco Rubio and one of Wiles’ daughters, saw its lobbying revenues skyrocket from $1.8 million in 2024 to more than $27 million in 2025. </p> 
<p>Checkmate Government Relations, which is led by Ches McDowell, a friend of Donald Trump Jr., reported receiving $70,000 from a single client at the end of 2024 but signed 80 clients and brought in more than $21 million in 2025.</p> 
<p>Looking ahead, lobbyists expect trade to continue driving client interest in 2026, especially as businesses await the Supreme Court’s decision on the legality of Trump’s so-called reciprocal tariffs. </p> 
<p>Even as they forecast a slowdown in legislation ahead of the midterm elections, lobbyists say they’ll also remain busy with congressional oversight, the government funding process as well as the administration's latest foreign policy moves.</p> 
<p>“Frankly, the lesson learned going forward is, Don't be surprised,” Elshami said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats are shying away from climate messaging. One of their own is fighting back.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-climate-affordability-trump-00745597</link>
      <description>There’s a schism within the Democratic Party about whether talking about climate change is the right message to win back control of Washington.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f1f4-dabb-ad9f-fffda3950000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/23/8e/20cab1e04de9922f36d8f44fe764/u-s-congress-10611.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse (D-R.I.) walks to a meeting at the U.S. Capitol on Dec. 8, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/23/8e/20cab1e04de9922f36d8f44fe764/u-s-congress-10611.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Amelia Davidson and Kelsey Brugger</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Amelia Davidson and Kelsey Brugger</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of Congress’ loudest climate hawks is trying to fend off a push within his party to abandon calls to combat climate change as left-leaning agenda-setters are plotting to reclaim both chambers of Congress in the midterms.</p> 
<p>"There’s a thing out there called a ‘climate husher,'” Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse, the top Democrat on the Environment and Public Works Committee, posted as part of a long social media thread last week.</p> 
<p>“Anyone who cares about what fossil fuel pollution is doing to Earth’s natural systems needs to ignore these so-called ‘climate hushers’ — people who think Dems should stop talking about climate,” he said.</p> 
<p>In a later interview about his posts, Whitehouse warned these “climate hushers” have also made their way into strategy conversations on Capitol Hill. He noted he’s been present for some of them, which he described as “polling presentations made to the Senate Democratic Caucus in a so-called strategy retreat that didn’t ask about climate change … There’s this massive blind spot.”</p> 
<p>In recent years, Democrats have been handwringing over the best messaging on environmental issues to reach an electorate that cares about “kitchen table” matters – and doesn’t uniformly consider the rapidly warming planet to be one of them. Environmentalists made a strong argument during the 2024 presidential campaign that the climate crisis should be a motivator in electing Kamala Harris — but the contest went to Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Now Democrats are increasingly showing they have decided it’s a losing message to tout the ways in which they’d curb fossil fuel production to thwart the most dire effects of climate change. Instead, they’re choosing to focus on policies that would lower energy costs and lean hard into affordability talking points embraced by Trump and congressional Republicans.</p> 
<p>Whitehouse understands the importance of talking about affordability — for years he’s spoken about the climate crisis as a threat to the global economy.</p> 
<p>His social media thread notes that people are feeling the economic burdens of climate change throughout the country, from home insurance hikes to drops in property values.</p> 
<p>That's the message Democrats should lean into, he said, rather than shy away from.</p> 
<p>“When leaders don’t talk about something, enthusiasm falls among voters,” Whitehouse wrote in his post. “In politics, you can often make your own wind, or you can make your own doldrums.”</p> 
<p>This is something Democrats are grappling with on Capitol Hill. Interviews with a half dozen House and Senate Democrats revealed how many are still struggling with how to discuss climate change, a problem they consider existential but that doesn’t register among voters’ top immediate concerns.</p> 
<p>Some are talking nearly exclusively about competitive prices for clean energy — largely in hopes of beating Republicans at their own messaging game.</p> 
<p>“My theory of the case is that the argument that I’ve been making for 30 years is finally breaking through,” said Rep. Sean Casten (D-Ill.), a former clean energy professional.</p> 
<p>“The urgency of climate change means that we have to focus on it especially when it’s not as salient with the American people, if we are to be the leaders we claim to be,” he added. “But I think that’s largely a separable conversation from what is the best way to talk about it in any given moment, that has the most ability to move public opinion.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Brian Schatz of Hawaii, who is on track to be the next Senate Democratic whip, has a similar perspective.</p> 
<p>Last year, he removed “climate hawk,” along with other self-descriptions, from his bio on X. And during an event this fall affiliated with New York Climate Week, he said that “those of us in the climate community who are used to making a more broad argument about where we are in the sweep of history have to get comfortable making a more immediate argument that says the reason prices are going up is a deliberate policy choice of the Republican Party.”</p> 
<p>Schatz said in a statement last week that he and Whitehouse were united in their ideas around “climate action,” but he also doubled down on the importance of affordability messaging at this time.</p> 
<p>“There are think tanks and advocacy organizations that are dedicated to the proposition that climate action is incompatible with affordable energy, but those factional rivalries have been overtaken by events,” Schatz said. “Cheap is clean, and clean is cheap.”</p> 
<p>Recent actions from the Democrats’ Sustainable Energy and Environment Coalition, or SEEC — of which Casten is vice-chair — have also focused squarely on energy costs and the ability of clean energy to lower Americans’ bills.</p> 
<p>At a SEEC press conference earlier this month meant to respond to the last year of energy and environment policy under President Donald Trump, a roster of climate-focused Democrats spoke nearly exclusively about energy prices. “Trump lied; Energy costs are up,” read the main sign at the presser.</p> 
<p>Rep. Melanie Stansbury (D-N.M.), a member of the House Natural Resources Committee, said in an interview that Democrats need to focus on energy prices because Trump has used that as a justification for executive actions that bolster oil and gas.</p> 
<p>“People, when they see the ways in which the energy policies that are serving big oil are hurting their pocketbooks, it makes it more tangible for why folks should care, in addition to the welfare of the planet,” Stansbury said.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Republicans have picked up on the Democrats’ shift in talking points and have used it to their advantage.</p> 
<p>“You actually see on the left, this debate going on right now, where a lot of people within the Democratic Party, they are talking about how they’ve lost the narrative, or the culture war, on climate,” EPA Administrator Lee Zeldin said on Fox Business this month.</p> 
<p>Left-leaning thinkers and independent analysts have also argued that Democrats may have gone too far in following the lead of environmental groups they say were out of touch with most Americans.</p> 
<p>Columnist Matt Yglesias argued in a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/18/opinion/democrats-liberals-oil-gas-industry.html" target="_blank"><i><u>New York Times</u></i><u> op-ed</u></a> that Democrats should not be hostile to oil and gas. Longtime energy expert Daniel Yergin wrote in <i>Foreign Affairs</i> about the “<a href="https://www.foreignaffairs.com/united-states/troubled-energy-transition-yergin-orszag-arya" target="_blank"><u>troubled energy transition</u></a>” and the need for a “pragmatic path” forward. And Veteran Democratic operative Adam Jentleson started the think tank <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/03/dems-are-quietly-forming-a-think-tank-to-help-them-win-again-00381601" target="_blank"><u>the Searchlight Institute</u></a> to curb the influence of the “groups” on party positions, including climate.</p> 
<p>Rep. Kathy Castor of Florida, the top Democrat on the Energy and Commerce’s Energy Subcommittee, downplayed the notion that congressional Democrats were at odds over how to message on climate change. Talking about affordability need not negate the focus on the impact of climate change, she said.</p> 
<p>“I think they are one in the same,” Castor said. “Take my community in Florida. We’re still recovering from Hurricane Helen and Milton and people understand that those storms were supercharged because the Gulf was very, very hot, very warm. And the rain was unlike anything we’ve ever seen. So they are trying to afford rebuilding their homes and paying their property insurance and also suffering higher rate increases.”</p> 
<p>Whitehouse in an interview acknowledged some shortcomings to Democrats’ past depictions of climate change “as sort of a moral imperative, as an intangible thing floating out there, something that will affect polar bears,” but said the solution wasn’t to be silent in calling out the harmful impacts of fossil fuel emissions and the influence of oil and gas companies on Trump administration policy.</p> 
<p>Ultimately, there's only so much he can do to press his case. In recent months he has organized forums on climate change as the senior Democrat on the Environment and Public Works panel, toured red states to talk about rising insurance rates related to natural disasters spurred by global warming and said he has commissioned his own polling on the issue.</p> 
<p>Those activities, plus delivering speeches and crafting social media posts, are among the limits of what he can achieve with his party in the minority and his colleagues making their own messaging choices.</p> 
<p>He isn't giving up.</p> 
<p>“Democrats and environmental groups’ climate messaging for years has been crap, and so if you go back to that crap messaging, obviously it’s not going to succeed,” Whitehouse said. “But that doesn’t mean that the alternative is to throw in the towel.”</p> 
<p><i>Andres Picon and Timothy Cama contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-24T19:20:28-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Shutdown risk grows as Democrats revolt after Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642</link>
      <description>Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said "Senate Democrats will not provide the votes" to fund immigration enforcement, part of a six-bill package set for action next week.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f25d-d452-a99b-fbffdaf10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 18:39:15 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/47/26/1beb046d49468116fc0a3e55f93f/u-s-congress-30162.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto of Nevada is among the Democrats who previously supported funding bills who are now opposing DHS appropriations.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/47/26/1beb046d49468116fc0a3e55f93f/u-s-congress-30162.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is on a path toward a partial government shutdown next week after Senate Democrats vowed to oppose Department of Homeland Security funding following the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">killing of a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident</a> by federal agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said in a statement Saturday night that Democrats would not help advance the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill spending package</a> set for consideration next week as long as it includes DHS funding. Republicans will need Democratic support in order to clear a 60-vote hurdle to advance the funding bill.</p> 
<p>“Senate Democrats will not provide the votes to proceed to the appropriations bill if the DHS funding bill is included,” Schumer said, adding that he would personally vote “no.”</p> 
<p>Congress has already passed full-year funding for some agencies — including the departments of Agriculture, Commerce, Interior and Justice — but not for several of the largest, including the Pentagon. Temporary funding for those departments, representing more than 75 percent of federal discretionary spending, expires midnight Friday.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats will hold a conference call Sunday evening, according to a Democratic aide granted anonymity to discuss the private meeting. The call will give them a chance to discuss next steps with the Senate stuck out of town <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/senate-vote-shutdown-snow-00745282" target="_blank">until at least Tuesday</a> because of the massive winter storm affecting much of the country. </p> 
<p>Earlier in the day, as news of the Minneapolis shooting spread, several Democratic senators who had previously voted to advance government funding measures under President Donald Trump vowed to oppose DHS funding this time. Funding for ICE and Border Patrol, the agencies involved in the Minnesota operation, is included in the pending Senate bill.</p> 
<p>“I am voting against any funding for DHS until and unless more controls are put in place to hold ICE accountable,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/201768" data-person-id="201768">Brian Schatz</a> (D-Hawaii) <a href="https://x.com/brianschatz/status/2015171159164096863?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">in a statement Saturday</a>. “These repeated incidents of violence across the country are unlawful, needlessly escalatory, and making all of us less safe.”</p> 
<p>Schatz helped advance a funding bill in March, and Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259552" data-person-id="259552">Catherine Cortez Masto</a> (D-Nev.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259494" data-person-id="259494">Jacky Rosen</a> (D-Nev.), who voted to end the 43-day shutdown in November, also both said Saturday that they will oppose the DHS funding bill.</p> 
<p>“I have the responsibility to hold the Trump Administration accountable when I see abuses of power — like we are seeing from ICE right now,” <a href="https://x.com/SenJackyRosen/status/2015172486392857019?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">Rosen said on X</a>. “That is why I’ll be voting against any government funding package that contains the bill that funds this agency, until we have guardrails in place to curtail these abuses of power and ensure more accountability and transparency.”</p> 
<p>The DHS bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402" target="_blank">passed the House Thursday 220-207</a>, with only seven Democrats voting for it. But Republican House leaders merged it with five other bills funding the departments of Defense, Health and Human Services and State, among others, sending it to the Senate as one package.</p> 
<p>More than half of the 47-member Democratic caucus has already vowed to oppose the package, many before Saturday’s shooting. And that number is growing as Democrats’ re-evaluate the legislation in the wake of the shooting and as they face pressure from House Democrats and their Senate colleagues, not to mention outside voices close to the party base.</p> 
<p>Abdul El-Sayed, a Democratic candidate seeking a Senate seat in Michigan, said in an interview Saturday he saw no way for any Democrat to justify a vote for DHS funding.</p> 
<p>“How many more people do they need to shoot?” he asked.</p> 
<p>A group of senators, including <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a> (D-Conn.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189610" data-person-id="189610">Alex Padilla</a> (D-Calif.), have been whipping colleagues for days to oppose the DHS bill, according to two aides granted anonymity to discuss their private effort. And two people familiar with the plans said House Democrats are scheduled to hold a private caucus call Sunday morning to discuss a response to the shooting.</p> 
<p>Cortez Masto, in a statement, suggested dropping the Department of Homeland Security bill from the larger package, noting there is a “bipartisan agreement on 96% of the budget.”</p> 
<p>“Let’s pass the remaining five bipartisan bills and fund essential agencies while we continue to fight for a Department of Homeland Security that respects Americans’ constitutional rights and preserves federal law enforcement’s essential role to keep us safe,” she said.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51223" data-person-id="51223">Jack Reed</a> (D-R.I.) said he would agree to “immediately pass” the other five bills while providing “short term funding for DHS so the Senate can fully debate and vote on common sense reforms to ICE that bolster the rule of law.”</p> 
<p>But stripping out the DHS bill before the Friday deadline would require every senator to agree — something Republicans aren’t likely to be able to get. Any changes to the package, meanwhile, will require sending it back to the House, which has already left town until after the shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>Instead, Republicans believe it's up to Democrats to decide whether or not to vote against the funding package and avoid a partial shutdown. GOP leaders aren’t currently expected to bring the House back early from its break, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy.</p> 
<p>Democratic aides, meanwhile, privately acknowledged Saturday that the odds of a shutdown were rising, though some questioned what alternatives are available if Democrats block the pending six-bill package.</p> 
<p>Heading into the weekend, some Democrats acknowledged they were conflicted — including Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151823" data-person-id="151823">Chris Coons</a> (D-Del.), a senior appropriator who has championed Congress’ ability to use the spending bills to reverse many of Trump’s foreign aid cuts.</p> 
<p>“I don't know the details of exactly what the language is in the Homeland Security bills in terms of trying to hold ICE accountable and trying to minimize their misconduct, and I don’t know whether it is worse to have a continuing resolution and how that might be misused,” Coons told reporters Friday.</p> 
<p><i>Adam Wren, Meredith Lee Hill and Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate cancels Monday vote as shutdown deadline looms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/senate-vote-shutdown-snow-00745282</link>
      <description>The Senate will instead hold its first vote of the week on Tuesday as Washington prepares for a weekend snowstorm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ecd0-d9a8-a7bf-eed233ce0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:45:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/3f/03/238e7b8b486fa398bb4c53a73464/u-s-congress-90876.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune speaks with reporters as he walks into his office at the U.S. Capitol on Jan. 12.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/3f/03/238e7b8b486fa398bb4c53a73464/u-s-congress-90876.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate is canceling its scheduled Monday night vote as the District of Columbia braces for a winter storm that will dump snow and ice on a significant swath of the country — with just days left for the chamber to avert a partial government shutdown.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/f340f334-a33f-49d3-a476-6eb321780d94" target="_blank">John Thune</a>’s office announced the scheduling change Friday, following days of private speculation among senators who have already received warnings of travel delays from airlines and wondered how and when they would get back to Washington.</p> 
<p>The Senate had been expected to vote Monday at 5:30 p.m. Instead, that vote is being moved to Tuesday at 5:30 p.m. “due to the impending weather event that is expected to impact a significant portion of the country,” Thune spokesperson Ryan Wrasse <a href="https://x.com/RWrasse/status/2014801309715538174?s=20" target="_blank">announced on X</a>.</p> 
<p>Monday’s vote isn’t related to the looming Jan. 30 government funding cliff, and Wrasse added that “the importance of funding the remaining portions of the government by Friday remains the same.”</p> 
<p>But the scheduling change will give senators a truncated timeline for haggling out a deal in person to avoid a shutdown of multiple federal agencies at the end of next week.</p> 
<p>The Senate is due to take up six funding bills already advanced by the House, which has left town for its previously-scheduled recess. Even though the six bills have been merged into <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">one package</a>, Senate leaders already needed all 100 members to cut a deal to speed up the process for moving the funding bills through the system in order to meet the Jan. 30 deadline.</p> 
<p>If the Senate fails to meet that deadline, a significant portion of the federal government would shutter, including the Pentagon, the Department of Homeland Security and the State Department, among others.</p> 
<p>Republicans and Democrats privately expect the package to pass the Senate in time to avoid a partial shutdown. That will require it to get support from at least eight Democratic votes, and potentially more, in order to clear a 60-vote hurdle to advance the bill. A growing number of Senate Democrats, however, have vowed to oppose the legislation because it includes <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">funding for the Department of Homeland Security</a> amid increasing unease over the administration’s immigration enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>“We are not living in normal times. The President is acting chaotically and unlawfully and we shouldn’t give his deranged decisions the imprimatur of congressional approval by passing this legislation without significant amendment,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" target="_blank" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.), who was one of the eight members of the Democratic caucus who helped end last year’s prolonged shutdown, said in a statement Friday.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151823" target="_blank" data-person-id="151823">Chris Coons</a> (D-Del.), a member of the Appropriations Committee, separately told reporters Friday he was undecided on how he would vote for the six-bill spending package.</p> 
<p>Republicans will also need to reach an agreement with their own members to move forward expeditiously. According to two people granted anonymity to disclose private conversations, a band of conservatives — which includes Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" target="_blank" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.) — is pushing leadership for a vote to remove earmarks from the spending package.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wesley Hunt dodges questions on spotty voting record</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/wesley-hunt-voting-record-00742874</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e7e5-d9a8-a7bf-e7e7dba30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 18:04:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Wesley Hunt refused to answer repeated questions about his spotty voting record Thursday after he appeared in the Capitol for the first time in two weeks.</p> 
<p>The Texas Republican has missed dozens of votes this Congress as he seeks the Senate seat now held by fellow Republican John Cornyn. His last recorded vote before providing the decisive vote Thursday to kill a measure constraining President Donald Trump’s war powers in Venezuela was on Jan. 7.</p> 
<p>“Y’all be safe, y’all be safe — the storm is coming,” he said, referring to the upcoming winter weather, as reporters peppered him with questions about why he has missed so many House votes.</p> 
<p>Earlier in the day a Hunt spokesperson said he was on his way back to Washington at Speaker Mike Johnson’s request after being told by another, unnamed GOP leader “that his presence in D.C. was not needed this week.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-22T17:05:09-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House approves DHS funding, other final spending bills amid ICE uproar</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402</link>
      <description>Only seven Democrats joined most Republicans in approving the Homeland Security bill ahead of a Jan. 30 shutdown deadline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e7a9-dabb-ad9f-ffed43a50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:44:05 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/2e/18/68ae36df4abca42471a34e8eee23/u-s-congress-48773.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Appropriations Committee Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) and Ranking Member Rosa DeLauro (D-Conn.) testify before the House Rules Committee at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 21, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2e/18/68ae36df4abca42471a34e8eee23/u-s-congress-48773.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House passed funding for the Department of Homeland Security Thursday by a narrow margin amid a Democratic uproar over President Donald Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p>The 220-207 vote puts Congress on track to clear the last annual spending bills ahead of the Jan. 30 deadline, avoiding a partial government shutdown. The <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">DHS measure</a> funds the Coast Guard, ICE, CBP, FEMA, TSA and other agencies through the end of the current fiscal year on Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers later voted 341-88 to pass a larger, more bipartisan measure funding the Pentagon and departments of Health and Human Services, Labor, Housing and Urban Development, Transportation, and Education, also through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>It was a victory for House GOP leaders, who overcame attendance issues and concerns about the overall size of the spending package within their ranks. The chamber has now passed all 12 annual appropriations bills.</p> 
<p>Democrats demanded a standalone vote on the DHS funding bill so that their caucus could voice their objection to the Trump administration’s harsh enforcement tactics — a concern that has been amplified by recent ICE and CBP operations in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>The bills passed Thursday rejected many of the steep funding cuts to major domestic agencies that the Trump administration sought in the White House budget request earlier this year, but neither do they offer significant funding boosts. The Department of Housing and Urban Development would see a 9 percent boost over current funding levels, totaling $84.3 billion for HUD. </p> 
<p>The Education Department would receive $79 billion, a slight increase of $217 million above current funding. The Department of Health and Human Services would be funded at nearly $117 billion, a $210 million increase, while the Department of Labor would get $13.7 billion, a $65 million hike.</p> 
<p>As recently as Tuesday morning, it was not clear that the two parties would be able to strike a compromise on funding DHS.</p> 
<p>“That was really negotiated right to the end,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a> of Connecticut, the top Democratic appropriator in the House, told reporters. “And I believe that portion of the negotiation had to go to the White House, where you had Stephen Miller and somebody who was really making a determination on it.”</p> 
<p>DeLauro was among the Democrats who voted against the bill, announcing on the floor that she had too many misgivings about the Trump administration’s immigration agenda. Only seven Democrats ended up voting for the bill; some argued that the negotiated bill was preferable to the alternatives — a stopgap measure that would give Trump a freer hand to run the department, or a shutdown that would affect key nonimmigration agencies such as TSA. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> of Kentucky was the only Republican opposed.</p> 
<p>Divisions over DHS funding have only deepened as the Trump administration has ramped up immigration enforcement, even far from the border. Coming to an agreement only got harder as Democrats stepped up their criticism after two incidents in Minnesota: one where an ICE agent shot and killed U.S. citizen Renée Good and another when an ICE officer shot an undocumented man during an arrest.</p> 
<p>Democrats were hoping to put significant guardrails on the conduct of ICE and CBP officers in the spending bill. The compromise bill that includes funding for body cameras and additional training did not satisfy most on the Democratic side.</p> 
<p>House Democratic leaders, including Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/house-democrats-dhs-funding-00738894" target="_blank"><u>spoke out against the bil</u></a>l during a closed-door caucus meeting Wednesday. Leadership heard “overwhelmingly” from their caucus members ahead of the vote that this bill did not do enough to rein in ICE following recent clashes in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats wanted more than guardrails, calling instead for defunding and dismantling ICE altogether.</p> 
<p>“It has some additional provisions for body cameras, for extra training, things like that, that we think will increase the professionalism, but it's a good, solid bill,” House Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51327" data-person-id="51327">Tom Cole</a> (R-Okla.) said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The final compromise would keep ICE funded at $10 billion for the fiscal year and would reduce the agency's budget for enforcement and removal efforts. It would require DHS to use $20 million to outfit immigration enforcement agents with body cameras, direct the department to give officers more training on defusing conflict while interacting with the public and provide a separate $20 million for independent oversight of DHS detention facilities.</p> 
<p>The House voted separately on the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">three-bill measure</a> to fund the Pentagon and other departments through the end of September. Under a procedural measure approved earlier Thursday, those bills will be bundled together with the DHS measure and a previously approved two-bill package before being sent to the Senate.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers voted down two amendments from conservatives before final passage. The chamber voted 291-136 to reject a proposal from Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/195970" data-person-id="195970">Ralph Norman</a> (R-S.C.) to eliminate all earmarks in the Labor-HHS-Education portion of the bill. </p> 
<p>It also rejected, in a 268-164 vote, a proposal to overturn a mandate that automakers equip new vehicles with technology that prevents drunk driving. The amendment from Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/194221" data-person-id="194221">Scott Perry</a> (R-Pa.) would scrap the mandate Congress enacted in 2021 for the Department of Transportation to create those regulations.</p> 
<p>The package also includes a scaled back attempt at reining in drug middlemen known as pharmacy benefit managers and renewals for several major public health programs, along with $4.6 billion in funding for community health centers pushed for by Democrats. </p> 
<p>The measure also includes the customary payment to the widows or heirs of lawmakers who have died in office, this time to Jill LaMalfa, widow of Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.), who died earlier this month.</p> 
<p>The Senate is expected to consider that six-bill package when the chamber returns from recess next week. While many Democratic senators are already announcing their opposition based on the ICE funding, others will be hard-pressed to reject spending on the Pentagon and key domestic agencies — many of which are being funded at levels well beyond what the Trump administration proposed.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story attributed the wrong state affiliation to Rep. Ralph Norman (R-S.C.).]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans tried to snag Jack Smith on technicalities. But they didn’t engage with the facts.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/jack-smith-testimony-trump-00742457</link>
      <description>Instead of focusing on the crux of the former special counsel’s Trump cases, GOP House members questioned him on process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e794-d9a8-a7bf-e796c3760000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:37:44 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/6f/6e/09d3b9814ebfa31f63990cd18a5f/congress-jack-smith-44925.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Justice Department special counsel Jack Smith, second from right, arrives before a hearing of the House Judiciary Committee at the Capitol in Washington, Thursday, Jan. 22, 2026. (AP Photo/Mark Schiefelbein)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/6f/6e/09d3b9814ebfa31f63990cd18a5f/congress-jack-smith-44925.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Kyle Cheney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Kyle Cheney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republicans finally had their moment to take on the man who tried to put President Donald Trump in jail. But they didn’t land any significant blows.</p> 
<p>During Thursday’s House Judiciary Committee hearing with Jack Smith, GOP members spent almost no time challenging the facts of the criminal case that the former special counsel brought against Trump: that he conspired to corrupt the results of the 2020 election and seize a second term he didn’t win.</p> 
<p>Instead, Republican committee members spent much of the hearing challenging the technical aspects of Smith’s probe into Trump’s election interference, including whether the veteran federal prosecutor properly signed his oath of office as special counsel and if he was sufficiently cognizant of the Constitution’s “speech or debate” clause that protects Congress from executive branch overreach.</p> 
<p>They questioned whether Smith was too friendly with a Justice Department official who recommended him for the special counsel position and challenged his approval of a $20,000 payment to a confidential human source for the FBI who was reviewing video and photos for the bureau.</p> 
<p>House Judiciary Committee chair Jim Jordan pressed Smith on his view of the House’s now-defunct select committee to investigate the events of Jan. 6, 2021, which also probed Trump’s 2020 election gambit. He also questioned that panel’s reliance on former Trump White House aide Cassidy Hutchinson to implicate Trump in plans to overturn the results favoring Joe Biden.</p> 
<p>“Democrats have been going after President Trump for 10 years. For a decade. And the country should never, ever forget what they did,” Jordan said.</p> 
<p>This nibbling around the edges by Republicans underscores the GOP’s lingering discomfort with Trump’s bid to subvert the election — an effort that preceded a violent attack on the Capitol by a mob of the president’s supporters. Several Republicans on the Judiciary Committee were among those who fled the rioters that day and condemned the violence at the time, and none at the hearing suggested Trump actually prevailed against Biden.</p> 
<p>The posture of committee Republicans Thursday also gave Democrats ammunition to claim that Republicans had no legitimate argument with the substance of Smith’s findings — both in the election interference case and in the case alleging mishandling of classified documents at Mar-a-Lago.</p> 
<p>“Our Republican colleagues want to try to dirty up his investigation, but they want to try to avoid as much as possible the underlying facts, because it's all about what is incontrovertibly true: Donald Trump's determined plan to overthrow the 2020 presidential election,” said Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the Judiciary Committee, in an interview during a break in the hours-long hearing convened to receive Smith’s first-ever public testimony.</p> 
<p>Raskin and other Democrats feel so emboldened by Smith's testimony Thursday that they are now asking Jordan to hold a continuation of the hearing as soon as a report is unsealed that would allow Smith to go into more detail about the classified documents charges he sought to bring up against Trump.</p> 
<p>The most forceful attack on Smith came from <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/trumps-tuning-in-to-smiths-testimony-00741228" target="_blank"><u>Trump himself</u></a> who appeared to have watched or been briefed on aspects of the hearing during his trip to Europe.</p> 
<p>“Jack Smith is a deranged animal, who shouldn’t be allowed to practice Law,” Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115939889414201547" target="_blank"><u>said on Truth Social</u></a>. “Hopefully the Attorney General is looking at what he’s done, including some of the crooked and corrupt witnesses that he was attempting to use in his case against me.”</p> 
<p>Smith, who later said he expected the Trump administration would pursue federal criminal charges against him “because they have been ordered to by the president,” forcefully defended his office’s work throughout the hearing Thursday. He denied that politics played any role in his team’s findings and calmly parried the attacks Republicans lobbed at him over his investigative tactics and decision to bring charges at all. </p> 
<p>And he repeatedly suggested the failure to hold Trump accountable for his 2020 election maneuvering could invite future attacks.</p> 
<p>“I have seen how the rule of law can erode. My feeling is that we have seen the rule of law function in our country so long that many of us have come to take it for granted,” Smith said. “The rule of law is not self-executing.”</p> 
<p>Smith’s hearing, which came weeks after the public release of his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-deposition-congress-00694730" target="_blank"><u>closed-door deposition testimony</u></a> to the panel late last year, also provided a venue for relitigating the events of Jan. 6 — specifically who was responsible for the violent event. Rep. Joe Neguse (D-Colo.) called the hearing “theater” for Republican lawmakers seeking to rewrite the history of the attack, noting the presence in the audience of police officers who defended the Capitol that day.</p> 
<p>Also in attendance at the hearing was Stewart Rhodes, the founder of the Oath Keepers, who was convicted of seditious conspiracy for his role in the Jan. 6 riot and sentenced to 18 years in prison before <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/27/ed-martin-stewart-rhodes-jan-6-pardon-00371222" target="_blank"><u>Trump commuted his sentence</u></a> last year.</p> 
<p>“I want to see true transparency in our government,” Rhodes said in an interview, adding that it was “really kind of surreal” to be back in the Capitol complex after being banned prior to his commutation.</p> 
<p>At some points emotions ran high, such as when former Metropolitan Police Force officer Michael Fanone coughed “<a href="https://x.com/Acyn/status/2014416164630434239" target="_blank"><u>Fuck yourself</u></a>” when Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Texas) opined that police bore responsibility for the Jan 6. security breach at the Capitol. There was also <a href="https://x.com/cspan/status/2014406968413196550" target="_blank"><u>a tense confrontation</u></a> between Fanone and Ivan Raiklin, an activist and advocate for Jan. 6 defendants, that almost culminated in a physical altercation.</p> 
<p>Throughout the day Smith remained straight-faced and measured, offering little visible reaction as the occasionally irate Republicans repeatedly condemned his work and attacked his character in deeply personal terms.</p> 
<p>He also appeared unmoved amid the effusive praise from Democrats, who repeatedly thanked him for his service to the country and urged him not to bow to intimidation from Trump and his allies.</p> 
<p>Democrats eagerly teed up the evidence Smith amassed in his Trump investigations that underscored their view that Trump knew he lost the election but attempted to stay in power anyway.</p> 
<p>Smith has said Trump’s campaign of lies about election fraud fueled the Jan. 6 attack on the Capitol that resulted in hundreds of assaults on law enforcement officers. He has also said Trump exploited the violence to try and pressure Congress to block Joe Biden’s victory.</p> 
<p>“I’m so pleased you’re here on national TV telling the American people that Trump was indicted, he was indicted lawfully and multiple grand juries secured those indictments,” said Rep. Ted Lieu (D-Calif.) said during the hearing.</p> 
<p>But Republicans spent little time questioning that narrative: Rep. Brandon Gill (R-Texas) asked whether Smith’s subpoenas for GOP lawmakers’ phone data — revelations that reignited the party’s determination to compel Smith’s Capitol Hill testimony — violated the Constitutional speech and debate clause that protects correspondence about the legislative process.</p> 
<p>Rep. Scott Fitzgerald (R-Wis.) suggested that Smith was appointed special counsel because of a friendship with another Justice Department staffer in the Biden administration.</p> 
<p>Even when a handful of Republicans did question Smith’s case against Trump, they focused largely on whether Trump could be excused for his conduct if he genuinely believed he won the election — even though he was defeated and the results were certified in Biden’s favor.</p> 
<p>“I’ve talked to Donald Trump over a period of time. Donald Trump is 100 percent certain he won that election,” said Rep. Glenn Grothman (R-Wis.). “There is zero percent chance that he believes he lost.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Laurel Lee (R-Fla.) noted that Trump relied heavily on a team of legal advisers as he worked to reverse the election results and said Smith needed to prove Trump “knowingly” sought to subvert the outcome.</p> 
<p>Smith, both in the indictment against Trump and his testimony Thursday, repeatedly argued that Trump knew he lost.</p> 
<p>“He was looking for ways to stay in power,” Smith said. ”When people told him things that conflicted with staying in power, he rejected them.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clintons are ‘working in good faith’ toward Epstein testimony, Jeffries says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/clintons-good-faith-epstein-talks-00741615</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e725-d1ea-a5df-f7a5531b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 14:21:41 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries said Bill and Hillary Clinton are “working in good faith” to comply with Oversight Committee subpoenas related to Jeffrey Epstein, a day after the panel voted to recommend holding them in contempt over their refusal to appear for testimony.</p> 
<p>The top Democratic leader said the former president and the former secretary of State “are working in good faith to try to reach an accommodation with the Oversight Committee in order to sit down and offer their testimony.”</p> 
<p>He said the contempt effort led by Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) “lacks any credibility” in part because “it has always been congressional practice that if someone is under a subpoena, you work to find reasonable accommodation in order to receive their testimony.”</p> 
<p>Nine Oversight Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/9-democrats-vote-to-hold-bill-clinton-in-contempt-of-congress-for-evading-epstein-testimony-00739940" target="_blank">voted with Republicans</a> Wednesday to recommend holding Bill Clinton in contempt, while three Democrats voted to recommend holding Hillary Clinton in contempt, both as part of the panel’s investigation into the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the House Oversight Committee said the Clintons’ attorneys had not been in touch since the contempt vote.</p> 
<p>Prior to Wednesday’s vote, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/jeffries-urged-opposition-to-clintons-contempt-resolution-00740222" target="_blank">Jeffries urged opposition</a> to a contempt recommendation.</p> 
<p>Asked if he was advising members not to support the contempt measure on the floor, Jeffries cited the opposition of Reps. Robert Garcia of California and Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrats respectively on the Oversight and Judiciary committees. He said his own position “remains unchanged.”</p> 
<p>“When it gets to the floor, if we need to have a broader caucus, wide conversation about it, we will,” he added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-22T16:46:04-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump is watching Jack Smith’s testimony — and has thoughts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/trumps-tuning-in-to-smiths-testimony-00741228</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e6cb-d9a8-a7bf-e6cb98af0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:51:16 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As former special counsel Jack Smith testifies publicly before Congress for the first time, President Donald Trump is watching.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115939889414201547" target="_blank">Truth Social post</a> Thursday afternoon, Trump wrote that Smith was being “DECIMATED” by members of the House Judiciary Committee — even as panel Republicans have yet to formally rebut the findings of Smith’s investigation into Trump’s retention of classified documents and attempts to subvert the results of the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>The president also suggested he hoped Attorney General Pam Bondi was looking into Smith's conduct.</p> 
<p>“If he were a Republican, his license would be taken away from him, and far worse!” Trump wrote of Smith. “Hopefully the Attorney General is looking at what he’s done, including some of the crooked and corrupt witnesses that he was attempting to use in his case against me.”</p> 
<p>Smith's cases were widely seen as the strongest vehicles for putting Trump behind bars. Both matters were ultimately dropped by the Justice Department before Trump took office for the second time in 2025.</p> 
<p>The Trump Justice Department has sought to bring criminal charges against several of the president's political adversaries, including New York Attorney General Letitia James and former FBI Director James Comey. Trump has also long argued for Smith's prosecution, too.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Smith declined to comment on Trump's post beyond Smith's remarks during the hearing. Rep. Joe Neguse (D-Colo.) asked Smith if he was aware of the president's social media message and if he had a response; Smith said he did not know about it and did not have anything to add.</p> 
<p>House Republicans have been antagonistic of Smith during the hearing so far but have focused their questioning heavily on Smith's procedure in pursuing his cases against the president — most notably the subpoenas he obtained for the phone data of several sitting Republican lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Asked about Trump’s post, House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) told reporters it was ultimately up to the Justice Department whether to look into Smith.</p> 
<p>“Our job is to do oversight,” Jordan said. “We'll leave it up to the Justice Department on whether they prosecute and who they may prosecute.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump: There is ‘probably’ going to be another government shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/donald-trump-government-shutdown-00741021</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e6ab-dabb-ad9f-ffef1f040000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:17:50 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump said Thursday that another government shutdown is likely as Congress approaches its Jan. 30 funding deadline, even as members work to hammer out funding agreements.</p> 
<p>“I think we have a problem, because I think we’re going to probably end up in another Democrat shutdown,” Trump said in <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/video/6388087049112?playlist_id=3166411554001" target="_blank">an interview with Fox Business</a> on the sidelines of Davos. Referring to the most recent shutdown that began last October, he added: “The shutdown cost us a lot, and I think they’ll probably do it again, that’s my feeling. We’ll see what happens.”</p> 
<p>Lawmakers have until Jan. 30 to pass the 12 annual appropriations bills needed to fund the government and avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p>House leaders are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/congress-clinches-funding-deal-for-dhs-pentagon-domestic-agencies-00735698?utm_campaign=dfn-ebb&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=sailthru" target="_blank">planning a vote on a bipartisan compromise</a> released Tuesday, providing $1.2 trillion in funding for several agencies including the Homeland Security and Defense departments. The legislation would also secure $10 billion in funding for Immigration and Customs Enforcement through the end of the fiscal year in September.</p> 
<p>Many Democrats are objecting to the negotiated bill that would fund ICE, albeit with some new restrictions. Still, there is no current expectation from many on the Hill that the opposition would prevent passage of the remaining funding bills ahead of the deadline.</p> 
<p>Congress has already passed six of the 12 annual funding bills, meaning only a subset of federal agencies would shut down if it fails to act.</p> 
<p>The most recent shutdown began Oct. 1, 2025, and lasted 43 days. It was the longest government shutdown in U.S. history.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Final spending bills move closer to House passage</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/house-rule-spending-bills-00741019</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e6a4-d452-a99b-effedb2c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:01:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans sent the last four fiscal 2026 spending bills over a key procedural hurdle Thursday, setting up two votes later in the day to send them together to the Senate.</p> 
<p>Republicans stayed mostly united on the 214-213 test vote to advance the package that would fund the Pentagon and departments of Health and Human Services, Labor, Housing and Urban Development, Transportation, and Education, as well as a separate measure to fund the Homeland Security Department through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>The vote was held open for nearly an hour as Speaker Mike Johnson first negotiated with Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/356900" data-person-id="356900">Lauren Boebert</a> (R-Colo.) to flip her vote, and then undertook a lengthy negotiation with Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/435358" data-person-id="435358">Andy Ogles</a> (R-Tenn.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/52758" data-person-id="52758">Zach Nunn</a> (R-Iowa). Boebert and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/276525" data-person-id="276525">Victoria Spartz</a> (R-Ind.) both flipped their votes to yes, and Nunn and Ogles voted in favor.</p> 
<p>The Homeland Security piece is politically fraught, with Democrats angry about immigration enforcement tactics under President Donald Trump requesting a separate vote on the measure. While bipartisan negotiators included some new fetters on ICE, some Democrats are calling to defund the agency entirely.</p> 
<p>Before the rule was adopted, the House <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/house-votes-to-kill-senate-data-seizure-payouts-00740925" target="_blank">voted 427-0 to include language</a> in the DHS bill to block payments to senators whose phone data was collected during probes under the Biden administration into Trump’s attempts to overturn the 2020 election. The proposal would block the payments that were codified in a stopgap spending bill signed into law last year, unbeknownst to many lawmakers.</p> 
<p>The payments are broadly unpopular among House members, and leadership is hoping the repeal could be a sweetener for the DHS bill, which has an uphill battle to passage.</p> 
<p>The other three bills — Defense, Labor-HHS-Education and Transportation-HUD — will be voted on together as a package.</p> 
<p>The vote Thursday to move forward with consideration of the funding measures will also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/house-minibus-amendments-ethanol-00739983" target="_blank">allow floor votes on amendments</a> sought by conservatives, including proposals to kill some earmarks and block enforcement of vehicle “kill switch” technology.</p> 
<p>Conservative hard-liners were pleased to have more input and opportunity for amendments on these bills after they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-earmark-angst-rears-ahead-of-spending-package-votes-00714135" target="_blank">threatened to block</a> an earlier spending package.</p> 
<p>Another group the leaders had to appease were farm-state Republicans upset that a provision allowing year-round sales of E15 fuel was not included in the spending package. To placate them, leadership agreed to set up a congressional working group focused on ethanol policy.</p> 
<p>These are the final four fiscal 2026 spending bills and if the House passes them, the Senate will be trying to clear them ahead of the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid another government shutdown.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House votes to kill Senate data-seizure payouts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/house-votes-to-kill-senate-data-seizure-payouts-00740925</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e688-d1ea-a5df-f68c2fbf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 11:29:16 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House lawmakers voted unanimously Thursday morning to overturn a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_5371" target="_blank">policy Senate Republicans got enacted last year</a> allowing senators to collect hundreds of thousands of dollars in legal payouts if their electric records were unknowingly collected — a measure aimed at benefiting lawmakers who saw their data seized as part of a Joe Biden-era investigation of President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>In an effort to force the Senate into accepting the provision, the House is including the language in the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">Homeland Security funding bill</a> the chamber plans to vote on later Thursday.</p> 
<p>The House already <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-votes-to-overturn-thunes-controversial-subpoena-measure-00661169" target="_blank">voted in November</a> to scrap the policy, but Senate Majority Leader John Thune has been steadfast against overturning it.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jim Jordan launches his attacks on Jack Smith</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/jordan-begins-jack-smith-grilling-00740848</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e64e-d452-a99b-effee0f80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 10:34:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan is looking to paint former special counsel Jack Smith as the culmination of a yearslong campaign by Democrats to leverage law enforcement activities against President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>In his opening remarks Thursday morning, the Ohio Republican reiterated complaints against a laundry list of government officials involved with investigations or criminal cases against Trump — among them Fulton County District Attorney Fani Willis, former FBI Director James Comey and a former deputy to Smith, Thomas Windom. </p> 
<p>Jordan has already referred Windom to the Justice Department for criminal prosecution over his refusal to cooperate with his panel’s investigative work.</p> 
<p>“We should never forget what took place, what they did to the guy ‘We the People’ elected president twice,” Jordan said, referring to Trump. “The good news is, the American people saw through it.”</p> 
<p>Jordan, a notable political showman and steadfast Trump ally, is seeking to portray Smith as hellbent on thwarting Trump’s electoral victory in 2024. Smith has said that politics played no part in his work investigating Trump's efforts to overturn the results of the 2020 election and Trump's handling of classified documents as part of the Biden Justice Department and insisted that he would have pursued the same case under the same conditions with a Democratic or Republican former president. </p> 
<p>Smith has served in administrations under both parties.</p> 
<p>During Jordan's remarks, Smith coolly sipped from his water bottle and remained stoic.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin (D-Md.) countered Jordan’s account of Smith’s work, noting that Trump has called for the imprisonment of the man who pursued criminal charges against him.</p> 
<p>“Not because you did anything wrong, mind you, but because you did everything right,” Raskin added. “You had the audacity to do your job.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Officers who defended the Capitol on Jan. 6 attend Jack Smith hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/jan-6-officers-watch-smith-testimony-00740837</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e639-d452-a99b-efff94250000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 10:13:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Several police officers who responded to the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the Capitol are in the hearing room to watch former special counsel Jack Smith testify in public for the first time before the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>They include Michael Fanone, Daniel Hodges, Aquilino Gonell and Harry Dunn. In an interview, Fanone — who was seated in the front row — said he was present to support Smith and hoped the former prosecutor would simply share the truth with the American public. </p> 
<p>Smith led the criminal case around allegations that President Donald Trump sought to overturn the results of the 2020 election, culminating in a violent riot of his supporters at the Capitol the day lawmakers were gathered to certify the results for Joe Biden.</p> 
<p>Gonell, asked whether he was concerned Republicans may try to incriminate Smith, said the GOP response was uncontrollable, but it was nevertheless important for the public to hear the case against Trump that Smith never got to make.</p> 
<p>“Whatever they want to do, it’s not going to wash away what was done to us and to the Capitol,” Gonell said of Republicans. “It’s about accountability and what was the betrayal [that] was done to not only us, but to the American people.”</p> 
<p>House Judiciary ranking member Jamie Raskin (D-Md.) welcomed them to the hearing room as the proceedings kicked off.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House to vote on 2 amendments to $1.2T funding package</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/house-minibus-amendments-ethanol-00739983</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e61e-d9a8-a7bf-e69ed17a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 09:33:38 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders will allow floor votes on two amendments to the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">$1.2 trillion funding package</a> they are trying to pass Thursday, including proposals to nix some earmarks and block enforcement of vehicle “kill switch” technology.</p> 
<p>The House Rules Committee voted Thursday morning to set up floor action on the four bills top appropriators released this week following a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/congress-clinches-funding-deal-for-dhs-pentagon-domestic-agencies-00735698" target="_blank">bipartisan, bicameral breakthrough</a> on funding for the vast majority of the federal government, including the Pentagon and the largest domestic agencies.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/52758" data-person-id="52758">Zach Nunn</a> (R-Iowa) and other Midwestern lawmakers had threatened to block movement of the funding package without an agreement to approve year-round sale of E15, an ethanol-laden gasoline blend.</p> 
<p>After late-night negotiations, GOP leaders agreed to set up a congressional working group focused on ethanol policy. The group would be created as part of the procedural measure the House will vote on to tee up debate on the spending bills.</p> 
<p>According to four people privy to the agreement granted anonymity to discuss it, the holdouts also believe they will get a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/ethanol-deal-funding-bill-00740048" target="_blank">vote on ethanol policy</a> by late February, as POLITICO previously reported.</p> 
<p>The House will not vote on amendments to the DHS funding bill, which will get a stand-alone vote under the GOP plan. Republican leaders could struggle to pass that legislation since nearly all House Democrats are <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/house-democrats-dhs-funding-00738894" target="_blank">expected to vote no</a>. To create pressure on lawmakers to pass all four bills, the three measures funding other federal agencies will not be sent to the Senate until the House passes the DHS measure. </p> 
<p>The two amendment votes will be allowed on the three-bill package that funds the departments of Defense, Housing and Urban Development, Labor, Health and Human Services, Education, and Transportation.</p> 
<p>The Rules Committee also approved language that will, upon passage, combine the four bills with another two-bill funding package <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/house-passes-two-more-funding-bills-with-four-more-to-go-00730088" target="_blank">the House passed last week</a>. House leaders hope that will make it easier for the Senate to swiftly clear the funding for President Donald Trump’s signature next week ahead of the Jan. 30 government shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders chose not to use the procedural vote on the funding bills to extend a self-imposed ban on votes challenging Trump’s tariffs before it expires at month's end. A band of rank-and-file Republicans warned leadership they would vote against any such effort. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Jack Smith speaks</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/jack-smith-testifies-congress-house-judiciary-trump-00740622</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e3df-dabb-ad9f-ffff7f2c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s the televised showdown both Republicans and Democrats have long wanted: Former DOJ special counsel Jack Smith <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/jack-smith-trump-charges-testimony-00740551" target="_blank">takes the hot seat</a> in front of the House Judiciary Committee Thursday morning. </p> 
<p>It’s likely to be a long and lively examination of his aborted effort to convict President Donald Trump for trying to overturn the 2020 election.</p> 
<p><b>— What Smith will say:&nbsp;</b>Smith plans to stand by his decision to prosecute Trump — and say that doing otherwise would have been “shirk[ing] my duties as a prosecutor and a public servant,” according to prepared remarks obtained by POLITICO. It’s similar to what he already <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/takeaways-jack-smith-congressional-testimony-00708747" target="_blank">told lawmakers behind closed doors</a>: that a jury would have found the president guilty of a criminal scheme had Smith been allowed to move forward with his evidence.</p> 
<p>“I made my decisions without regard to President Trump’s political association, activities, beliefs or candidacy in the 2024 presidential election,” Smith plans to say, adding that the evidence his team gathered “established that he willfully broke the very laws that he took an oath to uphold.”</p> 
<p>Smith ultimately dropped the charges he brought in the election subversion case after Trump won reelection in 2024, since the Justice Department is prohibited from charging or trying a current president.</p> 
<p>Not every question might get a satisfactory answer: A court order sealed the second volume of his report around the classified documents case, and Trump on Wednesday night urged a judge to make that order permanent.</p> 
<p><b>— What the GOP is looking for:&nbsp;</b>Republicans will likely hammer Smith on what they see as a political campaign against the GOP and Trump.</p> 
<p>Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) said Smith represents “a continuation of this weaponization of government against the president.”</p> 
<p>Jordan’s decision to allow Smith to testify publicly after initially only allowing a closed-door session will let Republicans tee off as the public, and likely Trump, are watching. Expect to hear plenty about how Smith secretly obtained phone records for several current GOP senators during his investigation.</p> 
<p><b>— What Dems are hoping for:&nbsp;</b>Democrats will take the opportunity to have Smith describe Trump’s alleged criminal behavior in painstaking detail — including the president’s attempt to stop Joe Biden from taking office.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ted Lieu (D-Calif.) said Wednesday he was “thrilled” that Smith would be testifying publicly so that he can tell the American people “all the evidence that he has collected” against Trump and why he was “lawfully indicted.”</p> 
<p>“American people are going to hear that,” Lieu said. “And I encourage everyone to watch.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House funding action: </b>Buckle up for a long, wild day as House GOP leaders try to muscle through the last four fiscal 2026 spending bills. The Rules Committee reconvened Thursday morning after Speaker Mike Johnson struggled late Wednesday to strike an amendment deal with hard-liners that would allow the panel to move forward on the package.</p> 
<p><b>— War powers vote: </b>House lawmakers will vote Thursday on a measure to rein in Trump’s military intervention in Venezuela. The margin is so thin that the vote could come down to attendance. GOP Reps. Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Don Bacon of Nebraska intend to support the Democrat-led resolution, and a few other Republicans are mulling voting “yes.”</p> 
<p><i>Hailey Fuchs, Kyle Cheney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers reached a surprise bipartisan health deal. Now they have to keep it.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/congress-health-deal-still-has-hurdles-00740600</link>
      <description>The package, which would reform the way the intermediaries between drugmakers and insurers and employers operate, faces a tough test this week.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e396-dabb-ad9f-ffff64fe0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/97/2c/acf611d84a85b21938197d706eef/u-s-congress-48049.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>It remains unclear whether Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and other fiscal hawks will balk at a new health package with reforms to PBMs and additional community health center funding.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/97/2c/acf611d84a85b21938197d706eef/u-s-congress-48049.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Robert King, Amanda Chu and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Robert King, Amanda Chu and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After months of fruitless negotiations to extend Affordable Care Act subsidies that have since expired, congressional leaders announced Tuesday they’d notched a rare bipartisan win to overhaul other parts of the health care system.</p> 
<p>Now they just have to hold onto it.</p> 
<p>The agreement, attached to a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">government spending bill</a>, would implement long-sought changes to the way pharmacy benefit managers operate, as well as extensions of public health programs and increased funding for community health centers. But even with strong support in both chambers, the bill faces significant hurdles.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers must navigate around the powerful lobbyists for pharmacy benefit managers, or PBMs — the intermediaries who negotiate drug prices on the behalf of employers and insurers — who have handily defeated similar proposals in the past.</p> 
<p>They also must reckon with conservative hard-liners who don’t like some of the provisions and could be prepared to weaponize the House GOP’s perilously slim margins to tank the effort by opposing a party-line procedural rule that would bring the funding measure to the floor.</p> 
<p>One such provision in the health care package, championed by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> (R-La) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51605" data-person-id="51605">Bernie Sanders</a> (I-Vt.) — the chair and ranking member of the Senate HELP Committee, respectively — would prevent PBMs from getting revenue from drug rebates. This proposal, which has buy-in from Senate and House GOP leadership, has infuriated the industry and its allies.</p> 
<p>“Especially in the time in which we’re seeing health insurance premiums go up, this is just going to make it worse,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192565" data-person-id="192565">Eric Burlison</a> (R-Mo.) in an interview Wednesday. “What Senator Cassidy has done has gone, I think, way too far over the line.”</p> 
<p>PBMs negotiate rebates, or discounts, with drugmakers for employer health plans and other payers in an opaque process that has drawn scrutiny over whether discounts are passed on to consumers or retained to boost profits. Drugmakers, under pressure to reduce high prescription drug prices, have been pointing the finger at PBMs as the culprit.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Cassidy declined to comment.</p> 
<p>If the health care package passes as part of the government funding measure, Democrats will have helped Republicans with a major health victory at a time when the GOP is particularly vulnerable on the issue.</p> 
<p>Democrats have been hammering Republicans for months over their inaction on extending the enhanced Obamacare subsidies that lapsed at the end of last year. They have made the premiums that have skyrocketed as a result the centerpiece of a nascent midterm campaign assailing Republicans on “affordability.”</p> 
<p>Talks for a subsidy extension remain ongoing in the Senate, but lawmakers left last week for a 10-day recess without reaching a deal. Abortion restrictions and minimum premium payments are the biggest impediments to landing a compromise.</p> 
<p>For many Republicans, the health care bill they want to pass now as part of legislation to fund several government agencies —including Health and Human Services — also answers President Donald Trump’s demands that Congress end kickbacks to PBMs and require more transparency from insurers. Those elements were included in the president’s health care proposal released last week.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats said the policy goal was too important to pass up, even though the deal did not include an extension of the ACA subsidies. A similar effort at the end of 2024 was torpedoed when billionaire Elon Musk blasted government funding legislation that contained the PBM measures, and there’s a desire not to squander the same opportunity this time around.</p> 
<p>“We’ve wanted to clean up PBMs. We have to believe that not everything they do is wrong,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227421" data-person-id="227421">Don Beyer</a> (D-Va.) Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Rep. Kathy Castor (D-Fla.), meanwhile, warned that while Republicans did the right thing on PBMs, it doesn’t mean healthcare will not be a major issue in the midterms.</p> 
<p>“Do they get credit for doing the right thing [that] they should have been doing all year long? Okay,” she said.</p> 
<h2>The GOP and free-market healthcare&nbsp;</h2> 
<p><br>Cassidy, in a statement, said the health package delivers “real, conservative reforms that rein in healthcare middlemen, make prescription drugs more affordable and increase access to lifesaving treatments for children.”</p> 
<p>The rebate provision in the bill he authored with Sanders does have support from traditional GOP allies in the business sector. The ERISA Industry Committee, which represents self-funded large employer health plans, has repeatedly pushed for targeting PBM rebates among other reforms.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a> (R-Texas) said earlier this week he is still reviewing the package, but mainly wanted more transformational overhauls as insurers who own PBMs could potentially negate any changes.</p> 
<p>“I am for the reforms, but at the end of the day insurers own the PBMs and they are just going to shuffle the deck chairs around and keep doing what they want to do,” he said.</p> 
<p>For Washington’s influence sector, Republican support for the PBM changes mark a shift within the party away from its free market orthodoxy.</p> 
<p>“It’s really like Congress dictating how two private companies can contract … From a historical context, Republicans are not big on interfering with the present marketplace,” said one insurance lobbyist granted anonymity to speak candidly.</p> 
<h2><b>Making a deal&nbsp;</b></h2> 
<p><br>Lawmakers have pushed to return to PBM overhaul legislation since the Dec. 2024 package’s collapse.</p> 
<p>“These should have been passed, a lot of them, last year,” said Castor. “They were poised to pass until Elon Musk got involved.”</p> 
<p>House Republicans have also been eager to make up for failed attempts to include several health care provisions in their sweeping tax and spending megabill last summer, but they were stripped out in the Senate for not complying with the rules governing the budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>January offered an enticing opportunity for lawmakers to try again as efforts to craft full-year appropriations bills picked up steam. Normally a health package runs as part of a larger, must-pass government funding measure to help ensure its success.</p> 
<p>But the government has been running on stopgap spending bills since March 2024. House Republican leadership has been reluctant to add policy riders to such bills to ensure enough support from fiscal hawks.</p> 
<p>This health care package came together relatively quickly this month as most of the items had already been considered – and vetted – previously, chiefly in the scrapped Dec. 2024 government funding legislation. There also were markups and committee hearings on the package’s contents, including regarding PBMs, throughout 2025, giving lawmakers a chance to become familiar with the policies. including on PBM reform, according to a Senate aide familiar with the negotiations.</p> 
<p>Pharmacy benefit managers “hate” the reforms “but they … should not be surprised, because it's been baked,” said another Senate GOP aide familiar with the health care package, granted anonymity to speak candidly of the PBM provisions. “And the cake has been sitting on a shelf in a deep freezer, perfectly maintained for like three years.”</p> 
<h2><b>Industry evasion&nbsp;</b></h2> 
<p><br>Even with the latest proposed changes designed to bring accountability to PBMs and how they operate, lobbyists representing insurers, pharmaceutical companies and pharmacies say that PBMs have still largely outmaneuvered Congress.</p> 
<p>The industry has spent years evading bipartisan congressional scrutiny, even as state legislatures moved in to reign in the sector. Since calls for reform took off in 2023, the Pharmaceutical Care Management Association, a major trade group, spent $47 million lobbying elected officials against placing guardrails on PBMs — about twice its spending from the prior three-year period.</p> 
<p>“The market has outpaced Congress on this by a pretty wide margin,” said Adam Colborn, associate vice president at the Academy of Managed Care Pharmacy, which counts UnitedHealth, CVS Health, and Express Scripts as members. “There’s been a lot of emotion on both sides of the debate, but getting down to the nuts and bolts, there’s a relatively low ceiling for change.”</p> 
<p>In October, Cigna announced that it would overhaul its pricing model and remove its system based on rebates, following a commitment from UnitedHealth to pass through 100 percent of rebates in January and a decision from CVS to do so in 2019 — a move analysts view as an effort by industry to get ahead of reform efforts on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>“I don't think anybody's gonna be shooting off fireworks here … It’s not going to be a game changer,” said one pharmaceutical lobbyist, granted anonymity to share internal discussions of the health care deal currently pending before lawmakers.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, PCMA slammed the Cassidy-Sanders PBM provision, warning that such a proposal would limit companies’ ability to use alternative payment models and raise prices and urging Congress to shift its scrutiny on the pharmaceutical industry instead.</p> 
<p>“PBMs are innovating business models to lower costs and meet employer demands far more quickly than Congress could ever implement,” Brendan Buck, PCMA’s chief communications officer, said in a statement. “It makes no sense to ban flexibility and choice and lock employers into a single system that will lead to higher drug costs.”</p> 
<p>In September, PCMA launched a six-figure ad campaign in Washington accusing pharmaceutical companies of keeping prices high, following a similar campaign targeting PBMs from the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America, which represents brand-name drugmakers in May.</p> 
<p>Lobbyists and experts predict the PBM overhauls proposed by Congress are likely only the beginning as lawmakers ramp up scrutiny of the health care sector over high prices – and seek more opportunities to show voters in an election year they care about lowering health care costs.</p> 
<p>“This is the opening salvo in what is going to be a long battle for reform,” said Sujith Ramachandran, an assistant professor at the University of Mississippi School of Pharmacy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
