<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 19:06:01 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Democrats eye vote on 3-year Obamacare subsidy extension</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/senate-democrats-obamacare-extension-00676149</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e6a5-da2c-af9f-ffededeb0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:58:22 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats will propose a three-year extension of soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies for an expected floor vote next week, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss caucus strategy.</p> 
<p>Democrats get to decide what proposal the Senate votes on as part of a deal struck with Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> last month to end the government shutdown. The Senate is expected to hold that vote Dec. 11.</p> 
<p>The strategy likely helps Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> keep his caucus unified on the vote, and it aligns his caucus with House Democrats' plan to try to force a vote on a three-year extension through a discharge petition.</p> 
<p>But it will also limit any chance they would be able to peel off more than a couple of Republicans. Thune said in an interview Wednesday that pitching a clean three-year extension is “designed to fail.”</p> 
<p>To get a deal on the subsidies through the Senate, it would need 60 votes to advance. Some GOP senators, including <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> of Maine, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> of North Carolina, have backed a two-year extension but have acknowledged there would need to be income caps and other restrictions to pick up more GOP support. Whether or not to include abortion funding restrictions is also a major sticking point.</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for Schumer didn’t immediately respond to a question about the plan. Schumer declined to tip his hand earlier Wednesday when asked after a meeting with House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> if Senate Democrats would offer a three-year extension.</p> 
<p>“Stay tuned,” he told reporters.</p> 
<p>Some of his members want Democrats to put up a more sweeping health care proposal, while others have been discussing a potential compromise with Republicans that would extend the subsidies but with new restrictions.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans need to decide whether they will offer their own counterproposal for a vote next week. Senate Finance Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> and Senate HELP Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> talked through their ideas, along with other GOP senators, at a closed-door Tuesday lunch.</p> 
<p>Thune on Wednesday evening said they had not yet made a “final decision” on whether they would put a proposal up for a vote next week.</p> 
<p>“We’ll kind of see what the temperature of our members is,” Thune said.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House backing push to attach Senate housing package to must-pass defense bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/white-house-backing-push-attach-senate-housing-package-defense-bill-00674916</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e69c-dd9e-afba-fefd16b40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:49:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House is backing an effort to attach most of a Senate-approved housing package to a must-pass <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_DRAFT20" target="_blank">annual defense bill</a>, according to three people with knowledge of the matter who were granted anonymity to discuss private talks.</p> 
<p>The administration’s support could breathe new life into the push to include the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2651?q=road+to+housing" target="_blank">ROAD to Housing</a> package in the National Defense Authorization Act at the eleventh hour. Both Senate leaders are also backing the push, the people said.</p> 
<p>A White House official who was granted anonymity to relay the administration's position said: "We’re open to seeing this moving forward."</p> 
<p>The ROAD package, backed by Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> (R-S.C.) and ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> (D-Mass.), includes an array of legislation aimed at boosting housing supply. The Banking panel approved the measure unanimously in July.</p> 
<p>Scott and Warren have pushed to include most of the package in the NDAA, but House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) has pushed back. Hill said in a statement that “any housing package must have the buy-in from the House Financial Services Committee.”</p> 
<p>“Given our Conference has not seen any text, it’s unclear how we could support its inclusion in the NDAA,” he said.</p> 
<p>Hill spoke on the House floor with Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> (R-La.) Wednesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>Congressional GOP leaders are now considering whether to add a revised or scaled-down version of the Senate’s legislation to the Pentagon bill, but no final decisions have been made, according to two people with knowledge of the discussions.</p> 
<p>House Financial Services ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51664" data-person-id="51664">Maxine Waters</a> (D-Calif.) expressed support for the ROAD package during a committee hearing Wednesday morning, calling it a “common-sense legislative package that would chip away at the [housing] crisis.” But she told reporters later in the day that she doesn’t “know what’s in” the latest proposal.</p> 
<p>“I’m supportive of absolutely getting all of my people on the ROAD bill — their bills into the NDAA package,” she said, referring to the fact that many of the measures in the Senate's housing bill have companion bills in the House. “If they have worked that out, I’m happy. But I want to know what it is. And I want to know how many of my members are covered.”</p> 
<p>House Financial Services has not seen the latest text reflecting what the White House supports, according to a House Democratic aide with knowledge of the matter.</p> 
<p>Trump officials and the president's top political aides are trying to push harder on housing policy, as high home costs and mortgages weigh on voters.</p> 
<p>Top Trump pollster Tony Fabrizio spoke extensively about housing policy as a key area of potential focus for Republicans during a closed-door briefing with the Republican Study Committee Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The RSC itself is pushing housing as a key focus for a potential party-line bill the GOP could pass ahead of the midterms. Notably, Fabrizio encouraged House Republicans to work on advancing so-called portable mortgages, an idea some Trump officials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/experts-slam-pulte-trump-50-year-mortgage-idea-00645379" target="_blank">have been mulling</a>. That would allow homeowners to essentially take their mortgage rate with them when they move.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NDAA delays pile up as GOP leaders work through last-minute snags</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/03/ndaa-delays-defense-bill-00676098</link>
      <description>Text of the massive defense policy bill is no longer expected Thursday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e697-da2c-af9f-ffffcd2d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:44:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f5/08/415e6bc346d3a005c25dbf8e4e69/u-s-congress-27873.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson (R-La.) speaks with reporters as he departs a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 3, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f5/08/415e6bc346d3a005c25dbf8e4e69/u-s-congress-27873.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Joe Gould and Connor O'Brien</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Joe Gould and Connor O'Brien</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican leaders on Capitol Hill are scrambling to hammer out a host of complex, 11th-hour intraparty policy fights in the massive <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_DRAFT20" target="_blank">annual defense policy bill</a>, delaying the release of final legislative text beyond the expected date of Thursday, according to four people granted anonymity to discuss the internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>They are still pushing to release text of the sprawling bill by the end of the weekend, according to two of the people. But GOP leaders are going back and forth with White House officials about a raft of final issues, including <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/white-house-backing-push-to-attach-senate-housing-package-to-must-pass-defense-bill-00674916" target="_blank">Senate housing legislation</a> that the administration wants but a key House committee chair opposes.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump and his deputies are eager to address housing costs, and top Trump pollster Tony Fabrizio told a closed-door meeting of House Republicans earlier Wednesday that Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/tony-fabrizio-health-drug-prices-00674841" target="_blank">need to focus more on housing issues</a> ahead of next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>With White House officials digging in, congressional GOP leaders are now considering whether to add a revised or scaled down version of the Senate’s “ROAD to Housing” legislation to the Pentagon bill, but no final decisions have been made, according to the people. House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> has previously opposed the parts of the measure and said in a statement late Wednesday that “any housing package must have the buy-in” of his committee.</p> 
<p>“Given our Conference has not seen any text, it’s unclear how we could support its inclusion in the NDAA,” Hill said.</p> 
<p>Other issues GOP leaders are still working through include whether to add in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/china-investment-crackdown-in-flux-as-lawmakers-rush-to-finalize-defense-bill-00673705" target="_blank">new restrictions on U.S. investments in China</a>, as well as provisions that would expand coverage for in vitro fertilization and other fertility services for military families under the Defense Department’s Tricare health system.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders are reviewing the IVF expansion, which was included in both the House and Senate-passed defense bills. Pushed by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198768" data-person-id="198768">Tammy Duckworth</a> (D-Ill.), Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/369735" data-person-id="369735">Sara Jacobs</a> (D-Calif.) and others, the provision wasn’t included in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/12/04/congress/tammy-duckworth-ivf-donald-trump-00192544" target="_blank"><u>last year’s defense bill</u></a> amid concerns about the practice from some conservatives.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said in a statement that he “has clearly and repeatedly stated he is supportive of access to IVF when sufficient pro-life protections are in place, and he will continue to be supportive when it is done responsibly and ethically.”</p> 
<p>The last-minute moves could weigh heavily on how easily Republican leaders can get the votes needed to pass the sprawling Pentagon bill, which the House aims to do next week.</p> 
<p>The annual National Defense Authorization Act typically passes with broad bipartisan support. Johnson won passage of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_3838" target="_blank">hard-right version of the defense bill</a> in September with just the support of a handful of Democrats, while the Senate cleared <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2296" target="_blank">its own version</a> with support from both parties.</p> 
<p>Bipartisan leaders of the House and Senate Armed Services committees made quick work of their negotiations on a compromise defense bill, which largely concluded before Thanksgiving.</p> 
<p>The legislation was then handed up to House and Senate leaders to hammer out what provisions that fall outside of Armed Services’ jurisdiction would be attached. Top lawmakers on those panels have cautioned against attaching unrelated issues that don’t have broad support and could tank the final bill.</p> 
<p>House and Senate leaders have already had to retreat on some fronts. Trump urged lawmakers to include a contentious moratorium on state regulations for artificial intelligence backed by House Majority Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> and other Republicans. But the effort foundered, and Scalise this week conceded the NDAA “wasn't the best place for this to fit.”</p> 
<p><i>Jasper Goodman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senior Johnson aide leaves for Holland &amp;amp; Knight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/johnson-aide-heads-to-k-street-00675871</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e670-da2c-af9f-ff7960e60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 18:04:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Chris Jaarda, who has spent the past two years as a senior policy adviser and counsel to House Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" target="_blank" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, has left the Hill to join Holland &amp; Knight as a partner in the firm’s lobbying practice.</p> 
<p>Jaarda’s portfolio in Johnson’s office spanned a variety of topics, including privacy, emerging technologies, foreign intelligence, homeland security and supply chain and production issues. His role also involved serving as a liaison between the speaker’s office and House panels such as the Energy &amp; Commerce Committee, Oversight Committee, Judiciary Committee and Homeland Security Committee. Jaarda said in an interview that he worked closely on seven of the 11 titles in this summer’s GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Now, he’ll advise the firm’s clients on their engagement at the state and federal levels as the Trump administration and statehouses begin to implement the law. (In August, Holland &amp; Knight hired Andrew Siracuse, another former Hill staffer who worked on the reconciliation bill under Texas GOP Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51170" target="_blank" data-person-id="51170">John Cornyn</a>.)</p> 
<p>Jaarda, who plans on registering to lobby, also has insights about key players on the Hill, especially as it pertains to the way Johnson has managed to navigate Republicans’ razor-thin House majority. “I think understanding that process, and what moves the needle on certain issues, hopefully will be very helpful” to the firm’s clients, he said.</p> 
<p>Jaarda earlier spent three years working for Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175665" target="_blank" data-person-id="175665">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Texas), including serving as Cruz’s deputy chief of staff for policy and legislative director. Before that, he did stints for former Rep. Ken Buck (R-Colo.), the Senate GOP Policy Committee and former Sen. John Ensign (R-Nev.), in addition to starting his own consulting firm.</p> 
<p>Jaarda is the latest House GOP leadership staffer to head downtown in the past year. Johnson’s policy director, Dan Ziegler, left the Hill in the spring to return to Williams &amp; Jensen. And a handful of top aides to House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" target="_blank" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a>, including his longtime chief of staff, have decamped for the private sector as well.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-03T16:20:16-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump pollster’s health care advice for Republicans: Pivot to drug prices</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/tony-fabrizio-health-drug-prices-00674841</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e5e2-db69-a9fb-e5e3a8500000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 15:25:07 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A top pollster for President Donald Trump advised a group of House Republicans on how to defend against Democrats’ attacks over expiring Obamacare tax credits: focus on reducing drug prices instead.</p> 
<p>Tony Fabrizio showed new polling to members of the Republican Study Committee in a closed-door meeting held a few blocks from the Capitol Wednesday. He argued the most effective way for Republicans to counter Democrats’ health care messaging is to change the subject and pivot to reducing drug prices in tandem with Trump.</p> 
<p>The presentation was described by a House Republican aide and two people in the room who were granted anonymity to discuss the closed-door event. Speaker Mike Johnson, an RSC member, attended the briefing. Fabrizio did not return a request for comment. </p> 
<p>Notably, the House GOP aide said Fabrizio did not recommend any extension of the insurance subsidies, something he has <a href="https://fabrizioward.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/pup-tcd-tax-credit-survey-memo.pdf" target="_blank">advocated for in the past</a>. The Trump administration has recently <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/trumps-cms-touts-12b-savings-from-medicare-drug-price-negotiations-00669231" target="_blank">refocused attention on drug pricing</a>, a topic the president tends to return to when Democrats try to hammer him on health care.</p> 
<p>Trump has tried to pressure House Republican leaders to address drug prices before, with little luck. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/johnson-not-a-big-fan-of-drug-policy-white-house-wants-for-trumps-megabill-00320974" target="_blank">wanted to add a most favored nation provision</a> to the GOP megabill in the final hours before its passage this summer, a policy opposed by the drug industry and GOP leaders themselves, along with some other Republicans. Speaker Mike Johnson said at the time he was "not a big fan" of the policy.</p> 
<p>Fabrizio also spoke extensively about housing as a key area of potential focus for Republicans as high home prices and interest rates weigh on voters. The RSC itself is pushing housing policy as a key focus for a potential party-line bill the GOP could pass ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>Notably, Fabrizio encouraged House Republicans to work on advancing so-called portable mortgages, an idea some Trump officials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/experts-slam-pulte-trump-50-year-mortgage-idea-00645379" target="_blank">have been mulling</a>. That would allow homeowners to essentially take their mortgage rate with them when they move.</p> 
<p>He also gave a postmortem rundown on the results from Tuesday’s Tennessee special election, where Republicans held onto the safe red seat albeit by a single-digit margin — raising concerns for the GOP ahead of next year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>Fabrizio argued it was a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/tennessee-election-republican-midterms-fallout-00674124" target="_blank">closer race than Republicans would have liked</a> because they weren’t talking enough about affordability issues facing voters. He told the group to “stay the course and talk about the realities of the economy,” one House Republican present said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stefanik says Johnson ‘certainly' wouldn’t be reelected speaker</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/stefanik-says-johnson-wouldnt-win-speaker-re-election-00674519</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e590-dd9e-afba-fdfd11010000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 14:13:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Elise Stefanik said Speaker Mike Johnson would lose an election to lead the House if a vote were suddenly called.</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-house-speaker-c41659cb?mod=Searchresults&amp;pos=1&amp;page=1" target="_blank">an interview with the Wall Street Journal</a> Tuesday night, the New York lawmaker said Johnson is an “ineffective leader” who is losing control of the Republican party.</p> 
<p>“He certainly wouldn’t have the votes to be speaker if there was a roll-call vote tomorrow,” said Stefanik, a close ally to President Donald Trump. “I believe that the majority of Republicans would vote for new leadership. It’s that widespread.”</p> 
<p>Johnson replaced former Rep. Kevin McCarthy to helm the lower chamber in 2023, accepting the speaker’s gavel after a historic series of multiple rounds of voting. He easily won reelection to the speakership earlier this year on a near-party-line vote.</p> 
<p>It’s not the first time Stefanik, who is running for governor, has criticized the speaker.</p> 
<p>Earlier this week, she <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-feud-00674030" target="_blank">accused Johnson</a> of blocking provisions to the National Defense Authorization Act that would notify Congress if the FBI begins investigating federal candidates.</p> 
<p>Johnson, she said Monday in <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995596731543671069" target="_blank">a post to X</a>, is “getting rolled by House Dems attempting to block my provision to require Congressional disclosure when the FBI opens counterintelligence investigations into presidential and federal candidates seeking office.”</p> 
<p>Still, Johnson appears to have the favor of Trump, who has been able to keep a lid on most GOP internal disputes this year and was credited with mediating the quarrel between Johnson and Stefanik.</p> 
<p>But <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/12/03/young-republicans-to-host-far-right-german-leader-after-leaked-chat-00674051" target="_blank">in an interview with Playbook</a>, Stefanik pointed out that between Trump and Johnson, “one has historic support among Republican voters, and one has catastrophic, plummeting support among Republican voters.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Democrats watching from the sidelines have cheered on the in-fighting with glee.</p> 
<p>“THE GIRLS ARE FIGHTING!” a <a href="https://mailchi.mp/dccc.org/the-girls-are-fighting-as-mike-johnson-and-elise-stefanik-brawl-online-mike-lawler-is-left-to-pick-his-favorite-party-boss?e=5f1378536e" target="_blank">Tuesday memo</a> from the DCCC highlighting the Stefanik-Johnson feud said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Henry Cuellar will seek reelection as a Democrat after Trump pardon</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/henry-cuellar-pardon-reelection-party-00674518</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e58c-dc85-abba-e7bf3c830000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:53:36 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Texas Rep. Henry Cuellar filed for reelection Wednesday as a Democrat and told reporters he had no intention to retire or switch parties hours after President Donald Trump announced pardons for him and his wife.</p> 
<p>“It came as a surprise,” Cuellar told a small group of reporters about the pardon. “I want to thank President Trump for this. … Now we clear the air. Nothing has changed, and we’re going to be ready to win re-election again.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s announcement of the pardons Wednesday morning immediately stoked speculation that the 11-term veteran might finally switch to the GOP after years of entreaties or simply retire — giving Republicans a much better chance to flip his competitive Rio Grande Valley seat.</p> 
<p>But Cuellar quickly assured a small group of senior Democrats that he would not switch parties, according to two people granted anonymity to describe the private conversations. He also filed reelection paperwork with Texas state officials Wednesday.</p> 
<p>“Nothing has changed — I'm a good old conservative Democrat,” Cuellar said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Trump claimed on Truth Social that Cuellar’s prosecution was the result of his speaking out against former President Joe Biden’s immigration policy. Cuellar and his wife Imelda were indicted last year on more than a dozen corruption charges including bribery.</p> 
<p>“Henry, I don’t know you, but you can sleep well tonight — Your nightmare is finally over!” Trump posted.</p> 
<p>The clemency for Cuellar comes as the president faces backlash for his use of the pardon power, including for officials in his own party. Trump has also railed for years about Biden’s alleged “weaponization” of law enforcement, and the Cuellar pardon could serve to show that his interest in that subject crosses party lines.</p> 
<p>But it stands to complicate the GOP’s longstanding effort to oust Cuellar from office. He is near the top of the party’s 2026 target list, and a top Republican recruit <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2025/12/02/webb-county-judge-tano-tijerina-congressional-run/" target="_blank">entered the race Tuesday</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump’s glowing praise of the Texas Democrat in his announcement of the pardon Wednesday — and Cuellar’s determination to seek reelection — shocked Republicans who have tried to defeat him for years.</p> 
<p>Rep. Pete Sessions, informed of the news, said Cuellar’s electoral intentions show “there was not a quid pro quo" with Trump over the pardon. But the veteran Texas Republican and former NRCC chair declined to opine further.</p> 
<p>“Very interesting,” he said. “Very interesting.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartisan group set to meet with Bill Cassidy on possible ACA fix</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/bipartisan-group-meeting-with-cassidy-wednesday-on-possible-aca-fix-00674474</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e577-da2c-af9f-ff7fb76f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 13:29:32 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan group of senators and House members led by Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260077" data-person-id="260077">Josh Gottheimer</a> (D-N.J.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.) will be meeting Wednesday afternoon with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> (R-La.) to see if there’s a path forward on bipartisan health care legislation, according to a person granted anonymity to share plans for the closed-door session.</p> 
<p>The meeting is notable because Cassidy, chair of the Senate HELP Committee, has been working with Senate Finance Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> (R-Idaho) on a party-line alternative to Democratic legislation that is expected to extend expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies. Gottheimer and Kiggans have been trying to forge a compromise on the subsidies; both are members of the Problem Solvers Caucus and have been working with a variety of lawmakers on the issue.</p> 
<p>Bipartisan discussions on potential health plans remain fragmented. Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> is facing intense pressure from conservatives to let the subsidies expire, but vulnerable House Republicans are adamant that something needs to be done to address skyrocketing premiums before the end of the year. </p> 
<p>Gottheimer and Kiggans are also set to announce a new "CommonGround 2025" framework Thursday that would extend the expiring premium tax credits. It is endorsed by more than 30 House members of both parties, according to a media advisory issued Wednesday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-03T12:55:07-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Jack Smith subpoenaed for closed-door House Judiciary interview</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/jack-smith-subpoena-house-judiciary-00674387</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e541-dd9e-afba-fd6d34930000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:37:05 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Judiciary Committee issued a subpoena to former special counsel Jack Smith, who led investigations into President Donald Trump, ordering him to appear at a closed-door session later this month.</p> 
<p>Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) demanded in a letter to Smith that the former DOJ official who oversaw cases around Trump’s retention of classified documents and efforts to subvert the results of the 2020 election provide documents by Dec. 12 and sit for a deposition with the panel on Dec. 17. </p> 
<p>It is a marked escalation after Smith signaled an <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/14/congress/jordan-wants-jack-smith-testimony-00607878" target="_blank">openness to answering questions</a> and weeks of negotiations over the terms of an interview. Smith asked for a public hearing rather than a closed-door interview.</p> 
<p>Smith’s lawyer Peter Koski said in a statement that his client looked forward to meeting with the panel later this month but that he regretted he could not appear in a public setting.</p> 
<p>“Nearly six weeks ago Jack offered to voluntarily appear before the House Judiciary committee in an open hearing to answer any questions lawmakers have about his investigation into President Trump's alleged efforts to unlawfully overturn the election results and retention of classified documents,” Koski said. “We are disappointed that offer was rejected, and that the American people will be denied the opportunity to hear directly from Jack on these topics.”</p> 
<p>Republican lawmakers have become increasingly fixated on the probes launched during Joe Biden's presidency and Smith’s stewardship of the cases, arguing that the efforts amounted to a campaign to undermine Trump. They have sought to argue that Biden and his allies weaponized the Justice Department, even as Trump has publicly called on his attorney general to prosecute his political adversaries.</p> 
<p>The cause has become personal for some GOP members following revelations that the Justice Department requested some lawmakers' phone records as part of its investigative work. Jordan recently revealed that the Justice Department subpoenaed years worth of his phone data.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin (D-Md.), the committee's top Democrat, defended the former special counsel and his tactics in a statement and questioned why Republicans are insisting on having Smith testify behind closed doors. But he also criticized the phone record request targeting Jordan, which was issued before Smith was named to his post.</p> 
<p>“Special Counsel Smith’s careful investigative steps stand in contrast to a separate subpoena issued for 2.5 years of Chairman Jordan’s personal phone records that was recently produced to the Committee and appears manifestly overbroad," he said, adding that Smith's requests "were narrowly tailored to obtain phone records for the days surrounding January 6."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-03T19:06:01-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Epstein island photos, videos released by House Oversight Committee</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/jeffrey-epstein-house-oversight-jpmorgan-00674304</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e508-da2c-af9f-ff6942c30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 11:50:50 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Oversight Committee has received new materials from major financial institutions as part of its investigation into the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, as well as photos and videos of Epstein's private compound from authorities in the U.S. Virgin Islands.</p> 
<p>The files from JPMorgan Chase and Deutsche Bank have not yet been publicly released, though Democrats on the panel say they expect to release them in the coming days after a review. These documents are separate from the federal law enforcement records Congress voted to make public last month; the Justice Department is required to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/the-epstein-files-are-coming-what-should-we-expect-00660323" target="_blank">make those materials public</a> later this month.</p> 
<p>“[House Oversight Democrats] intend to release files to the public in the days ahead,” said Rep. Robert Garcia, the top Democrat on the panel, in a post on X. A spokesperson for the committee’s Republican majority confirmed the receipt of the materials.</p> 
<p>Democrats publicly <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fo/e7n5g4wz0cjngv9u9qys2/AHNOf8vcSNtejTpIcQGaICs?dl=0&amp;e=2&amp;rlkey=c8fds6c4a8t6zwoiglx4c7kt3&amp;st=16dpmuw0" target="_blank">posted videos and photos</a> Wednesday that were provided by the government of the U.S. Virgin Islands, where Epstein owned his infamous private retreat. <br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/4d/fa/41ab8b5c44dc80cb7c06b635337c/unlimiteduse-epsteinusvi-016.JPG" alt="An undated photograph of Jeffrey Epstein's island compound provided by authorities in the U.S. Virgin Islands, published Dec. 3, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee." data-portal-copyright="Government of the U.S. Virgin Islands via House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="An undated photograph of Jeffrey Epstein's island compound provided by authorities in the U.S. Virgin Islands, published Dec. 3, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee."/><p>They include shots inside the island compound, including a photo of Epstein and his associate Ghislaine Maxwell with Pope John Paul II. Others showed various parts of the property.</p> 
<p>Maxwell is currently serving a 20-year sentence for her part in the sex trafficking scheme.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, a bipartisan coalition of lawmakers asked Wednesday for a meeting with Justice Department personnel to ascertain what information is in its possession and is subject to release. <br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/fd/40/72d64553488b9cc2bd4b9bc057fc/unlimiteduse-epsteinusvi-020.jpg" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's island compound provided by authorities in the U.S. Virgin Islands shows Epstein and Ghislane Maxwell with Pope John Paul II, published by the House Oversight Committee on Dec. 3, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Government of the U.S. Virgin Islands via House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's island compound provided by authorities in the U.S. Virgin Islands shows Epstein and Ghislane Maxwell with Pope John Paul II, published by the House Oversight Committee on Dec. 3, 2025."/><p>Reps. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) and Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) and Sens. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska), Ben Ray Luján (D-N.M.) and Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.) told Attorney General Pam Bondi in a letter that that they are “particularly focused on understanding the contents of any new evidence, information or procedural hurdles that could interfere with the Department’s ability meet this statutory deadline.”</p> 
<p>The lawmakers, who were the lead sponsors of the Epstein files legislation, asked for a briefing no later than Friday and urged the DOJ to coordinate with the lawyers for Epstein’s accusers. A Justice Department spokesperson confirmed receipt of the letter but declined to comment.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/07/8a/bb32b87240cfac405b775ccd68fb/unlimiteduse-epsteinusvi-014.JPG" alt="An undated photograph of Jeffrey Epstein's island compound provided by authorities in the U.S. Virgin Islands, published Dec. 3, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee." data-portal-copyright="Government of the U.S. Virgin Islands via House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="An undated photograph of Jeffrey Epstein's island compound provided by authorities in the U.S. Virgin Islands, published Dec. 3, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee."/>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-03T12:18:01-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump pardons Texas Democrat Henry Cuellar</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/henry-cuellar-trump-pardon-00674210</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e4da-dc85-abba-e6ff1d3e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 10:48:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump pardoned Rep. Henry Cuellar (D-Texas), the president announced in a Truth Social post on Wednesday, blaming former President Joe Biden for weaponizing the Justice Department against his opponents.</p> 
<p>“Sleepy Joe went after the Congressman, and even the Congressman's wonderful wife, Imelda, simply for speaking the TRUTH,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115656343773820545" target="_blank">Trump wrote</a>. “It is unAmerican and, as I previously stated, the Radical Left Democrats are a complete and total threat to Democracy.”</p> 
<p>Cuellar and his wife were <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/05/03/congress/cuellar-indicted-00155977" target="_blank">charged in 2024 with accepting $600,000</a> in bribes from foreign entities. The moderate Democrat — who has long been a battleground target for Republicans — was nonetheless reelected to his South Texas seat in November.</p> 
<p>Trump’s pardon of Cuellar comes just a day after national Republicans got their top recruit to challenge him in a seat made redder thanks to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/20/texas-republican-maps-redistricting-trump-00517274" target="_blank">Texas’ mid-decade redistricting</a>. Webb County Judge Tano Tijerina, a <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2024/12/10/texas-webb-county-judge-tano-tijerina-republican/" target="_blank">former Democrat who switched parties last year,</a> announced his campaign for the 28th District as a Republican on Tuesday after months of speculation.</p> 
<p>Cuellar told a small group of Democrats Wednesday he is not planning to switch parties after Trump pardoned him, according to two people granted anonymity to describe the private calls. He just filed for re-election in South Texas.</p> 
<p>His office did not immediately respond to a request for comment on his pardon, but he thanked Trump in a social media post shortly after the president’s announcement. The longtime lawmaker had denied any criminal allegations in a statement following his indictment.</p> 
<p>“I want to thank President Trump for his tremendous leadership and for taking the time to look at the facts,” <a href="https://x.com/RepCuellar/status/1996254124354986003" target="_blank">Cuellar wrote on X</a>. “This decision clears the air and lets us move forward for South Texas.”</p> 
<p>On Truth Social on Wednesday, Trump accused the Biden administration of targeting Cuellar, even though he is a Democrat, due to the lawmaker’s position on immigration.</p> 
<p>The Texan had been a vocal critic of Biden and his immigration policies, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/05/12/henry-cuellar-pbdd-00096425" target="_blank">telling POLITICO in 2023</a> that he believed Biden was too influenced by his party’s left flank on immigration.</p> 
<p>“They will attack, rob, lie, cheat, destroy, and decimate anyone who dares to oppose their far left Agenda, and Agenda that, if left unchecked, will obliterate our magnificent country,” Trump wrote.</p> 
<p>Attached to the president’s Truth Social post was a letter sent by Cuellar’s children. They described their parents as “good, decent people who have spent their lives giving more than they’ve taken” and raised concerns that “our father’s independence and honesty may have contributed to how this case began.”</p> 
<p>This isn’t the first time Trump has dropped charges against a Democratic official. In February, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/10/trumps-justice-department-moves-to-drop-charges-against-eric-adams-00203483" target="_blank">Justice Department tossed a bribery case against New York City Mayor Eric Adams</a>, reportedly part of an effort to gain his cooperation on immigration enforcement in the city.</p> 
<p>The president has made extensive use of his clemency powers since retaking office, most recently to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/trump-honduras-pardon-drug-trafficking-00672632" target="_blank">pardon former Honduran President Juan Orlando Hernández</a>. Hernández faced a 45-year prison sentence after being <a href="https://www.justice.gov/archives/opa/pr/juan-orlando-hernandez-former-president-honduras-sentenced-45-years-prison-conspiring" target="_blank">convicted on drug trafficking charges in 2024</a>.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Ben Johansen and Jessica Piper contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stefanik secures NDAA provision after high-profile fight with Johnson</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-ndaa-00674161</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e46c-dd9e-afba-fc6d142c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 08:36:45 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227481" data-person-id="227481">Elise Stefanik</a> declared victory over Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> Wednesday, saying she had secured the inclusion of a key provision she wanted attached to the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_DRAFT20" target="_blank">annual Pentagon policy bill</a> after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-feud-00674030" target="_blank">remarkable public spat with the speaker</a> a day earlier. </p> 
<p>Others involved credited President Donald Trump for playing mediator after the New York Republican threatened to "tank" the must-pass National Defense Authorization Act as part of her public targeting of Johnson. The three spoke by phone Tuesday night about her threats, according to two people granted anonymity to describe the private call. </p> 
<p>Stefanik said in a <a href="https://x.com/elisestefanik/status/1996184177335480682?s=46" target="_blank">Wednesday norning X post</a> that “after a productive discussion” with Trump and Johnson last night, “the provision requiring Congressional disclosure when the FBI opens counterintelligence investigations into presidential and federal candidates seeking office will be included” as part of an agreement to pass the Pentagon bill. </p> 
<p>A floor vote on the package is expected next week. A spokesperson for Johnson declined to weigh in on the private conversations.</p> 
<p>Stefanik, a member of Johnson’s leadership team, accused the speaker Tuesday of personally excluding her measure from the defense bill and lying about it. Johnson said those allegations were “false” and countered that bipartisan committee leaders had not agreed to add it.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-03T08:11:12-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP fears what Tennessee means for 2026</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/03/congress/tennessee-republicans-2026-midterms-johnson-problems-00674146</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e291-da2c-af9f-fbf9f3000000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson held onto a much-needed red seat in Tennessee Tuesday night — but fellow Republicans say this <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/tennessee-aftyn-behn-matt-van-epps-democrats-00674118" target="_blank">isn’t cause for celebration</a>.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s leadership’s team was bracing for a tighter-than-comfortable race in the special election to succeed former Rep. Mark Green.</p> 
<p>But the single-digit margin of victory for Matt Van Epps was still a hard pill to swallow after national Republicans pulled out all the stops to rescue their candidate on the final days of the campaign, with the speaker himself traveling to the district to make a final pitch.</p> 
<p>“It was too close,” said one House GOP leadership aide.</p> 
<p>The surprisingly-tight race between Van Epps and Democrat Aftyn Behn “is a sign that 2026 is going to be a bitch of an election cycle,” one House Republican told POLITICO. “Republicans can survive if we play team and the Trump administration officials play smart. Neither is certain.”</p> 
<p>Retiring Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) warned “the GOP should not ignore” how close it came to losing a district President Donald Trump won by 22 points in 2024 — not to mention the Democratic gubernatorial victories in Virginia and New Jersey last month.</p> 
<p>Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas) agreed it was a “dangerous” sign for his party. “In a year, it’s going to be a turnout election, and the left will show up,” Cruz said in an interview with Fox on Tuesday night. “Hate is a powerful motivator. They hate President Trump.”</p> 
<p>This close call in Tennessee adds to the ongoing headaches for Johnson back in Washington.</p> 
<p>The speaker is facing a revolt led by a member of his own leadership team, Rep. Elise Stefanik (R-N.Y.), over news that the National Defense Authorization Act likely won’t include her provision to require the FBI to notify Congress when it opens investigations into candidates running for federal office.</p> 
<p>Stefanik, who is running for governor, announced Wednesday morning the provision was added back into the NDAA after talking to Johnson — a day after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-feud-00674030" target="_blank">accusing the speaker of blocking the provision</a> and “lying” about it. But with the language back in, Johnson risks losing Democratic support that could be crucial for getting the historically-bipartisan package over the finish line.</p> 
<p>Johnson could also be on the verge of being undermined by his own members who want a vote on legislation that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/anna-paulina-luna-congressional-stock-trading-ban-00673180" target="_blank">ban congressional stock trading</a>. Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) officially moved Tuesday to lay the groundwork to circumvent leadership and force that vote, with Rep. Tim Burchett (R-Tenn.) saying he and Luna were “tired” of waiting.</p> 
<p>Also on Tuesday: Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/college-sports-bill-heads-to-final-vote-despite-gop-defections-00673376" target="_blank">faced a small rebellion</a> on the House floor over a procedural move involving legislation to regulate name, image and likeness compensation in college sports. That could spell trouble around a final vote coming Wednesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>And then there’s health care. Johnson is promising that House Republicans will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/republicans-want-a-health-care-plan-they-dont-know-what-will-go-in-it-00673969" target="_blank">come up with a health policy proposal</a>. But there’s no sign he’ll be able to bring together moderates like Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.), who wants to extend the enhanced Obamacare tax credits, and conservatives who are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/03/obamacare-subsidies-expire-this-month-many-republicans-are-shrugging-00672949" target="_blank">downplaying the effects</a> of letting the subsidies lapse.</p> 
<p>As retiring Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said Tuesday, midterm backlash for the GOP could be substantial if Republicans don’t do something to prevent premiums going up come January.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Venezuela fallout: </b>Significant <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/boat-strike-republican-trump-loyalty-00673439" target="_blank">cracks in GOP unity</a> are growing amid Trump’s campaign to kill alleged drug traffickers off the coast of Venezuela. </p> 
<p><b>— Hawley’s health care pitch: </b>Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) is rolling out a bill to allow all taxpayers to deduct up to $25,000 in medical expenses. The bill also allows out of pocket expenses on health care premiums to be deducted.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA latest: </b>House and Senate leaders are <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/china-investment-crackdown-in-flux-as-lawmakers-rush-to-finalize-defense-bill-00673705" target="_blank">engaged in last-minute talks</a> over whether to include new restrictions on U.S. investments in China in the NDAA. It's one of the last outstanding issues for lawmakers to resolve as they look to release compromise bill text Thursday.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Hailey Fuchs, Jordain Carney, Robert King, Alice Miranda Ollstein, Calen Razor and Jasper Goodman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dems fall short of flipping deep-red House seat in surprisingly competitive Tennessee special election</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/republican-matt-van-epps-wins-tn-special-election-00673966</link>
      <description>Republican Matt Van Epps won after both parties spent significant effort in a district Trump won by more than 20 points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e17e-da2c-af9f-fb7f333a0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 21:38:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0b/b0/cea3df124b91ba1add94bfab16b4/van-epps-02708.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Republican Matt Van Epps won the special election for Tennessee’s 7th Congressional District.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0b/b0/cea3df124b91ba1add94bfab16b4/van-epps-02708.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican Matt Van Epps won a Tennessee House special election on Tuesday, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/tennessee-aftyn-behn-matt-van-epps-democrats-00674118" target="_blank">Democrat Aftyn Behn significantly cut into GOP margins in the district</a>, continuing a streak of overperformances this year.</p> 
<p>National outside groups poured millions into the race, as Republicans grew concerned about a potential upset.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump carried the district by 22 points last fall, but voters’ dissatisfaction with cost of living helped Behn trim that margin.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elise Stefanik’s feud with Johnson reflects a House spinning out of control</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-feud-00674030</link>
      <description>The New York Republican took remarkable public shots at the speaker Tuesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e1ba-db69-a9fb-e5fb91270000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 20:04:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b1/ab/516c363b4e3b80e772cfe092dd55/u-s-congress-03347.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Stefanik, left, is getting backup from House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan, right, in her battle to get her pet provision in a must-pass bill.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b1/ab/516c363b4e3b80e772cfe092dd55/u-s-congress-03347.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Even by the high standards of chaos for the 119th Congress, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> being accused Tuesday by a member of his own leadership team of protecting the “deep state” was a remarkable development.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227481" data-person-id="227481">Elise Stefanik</a>’s rare move to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/stefanik-accuses-johnson-lying-00672634" target="_blank">publicly accuse the speaker</a> of being a liar and then, in a separate provocation, signing on to an effort to force a vote on legislation Johnson has kept bottled up is the latest symptom of a House Republican Conference seemingly on a razor’s edge.</p> 
<p>Increasingly, rank-and-file House Republicans are bringing their spats with Johnson into the open, suggesting the speaker is losing further control over his restive members as his already slim majority threatens to narrow further and potentially devastating midterm elections loom.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260571" data-person-id="260571">Kevin Kiley </a>(R-Calif.), who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/kevin-kiley-shutdown-gop-critic-00608517" target="_blank">openly challenged Johnson’s decision</a> to keep the House out of session for seven weeks this fall and criticized him for not pushing back on the GOP’s mid-decade redistricting campaign, said in a brief interview Tuesday that he saw Stefanik’s anger as part of broader trend.</p> 
<p>“I do think that there's a lot of frustration right now in the House with the effectiveness or lack thereof of this body in recent months,” he said. “The House has … in some cases ceded its own authority, hasn't taken the lead on a lot of important policy measures and has even taken steps now to limit the agency of individual members.”</p> 
<p>For much of his two-year tenure, Johnson has been able to keep a handle on the infighting thanks to President Donald Trump’s stranglehold on the Republican Party, with the president personally intervening at key points this year to settle internecine disputes.</p> 
<p>But many sense that is changing as the speaker suffers public setbacks — such as his recent failure to prevent passage of a bill mandating the release of Justice Department files related to the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein. Things could fray further depending on how the GOP fares in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/house-republicans-tennessee-special-election-00672582" target="_blank">Tuesday’s special election in Tennessee</a>.</p> 
<p>"That model only works if no one challenges him and gets away with it," said one senior House Republican granted anonymity to speak frankly about conference dynamics. "And that's not what's happening now. … People are less willing to stay quiet.”</p> 
<p>In particular, several high-profile GOP women have clashed with the speaker over various issues in recent months. Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/337881" data-person-id="337881">Marjorie Taylor Greene</a> of Georgia, Nancy Mace of South Carolina and Lauren Boebert of Colorado were instrumental in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/epstein-files-bill-congress-00655286" target="_blank">pushing through the Epstein bill</a>. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> of Florida filed her second discharge petition of the year Tuesday, seeking to force a vote on a bill banning member stock trading that the speaker has so far declined to advance. And several women in the House GOP raised concerns about leaders’ handling of Rep. Cory Mills (R-Fla.), who is facing multiple accusations regarding his conduct and ethics.</p> 
<p>Stefanik is in another category altogether. A year ago, she was the No. 4 House GOP leader before relinquishing her post in anticipation of her confirmation as ambassador to the United Nations. But Trump withdrew her nomination amid concerns about the thin GOP majority — a move for which Stefanik has privately faulted Johnson.</p> 
<p>Johnson granted her an unelected junior leadership role as a consolation prize, but she has decided her political future will not lie in the House, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/07/elise-stefanik-new-york-governor-campaign-launch-00641679" target="_blank">launching a campaign for New York governor</a> instead of seeking re-election. And now she appears to be all-in on a scorched earth campaign against the speaker.</p> 
<p>"Elise is running for governor and frankly does not give a fuck anymore about playing nice," said a second House Republican granted anonymity to speak frankly about the dispute.</p> 
<p>The precipitating cause for Stefanik’s public outburst, in her telling, was a leadership-level decision to exclude legislation requiring that Congress be informed of counterintelligence probes into candidates for federal offices from the annual defense policy bill — a must-pass measure to which lawmakers are keen to attach their personal priorities.</p> 
<p>After Stefanik <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/stefanik-accuses-johnson-lying-00672634" target="_blank">posted her displeasure</a> to her X account, Johnson tried to tamp down the furor Tuesday. The speaker, who sometimes jokes he’s more of a mental health counselor, told reporters he couldn’t understand why Stefanik “didn’t just call me” and that the two could have handled the dispute in private.</p> 
<p>“Just more lies from the Speaker,” Stefanik retorted, <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995886289527214190" target="_blank">again on X</a>, mocking Johnson’s claims of ignorance. “This is his preferred tactic to tell Members when he gets caught torpedoing the Republican agenda.”</p> 
<p>House Republicans close to Stefanik argue there are more GOP members who are upset about the congressional notice provision falling out of the Pentagon bill. Notably, House Judiciary Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51745" data-person-id="51745">Jim Jordan</a> (R-Ohio) said he had not yet thought about whether he would join Stefanik in withholding his support for the bill over its exclusion.</p> 
<p>“We want this protection in there,” he told reporters. “I think it makes sense.”</p> 
<p>Just hours after Stefanik’s comments, Johnson faced down a brief revolt over a procedural measure on the House floor led by hard-line Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and other incensed Republicans that would have derailed GOP leaders’ floor plans for the week.</p> 
<p>As that crisis was still unfolding, Luna launched her <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/house-discharge-petitions-mike-johnson-00666557" target="_blank">discharge petition</a> to force a vote on a congressional stock trading ban — and Stefanik quickly announced she was signing on to the move undermining the speaker’s authority.</p> 
<p>Members of Johnson’s leadership circle and other senior Republicans were privately shocked by Stefanik’s sharp public criticism of the speaker — and that she didn’t later decide to delete them — according to three people granted anonymity to describe conversations that unfolded Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s staff have reached out to Stefanik’s team and are seeking to resolve the spat privately, according to two other people with direct knowledge of the matter.</p> 
<p>The speaker’s allies argue the disgruntled Republicans are just that — people with axes to grind against Johnson.</p> 
<p>But Stefanik is getting backup from other malcontents inside the House GOP, including Greene, who was once seen as being on the opposite pole of the Republican conference. Both women were kept in close consultation by the previous speaker, Kevin McCarthy, and have since fallen out with Johnson.</p> 
<p>After helping to engineer the successful Epstein files vote, Greene <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972" target="_blank">announced her imminent resignation</a> — itself a slap at Johnson, given the tight GOP majority — and publicly railed against the House’s diminished power and Johnson’s speakership. She weighed in again Tuesday after Stefanik aired her accusations about the Pentagon bill.</p> 
<p>“No surprises here,” Greene said in her <a href="https://x.com/RepMTG/status/1995869033590321660" target="_blank">own X post</a>. “As usual from the Speaker, promises made promises broken. We all know it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans want a health care plan. They don’t know what will go in it.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/republicans-want-a-health-care-plan-they-dont-know-what-will-go-in-it-00673969</link>
      <description>House and Senate Republicans need to build consensus around a health care proposal by the end of next week if they want to compete with a Democratic plan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e18c-da2c-af9f-fbeda5ed0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 19:11:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/51/4e/e45f580c4d7d9885a212a944121d/u-s-congress-07906.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) is seen at the U.S. Capitol Oct. 1, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/51/4e/e45f580c4d7d9885a212a944121d/u-s-congress-07906.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican lawmakers are looking to craft their own health care policy overhauls by the end of next week, when Senate Democrats get a vote on expiring Obamacare subsidies. So far they don’t agree on what their competing plan should look like.</p> 
<p>In separate closed-door meetings Tuesday, House and Senate Republicans debated what they could put forth as they face the reality that health insurance premiums will skyrocket if enhanced Affordable Care Act tax credits lapse after Dec. 31. Speaker Mike Johnson for the first time definitively promised his anxious members he would put forward some kind of health care blueprint in the coming days, while Senate Republicans discussed how to lower health care costs including through a revamp of health savings accounts. </p> 
<p>But GOP leaders in both chambers face deep divisions within their ranks about how to proceed, including whether to extend the credits at all and force Republicans to vote for the first time to affirm Obamacare. With Tuesday’s conversations producing little clarity, GOP lawmakers said they are still far away from a plan they could unite behind by the end of next week.</p> 
<p>“Have you ever heard of a Rorschach test? Let’s smear it all over the wall,” Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) said about the state of the GOP’s health care discussions. </p> 
<p>Some Republicans on Capitol Hill worry that the failure to come up with any plan in the coming days could be a political nightmare heading into the 2026 midterms, with GOP candidates being dogged by questions about increased health care costs. </p> 
<p>Retiring Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) Tuesday warned of a potential backlash during the midterms if the subsidies expire, predicting Democrats would pummel Republicans in 2026 by highlighting a “number of sympathetic cases” where Americans have seen their health insurance costs go up.</p> 
<p>“There’s a lot of harmonization that needs to be done,” he said about the GOP’s health care talks. </p> 
<p>During their weekly lunch Tuesday, Senate Republicans heard from Finance Chair Mike Crapo and HELP Chair Bill Cassidy about their progress in developing a Republican proposal that could be put on the floor alongside the Democratic plan. Senate Majority Leader John Thune is giving Democrats a vote as part of a deal he struck to re-open the government.</p> 
<p>As part of the lunch, Republicans discussed providing more flexibility for how health savings accounts are used, imposing income caps on ACA subsidies and requiring ACA enrollees to make minimum payments on premiums, according to senators in attendance. </p> 
<p>Cassidy, a physician, has been an evangelist for boosting health savings accounts as an alternative to extending the tax credits. He’s poised to use a HELP Committee hearing on the topic Wednesday to tout this proposal.</p> 
<p>Thune is facing competing pressures within his conference over whether the ACA subsidies should be extended or allowed to sunset. Some GOP senators said after Tuesday’s lunch they expected there would be a vote on some kind of Republican health care measure next week, but Thune wouldn’t commit to that timeline, telling reporters only that his members would continue to discuss ideas. </p> 
<p>Crapo, in an interview, said it would be a “collective decision” from the Senate GOP Conference about whether his proposal with Cassidy would get a vote next week. </p> 
<p>Republicans are also still waiting to see what the Democratic proposal will be. Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer told reporters after a closed-door lunch with his own caucus that they discussed the idea and to “stay tuned” on where they would land. Democrats are likely to offer a clean extension of the subsidies, but haven’t said how long that extension would be. </p> 
<p>Across the Capitol, Johnson pledged Tuesday for the first time that House Republicans will put forward a health care plan soon. Many House Republicans left a closed-door conference meeting with the sense that GOP leaders could produce a framework by the end of this week. </p> 
<p>But House GOP leaders are confronting their own internal squabbling, with one person close to leadership, granted anonymity to speak candidly, describing that goal as “ambitious.” </p> 
<p>Leaders of the House Republican Conference have also pushed to omit any ACA subsidy extension from their upcoming health care plan, alarming GOP moderates who worry their reelection prospects hinge on the subsidies’ survival.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise got an earful on the concerns about proceeding without an ACA extension during a lunch meeting with the centrist Republican Governance Group, according to four Republicans in the room. </p> 
<p>One of the Republicans, granted anonymity to discuss the private conversation, said that nearly every member of that caucus complained to Scalise that “something needs to be done” on health care before the end of the year. Many of the members present advocated for an ACA subsidy extension. </p> 
<p>Scalise didn’t make any promises but said the “will of the conference” would decide whether Republicans could back health care provisions like an extension of the ACA subsidies — though a majority of House Republicans don’t support it. </p> 
<p>“We had a good conversation about all the work that's been done by the three committees of jurisdiction,” Scalise said in an interview after the meeting, referring to House Energy and Commerce, Ways and Means and Education and the Workforce.</p> 
<p>“Of course, members that aren't on those committees, you know, haven't been aware of some of the things that have come out, but we also wanted to get their feedback,” Scalise added.</p> 
<p>Some Republicans are holding out hope for a bipartisan breakthrough, as GOP leaders pursue what would likely be party-line options.</p> 
<p>House Problem Solvers Co-Chair Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) is working on a bill that reflects the leaked health care framework the White House was planning to reveal last week but held back amid conservative backlash. He told reporters Tuesday he has discussed the bill with the White House and it is “not addressing” abortion restrictions — a bid to entice Democrats.</p> 
<p>"We're trying to get a bill that can get 218,” Fitzpatrick said. "I think it's the most serious attempt out there."</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rep. Ayanna Pressley will run for reelection, foregoing Senate race</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/pressley-seeks-reelection-00673538</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e0ed-da2c-af9f-fbede9820000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 16:33:10 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Ayanna Pressley won’t challenge Sen. Ed Markey for his Senate seat and instead plans to seek reelection to her House seat, she announced today, ending weeks of speculation about the progressive Democrat’s political future.</p> 
<p>“Hearing from so many people from throughout our Commonwealth encouraging me to run for the United States Senate was deeply humbling and a testament to the strength of our movement. It would be an honor to serve the whole Commonwealth—but with our daughter in her last year at home before college and a district that has been in the crosshairs of this White House, I am certain that the Massachusetts 7th is where I belong in this moment,” Pressley said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Markey, who will be 80 when he’s up for reelection next year, is already facing a challenge from Rep. Seth Moulton. The Salem Democrat has centered his campaign on a call for generational change in the wake of the 2024 elections.</p> 
<p>Pressley <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/04/congress/ayanna-pressley-for-senate-00636295" target="_blank">was considering her own bid for Senate</a>, and a recent <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2025/11/25/metro/full-poll-results-massachusetts-voters/?p1=Article_Inline_Related_Link" target="_blank">Suffolk University/Boston Globe poll</a> showed her neck-and-neck with Markey in a three-way Democratic primary. But polling also showed her entrance into the race would narrow Markey’s lead over Moulton, raising concern among progressives in the state that a three-way race could open a lane for the more moderate congressman.</p> 
<p>“Now, more than ever, is the time to dig deep, to lean into mutual aid, and to use every tool available to stand in the gap in defense of our neighbors and our democracy,” Pressley said.</p> 
<p>In a statement responding to Pressley’s announcement, Moulton called her “a powerful advocate for justice and opportunity in Massachusetts,” and Markey described the Squad member as “a champion for the 7th Congressional District, for Massachusetts, and for our nation.”</p> 
<p>“I share her commitment to the fight against authoritarianism, to take back the House and the Senate in 2026, and I am deeply grateful for her continued partnership,” Markey said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Luna pushes to force a vote banning congressional stock trading</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/anna-paulina-luna-congressional-stock-trading-ban-00673180</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e08e-dbbc-a3fa-f2eed7d90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 14:56:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Anna Paulina Luna is pushing forward with a discharge petition to circumvent Speaker Mike Johnson and force a vote on a <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/house-resolution/725" target="_blank">congressional stock trading ban</a>, she said in an interview Tuesday.</p> 
<p>The politically explosive topic is still divisive among House Republicans, but broadly popular with the public. Luna (R-Fla.) said she's done with waiting around for accountability on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Rep. Tim Burchett (R-Tenn.), who is working on the effort with Luna, agreed many Republicans are “tired” of GOP leaders pushing off the legislation.</p> 
<p>It’s just the latest internal GOP fight Johnson has to deal with. At the same time Luna and Burchett formally launched their discharge petition effort Tuesday afternoon, Johnson faced a revolt among his members on the House floor over a procedural move involving legislation to regulate name, image and likeness compensation in college sports.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thune says abortion language a sticking point in health care talks</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/thune-abortion-language-health-care-00672635</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e002-d51c-a39e-ed0bb5e30005</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 12:02:27 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said Tuesday that while bipartisan discussions are ongoing around the fate of soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies, abortion restrictions are a major sticking point.</p> 
<p>“There are conversations that continue, but as you know the Hyde issue is a difficult and challenging one on both sides,” Thune told reporters.</p> 
<p>The fight over the so-called Hyde Amendment, which bars federal funding for abortion, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/24/congress-republicans-abortion-health-00577631" target="_blank">has been looming over any potential deal</a> to extend the enhanced Obamacare tax credits. And GOP lawmakers, not to mention a cadre of influential anti-abortion groups, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/republicans-trump-obamacare-abortion-00669389" target="_blank">quickly noticed the White House’s framework was silent</a> on the issue.</p> 
<p>The White House ultimately held off on releasing that framework as it faced a mountain of GOP criticism from conservatives who felt caught off guard that Trump would back a two-year extension of the subsidies — even when paired with new income caps and other restrictions.</p> 
<p>The Senate is expected to vote next week on a proposal from Democrats to extend the ACA subsidies, but Democrats haven’t yet detailed what bill they will put on the chamber floor.</p> 
<p>Republicans are separately working on a potential counterproposal that would come from Sens. Mike Crapo and Bill Cassidy, chairs of the Senate Finance and HELP Committees, respectively. GOP senators also have yet to decide whether they’ll roll out that plan in time for a vote next week, though, and the substance remains in flux.</p> 
<p>Sens. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) and Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said Monday night that while efforts to reach a bipartisan agreement persist, many lawmakers believe they are ultimately headed toward a failed vote next week. Some senators are already looking at Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cut-off for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think we’re close to a 60-vote threshold yet,” Thune said of bipartisan health care talks.</p> 
<p>There’s also uncertainty on the other side of the Capitol about how Republicans will respond to the looming expiration of the subsidies, which could cause premiums to skyrocket in the new year. Speaker Mike Johnson told reporters at his weekly press conference that he “didn’t commit to” a short-term extension during a closed-door House GOP members’ meeting Tuesday morning but that “there will be a Republican response to this.”</p> 
<p>“What I’ve got to do is build consensus deliberately around the best ideas,” Johnson said. “We’re pulling those ideas together … I can’t project in advance what that will be because I don’t know what the consensus is in that room.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stefanik accuses Johnson of lying, ‘blocking’ her defense bill provision</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/stefanik-accuses-johnson-lying-00672634</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dff1-d49b-af9f-fff50d260000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 11:43:07 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Elise Stefanik is taking aim directly at Speaker Mike Johnson over signals a provision she has championed won’t be included in the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_DRAFT20" target="_blank">annual defense policy bill</a> the House wants to pass next week — marking a notable and unusual split inside the House GOP leadership team.</p> 
<p>Stefanik, a New York Republican who serves as a member of Johnson’s leadership team, said in <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995856738994565416" target="_blank">a social media post</a> Tuesday morning she would help tank the National Defense Authorization Act if it doesn’t incorporate her provision that would require the FBI to notify Congress when it opens investigations into candidates running for federal office.</p> 
<p>“This is an easy one,” the New York Republican posted on social media Tuesday morning. “This bill is DOA unless this provision gets added in as it was passed out of committee.”</p> 
<p>Stefanik also blamed Johnson for the expected omission.</p> 
<p>“[T]he Speaker is blocking my provision to root out the illegal weaponization that led to Crossfire Hurricane, Arctic Frost, and more,” she wrote on X. “He is siding with Jamie Raskin against Trump Republicans to block this provision to protect the deep state.”</p> 
<p>Stefanik’s proposal, which would require the public disclosure of all “FBI counterintelligence investigations into presidential and federal candidates seeking office,” is designed to combat what many Republicans consider politically motivated investigations related to Russian interference in the 2016 election and former special counsel Jack Smith’s probe into President Donald Trump’s efforts to subvert the election in 2020.</p> 
<p>Asked about whether he thwarted the provision’s inclusion in the NDAA, Johnson said Stefanik’s retelling of events is “false.” He said he supported the provision and that there could still be a path for its passage in some other legislative vehicle.</p> 
<p>“I don’t exactly know why Elise just won’t call me,” he said, recalling that he told his colleague over text, “What are you talking about? This hasn’t even made it to my level.”</p> 
<p>Johnson explained the bipartisan leaders of the House and Senate Judiciary Committees, who he suspected have jurisdiction over this issue, had not agreed to include the language, leading to the provision being dropped from the defense bill. A spokesperson for Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary panel, deferred to Johnson’s explanation.</p> 
<p>Stefanik quickly responded in <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995886289527214190" target="_blank">another post on X</a>, “Just more lies from the Speaker,” while insisting the Intelligence Committee, on which Stefanik sits, has jurisdiction over her provision.</p> 
<p>Leaders of the House and Senate Armed Services Committees have been negotiating the NDAA for weeks and could roll out a compromise package as soon as Thursday; Stefanik said in her social media post that she got early details of that package in an Intelligence Committee briefing.</p> 
<p>The narrow GOP majority in the House means that Johnson can barely afford to lose any Republican support if Democrats reject the legislation en masse, but it’s far from guaranteed Stefanik’s opposition will doom the NDAA on its own.</p> 
<p>While most Democrats opposed the hard-right version of the Pentagon bill the House passed in September, more Democrats might come on board to support a compromise measure and make up for a shortfall of votes on the Republican side of the aisle. The NDAA is typically a broadly bipartisan package.</p> 
<p><i>Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Republicans sweat Tennessee election, despite Hudson’s assurances</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/house-republicans-tennessee-special-election-00672582</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dfa5-d51c-a39e-ffad95540000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 10:20:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders are trying to steady their restive conference as they seek to avert disaster in a Tennessee special election for a ruby-red GOP-controlled seat on Tuesday night.</p> 
<p>NRCC Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/43694" data-person-id="43694">Richard Hudson</a> told House Republicans in their closed-door meeting Tuesday morning that Republican Matt Van Epps will win the race. But he also said members need to remember special elections are special, according to four people in the room, all of whom were granted anonymity to discuss the private meeting.</p> 
<p>National Republicans have had to intervene to attempt to rescue Van Epps from a potential defeat in Tennessee's 7th Congressional District, a conservative stronghold President Donald Trump won by more than 20 points.</p> 
<p>The race between Van Epps and Democrat Aftyn Behn has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/a-nationalized-tennessee-special-election-has-both-parties-on-edge-00671736" target="_blank">attracted millions in outside spending</a> from both sides, despite the typically uncompetitive nature of the district.</p> 
<p>Republicans in the room for Hudson's remarks Tuesday morning, however, did not feel much better about the state of the conference and the special election ahead of next year's midterms.</p> 
<p>"It was not overly comforting," one House Republican who attended the meeting said, noting that some GOP members quietly glanced over at each other as the North Carolina congressman argued a win is a win.</p> 
<p>Another House Republican predicted the GOP conference would spend some time reeling from the fallout of the race, given that it shouldn't have been competitive in the first place.</p> 
<p>“If our victory margin is single digits, the conference may come unhinged,” one senior House Republican said. A loss would be catastrophic and the conference would "explode," the Republican added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: The health care talks to watch</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/health-care-obamacare-bipartisan-deal-talks-murkowski-thune-00672353</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dd5d-d739-a3ba-ddfd49340000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senators will be voting on health care in about a week. Their chances of success are not good.</p> 
<p>The most likely outcome: Two failed votes on competing partisan proposals and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/senate-barrels-toward-failure-on-health-care-00672273" target="_blank">no certain solution</a> to the Affordable Care Act subsidy cliff.</p> 
<p>But that doesn’t mean all is said and done. Senate Republicans and Democrats head into their respective party lunches Tuesday with lots of competing options to discuss. And even after the likely-to-fail Senate votes, talks will continue — with many lawmakers now viewing the Jan. 30 government funding deadline as the real drop-dead date.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said there’s “groundwork being laid that could end up in actually something getting done.”</p> 
<p>Here are the multiple tracks to keep an eye on:</p> 
<p><b>— The Senate Democratic proposal:</b> Expect Democrats to discuss Tuesday what they plan to offer up next week. Most likely is a “clean” extension of the ACA subsidies that few Republicans support, though they could offer GOP-favored eligibility restrictions as an olive branch to conservatives.</p> 
<p><b>— The Senate GOP alternative:</b> Most Republicans expect a “side-by-side” vote with a GOP alternative to the Democratic bill. GOP Sens. Mike Crapo of Idaho and Bill Cassidy of Louisiana are preparing that counterproposal, though it’s unclear what that might include or when it would be introduced.</p> 
<p><b>— The House GOP framework:</b> House leaders have tasked three committees with assembling a package of bills which they are tentatively looking to put on the floor before the chamber’s scheduled Dec. 18 departure for the holiday recess. Don’t expect this to get any Democratic buy-in.</p> 
<p><b>— The House centrists’ plan:</b> Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) told POLITICO Monday he has talked with the White House about a bill he is working on and shopping with like-minded moderates that would largely mirror Presdient Donald Trump’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635" target="_blank">unreleased framework</a>: “It’s one of those things where nobody’s going to love it. But hopefully enough people are okay with it.”</p> 
<p><b>— The Senate bipartisan talks:</b> If a passable product is ever going to emerge, it’s probably coming out of this effort dating back to before the government shutdown involving the likes of Sens. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) and Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska). They are looking to forge compromise on an extension of the subsidies, but there’s not much time left.</p> 
<p>“The calendar is not necessarily our friend right now,” Murkowski said in a brief interview.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Special election fight in Tennessee: </b>Speaker Mike Johnson spent valuable time Monday boosting a Republican candidate in Tuesday’s Tennessee special election as the GOP hopes to shore up its slim House majority. Polling shows Republican Matt Van Epps leading Democrat Aftyn Behn by only single-digit margins, catching the attention of the president and national Republicans as they scramble to hang onto what should be a deep-red district.</p> 
<p><b>— Children’s internet safety hearing: </b>A partisan fight is brewing over whether to include state AI laws in legislation to protect kids’ safety online. A House Energy and Commerce subcommittee will hold a hearing Tuesday on the issue, fulfilling a promise made by committee Chair Brett Guthrie (R-Ky.) to advance kids’ safety legislation.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA text coming Thursday: </b>House Armed Services plans to release text for the National Defense Authorization Act on Thursday, Chair Mike Rogers (R-Ala.) and ranking member Adam Smith (D-Wash.) said Monday night. Rogers said he believes a moratorium on state AI regulation will not make it into the final version of the NDAA, despite an effort from Trump and some GOP leaders to include the language.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Calen Razor, Meredith Lee Hill, Katherine Long and Alfred Ng contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate barrels toward failure on health care</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/senate-barrels-toward-failure-on-health-care-00672273</link>
      <description>A bipartisan breakthrough appears unlikely ahead of next week's scheduled votes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dcd5-d739-a3ba-dcfddb530000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 21:15:29 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/99/93/4b04ee3c4ab39ed43bdb08b353a0/u-s-congress-82476.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) walks to a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 1, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/99/93/4b04ee3c4ab39ed43bdb08b353a0/u-s-congress-82476.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Calen Razor and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Calen Razor and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senators have about a week before they're set to vote on soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies. Most of them already believe the chances for a bipartisan breakthrough by then are roughly zero.</p> 
<p>There’s no clear momentum for any plan that would avoid a lapse in tax credits that could raise insurance premiums for 20 million Americans. House and Senate members involved in the talks said Monday they are still trading ideas, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-health-care-subsidies-congress-00671172" target="_blank">Congress is in the dark</a> about whether President Donald Trump will roll out an 11th-hour framework for an extension, which could help provide a needed boost.</p> 
<p>“Right now, it’s not on a fast track,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198817" data-person-id="198817">Markwayne Mullin</a> (R-Okla.) said about the chances for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>Instead, the most likely outcome is that Senate Democrats put up a bill that has little GOP support for a vote, if any, while Republicans offer a competing bill of their own. And even those partisan proposals remained in flux as lawmakers returned to Washington from a weeklong recess.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), who has been a key figure in the bipartisan negotiations over a potential extension, said that while she still believes there is time to craft a compromise proposal before the vote, it “remains to be seen” if people are willing to move that quickly.</p> 
<p>On a separate track, GOP Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> of Idaho and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana are working behind the scenes on a bill meant to serve as the Republican counterproposal to whatever Democrats offer, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss private deliberations. Aside from the unsettled substance of the bill, when it might be unveiled remains in question.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and two other people familiar with internal conference discussions didn’t rule out a vote on a GOP health care plan next week but would not commit to that timing.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see what the Dems want to put up,” Thune said Monday. “There’s obviously something that we could put up as a side-by-side, neither of which would probably get 60 [votes to advance], but I think in the end you would like to see if there’s a path forward on something that could merge.”</p> 
<p>Some Senate Republicans don’t see the point in forcing a symbolic vote on a GOP counterproposal.</p> 
<p>“I don’t want to take a vote just for the heck of it,” said Mullin, who spoke with Trump about health care last week. ”If we’re going to vote, let’s make sure we do something that’s going to be productive.”</p> 
<p>Health care is expected to be the dominant topic at both Senate party lunches Tuesday. Democrats will use the closed-door meeting to talk through their options, which include offering a “clean” extension of the ACA subsidies — which few Republicans support — or an extension paired with GOP-favored eligibility restrictions as an olive branch to conservatives.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are facing their own dilemma — and internal divisions — over which approach to take. Some, like Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> of Maine and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska, have backed an extension of the subsidies, but a chunk of the Senate GOP conference, to say nothing of their counterparts in the House, want to end the subsidies cold turkey.</p> 
<p>Many Republicans, including Cassidy, are focused on alternatives that would structure federal health care subsidies around health savings accounts, an idea that Trump has also endorsed. But lawmakers agree there is virtually no time to develop and implement such a system before the existing subsidies expire, leading some Republicans to favor a temporary extension.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she is “very hopeful” about the bipartisan talks underway but acknowledged the time pressure: “The calendar is not necessarily our friend right now.”</p> 
<p>Nor, for now, is Trump, who appears to be sitting on the sidelines even as some congressional Republicans are begging him to get involved and sketch out a health care plan that could help unite and energize GOP factions in the House and Senate.</p> 
<p>The president appeared <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">poised to roll out a plan</a> late last month that would extend the ACA subsidies with an income cap and other eligibility restrictions. But the White House scuttled that plan amid a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">mountain of GOP backlash</a>.</p> 
<p>“I think without White House leadership, we're not going to have a well received product,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.), who has backed a temporary extension. “If we produce something in the Senate, it won't be well received in the house unless the president works his magic, which he's very capable of doing.”</p> 
<p>Thune said Monday he doesn’t believe the White House is “advocating for advancing anything at the moment,” while making the point that health care talks could continue past next week’s votes. Lawmakers increasingly view Jan. 30 — the next government funding deadline — as the real cutoff for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>“I think there’s, you know, groundwork being laid that could end up in actually something getting done,” he said. “I just don’t know if it can get done by next week. That’d be a pretty heavy lift.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, House Republicans are on a separate track altogether, with party leaders looking to assemble a suite of health care bills from three committees — Ways and Means, Energy and Commerce, and Education and Workforce. Their plan is less about making law, which would require buy-in from Senate Democrats, and more about showing voters that Republicans have plans to address rising health care costs.</p> 
<p>Under pressure from unhappy GOP centrists, House leaders are tentatively planning to put legislation on the floor before the chamber’s scheduled Dec. 18 departure for the holiday recess. But that could change. The Ways and Means and Energy and Commerce panels are holding listening sessions with Republican members this week, indicating their plans remain in development.</p> 
<p>“We want to get it done as soon as we are ready to get it passed,” Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said in a brief interview Monday.</p> 
<p>Some GOP chairs raised questions and made messaging suggestions on health care during a leadership meeting Monday with Scalise, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the private conversation. One of the people added that there’s still “not a lot of direction” from Republican leaders on the topic, and even conservative Republicans are rankled that no firm proposals are being circulated widely inside the conference with just 11 scheduled session days remaining in the year.</p> 
<p>“We’re nowhere on health care,” said one senior House Republican who was granted anonymity to candidly describe the situation.</p> 
<p>Republican leaders are also under pressure from some House GOP centrists who are threatening to use a discharge petition to effectively force a subsidy extension bill to the floor.</p> 
<p>One of those centrists, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> of Pennsylvania, said Monday he has spoken with the White House about a bill he is working on and shopping around to colleagues, which would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635" target="_blank">largely mirror Trump’s unreleased framework</a>.</p> 
<p>“It's one of those things where nobody's going to love it,” Fitzpatrick said. “But hopefully enough people are okay with it.”</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schumer says his NY offices received 'MAGA' bomb threats</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/01/congress/chuck-schumer-maga-bomb-threats-00671737</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dba0-d51c-a39e-ffa92bbf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 15:51:50 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said Monday his offices in three New York cities received bomb threats via an e-mail titled "MAGA."</p> 
<p>Schumer in a statement said the threats were made against offices in Rochester, Binghamton and Long Island. In addition to the "MAGA" subject line, the emails alleged that the 2020 election was "rigged," the top Senate Democrat said.</p> 
<p>"Everyone is safe, and I am grateful for their quick and professional response to ensure these offices remain safe and secure for all New Yorkers," Schumer said, reporting "full security sweeps" from local and federal law enforcement.</p> 
<p>“As I have said many times, these kinds of violent threats have absolutely no place in our political system. No one—no public servant, no staff member, no constituent, no citizen—should ever be targeted for simply doing their job," he added.</p> 
<p>A U.S. Capitol Police spokesperson declined to comment, saying the department "cannot discuss member security.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Health deal hinges on Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/01/congress/health-care-obamacare-deal-trump-fitzpatrick-00671204</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-d7db-d51c-a39e-ffdb43c30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is back. Welcome to the December of Hellth.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers now have a mere 30 days to address expiring Obamacare tax credits and prevent health insurance hikes for millions of Americans. Republicans and Democrats agree success hangs on one question: Will President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-health-care-subsidies-congress-00671172" target="_blank">figure out what he wants</a>?</p> 
<p>Interpreting Trump’s intentions has gotten tougher since lawmakers left Washington. Early in the break, Trump appeared to be on the brink of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">announcing a framework</a> to extend the Affordable Care Act subsidies with new eligibility restrictions, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">only to pull back</a> after GOP criticism. He then <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/trump-obamacare-subsidy-extension-aca-00669491" target="_blank">said he doesn’t want</a> to extend the subsidies but understands it might be necessary.</p> 
<p>Capitol Hill factions are trying to figure out what Trump wants and how to entice him to their side.</p> 
<p>“The president has got to sign whatever we do, otherwise it’s a legislative exercise,” says Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick, the Pennsylvania Republican who is drafting what he describes as a bipartisan proposal that would largely align with last week’s leaked White House framework.</p> 
<p><b>The timeline as we know it — </b>Though the ACA tax credits expire at month’s end, some lawmakers are looking at Jan. 30, the next shutdown deadline, as the real cutoff for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>The Senate will vote as soon as Dec. 9 on an undefined health care proposal, the fulfillment of the bipartisan deal to reopen the government.</p> 
<p><b>What’s in the works — </b>Fitzpatrick and other centrists are looking to build bipartisan support for an extension of the subsidies with new income restrictions and other safeguards. Their efforts have loose backing from the Republican Main Street Caucus, whose chair Rep. Mike Flood (Neb.) endorsed the contours of the leaked White House health plan.</p> 
<p>A coalition of House and Senate Republicans that includes key committee chairs are working behind the scenes on a range of possible proposals, but there’s no guarantee the GOP will fall in line or the lawmakers will produce a bill this year.</p> 
<p>Senate Finance Chair Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) says he is “working to try to find a pathway to get some bipartisan solution” — not a budget reconciliation bill.</p> 
<p>As a fail-safe, centrist House Republicans are prepared to launch a discharge petition to force a floor vote on a subsidy extension. But they’re also trying to give space to the Senate to see if a bipartisan deal can be reached.</p> 
<p>Democrats have yet to reach a consensus.</p> 
<p>A group of Democrats including Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (N.H.) and Rep. Tom Suozzi (N.Y.) has been in close contact with Republicans including Fitzpatrick and Sen. Lisa Murkowski (Alaska) about what could get bipartisan support. But others, including independent Sen. Bernie Sanders of Vermont, want Democrats to embrace a sweeping health care plan that could be a rallying cry for the midterms but has no chance of winning GOP votes.</p> 
<p>There’s widespread skepticism that Republicans will agree to any plan that isn’t fully endorsed by Trump. A significant swath of GOP lawmakers will simply never vote to extend anything related to Obamacare, according to three GOP aides granted anonymity to discuss internal dynamics.</p> 
<p>“That’s the trouble today,” says Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.). “You can have good-faith negotiations with Republicans, but it just doesn’t matter until Donald Trump weighs in.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— What’s next for appropriations: </b>House GOP appropriators aren’t yet ready to advance the two biggest outstanding funding bills — Defense and Labor-HHS-Education — and are instead rooting for a cross-chamber compromise on several smaller funding measures, with sights on enactment by month’s end.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are also looking for a smaller group of bills that could get signed into law as they continue to pursue a separate minibus that would pair defense funding with Labor-HHS-Education and other bills, according to two aides granted anonymity to disclose internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>Any appropriations bills finalized in the next three weeks would be ripe for hitching to a year-end agreement on health insurance subsidies, should one materialize.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA deal incoming:</b> Lawmakers plan to release the final text of a compromise version of the National Defense Authorization Act this week and tee up a House floor vote as soon as next week, though House and Senate leaders still need to sign off on the final product.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Record-setting personnel issues are marring Trump’s second term</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-nominations-withdrawals-record-00669890</link>
      <description>The president has nearly doubled Joe Biden’s mark for nominees withdrawn from the Senate in the first year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c161-d49b-af9f-f5e52ba40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/09/b2/b66eac514788ac0a8c7d4937bf8f/unlimiteduse-11-10-2025-wh-009.JPG">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Craig Hudson for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Some GOP insiders trace the record pace of nominee withdrawals to the influence of Sergio Gor, left, the former White House personnel chief.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/09/b2/b66eac514788ac0a8c7d4937bf8f/unlimiteduse-11-10-2025-wh-009.JPG" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Alex Gangitano and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Alex Gangitano and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On the surface, President Donald Trump’s second-term personnel operation has been a smoothly running machine. The Senate has confirmed more than 300 civilian nominees since January, even changing the chamber’s rules to move them faster.</p> 
<p>But there are clear signs of breakdowns behind the scenes. Trump has withdrawn a record number of nominees for a president’s first year in office as he faces a combination of GOP pushback against some picks, vetting issues, White House infighting and, in some cases, the president’s own mercurial views.</p> 
<p>Trump has withdrawn 57 nominations, <a href="https://www.congress.gov/quick-search/nominations?wordsPhrases=&amp;wordVariants=on&amp;congressGroups%5B0%5D=0&amp;congresses%5B0%5D=119&amp;nomCivil=on&amp;nomOther=on&amp;pnNumbers=&amp;nomineeNames=&amp;positions=&amp;organizations=&amp;stateTerritories%5B0%5D=any&amp;nominationAction=97&amp;dates=datesReceivedInSenate&amp;dateOperator=after&amp;startDate=01%2F19%2F2025&amp;endDate=&amp;dateIsOption=yesterday" target="_blank">according to Senate data</a> — roughly double the 22 nominations he withdrew during the first year of his first administration and the 29 his immediate predecessor, Joe Biden, withdrew during his first year.</p> 
<p>The pace of withdrawals, the highest since at least the Ronald Reagan presidency, has flown below the radar in the day-to-day churn on Capitol Hill, with many Republican senators expressing surprise at the data in interviews. But they also acknowledged the obvious: In some instances, the White House just isn’t making sure Trump’s nominees can get the votes.</p> 
<p>“It would appear that some nominees haven’t been vetted, and … somebody says, ‘Go with them anyways,’” Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Perhaps the most vivid example was the monthslong intraparty drama over Paul Ingrassia’s nomination to lead the Office of Special Counsel.</p> 
<p>After POLITICO reported he made racist comments in a group chat, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/trump-pulls-ingrassia-nomination-racist-texts-00617041" target="_blank">Ingrassia withdrew</a> despite telling senators he had “no recollection of these alleged chat leaks, and do not concede their authenticity.” But Senate Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/23/how-senate-republican-finally-said-no-to-ingrassia-00619273" target="_blank">had already privately telegraphed</a> to the Trump administration for months that his nomination was in serious peril.</p> 
<p>Asked about the withdrawals, a person close to the White House granted anonymity to speak candidly about internal dynamics pointed to Ingrassia as a key example.</p> 
<p>“Would I say some vetting has been questionable? One thousand percent,” the person said, adding of Ingrassia: “That was a vetting nightmare that was only allowed to happen based on certain relationships and acquaintances with people that are making the decisions.”</p> 
<p>Trump faced similar pushback from Republican senators over Ed Martin’s nomination to be the U.S. attorney in Washington. Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), a key vote on the Judiciary Committee, essentially killed Martin’s nomination after he told the White House that he couldn’t support him over his past defense of accused Capitol rioters. But even before that, Martin <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/ed-martin-senate-confirmation-woes-00322346" target="_blank">was on thin ice</a> with GOP senators.</p> 
<p>A Senate aide who was granted anonymity to speak frankly about White House personnel issues said that in several cases the nominees were being withdrawn not because of issues with GOP senators but intra-administration snags. A White House official, granted anonymity because they were not authorized to speak publicly about the withdrawals, acknowledged the presidential personnel office had recently strengthened its background checks for nominees.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/97/a2/f060e99048ea8979d006c39400bd/trump-washington-prosecutor-23335.jpg" alt="Ed Martin was pulled after it became clear his U.S. attorney nomination would fail in the Senate Judiciary Committee." data-portal-copyright="Amanda Andrade-Rhoades/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Ed Martin was pulled after it became clear his U.S. attorney nomination would fail in the Senate Judiciary Committee."/><p>The person close to the White House said that “not all of these nominations were done so in good faith” under Sergio Gor, who served as the director of the White House Presidential Personnel Office until his confirmation as ambassador to India. The person suggested Gor’s successor as personnel chief, longtime Trump loyalist Dan Scavino, would oversee fewer withdrawals.</p> 
<p>“I think Dan is a little bit wiser and less inclined to give out jobs like candy to people who haven’t earned them or would not pass vetting,” the person added.</p> 
<p>Gor and the U.S. Embassy in India did not return messages seeking comment. The White House official said the 57 withdrawals, which include instances where the same nominee was put forward for multiple positions, were done “for a variety of reasons — clerical changes, new positions or adding new responsibilities to their original role.”</p> 
<p>Frank Bisignano’s nomination for Social Security commissioner, for example, was withdrawn and immediately resubmitted to the Senate in January.</p> 
<p>The official added that Trump is nominating new individuals at a “record pace” and noted he has gotten more nominees confirmed at this point than he did during his first term or than Biden did by this point.</p> 
<p>Republicans were already confirming Trump nominees at a faster clip than in his first administration. But in September they enacted a party-line rules change, allowing most nominees to now be confirmed in groups of unlimited size. One <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/senate-resolution/377/text" target="_blank">group of 108</a> was confirmed in September; a <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/senate-resolution/412/text" target="_blank">group of 48 more</a> followed in October.</p> 
<p>Tillis, who described himself as surprised by the total number of nominees withdrawn, pointed to Trump’s fast pace in making nominations as one possible reason for the sloppy vetting.</p> 
<p>“Obviously, when you move more quickly and you’ve got new folks in play, then you are going to run into people who have lifestyle issues,” Tillis said, adding that he believes only “outliers” have run into issues in the Senate.</p> 
<p>Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.), who like Tillis expressed surprise at the number of nominees withdrawn, added that “part of our responsibility is advise and consent.”</p> 
<p>“And sometimes the advice is to maybe reconsider something,” Rounds said. “You don't have to make a big deal out of it, but you can share that with the administration. And sometimes they take a second look at the nominee, and they say, ‘You know, yeah, you're right.’”</p> 
<p>Asked about the withdrawals, White House spokesperson Liz Huston said in a statement that Trump is “nominating the most talented patriots to successfully carry out his America First agenda.”</p> 
<p>“Under President Trump’s leadership, these appointees are delivering on his core campaign promises in record time from securing the border, ending Joe Biden’s inflation crisis, unleashing American energy, and restoring common sense policies,” she added.</p> 
<p>While Martin and Ingrassia are two high-profile examples of nominees running aground in the Senate, there have been other quieter examples — including Joel Rayburn, who had been nominated to be an assistant secretary of State but <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/27/us/politics/trump-middle-east-state-department-nominee-rayburn.html" target="_blank">faced fierce public opposition</a> from Sen. Rand Paul (R-Ky.).<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ec/57/c909c49844a598c4338397a8e547/prosecutor-firings-93313.jpg" alt="Activist Laura Loomer took credit for Trump's recent backtrack on his pick for IRS chief counsel." data-portal-copyright="Chris Szagola/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Activist Laura Loomer took credit for Trump's recent backtrack on his pick for IRS chief counsel."/><p>Trump has also withdrawn nominees for his own reasons. He abruptly withdrew Rep. Elise Stefanik’s nomination to be the U.S. ambassador to the United Nations earlier this year amid concerns about how the New York Republican’s departure would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/13/elise-stefanik-united-nations-delay-00204172" target="_blank">trim the House majority</a>. He later pulled Jared Isaacman's nomination to lead NASA over his "prior associations," <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/trump-nominates-isaacman-nasa-administrator-00636497" target="_blank">only to renominate him</a> five months later.</p> 
<p>Late last month, he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-pulls-nominee-for-top-irs-post-who-drew-conservative-activists-ire-00652355" target="_blank">withdrew Donald Korb’s nomination</a> as top IRS lawyer after a pressure campaign led by right-wing activist Laura Loomer. She publicly boasted that Korb had been “Loomered” after Trump’s announcement.</p> 
<p>Others have been snagged by the blue-slip precedent, which allows home-state senators to effectively block district court and U.S. attorney nominees. For instance, Democratic Sens. Cory Booker and Andy Kim refused to return a blue slip for Alina Habba, who was nominated to be U.S. attorney for New Jersey. Trump withdrew her nomination and attempted to place her in the role as an acting U.S. attorney, which sparked a legal battle.</p> 
<p>Trump is so far standing by other nominees subject to blue-slip objections, and he is pressuring Senate Judiciary Committee Chair Chuck Grassley to get rid of the practice altogether. Republicans did away with it for appeals court judicial nominees during Trump’s first term, but Grassley and many other GOP senators remain opposed to a wholesale elimination.</p> 
<p>Trump told Senate Republicans last month that he ousted one official after finding out that he had been backed by Virginia’s Democratic senators. Trump recently withdrew nominations for Todd Gilbert, whom he had nominated to be U.S. attorney for the Western District of Virginia, and Erik Siebert, who had been nominated to be U.S. attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia.</p> 
<p>“I had one Republican who got two great letters, but it turned out that he was a RINO,” Trump said during a White House breakfast with senators. “When I saw that the two senators from Virginia gave him glowing remarks … I said let me see this, I read the most beautiful letters I’ve ever seen. I called him up; I said, ‘Sorry, you’re fired — get the hell out of here.’”</p> 
<p><i>Dasha Burns contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Time is not our friend’: Health care scramble begins amid mixed signals from Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-health-care-subsidies-congress-00671172</link>
      <description>The president injected more uncertainty last week, saying he doesn’t want to extend key insurance subsidies but understands it might be necessary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-d704-d51c-a39e-ff0db51a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8a/f5/3990712f4fe78084f263da013241/house-of-representatives-19187.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) said President Donald Trump has to endorse any health plan Congress pursues, "otherwise it’s a legislative exercise."</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8a/f5/3990712f4fe78084f263da013241/house-of-representatives-19187.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress returns to session Monday and kicks off a December sprint to address expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies and prevent health insurance premium hikes for millions of Americans.</p> 
<p>Members of both parties acknowledge success hangs on one question: Will President Donald Trump ever figure out what he wants?</p> 
<p>Since lawmakers left town 10 days ago, the picture has only grown foggier. Early in their holiday break, Trump appeared to be on the precipice of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">announcing a framework</a> to temporarily extend the Obamacare subsidies with new eligibility restrictions, only to pull back after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">mountain of internal GOP criticism</a>.</p> 
<p>In his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/trump-obamacare-subsidy-extension-aca-00669491" target="_blank">only comments on the matter</a>, Trump injected more uncertainty last week, saying he doesn’t want to extend the subsidies but understands it might be necessary.</p> 
<p>The mixed signals have left the various factions on Capitol Hill trying to figure out where Trump will ultimately come down — and how to entice the president to back their side in a thorny policy fight that could have major political consequences in next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>“The president has got to sign whatever we do, otherwise it’s a legislative exercise,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.), who is drafting what he describes as a bipartisan proposal that would largely align with the leaked White House framework.</p> 
<p>But Fitzpatrick and other lawmakers are quickly running out of time to pin Trump down. The Senate will vote next week, as soon as Dec. 9, on a health care proposal. It’s unclear what will be in the bill, but it’s the fulfillment of a promise Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> made to Democrats as part of a deal to end the 43-day government shutdown.</p> 
<p>“The question is, how quickly can something come together?” Thune said before leaving Washington for Thanksgiving.</p> 
<p>Or as Fitzpatrick put it: “Time is not our friend.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and other centrists are looking to build bipartisan support for an extension of the subsidies, a priority for Democrats, with new income restrictions and other safeguards, which are a priority for Republicans. Their efforts have loose backing from the Republican Main Street Caucus, whose chair, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196030" data-person-id="196030">Mike Flood</a> of Nebraska, quickly endorsed the contours of the leaked White House framework last week.</p> 
<p>But others in the GOP want to pursue a more radical overhaul of Obamacare, with Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> of Florida pitching the president on plans centered around individual spending accounts. Scott even termed his vision as “Trump Health Freedom Accounts.”</p> 
<p>Trump has kept Congress in limbo as lawmakers try to figure out what he will support. Republicans spent much of November thinking the president was turning away from extending the tax credits, only to be blindsided by news that the White House framework would do just that.</p> 
<p>Most House and Senate Republicans, including senior members of leadership, learned details of the tentative White House proposal — and how quickly it could be rolled out — from media reports, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">including POLITICO’s</a>. Their objections prompted the White House to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">scuttle the rollout</a>.</p> 
<p>A House Republican granted anonymity to discuss internal conference thinking acknowledged that it would have been “wiser” if the Trump administration had consulted directly with Hill GOP leaders before word of the framework leaked out.</p> 
<p>The GOP lawmaker added that Trump “cannot please everyone” with any health plan.</p> 
<p>“Most took it as a good sign that the [White House] initially accepted a modified extension,” the lawmaker said. “Yes, a subset complained, but I think they’re in the minority.”</p> 
<p>Getting an extension of the subsidies through the House and Senate, not to mention Trump, will require navigating a political obstacle course.</p> 
<p>For one, the framework was silent on new abortion restrictions, which are a key demand for many Republicans and a deal-break for many Democrats.</p> 
<p>“We’re not going to allow public funds to be used for funding abortion,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/221844" data-person-id="221844">Mike Rounds</a> (R-S.D.) told reporters before Thanksgiving.</p> 
<p>While much of the GOP backlash to Trump’s unreleased framework was about how lawmakers found out about it, there’s a significant swath of Republicans who will simply never vote to extend anything related to Obamacare, according to three GOP aides granted anonymity to discuss internal dynamics.</p> 
<p>In addition to the Scott and Cassidy plans, a coalition of House and Senate Republicans that includes key committee chairs are working behind the scenes on a range of possible health care proposals, but there’s no guarantee the GOP will fall in line behind the plans or whether the lawmakers will even produce a bill this year.</p> 
<p>As a fail-safe, House GOP centrists are preparing to launch a discharge petition to force a floor vote on a subsidy extension. But they are also trying to give space to the Senate to see if a bipartisan deal can be reached, according to two Republicans granted anonymity to discuss the talks.</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers are already looking at Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cutoff for a health care deal, even though the credits would have expired by then. And some hard-liners want GOP leaders to embrace a party-line approach <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">amid widespread skepticism</a> among their colleagues that’s even doable.</p> 
<p>Senate Finance Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> (R-Idaho), whose committee shares oversight of the ACA, said he is “working to try to find a pathway to get some bipartisan solution” — not a partisan, filibuster-skirting bill Republicans could pursue under the budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>“There are a lot of things going on,” he said. Crapo added that even if the promised Senate vote fails, “We will need to be continuing to work … with our colleagues on both sides of the aisle to try to find some broader health care solutions.”</p> 
<p>Democrats were initially buoyed by news that Trump was preparing to endorse an extension of the subsidies, despite the eligibility restrictions, believing that it was a good sign that he was even thinking about it. But that optimism faded after witnessing the Republican backlash.</p> 
<p>They have their own internal divisions over what their own strategy should be as the clock ticks. Senate Democrats, as part of the agreement with Thune, will get to decide what proposal they vote on. But they haven’t yet come to consensus and are expected to use a Tuesday caucus lunch to discuss their options.</p> 
<p>A group of Democrats, including Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> of New Hampshire and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259491" data-person-id="259491">Tom Suozzi</a> of New York, has been in close contact with Republican lawmakers including Fitzpatrick and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska about what could get bipartisan support. But others, such as independent Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51605" data-person-id="51605">Bernie Sanders</a> of Vermont, want Democrats to instead embrace a sweeping health care plan that would have no chance of winning GOP votes but would give them a rallying point heading into the midterm elections.</p> 
<p>That divide has haunted congressional Democrats since January as they’ve repeatedly struggled to unify at key moments. There’s also widespread skepticism that Republicans will ever agree to any health care plan that isn’t fully endorsed by Trump.</p> 
<p>“That’s the trouble today: You can have good-faith negotiations with Republicans, but it just doesn’t matter until Donald Trump weighs in,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a> (D-Conn.). “The pollsters have obviously told them that they are going to get their clocks cleaned if they don’t fix the health care mess they created. They may hate the ACA and Barack Obama so much they are willing to lose an election.”</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forget Mamdani. New York’s real political shift happened everywhere else.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/28/new-york-upstate-blue-wave-mamdani-00668749</link>
      <description>Democrats flipped over 50 county legislative seats across the state. Republicans flipped one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bcd5-d49b-af9f-bcf507bd0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 09:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/03/f6/70eca5c8449e90fed1da5dc39a54/unlimiteduse-electionday-ny-11-04-2025-063.JPG">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Bing Guan for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A voter deposits their ballot into a ballot counting machine at a polling site inside P.S. 20 in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York, on Electio Day, Nov. 4, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/03/f6/70eca5c8449e90fed1da5dc39a54/unlimiteduse-electionday-ny-11-04-2025-063.JPG" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Bill Mahoney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Bill Mahoney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Zohran Mamdani’s decisive win in New York City — along with key victories in New Jersey and Virginia — suggested Democrats are headed into the midterms from a position of strength. But they didn’t capture how deep that strength ran.</p> 
<p>Across suburbs, rural counties and small towns in New York, Democrats posted electoral gains that rival — and in many cases surpass — the party’s 2017 “Blue Wave.” In a state with enough competitive House races to decide control of the chamber, the outcome amounts to a wakeup call for already-wary Republicans.</p> 
<p>New York Democrats once viewed the 2017 elections as among their best ever. The Blue Wave that year was driven by purple suburbs making a hard shift left. This year in New York, that tilt was felt even more widely — with Democrats in every corner of the state pointing to economic uncertainty exacerbated by President Donald Trump’s policies as voters’ top concern.</p> 
<p>“It was about peoples’ anxiety,” said Leslie Berliant, who ousted a Republican incumbent to win a seat in the Otsego County Legislature. “It definitely was a feeling that we don’t feel protected by what’s happening in the federal government, and we need to make sure we have people in place at the local level who care about our needs. Democrats ran on that, and I think it worked.”</p> 
<p>Much of the early narrative from this fall’s elections has cast Democrats’ gains as occurring mostly in places where they often win. An examination of every race on the ballot in New York shows the shift was far more widespread, with Democrats having their best-ever performances in numerous deep red towns and rural areas.</p> 
<p>There’s still plenty of time for conditions to change before the 2026 midterms. But a year out, this year’s contests offered very little solace for Republicans as they prep for seven battleground congressional races in New York and a gubernatorial election in which they hope to build on the rightward momentum of the 2022 and 2024 elections.</p> 
<p>A POLITICO review of results in 268 county, town and village executive branch races found an average 10 point increase in the Democratic margin.</p> 
<p>Democrats made gains in at least 18 different county legislative bodies in November, flipping over 50 seats across the Empire State. They gained five seats in Oswego County, which Trump won by 27 points in 2024. They picked up five in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history. And they flipped five in Onondaga and gained their first majority there since the 1970s.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/2e/42/1c9870ba4f8a91b982bf30d4b66a/ap9724584833457619.jpg" alt="Shown above, New Paltz in Ulster County. Democrats picked up five seats in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history" data-portal-copyright=" Historic Hotels of America and Mohonk Mountain House via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Shown above, New Paltz in Ulster County. Democrats picked up five seats in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history"/><p>For Republicans, the outcome painted a bleak picture: GOP candidates flipped one county legislative seat in the entire state.</p> 
<p>Democrats who won these local contests shared similar stories about what they saw on the ground. Trump voters didn’t necessarily throw their MAGA hats into bonfires. But economic anxiety persists in every corner of the state. And Republican voters feeling the pinch — whether over federal cuts, tariffs, or inflation — are now at least willing to hear a pitch from Democrats.</p> 
<p>In the town of Erwin, just north of the Pennsylvania border, Democrat Debbie Shannon ousted Republican Steuben County Legislator James Kuhl, the son of a former congressman.</p> 
<p>“I knocked on everyone’s door, and the economy is the big hot button issue,” Shannon said. “Especially for Republicans who said Trump ran on ‘I’m going to lower the price of eggs,’ and that isn’t happening. I think they’re breaking with the administration.”</p> 
<p>This November was only the second time since 1989 that Democrats won mayoral races in each of the state’s five largest cities. Sharon Owens was the first Democrat elected Syracuse’s mayor in 12 years, Sean Ryan received the most votes in a contested Buffalo race since 1981, and Mamdani received more votes than any Democratic nominee in New York City since at least 1965.</p> 
<p>Democratic performance in places that were once untouchable Republican strongholds is perhaps more notable when looking ahead to next year. Consider, for example, the Rochester suburbs: Penfield elected a Democratic supervisor for the first time in four decades, Greece for the first time in 120 years, and Perinton for the first time <a href="https://www.democratandchronicle.com/story/news/politics/elections/2025/11/05/monroe-county-ny-election-takeaways-from-2025/87098791007/" target="_blank">since the Civil War</a>.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/76/a4/2a3681d04783be8a1a4780c9a816/2024-election-61546.jpg" alt="Voters cast their ballots at the Susan B. Anthony Museum & House in Rochester in 2024." data-portal-copyright="Lauren Petracca/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Voters cast their ballots at the Susan B. Anthony Museum & House in Rochester in 2024."/><p>Democrats also flipped mayoral or supervisor offices in places like Tonawanda, Oneonta, Monroe, Rensselaer, Johnson City and Riverhead.</p> 
<p>All told, there were 118 municipal executive races outside of New York City this year that were contested in either 2021 or 2023. The number of ballots cast for Democrats grew from 1.3 million to 1.6 million, a 22 percent increase. The number for Republicans grew 1 percent to 1.6 million.</p> 
<p>That means that while the typical upstate or Long Island Democrat lost by 10 points in the last go-around, they received 50 percent of the vote this year.</p> 
<p>Even in places where Republicans had good nights, there’s little evidence of a broader rightward shift. Republicans made gains in Saratoga Springs, but not as many as Democrats made in the larger, neighboring town of Clifton Park. Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman won big in his reelection campaign. But Democrats improved on their performance in 17 of the other 21 executive offices on the ballot on Long Island. And in the other major suburban county, Westchester’s Ken Jenkins had the best performance by a Democratic county executive candidate in two decades.</p> 
<p>The Democratic gains were thus much broader than those in 2017. The following year, New York Democrats flipped three congressional seats, and the number of people voting for Andrew Cuomo in the gubernatorial contest grew 76 percent in 2018 compared with 2014.</p> 
<p>All of that is promising to Democrats like Gov. Kathy Hochul who are on the ballot in 2026. The Republican path to a statewide victory involves running up the numbers in red parts of the state, doing well in suburban towns and minimizing the Democratic margin in New York City. All three of those need to happen in 2026 for a GOP win to be plausible in statewide contests — and this November, none of them did.</p> 
<p>But there were also hints of an anti-establishment trend mixed in with the leftward shift — and certainly more than a glimmer of that in New York City. That trend makes forecasting Hochul’s fate a little less clear come next June or November.</p> 
<p>Not everybody who won said they did so by running on a Democratic platform. Candidates in the rural North Country, for example, attempted to outdo each other in criticizing Hochul’s handling of <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2025/02/25/kathy-hochul-prison-crisis-corrections-officers-00206033" target="_blank">a prison strike</a> earlier this year.</p> 
<p>Voters are looking “for leadership that kind of ignores traditional party stances,” said Lebanon Supervisor-elect Adam Carvell, who noted he wasn’t focused on purely partisan issues before receiving 63 percent of the vote as a Democrat in a town where Trump received 60 percent last year. The electorate, he said, wasn’t just bothered by the White House’s actions, but policies <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/05/democratic-lawmaker-readies-clean-car-delay-proposal-00336271" target="_blank">supported by</a> the sitting Democratic governor, such as an electric vehicle mandate.</p> 
<p>“The municipal electrical vehicle mandate that was coming down, it’s a Hochul thing,” said Carvell. “The boots-on-the-ground take on that here is that’s unworkable … The idea of introducing very expensive, hard to maintain [electric snow plows] scared a lot of people.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/96/8b/b891625e4ff8be183e7d56d48fd9/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2246393039" alt="New York Gov. Kathy Hochul speaks at a ribbon-cutting ceremony at the National Urban League's new headquarters in Harlem on Nov. 12, 2025, where she was joined by New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani." data-portal-copyright="Spencer Platt/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="New York Gov. Kathy Hochul speaks at a ribbon-cutting ceremony at the National Urban League's new headquarters in Harlem on Nov. 12, 2025, where she was joined by New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani."/><p>Yet even the candidates who eschewed strict partisanship repeatedly highlighted the federal government and its role in the economy as the top concern on voters’ minds.</p> 
<p>Don Dabiew, who won a seat in Franklin County’s Legislature, pointed to a hit to Canadian tourism.</p> 
<p>“Almost all the small towns around are seeing an impact of that because people aren’t coming across anymore,” Dabew said. “There’s some people that are upset with our country as a whole, and they don’t want to support us anymore.”</p> 
<p>In Canandaigua, mayor-elect Thomas Lyon highlighted federal cuts.</p> 
<p>“DOGE was eliminating jobs left and right,” he said. “The national veterans’ suicide hotline is located here in Canandaigua at our VA, and you had people losing their jobs, not being able to provide support to our veterans.”</p> 
<p>Even in local elections where partisanship wasn’t rampant, Democrats said the current frustrations about the country as a whole are opening doors that hadn’t been open before.</p> 
<p>“We listened and said, ‘We’re not talking about federal politics here; we’re talking about right here, right now, our town,’” said Lisa Moore, who won the South Bristol supervisor’s race.</p> 
<p>“A lot of people were just so sick and tired of the divisiveness at the federal level, and the sort of miserableness, that they were happy to not demonize Democrats, as Democrats have been demonized in our town in the past.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-26T21:55:06-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>White House presses Congress for drone powers ahead of World Cup, Olympics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/white-house-asks-congress-for-power-to-take-down-drones-00670564</link>
      <description>The administration is facing resistance from GOP leadership of the Senate Commerce Committee.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c2fc-d739-a3ba-defcd0910001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 20:46:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ad/c8afee09486f9e9a81622a73d0d8/white-house-80173.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump walks on the South Lawn of the White House after disembarking from Marine One Nov. 2, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ad/c8afee09486f9e9a81622a73d0d8/white-house-80173.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House is pressing lawmakers to give the administration more power to take down aerial drones in domestic airspace in advance of the U.S. hosting the 2026 World Cup and 2028 Olympic games, according to three people involved in ongoing negotiations.</p> 
<p>The push to attach the measure to a must-pass defense policy bill in the coming weeks is facing resistance on Capitol Hill, including from the Senate Commerce Committee led by Sen. Ted Cruz, amid concerns the proposal constitutes federal overreach. The Commerce panel has jurisdiction over aviation affairs.</p> 
<p>Draft <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-c28a-df0f-abfa-e3eabde50000" target="_blank"><u>legislation floated by the White House</u></a> and obtained by POLITICO would give agencies including the Departments of Homeland Security and Justice new authority to take counter-drone measures for “large scale public gatherings or events, critical infrastructure or correctional facilities.” The proposal would also broaden “counter-drone authority” for state and local law enforcement.</p> 
<p>Under current law, federal agencies are empowered to intervene against drone threats only when specific, high-risk facilities, including government operations and power plants, are deemed to be at risk.</p> 
<p>The push comes as the leaders of the House and Senate Armed Services Committees are trying to finalize the text of the defense bill by early next week. Spokespeople for the Republican chairs and top Democrats on the committees did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>The White House request of Congress is the administration’s latest move to ramp up security ahead of the World Cup and Olympic games. The administration announced earlier this month it was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/13/drone-defenses-world-cup-00606174" target="_blank"><u>launching a $500 million program</u></a> to help state and local governments develop anti-drone strategies ahead of the events as well as any celebrations that might take place around the 250th anniversary of the signing of the Declaration of Independence.</p> 
<p>“This is an important issue we must address as we prepare for global events such as the World Cup and the Olympics, and we need to ensure proper authorities are in place to protect the American people,” said a House GOP leadership aide granted anonymity to discuss the negotiations.</p> 
<p>A White House official granted anonymity to describe ongoing deliberations said the White House Office of Legislative Affairs has been working on legislative language and circulating related proposals among congressional offices since September. The administration has been working closely with Speaker Mike Johnson’s office on the legislative draft and has also engaged with Senate Majority Leader John Thune’s office, according to the official.</p> 
<p>“It’s something that the admin feels is extremely important given particularly all of the events of the next year,” the White House official said. “Having a strong strong event infrastructure and drone counter-measures is very important.”</p> 
<p>It’s unclear if Congress will adopt the plan. A person granted anonymity to discuss private negotiations said Senate Commerce views the draft provision as an “extremely problematic” power grab that would give federal security officials too much leeway in determining how best to “protect the public."</p> 
<p>Phoebe Keller, a spokesperson for Cruz on the Commerce Committee, said in a statement, “We are happy to work with the administration on this proposal and any suggestion to the contrary is simply untrue."</p> 
<p>Sen. Eric Schmitt, a Missouri Republican on Senate Commerce, also supports tougher counter-drone legislation. Kansas City, Mo., is scheduled to host six World Cup matches next year.</p> 
<p>“Unauthorized drones pose a clear risk to Americans and our homeland, and it’s time Congress acts and shows more urgency,” Schmitt spokesperson Rachel Dumke said in a statement. “Senator Schmitt looks forward to continuing to work with his colleagues to find a path forward.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Trump targeting these Democrats could backfire</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/democrats-trump-sedition-backfire-00670552</link>
      <description>The administration’s attacks have elevated the six moderate lawmakers who cut an anti-Trump video urging troops to disobey illegal orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c255-d49b-af9f-f6f549780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 18:03:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d8/77/689cf1054421aafa8a8228245780/main-wu-brakkton-demssedition.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Claudine Hellmuth/POLITICO (source images via AP)</media:credit>
        <media:title>From left to right: Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), Rep. Chris Deluzio (D-Pa.), Rep. Chrissy Houlahan (D-Pa.), Sen. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.), Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) and Rep. Maggie Goodlander (D-N.H.)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d8/77/689cf1054421aafa8a8228245780/main-wu-brakkton-demssedition.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump is going to war with Democrats over the military. It could backfire on him.</p> 
<p>The president’s attacks on six Democrats who recorded a video encouraging military members to buck unlawful orders are elevating members of a faction that just delivered big off-year wins for their party. Most hail from swing states or districts, identify as centrists and are leveraging their national security backgrounds to argue that Democrats can retake the patriotic lane.</p> 
<p>Trump is also boosting some potential 2028 presidential hopefuls, Arizona Sen. Mark Kelly and Michigan Sen. Elissa Slotkin, while further undercutting the GOP’s attempts to make New York progressives like Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani and Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez the face of the Democratic Party.</p> 
<p>“Pete Hegseth and Donald Trump are providing Mark Kelly with the kind of visibility that almost no amount of money could buy,” said Barrett Marson, an Arizona-based Republican strategist, referring to the Defense secretary who ordered an investigation of Kelly. “Every 2028 contender wishes they could be attacked like this by the Trump administration.”</p> 
<p>Since Trump accused the six of “sedition” and even suggested they could be executed, they’ve racked up millions of views on social media, done the cable news circuit and blasted out fundraising appeals highlighting the attacks.</p> 
<p>It’s heightened the stature of even those who have already been the subject of speculation about their 2028 aspirations. Kelly, who was on the short list to be Vice President Kamala Harris’ running mate last year, has already <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/west-wing-playbook-remaking-government/2025/07/23/reviews-are-in-on-the-first-2028-dem-hopefuls-00471732" target="_blank">visited a raft of early primary</a> and general-election battleground states this year. But only after Trump’s attack was he invited on “Jimmy Kimmel Live!” this week.</p> 
<p>In recent months, Slotkin has been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/24/slotkin-has-a-war-plan-to-beat-trump-dont-be-weak-and-woke-00308176" target="_blank">testing what she calls a “war plan”</a> to “contain and defeat Donald Trump” in speeches outside of her state, meeting with <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook/2025/11/14/slotkin-finds-dems-at-a-crossroads-00651647" target="_blank">low-propensity voters</a> and theorizing about what she calls “Project 2029.” Now she’s brought those themes to a series of interviews and public appearances over the past week.</p> 
<p>As Democrats debate how far to lean into themes of patriotism more often claimed by conservatives, a group of lawmakers organized by Slotkin released a <a href="https://x.com/ElissaSlotkin/status/1978930764692455430?s=20" target="_blank">video with anti-authoritarian themes</a> ahead of the “No Kings” protests last month. A <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2558895077819811" target="_blank">follow-up video last week</a> called on troops not to obey unlawful orders, prompting Trump’s explosion.</p> 
<p>The president posted on social media they were committing “SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL” by suggesting military members ignore their chain of command and shared a post calling for traitors to be hanged. The White House later denied Trump was threatening the lawmakers with death. Since then, the Pentagon has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894?" target="_blank">opened an investigation</a> into Kelly, who is a retired Navy captain, and the six lawmakers claim the FBI <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/democrats-fbi-trump-00668584" target="_blank">has made inquiries</a> through congressional authorities.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/9c/cc/3f39da1f4b4a8b675b81bf61bdc9/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2162570114" alt="Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), another Democrat with a military background, said " data-portal-copyright="Samuel Corum/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), another Democrat with a military background, said "/><p>Democrats, particularly those with military backgrounds, have leapt to their colleagues’ defense, echoing their message about following the law and accusing Trump of weaponizing the government against his political opponents.</p> 
<p>“Trump knows that we’re a threat” to Republicans’ grip on Washington, said Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), a military veteran whose Serve America PAC supports several of the Democrats in the video. “These are great leaders who can take the fight to Trump and MAGA.”</p> 
<p>“It’s classic Trump — he ratchets everything up to an 11 and it blows up in his face,” said Austin Cook, a Democratic strategist and former Slotkin spokesperson. “Not only did it reinforce everything swing voters have always hated about him, but it’s also given this group the biggest megaphone they’ve ever had.”</p> 
<p>But Tim Edson, a GOP strategist and former political director for the National Republican Senatorial Committee, said the video will only confirm the GOP base’s preconceived, negative views of Democratic officials.</p> 
<p>“Republicans believe these Democrats are deranged with hatred of Trump, and it’s just their latest attempt to undermine lawful policies simply because they’re Trump’s policies,” Edson said. “These embarrassing antics only rally Republicans to the president.”</p> 
<p>Some Democrats think it’s too early to tell how things will shake out for the “seditious six,” as some Trump officials are <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/video/6385589967112" target="_blank">calling the lawmakers</a>.</p> 
<p>“Whether it works or not will depend on what comes next, if an illegal order actually does come down they get to be leaders saying ‘I told you so,’” texted one strategist who has consulted for Democratic veterans and was granted anonymity to speak candidly. “If one doesn’t, they’ve simply made themselves victims to Trump’s latest attacks. Most Democrats fail at playing on his turf.”</p> 
<p>Kelly doubled down on the video’s message during his talk-show appearance Tuesday night and noted some of his Republican colleagues are expressing support: “People are starting to take a look at this and saying, ‘Wow, this is just nuts that he's going after U.S. senators and members of the House for something they said.’”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
