<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:16:33 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-17T18:30:40-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>The day Brian Fitzpatrick finally said enough</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-discharge-petition-00696644</link>
      <description>The purple-district Pennsylvanian had staked out an aisle-crossing persona without impeding GOP prerogatives. Until Wednesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2e92-d369-affb-6fbe94d30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:16:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/05/bb/f20d5791449f958f50f5e7898320/u-s-congress-97689.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I’ve made it clear where this was all headed,” Fitzpatrick said Wednesday. “This was never a secret.”</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/05/bb/f20d5791449f958f50f5e7898320/u-s-congress-97689.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Brian Fitzpatrick, the five-term House Republican and perennial campaign target for Democrats, has long been viewed by GOP leaders as a team player. Until now.</p> 
<p>On Wednesday, his 52nd birthday, the congenial Pennsylvanian led a GOP mutiny against Speaker Mike Johnson over his handling of expiring Obamacare subsidies used by more than 20 million Americans. Fitzpatrick became the first Republican to back a Democratic-led effort to sidestep the speaker and force action on an extension of the tax credits. Three fellow GOP moderates quickly followed, cementing a January vote.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, who has consistently won re-election in one of the most competitive districts in the country, said in an interview the rebellion should have come as no surprise to Johnson.</p> 
<p>“I’ve made it clear where this was all headed,” he said Wednesday. “This was never a secret.”</p> 
<p>But it stunned many who have watched Fitzpatrick maneuver over the past decade, staking out an aisle-crossing persona while also being careful not to impede leadership prerogatives. He voted at several key junctures to advance the GOP’s party-line megabill this year, for instance, while eventually <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/brian-fitzpatrick-trump-megabill-obbba-00439788" target="_blank">voting against its final passage</a>.</p> 
<p>Now he is earning some begrudging praise from Democrats for, they say, finally walking the bipartisan walk instead of just talking the talk.</p> 
<p>“It was politically the smart thing for him to do in such a challenging district, but it also is a courageous thing, and I want to acknowledge that,” said Rep. Greg Stanton (D-Ariz.).</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick’s decision to embrace a discharge petition filed by House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries has infuriated allies of Johnson, however, who argue that he is merely scrambling for political cover after moving too late to prevent a Dec. 31 lapse in the subsidies.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman (R-S.C.), a House Rules Committee member, blasted the “horrible” move from Fitzpatrick and allies and said he would try to kill the effort in the panel.</p> 
<p>“I’ll do everything I can to block it,” he said.</p> 
<p>Wednesday morning’s drama was the culmination of weeks of mostly behind-the-scenes wrangling between a small group of moderate House Republicans and party leaders, who knew that there was a limited appetite in the GOP ranks for any sort of extension for the Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>As co-chair of the centrist Problem Solvers Caucus, Fitzpatrick was at the middle of those contentious dealings as he sought to build support for a two-year extension of the subsidies that would also include new eligibility restrictions and anti-fraud guardrails. But the effort was caught between Democratic leaders who wanted their members to unite behind a straight three-year extension and GOP leaders who wanted none at all.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick last week filed a discharge petition for his two-year proposal, drawing a dozen GOP colleagues but limited buy-in from Democrats. Jeffries wanted his own discharge petition on a three-year bill — which already had 214 Democratic signatures — to remain the most viable option to force a House vote.</p> 
<p>At the same time, Johnson was moving to assemble a much more limited response to the expiring subsidies — a bill that would tinker around the edges of the insurance markets but do nothing to extend the subsidies.</p> 
<p>When a POLITICO reporter informed Fitzpatrick last week that his GOP leadership was working on a health care framework that would not include a subsidy extension, he accused GOP leaders of living in a “fantasyland” and suggested Republicans would be hurting their own constituents for ideological reasons.</p> 
<p>“These are people that we care about — these are our friends and neighbors that are receiving these subsidies,” Fitzpatrick said. “This is a personal thing for me.”</p> 
<p>In the days that followed, a group of moderates that included Fitzpatrick as well as Reps. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.), Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.), Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.), Nick LaLota (R-N.Y.) and others sought to cut a deal that would allow some sort of a House vote on a subsidy extension.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders, Fitzpatrick said, denied their requests to take one of their compromise measures directly to the floor. They were encouraged to file an amendment to the Johnson-backed health bill with the Rules Committee, but making their measures comply with GOP conference requirements became “unnecessarily complicated,” he said, as they forged ahead.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s allies counter that Fitzpatrick and the GOP moderates weren’t completely united and simply couldn’t deliver on the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/fitzpatrick-declines-to-turn-off-aca-discharge-petition-as-amendment-talks-drag-on-00694065" target="_blank">basic criteria</a> Johnson laid out to strike a deal for an amendment. The speaker himself told reporters Tuesday, “I thought there was an agreement on the Fitzpatrick amendment and then they made different decisions.”</p> 
<p>Ultimately, late Tuesday night, the Rules Committee voted to send a bill to the floor with no amendments.</p> 
<p>“So that's what led us to today,” Fitzpatrick said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>There is one silver lining for Johnson: Fitzpatrick went back to playing team ball soon after signing the Democratic discharge petition and voted to send Johnson’s health bill to the floor. He went on to vote to pass it: “I’m not going to vote against something out of spite.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick’s careful political balancing act will get a serious test this year as Democrats redouble their efforts to oust him from his swingy Bucks County district. He won his last race in 2024 by more than a dozen percentage points even as former Vice President Kamala Harris carried his district.</p> 
<p>“I think it demonstrates how much danger they're in politically by siding with the MAGA majority, which was just throwing caution to the winds in terms of people's health care,” said Rep. Jamie Raskin (D-Md.). ”These are the desperate members of the Republican majority who are trying to hang on to their seats, and good for them that they understand what America wants.”</p> 
<p>As Johnson was swarmed by reporters Wednesday morning asking about Fitzpatrick and the discharge petition, he said, “I have not lost control of the House.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick was a close ally of former Speaker Kevin McCarthy and is not seen as being especially close to Johnson. He could engage in additional freelancing in the coming year that would make governing the tiny Republican majority even more difficult for top party leaders.</p> 
<p>In addition to the five discharge petitions he’s already signed this year, he is working with Rep. Gregory Meeks (D-N.Y.) to introduce another, on Russian sanctions.</p> 
<p>“Every time somebody says that's a tool of the minority, I correct them — it's a tool of the rank-and-file,” Fitzpatrick said earlier this month. “To weaken the discharge would be just to empower the [party leaders], and we need more rank-and-file empowerment.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-time NASA nominee confirmed to lead space agency</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/jared-isaacman-nasa-head-00695557</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2e0f-d020-a7ff-2f0f99f10006</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 15:47:41 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate on Wednesday approved Jared Isaacman for the top job at NASA — an unprecedented comeback after President Donald Trump yanked his nomination this spring.</p> 
<p>Senators confirmed the billionaire private astronaut in a 67-30 vote.</p> 
<p>Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/trump-nominates-isaacman-nasa-administrator-00636497" target="_blank">renominated Isaacman</a> for NASA administrator in November, after pulling his original nomination in May. He cited Isaacman’s relationship with SpaceX CEO Elon Musk, with whom Trump had just had a falling out, as the rationale for his decision.</p> 
<p>Isaacman’s surprise rebound followed months of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/22/nasa-issacman-duffy-second-chance-00618595?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nrid=27cbdb93-64bc-42e1-9b60-42d49331f42f" target="_blank">political jockeying</a> and help from high-profile figures in Trump’s orbit.</p> 
<p>Isaacman was the CEO of the payment processing company Shift4, and has done business with Musk. He has pushed back in recent weeks about his ties to Musk, arguing that they aren’t friends and he has no connections to the space company.</p> 
<p>“Every story I see that writes about my nomination refers to the Musk ally or the Musk friend,” Isaacman said at his second confirmation hearing in December. “It's funny that in a world where everybody has a phone with a camera on it, there are no pictures of us at dinner, at a bar, on an airplane or on a yacht, because they don't exist.”</p> 
<p>Isaacman garnered backing from lawmakers during his hearing by confirming his support for NASA’s Artemis moon-landing mission, a key prerogative for Capitol Hill. He also committed to instilling urgency at the space agency, citing China’s space ambitions.</p> 
<p>“This is not the time for delay, but for action,” Isaacman said. “If we fall behind, if we make a mistake, we may never catch up, and the consequences could shift the balance of power here on Earth.</p> 
<p>Senate Commerce committee heads <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175665" data-person-id="175665">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Tx.) and ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51160" data-person-id="51160">Maria Cantwell</a> (D-Wa.), have said they want to see him in the role before the end of the year.</p> 
<p>A permanent head at NASA will come as a relief for the space agency, as it grapples with budget uncertainty and the exodus of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/09/nasa-staff-departures-00444674" target="_blank">thousands of senior employees</a>. Isaacman will also need to solidify plans for numerous high-profile programs, such as plans to land humans on the moon and replace the International Space Station.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartisan group discusses using discharged House bill for compromise health plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/problem-solvers-meeting-obamacare-00695105</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2d94-d71a-abff-7fff29ad0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 13:32:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan group of moderate lawmakers privately strategized Wednesday about how to pass an extension of expiring Obamacare subsidies early next year — possibly by using a newly discharged House bill as a vehicle for a Senate-backed bipartisan compromise.</p> 
<p>The closed-door discussion among House and Senate members about amending the discharged measure was described by four people who were granted anonymity to comment on the sensitive negotiations. It took place at a Capitol Hill meeting hosted by the bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus, whose members have spent weeks exploring possible compromises to extend the subsidies past Dec. 31.</p> 
<p>The effort hit a wall this week, after talks with Speaker Mike Johnson to get a floor vote on a compromise extension proposal failed. Four of them, including Problem Solvers Co-chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.), broke ranks Wednesday and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688" target="_blank">completed a discharge petition</a> led by Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>.</p> 
<p>Not all members of the Problem Solvers coalition are convinced that amending the Jeffries-backed bill — a straight three-year extension of the enhanced subsidies enacted under former President Joe Biden — would be the most viable proposal.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats privately noted that the three-year extension is already drafted and has support from a majority of House and Senate lawmakers. They also pointed out that other subsidy extension proposals, which include new eligibility limitations and anti-fraud measures, have less support in the House.</p> 
<p>But Republicans involved in the talks argue the three-year extension won’t be able to pass the Senate — it fell short of the necessary 60 votes last week — and are trying to rally support behind a compromise proposal that could pick up additional GOP support. In any case, no action is expected before Congress adjourns for the year.</p> 
<p>"They're going to have to put something on the floor,” Fitzpatrick said of the Senate in an interview. “We're going to send them a vehicle. … I mean, that was the whole point of the meeting with the senators."</p> 
<p>Senators who attended included <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/232351" data-person-id="232351">Maggie Hassan</a> (D-N.H.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> (R-Ohio). </p> 
<p>Moreno, who has put forward his own compromise proposal with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine), said the group was talking in “good faith” and “working together to get something done.”</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers in the meeting suggested that a deal could encompass more than proposals to extend the enhanced premium tax credits. Republicans have also endorsed ideas to expand tax-advantaged health savings accounts and make it easier for small businesses to create insurance plans.</p> 
<p>“The talks about what we might be able to come together around included other provisions, and I’m not going to get into any of those details,” said Shaheen, one of the lead Senate Democratic negotiators.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cruz seeks fast-track passage of military helicopter safety bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/cruz-aims-to-fast-track-passage-of-rotor-act-00694954</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2d76-dc54-a3df-6d7ec8960000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 12:59:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Commerce Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175665" data-person-id="175665">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Texas) is hoping to quickly pass a bill Wednesday dealing with military helicopter safety. </p> 
<p>According to a person familiar with the negotiations who was granted anonymity to speak candidly, Cruz plans to bring his bipartisan <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2503?q=s+2503" target="_blank">ROTOR Act</a> legislation to the floor via unanimous consent, a fast-track procedure. </p> 
<p>The bill would include a new provision striking a contentious helicopters-related section of the National Defense Authorization Act, according to the person.</p> 
<p>Cruz plans to speak around 2 p.m. and seek the unanimous consent agreement, the person said. Cruz’s office has struck an agreement with other senators, including Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a>, to pass the legislation via this fast-track mechanism, said the person, who added that they are making progress with the White House and Pentagon.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Thune didn’t immediately provide comment.</p> 
<p>The Senate cleared the NDAA earlier Wednesday, 77-20. Cruz voted for the bill.</p> 
<p>Cruz's ROTOR Act, which is cosponsored by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51160" data-person-id="51160">Maria Cantwell</a> of Washington, the committee’s top Democrat, seeks to address a litany of issues raised following January’s midair collision near Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport between a regional jet and an Army Black Hawk helicopter.</p> 
<p>The two lawmakers had raised safety concerns about the NDAA provision, which the nation’s top transportation accident investigator argued would allow certain military helicopters to fly without using an advanced location-broadcasting technology in the Washington area, endangering flyers.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-17T18:58:50-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Jack Smith makes his case against Trump in closed-door deposition</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-deposition-congress-00694730</link>
      <description>The former special counsel said the president is responsible for his own actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2cfe-dc54-a3df-6cfefaff0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 11:10:45 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/43/1e/1f6ecd2a42e29b145902174481b0/u-s-congress-01331.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Department of Justice Special Counsel Jack Smith arrives for a closed deposition before the House Judiciary Committee on Capitol Hill, on Dec. 17, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/43/1e/1f6ecd2a42e29b145902174481b0/u-s-congress-01331.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former special counsel Jack Smith, who led the federal criminal cases against President Donald Trump during the Biden administration, defended his investigations in a closed-door deposition Wednesday with members of the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>His testimony — stretching over eight hours, with breaks — was the culmination of a months-long congressional effort to investigate Smith and compel the former Justice Department official to appear on the Hill. It was also wrought with potential legal risks after Trump has openly and repeatedly called for Smith's prosecution.</p> 
<p>In his opening statement to lawmakers, portions of which were obtained by POLITICO, Smith defended his findings of allegations that Trump mishandled classified documents and sought to overturn the results of the 2020 presidential election.</p> 
<p>“The decision to bring charges against President Trump was mine, but the basis for those charges rests entirely with President Trump and his actions, as alleged in the indictments returned by grand juries in two different districts,” said Smith, according to a copy of portions of that statement.</p> 
<p>He maintained that this team found evidence to prove “beyond a reasonable doubt that President Trump engaged in a criminal scheme to overturn the results of the 2020 presidential election and to prevent the lawful transfer of power.”</p> 
<p>Smith also said his team found "powerful evidence” in the classified documents case and alleged that the president “repeatedly tried to obstruct justice.”</p> 
<p>“I made my decisions in the investigation without regard to President Trump’s political association, activities, beliefs, or candidacy in the 2024 presidential election,” Smith said in his statement. “We took actions based on what the facts and the law required — the very lesson I learned early in my career as a prosecutor.”</p> 
<p>He added that he would have made the same decision if Trump had been a Democrat or a Republican — a nod to the GOP members of the committee who believe Smith was pursuing a partisan witch hunt against the president. Their fury has only intensified in the wake of recent revelations Smith secretly obtained phone records of at least eight Republican senators in his election interference probe.</p> 
<p>Smith also defended that decision to request lawmakers’ phone data, for which Smith’s team did not receive the content of the calls.</p> 
<p>“Exploiting that violence, President Trump and his associates tried to call Members of Congress in furtherance of their criminal scheme, urging them to further delay certification of the 2020 election,” Smith said. “I didn’t choose those Members; President Trump did.”</p> 
<p>Abigail Jackson, a White House spokesperson, in a statement said that “Jack Smith is a lying hack who willingly weaponized the justice system against President Trump to try and benefit his Democrat cronies.” </p> 
<p>In the wake of repeated calls for his prosecution from Republicans and Trump himself, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-congress-investigations-00693884" target="_blank"><u>Smith faces unique political and legal dangers</u></a>. His testimony is hamstrung by grand jury secrecy rules and Justice Department policy — as well as an order from a federal judge in Florida that the second volume of his report surrounding the classified documents case remain under seal.</p> 
<p>Smith, however, defended his record as a career prosecutor from Republican allegations that he shepherded a weaponization of the Justice Department against conservatives — to the extent he could.</p> 
<p>Walking into the deposition room, Smith did not answer shouted questions from reporters.</p> 
<p>“The hunters become the hunted, huh?” someone shouted from the rowdy crowd swarming the former prosecutor.</p> 
<p>Smith is represented by the big law giant Covington &amp; Burling, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/25/donald-trump-jack-smith-covington-lawyers-022770" target="_blank"><u>which was sanctioned</u></a> by the Trump administration earlier this year after revelations that it was providing free legal services to Smith. The move suspended security clearances for lawyers at the firm.</p> 
<p>“In today testifying before this committee, Jack is showing tremendous courage in light of the remarkable and unprecedented retribution campaign against him by this administration and this White House,” one of Smith’s attorneys, Lanny Breuer, told reporters. “Let's be clear: Jack Smith, a career prosecutor, conducted this investigation based on the facts and based on the law and nothing more.”</p> 
<p>Breuer said his client “looks forward” to answering questions surrounding both of the cases he oversaw: the classified documents case and the case surrounding Trump’s efforts to subvert the results of the 2020 election. Smith was forced to drop both cases after Trump’s electoral victory in 2024, citing Justice Department policy against prosecuting a sitting president.</p> 
<p>A number of lawmakers filed into the deposition room Wednesday morning to watch the questioning — among them Reps. Scott Fitzgerald (R-Wis.), Ben Cline (R-Va.), Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) and Hank Johnson (D-Ga.). House Judiciary Committee chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) and ranking member Jamie Raskin (D-Md.) are also attending.</p> 
<p>"Jack Smith has just spent several hours schooling the Judiciary Committee on the professional responsibilities of a prosecutor and the ethical duties of a prosecutor," Raskin told reporters Wednesday afternoon, while declining to provide details on Smith's remarks. </p> 
<p>"He didn't come with any particular message," Raskin continued, "but I'll just say that he's answered every single question to the satisfaction of any reasonable-minded person in that room."</p> 
<p>Smith had been requesting a public forum for his testimony to set the record straight about the scope of his work and the cases he would have pursued against Trump.</p> 
<p>Jordan, however, declined that request, instead opting for a deposition behind closed doors. After the conclusion of the deposition, however, Jordan told reporters that he had not ruled out the possibility of Smith appearing in a public venue.</p> 
<p>Democrats agreed that Smith should be given a chance to speak in an open hearing. Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) noted that previous special counsels have been given their own hearings.</p> 
<p>“We're having a deposition behind closed doors because this chairman, this administration, this president — these Republicans want to hide from the American people the results of this investigation,” she said. “There's also no reason to keep Jack Smith from testifying … to the American people about what was in his investigation and why he came to the conclusions that he did.”</p> 
<p>After the hearing, Breuer told reporters that "[a] person who listened today to the deposition would know without any doubt that Jack Smith's investigation was based purely on the facts and the law and the evidence, nothing more and nothing less."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-17T11:08:24-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Frustrated GOP moderates join Democrats to force Obamacare extension vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2cbf-dc54-a3df-6cff63b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 09:40:32 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Four House Republicans joined Democrats Wednesday to force a House vote on a straight three-year extension of the enhanced Obamacare tax credits that will expire Dec. 31, delivering a sharp rebuke to Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and other GOP leaders.</p> 
<p>Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick </a>of Pennsylvania, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> of New York, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478639" data-person-id="478639">Rob Bresnahan</a> of Pennsylvania and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/194184" data-person-id="194184">Ryan Mackenzie</a> of Pennsylvania signed the discharge petition filed by House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries </a>— hours after House GOP leaders rejected attempts by Fitzpatrick and other Republican moderates to seek a floor vote on extending the subsidies used by more than 20 million Americans.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick said in a late-night House Rules Committee meeting Tuesday that "the only thing worse than a clean extension ... would be expiration, and I would make that decision." Lawler added that "the only feasible path forward is a discharge petition" if GOP leader reject a floor vote.</p> 
<p>Under House rules, a completed discharge petition is subject to a waiting period, meaning no vote could happen until next month. Johnson could choose to move sooner, but there are no plans to call up the three-year extension bill early, according to two people granted anonymity to describe internal GOP leadership conversations.</p> 
<p>“We have worked for months to craft a two-party solution to address these expiring healthcare credits," Fitzpatrick said in a statement Wednesday. "Our only request was a Floor vote on this compromise, so that the American People’s voice could be heard on this issue. That request was rejected. ... Unfortunately, it is House leadership themselves that have forced this outcome.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries told reporters Wednesday his discharge petition is "the most straightforward path to ensuring that tens of millions of Americans don't have their health care ripped away from them because of the expiration of the Affordable Care Act tax credits."</p> 
<p>The bill, however, unlikely to advance in the Senate. While four GOP senators voted to advance a three-year extension alongside Democrats last week, the proposal fell short of the necessary 60 votes to proceed. Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> was dismissive when asked Monday if he would take up a similar bill if the House sent one over.</p> 
<p>"If they just did what they did over here, which is a straight-up three-year extension, then no," he said. Asked the same question Wednesday, he said, "We'll cross that bridge when we come to it."</p> 
<p>Even if the Senate does not take up a House-passed extension, it could build pressure on Thune and Johnson to take action on some sort of extension when lawmakers return to Washington next month. Fitzpatrick is hosting some rank-and-file senators who have been exploring a health deal at a Problem Solvers Caucus meeting Wednesday in the Capitol.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Jack Smith jumps into a Judiciary minefield</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/jack-smith-deposition-house-judiciary-testimony-trump-00694588</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2ab2-d716-abfb-fafbce910000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jack Smith wants to make his case against Donald Trump to Congress — but he’s walking into a political and legal minefield.</p> 
<p>The Biden-era special counsel who brought the first and only federal criminal charges ever leveled against a former president is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-congress-investigations-00693884" target="_blank">set to testify Wednesday morning</a> to members of House Judiciary.</p> 
<p>The stakes are high.</p> 
<p>Republicans are looking to portray Smith as a tool of a weaponized Justice Department — an allegation Republicans have brandished amid recent revelations Smith obtained phone records of <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/29/congress/senate-gop-blasts-jack-smith-00629073" target="_blank">at least eight GOP senators</a> as part of his probe into Trump’s efforts to subvert the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>“What they did all along, everything was wrong … a lot of things that were just not normal course of investigation or prosecution,” Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) told POLITICO. “If he comes in and doesn’t answer questions, that’s going to be a problem.”</p> 
<p>Judiciary Republican Troy Nehls of Texas, when asked about his ideal outcome for Smith’s deposition, didn’t hold back.</p> 
<p>“Jack Smith should be in jail — if not prison,” he said. “He’s a crook … and he needs to be held accountable for all his games that he played.”</p> 
<p>Democrats, meanwhile, are eager for more information about the investigations Smith had to abandon after Trump won reelection in 2024, bowing to the fact that sitting presidents cannot face federal charges while in office. Smith was investigating Trump for election subversion attempts and mishandling classified documents.</p> 
<p>“We want to hear exactly what he found, and what he did,” said Jamie Raskin (D-Md.), the top House Judiciary Democrat.</p> 
<p>Peter Koski, a former top DOJ official and a member of Smith’s legal team, said in a statement his client is “looking forward to answering the committee’s questions, sharing the legal basis for his investigative steps, and discussing the evidence of President Trump’s alleged efforts to overturn the 2020 election and his unlawful possession of classified documents at Mar-a-Lago.”</p> 
<p>But Smith is bound by complex secrecy rules that limit what he is able to share with lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Raskin maintains Smith’s task Wednesday is simple: “He just needs to come and tell the truth.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Decision day for health care: </b>The House will vote Wednesday on the GOP health care package without an Affordable Care Act subsidy extension — and without any of the amendments moderates were seeking. Members are set to vote on the rule Wednesday morning, with the final vote on the bill expected Wednesday afternoon (assuming the rule is adopted). </p> 
<p>The Problem Solvers will also huddle with rank-and-file senators Wednesday to discuss a framework that includes an ACA extension and other health policy items for January.</p> 
<p><b>— Carr in the hot seat:</b> FCC Chair Brendan Carr’s appearance before Senate Commerce Wednesday will be a <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/inside-brendan-carrs-tightrope-with-republicans-00693611" target="_blank">telling moment for Republicans</a> as GOP committee members balance concerns over free speech with their reluctance to criticize the administration. </p> 
<p>Commerce Chair Ted Cruz (R-Texas) told reporters Tuesday he plans to use the FCC oversight hearing to explore free speech concerns, though it’s unclear how far most Republicans on the committee will go in relitigating Carr’s threats against TV show host Jimmy Kimmel earlier this year. </p> 
<p><i>Kyle Cheney, Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and John Hendel contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jack Smith wants to tell Congress about his Trump investigations. That comes with risks.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-congress-investigations-00693884</link>
      <description>The House Judiciary Committee will question the former special counsel behind closed doors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2929-d716-abfb-f9eb85840000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/53/30/72e9a6514f3d853a6f5c6f17f001/biden-democracy-analysis-37581.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jacquelyn Martin/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Special counsel Jack Smith arrives to speak about an indictment of Donald Trump, Aug. 1, 2023, at a Department of Justice office in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/53/30/72e9a6514f3d853a6f5c6f17f001/biden-democracy-analysis-37581.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Kyle Cheney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Kyle Cheney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jack Smith wants to make his case against Donald Trump to Congress — but he’s walking into a political and legal minefield.</p> 
<p>The Biden-era special counsel who brought the first and only federal criminal charges ever leveled against a former president is set to testify behind closed doors Wednesday to the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>To do so, he must navigate Byzantine secrecy laws and rules that limit what he can disclose to lawmakers. All the while, Republicans are looking to trip him up and incriminate him, to portray him as a tool of a weaponized Justice Department — an allegation they’ve brandished amid recent revelations that Smith obtained phone records of at least eight GOP senators as part of his probe into Trump’s efforts to subvert the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>“What they did all along, everything was wrong … a lot of things that were just not normal course of investigation or prosecution,” House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan said in an interview. “If he comes in and doesn’t answer questions, that’s going to be a problem.”</p> 
<p>At the same time, Democrats are eager for further details about the investigations Smith had to abandon after Trump won reelection in 2024, bowing to the reality that sitting presidents cannot face federal charges while in office. Smith was investigating Trump for election subversion attempts and mishandling classified documents.</p> 
<p>“We want to hear exactly what he found, and what he did,” Rep. Jamie Raskin, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, said in an interview. “He just needs to come and tell the truth.”</p> 
<p>It’s all forcing Smith into a delicate, high-stakes dance with members of both parties. Democrats want to exploit any opportunity to discredit Trump, but Republicans are hoping to back Smith into a corner and portray him as a politically motivated activist.</p> 
<p>“Jack Smith should be in jail — if not prison,” said Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Texas), a member of the Judiciary Committee, when asked about his ideal outcome for Smith’s deposition. “He’s a crook. Jack Smith is a crook, and he needs to be held accountable for all his games that he played.”</p> 
<p>Peter Koski, the former deputy chief of the DOJ Public Integrity Section and a member of Smith’s legal team at Covington &amp; Burling, said in a statement Tuesday his client is “looking forward to answering the committee’s questions, sharing the legal basis for his investigative steps, and discussing the evidence of President Trump’s alleged efforts to overturn the 2020 election and his unlawful possession of classified documents at Mar-a-Lago.”</p> 
<p>Ultimately, though, there are restrictions for what Smith can and cannot tell members. He remains bound by grand jury rules that bar prosecutors from disclosing evidence that was never made public, at least without the permission of a court.</p> 
<p>And in his capacity as a former Justice Department employee, he’s also limited in what he can share about his prosecutorial work. DOJ has provided an authorization letter to facilitate Smith’s testimony, according to a person granted anonymity to share details of private correspondence; however, the scope of the waiver is not clear.</p> 
<p>A federal judge in Florida has also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/trump-jack-smith-classified-docs-report-00673178" target="_blank"><u>maintained an 11-month prohibition</u></a> on the release of any details of Smith’s final report in the classified documents probe — a restriction Trump has urged her to maintain indefinitely — further narrowing what Smith is legally permitted to share about that investigation.</p> 
<p>Complicating matters further is that Trump has called repeatedly for Smith’s prosecution, fueling the GOP appetite for incriminating Smith. That’s forcing Smith to weigh potential risks of criminal accusations against his desire to share information about his work with lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Jordan has already sent out a criminal referral for Thomas Windom, a top Smith deputy, after the former senior assistant special counsel repeatedly declined to answer questions during his September deposition before investigators with the Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>“They are trying to get him on the fast road to one of their ridiculous prosecutions,” Raskin said, of Smith.</p> 
<p>House Judiciary Democrats are simultaneously pressing for the public release of Smith’s report detailing the results of his investigation into Trump’s alleged mishandling of classified documents.</p> 
<p>Earlier this month, committee Democrats filed an amicus brief to a federal court in Florida urging Judge Aileen Cannon to allow its release, citing the ongoing panel’s investigations and the need to balance out what is currently a “one-sided public record.”</p> 
<p>“Neither the Committee nor the public can meaningfully evaluate Mr. Smith’s conduct, or assess the Committee’s accusations, without access to the report that memorializes what the Special Counsel actually did and why,” stated the amicus brief, submitted by the Democrats’ lawyers.</p> 
<p>Cannon, a Trump appointee who once ruled Smith was put into the special counsel role unconstitutionally, has so far maintained that the report will not be released. This decision could further complicate Smith’s testimony before Congressional investigators, adding limitations to what he can share.</p> 
<p>“Every other special counsel committee report has been released, and I believe every other special counsel or independent counsel has appeared before Congress publicly,” Raskin said, “so our Republican colleagues seem to fear the strength of Jack Smith's advocacy and presentation.”</p> 
<p>Jordan said he intends to ask Smith about the classified documents case, including the FBI’s search of Trump’s Mar-a-Lago home in 2022. He also wants Smith to answer for DOJ’s efforts to obtain phone data from former Speaker Kevin McCarthy as part of his probe.</p> 
<p>Smith preferred that all this take place in a public setting, with his legal team pressing Congressional Republicans hard to let the testimony proceed in an open hearing. Jordan declined that request. The GOP-led Senate Judiciary Committee, in contrast, has expressed an openness to facilitating such a hearing as it pursues its own Smith investigation, and Sen. Ron Johnson (R-Wis.) said he believed the House deposition will lay the groundwork for the Senate’s questioning.</p> 
<p>"Before you interview somebody, before you hold a hearing — you need information, otherwise they run circles around you. You get nothing fruitful out of them," said Johnson, who is co-leading the Senate's probe into Smith's investigations in his role as chair of the Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations.</p> 
<p>Johnson said he expected Jordan would eventually produce a transcript of Smith’s House deposition. “Those would be the documents we’ll use when we interview him,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fitzpatrick declines to turn off ACA discharge petition as amendment talks drag on</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/fitzpatrick-declines-to-turn-off-aca-discharge-petition-as-amendment-talks-drag-on-00694065</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2985-dffa-a7db-6fb7861d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:36:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Vulnerable Republican Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick told Speaker Mike Johnson on the House floor Tuesday he would not withdraw his discharge petition that would force a floor vote on extending expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies — amid Johnson’s attempt to find a potential agreement to allow a vote on an amendment instead that would be similar in substance.</p> 
<p>The standoff, described by three people granted anonymity to divulge private conversations, shows the pressure GOP leadership is under to defuse a politically challenging dynamic around the future of the enhanced Obamacare subsidies that have divided Johnson’s conference.</p> 
<p>At the same time, the speaker’s allies argue it shows that the GOP moderates themselves are still refusing to reach a deal ahead of a Wednesday vote on a health care bill Republicans want to pass to show they are serious about preventing a looming spike in insurance premiums.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and Rep. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.), in private conversations with Johnson and other Republicans, have both so far declined to turn off their respective discharge petitions in the absence of an agreement they can vote on this week alongside the GOP health care bill.</p> 
<p>Johnson in recent days told GOP moderates who want a vote on an ACA subsidies extension he would agree to such a vote if they in turn agreed to turn off their various discharge petitions and make sure the amendment was paid for with a satisfactory offset. Johnson also wanted to use Fitzpatrick’s two-year ACA extension bill as the base for a compromise amendment, according to two people with direct knowledge of the matter. But those talks never produced a deal.</p> 
<p>The speaker told reporters after talking to Fitzpatrick Tuesday afternoon that they're still “working” on various ACA amendment options. But, he said, “I thought there was an agreement on the Fitzpatrick amendment and then they made different decisions.” </p> 
<p>The speaker added later he thought “there’s a real possibility they get a vote on it” and noted he “certainly tried my best to provide for that.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.) huddled with Johnson on the floor Tuesday evening, along with Kiggans and a larger group of moderates and Johnson’s top floor and policy staff, but the group still disbanded without an agreement, according to two people involved in the conversation.</p> 
<p>The House Rules Committee, meanwhile, is meeting to pave the way for floor consideration of the narrow health package endorsed by House Republican leaders, as centrists have submitted more than five proposed amendments to either extend the subsidies or provide new tax deductions for health insurance premiums.</p> 
<p>If no ACA extension amendment makes it to the floor Wednesday, there are several House Republicans who are considering signing onto Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries three-year clean extension of the ACA subsidies he is also pushing through a discharge petition, according to three people granted anonymity to share their direct knowledge of the matter.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and his bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus will also meet with a bipartisan group of rank and file senators Wednesday to discuss a possible framework they could agree on for a health care deal.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP pushes major permitting bill through key vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/hardline-republicans-arrest-the-speed-act-00693199</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-290a-dffa-a7db-6f3b96800006</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 16:22:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans succeeded Tuesday in advancing a bipartisan bill aimed at speeding up the federal permitting process, fending off a late challenge from hard-liners who wanted more power to kill offshore wind projects.</p> 
<p>The House adopted the rule governing floor debate on several bills in a 215-209 vote. Among those bills that will now be considered on the chamber floor later this week is the so-called SPEED Act, which would overhaul the National Environmental Policy Act to remove regulatory roadblocks around building and completing energy projects.</p> 
<p>But in order to secure the support of holdouts — led by GOP Reps. Andy Harris of Maryland and Jeff Van Drew of New Jersey — Republican leaders will have to alter a provision of the bipartisan legislation in the Rules Committee to ensure the Trump administration can continue to block offshore wind developments in these two states specifically.</p> 
<p>This adjustment will be made as part of a separate rule paving the way for floor consideration of a health care package the Rules Committee is debating Tuesday afternoon and that the full House is expected to vote on Wednesday.</p> 
<p>A floor vote on the SPEED Act, with the new change, is still on track for Thursday. Van Drew said it would include “really important language so we can go back and show these wind projects were rushed through and that the permitting wasn’t proper.”</p> 
<p>Natural Resources Chair Bruce Westerman had included the original provision in the SPEED Act during the panel markup that would make it harder for presidents to cancel permits for any energy project. <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/11/natural-resources-committee-approves-measure-to-stop-executive-branch-revoking-energy-permits-00662581" target="_blank">It was added</a> to address concerns from Democrats that President Donald Trump was prepared to attack wind and solar projects — and assuage anxieties across all energy industries that their project approvals could get arbitrarily yanked depending on the party in power.</p> 
<p>But Harris, Van Drew and others argued the provision would <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/conservative-lawmakers-warn-trump-against-gop-led-nepa-overhaul-00684686" target="_blank">undermine Trump’s anti-offshore wind agenda</a>, with which the two Republicans align.</p> 
<p>Alongside Van Drew and Harris, the rule initially had GOP defections from Reps. Scott Perry of Pennsylvania, Chris Smith of New Jersey, Tim Burchett of Tennessee and Anna Paulina Luna of Florida. Leaders were able to flip all the “no” votes with the exceptions of Luna and Smith.</p> 
<p>Other Republicans, including Reps. Chip Roy of Texas, Kat Cammack of Florida, Andrew Clyde of Georgia and Andy Biggs of Arizona initially withheld their votes.</p> 
<p>Most of these members were seen huddling in long conversations on the House floor with Speaker Mike Johnson, Majority Leader Steve Scalise and Majority Whip Tom Emmer.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson confronted by GOP moderates over Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-johnson-confronted-gop-moderates-00693242</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2882-da7a-a9bf-bcd373cc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 13:54:48 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A group of vulnerable House Republicans confronted Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> inside a closed-door meeting Tuesday about expiring Obamacare health insurance subsidies — and Johnson’s refusal to allow a vote on extending them.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) could be heard yelling outside the room where the centrist Republican Governance Group was meeting with Johnson in attendance, sounding off about GOP leaders’ opposition to a vote this week and mocking the assurance from some that Republicans could work on a party-line health care bill next year.</p> 
<p>Lawler — who earlier in the day <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-lawler-obamacare-lapse-00692577" target="_blank">publicly accused GOP leaders</a> of “political malpractice” — shot back that Republicans would “never” get a second reconciliation bill passed, despite the wishful thinking.</p> 
<p>A stern Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.) also pressed Johnson, according to three people in the room granted anonymity to describe the private meeting, asking why he and other leaders didn’t act sooner on the expiring subsides and health care generally.</p> 
<p>The venting session was a remarkable climax to a monthslong debate within the GOP over how to address spiking insurance premiums for millions of Americans starting next year. In the view of many GOP moderates, the Obamacare subsidies are poised to lapse without any comprehensive plan over how to manage the inevitable political fallout ahead of the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>The moderates are nonetheless making some last-minute moves to try to force the issue.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) <a href="https://amendments-rules.house.gov/amendments/FITZBR_092_xml251216113645604.pdf" target="_blank">submitted an amendment</a> Tuesday to a narrow GOP health package set to hit the House floor this week that would extend the expiring tax credits for two years with anti-fraud and income eligibility restrictions. Kiggans is also expected to file an amendment that would extend the subsidies while cracking down on fraud, and there are efforts to craft a third amendment that Johnson told reporters might be amendable to a wider group of Republicans.</p> 
<p>As Johnson left the meeting with the moderates, he brushed off the intraparty barbs, saying they were “trying to solve the equation” for everyone and the group had some ideas worth considering.</p> 
<p>House Democrats are championing an alternative — a straight three-year extension of the expiring subsidies — and are urging a handful of Republicans to join a discharge petition that would force a floor vote on it.</p> 
<p>The GOP moderates have previously rejected the Democrats’ proposal, arguing the subsidies need new guardrails. But Lawler said Tuesday morning, “All options are on the table,” while Fitzpatrick said after the Tuesday meeting, “Ask me after today.”</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misstated the day of the Republican Governance Group. It was on Tuesday.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House permitting vote at risk over offshore wind backlash</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/house-permitting-rule-vote-00692850</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2837-dffa-a7db-6f378ca10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 12:33:19 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An intraparty war over the House GOP’s flagship legislation to speed up the federal permitting process for energy projects is threatening to freeze the chamber’s floor before lawmakers leave for the holidays.</p> 
<p>Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151768" data-person-id="151768">Andy Harris</a> (R-Md.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew </a>(R-N.J.) said in interviews that they plan to vote against the procedural measure setting up debate on the bipartisan SPEED Act and believe they have enough allied Republicans to kill it. The two lawmakers are among those arguing that language in the bill making it harder for presidents to cancel permits would <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/conservative-lawmakers-warn-trump-against-gop-led-nepa-overhaul-00684686" target="_blank">undermine Donald Trump’s assault on offshore wind</a>.</p> 
<p>Despite the threat, GOP leaders are moving forward with the rule vote as they track a handful of Republican holdouts, according to four people granted anonymity to describe internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>’s leadership circle privately acknowledges that success on the procedural vote will likely depend on attendance and a final push to convince Republicans to support the measure.</p> 
<p>Republicans cannot afford even modest defections given their razor-thin majority, since the minority party rarely votes with the majority on rule votes.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see — it always depends on attendance,” said Natural Resources Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189075" data-person-id="189075">Bruce Westerman</a> (R-Ark.), the architect of the SPEED Act, in a Tuesday interview. “I still have faith we can get somewhere because this is so important to the country in so many ways. I am not going to give up on it.”</p> 
<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said Tuesday he’s “talked to those members” threatening to oppose the rule and told them “this is just the first step” to enact permitting reform as House and Senate leaders negotiate a broader package.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/republicans-make-concessions-to-conservatives-on-permitting-bill-00692343" target="_blank">already made some concessions to hard-liners</a>, with the House Rules Committee agreeing Monday to allow votes on amendments they demanded — including one stripping the contentious offshore wind language from the bill.</p> 
<p>Westerman said Tuesday he would plan to oppose that amendment if the rule is adopted and the bill moves to the floor.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-16T11:24:33-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘Absolute bulls--t’: Endangered House Republican blasts leaders over impending Obamacare lapse</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-lawler-obamacare-lapse-00692577</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-27c0-d653-afff-67c009d90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 10:22:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An infuriated Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> left a closed-door House Republican meeting Tuesday and sounded off on GOP leaders who are planning to allow key Obamacare subsidies to expire in two weeks.</p> 
<p>"This is absolute bullshit," the New York Republican said.</p> 
<p>“I think it's idiotic not to have an up-or-down vote on this issue,” he told reporters of leaders’ refusal to hold a vote on a modified version of the expiring subsidies. “It is political malpractice.”</p> 
<p>Lawler also laid into House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>, arguing that Democrats don’t actually want to compromise on the issue and instead want to use health care as a political cudgel against the GOP in the midterms.</p> 
<p>“They want to kill it. They want the issue,” said Lawler. “That's why [Minority Leader] <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> put a nonsensical three-year vote on the floor of the Senate when given an opportunity.”</p> 
<p>At the same time, Lawler did not rule out joining a Democratic-led discharge petition that would force a vote on a three-year extension to send a message to GOP leaders.</p> 
<p>“All options are on the table,” he said.</p> 
<p>Lawler’s outburst came after Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> told his members in the closed-door meeting that he’s moving forward with a Wednesday vote on a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/whats-in-the-gop-health-bill-00689950" target="_blank">GOP health care bill</a> that would not extend the expiring Obamacare subsidies, according to four people in the room who were granted anonymity to describe the closed-door comments.</p> 
<p>Lawler stood up in the meeting, two of the people said, to call Republican leaders' decision to allow the expiration “a mistake.”</p> 
<p>Johnson pushed back on the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/house-gop-moderates-signal-theyll-fall-in-line-with-johnsons-health-plan-00692138" target="_blank">criticism from Lawler and allies</a> such as Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) at a Tuesday news conference. </p> 
<p>"Fitzpatrick and Lawler and the others are fighting tooth-an-nail for their constituents — I understand that as well as anyone, because I'm the one in their districts campaigning with them," Johnson told reporters, adding that "the solution that is being sought by Democrats would further harm the system."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Parallel pushes for an 11th-hour health deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/health-care-deal-moderates-obamacare-subsidies-00692374</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-259b-da9a-a7db-3dbf9bec0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rank-and-file dealmakers in both chambers are making last-ditch attempts to extend key Obamacare subsidies this week, even as it becomes crystal clear the subsidies will expire first.</p> 
<p>House GOP moderates are hashing out what sort of extension to offer as an amendment at Tuesday afternoon’s Rules meeting — even as they signal they will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/house-gop-moderates-signal-theyll-fall-in-line-with-johnsons-health-plan-00692138" target="_blank">fall in line</a> with Speaker Mike Johnson’s health care plan whether they get a vote or not. A bipartisan Senate group is working simultaneously toward an extension framework that they hope to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/senators-obamacare-extension-talks-00692316" target="_blank">announce by the end of the week</a>, while acknowledging it won’t get a vote till next year.</p> 
<p>Here’s where the mod movement in each chamber stands.</p> 
<p><b>— In the House: </b>Majority Leader Steve Scalise said Monday night there’s no “final decision” on putting a subsidy extension amendment on the floor. Tuesday morning’s GOP Conference meeting could get heated as frustrated moderates — who call a subsidy extension omission “a huge mistake” — make their last plea for a vote.</p> 
<p>But they face a huge obstacle at the 2 p.m. Rules meeting Tuesday, where Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) and other moderates are unlikely to get a warm welcome from the panel’s conservative hard-liners, who are firmly against extending Obamacare in any form.</p> 
<p>The moderates could pull a page out of the Freedom Caucus playbook and threaten to tank the rule or the underlying bill in return, but that does not appear to be in the cards: “I wouldn’t vote against it in protest,” Fitzpatrick said.</p> 
<p><b>— In the Senate:&nbsp;</b>Meanwhile, nearly two dozen senators convened by Sens. Susan Collins (R-Maine) and Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) discussed issuing a roadmap this week toward a bipartisan deal.</p> 
<p>The rough framework under discussion would pair a two-year subsidy extension with a new income eligibility cap and fraud prevention language. A potential extension of open enrollment for Obamacare exchanges and possible restrictions on abortion funding also remain under consideration.</p> 
<p>That’s similar to Fitzpatrick’s proposal in the House, but the two efforts so far are entirely parallel. There is some hope they might eventually converge: Rank-and-file senators are invited to join a Problem Solvers Caucus meeting Fitzpatrick is hosting Wednesday to discuss a joint effort.</p> 
<p>But this much is clear: The Dec. 31 deadline for the subsidies is certain to come and go.</p> 
<p>“The calendar precludes getting something done this week,” Sen. Bill Cassidy (R-La.) told reporters. “But, still, a commitment to work together is a lot of progress.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Boat strikes oversight:</b> The Pentagon will make video of the Sept. 2 strikes on an alleged drug boat leaving Venezuela available to all members of the House and Senate Armed Services committees later this week, a White House official said. It’s only been shown thus far to the Gang of Eight leaders as well as top members of the Armed Services and Defense Appropriations panels.</p> 
<p><b>— Approps movement in the Senate: </b>Senate Republicans are getting close to reaching agreement within their own ranks to move a five-bill spending package before they leave for the holiday recess. Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.) said that he and Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah) are in discussions with GOP leaders to get a vote stripping earmarks out of the package and potentially also an amendment related to balancing the budget.</p> 
<p><b>— SPEED Act speeds through: </b>The House GOP’s flagship legislation to speed up federal permitting for energy projects is on track for the chamber floor after House Rules agreed to allow amendment votes demanded by conservative hard-liners — including three from foes of offshore wind, who had otherwise threatened to oppose the measure. One of those amendments would strip language that would limit the president's power to revoke approved permits for energy projects.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Jennifer Scholtes and Josh Siegel contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Oversight delays Clintons’ Epstein testimonies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/clintons-depositions-delayed-00692160</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2499-da9a-a7db-3cbf8db40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 20:18:32 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bill and Hillary Clinton were scheduled to give depositions this week on Capitol Hill about their ties to Jeffrey Epstein, but their appearances have been officially punted into January.</p> 
<p>It sends a strong signal members of Congress will continue to investigate the late, convicted sex offender — even as the Justice Department is due to release a trove of materials related to the Epstein case by Friday.</p> 
<p>House Oversight and Government Reform Committee Chair James Comer, who is leading the congressional investigation into Epstein, announced the delay in a letter to an attorney for the Clintons, obtained by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>In that letter, Comer maintained that former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton must appear before his committee Jan. 13 and Jan. 14, respectively, or risk being held in contempt of Congress.</p> 
<p>“If your clients do not comply with these new dates, the Committee will move immediately to contempt proceedings,” Comer, a Kentucky Republican, wrote. </p> 
<p>Comer noted that the Clintons’ attorney had said previously the Clintons were unable to testify this week due to a funeral but declined to provide alternative dates for their depositions, prompting him to unilaterally assigned the former first couple new dates early next month.</p> 
<p>The attorney for the Clintons did not immediately return a request for comment. A spokesperson for Bill Clinton has said the former president disassociated himself with Epstein prior to Epstein’s 2019 arrest and had no knowledge of his crimes.</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton was also featured in a picture as part of a recent trove of photographs handed over to the Oversight committee by the Epstein estate. Oversight Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/trump-clinton-gates-included-in-epstein-photo-trove-00688628" target="_blank">released select photos</a> to the public Friday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP moderates signal they’ll fall in line with Johnson’s health plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/house-gop-moderates-signal-theyll-fall-in-line-with-johnsons-health-plan-00692138</link>
      <description>Vulnerable members have agitated for a vote to extend Obamacare subsidies. But that appears unlikely to happen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2488-d5c5-a7bf-6edb98bf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 19:23:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a1/ac/2465831243ecb0e6e117c1a9bbe7/u-s-congress-93917.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. David Valadao of California (left) has been among the moderates pushing Speaker Mike Johnson (center) for a vote on expiring insurance subsidies.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a1/ac/2465831243ecb0e6e117c1a9bbe7/u-s-congress-93917.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s a time of choosing for a band of vulnerable House Republicans who have long warned about the expiration of key Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> is barreling toward a Wednesday vote on a health care bill he and other Republican leaders are <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/whats-in-the-gop-health-bill-00689950" target="_blank">presenting as an alternative to the tax credits</a> that are set to expire at the end of the month. They have no plans to allow a vote before then on extending the subsidies.</p> 
<p>The early signs are that the group of GOP moderates who have voiced concern about their constituents’ health care costs — not to mention their own political futures — is preparing to fall in line this week.</p> 
<p>"I haven't seen anything objectionable yet,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) said Monday. “For me to vote against it, I'd have to find something objectionable. I wouldn't vote against it in protest."</p> 
<p>While he said it would be “a huge mistake” to not include an extension, Fitzpatrick said he votes “for or against legislation based on the merits of the bill.”</p> 
<p>Others in the centrist Republican group said much the same privately — that they are still prepared to vote for the GOP health care bill even with their bid for an amendment vote extending the subsidies apparently doomed.</p> 
<p>“We’re not going to cut off our nose to spite our face,” said one who, like others interviewed, was granted anonymity to comment on private discussions among the group.</p> 
<p>If that sentiment holds, it would be the latest instance of how the group of moderates has largely followed Johnson’s lead in 2025 — voting in lockstep on the party’s domestic policy bill despite objections over Medicaid cuts, for instance, and keeping their names off discharge petitions meant to circumvent the speaker’s control of the House floor.</p> 
<p>But the Obamacare lapse represents a particularly acute test for the group at a sensitive moment — after many of them have spoken out publicly.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a>, a Republican in a highly competitive Virginia district, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/15/kiggans-house-gop-aca-00561747" target="_blank">warned of the political fallout</a> for House Republicans in a closed-door House GOP conference meeting last week. Fitzpatrick and fellow GOP Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478639" data-person-id="478639">Rob Bresnahan</a> of Pennsylvania, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/81211" data-person-id="81211">Nick LaLota</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> of New York and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/159021" data-person-id="159021">David Valadao</a> of California have been involved in efforts to broker an extension of the subsidies, so far to no avail.</p> 
<p>It was already virtually assured the enhanced tax credits enacted and extended by Democrats under former President Joe Biden would lapse on Jan. 1, given the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/senate-rejects-health-care-bills-00686855" target="_blank">Senate’s failure to act last week</a> on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3385" target="_blank">Democratic proposal</a> for a three-year extension.</p> 
<p>Forcing a House vote on the matter this week, however, could put additional pressure on Republican leaders to explore a solution next month that would maintain the subsidies in some form for the 20 million Americans who now use them.</p> 
<p>But the GOP moderates, most of whom hail from purple districts and are at serious risk of losing their seats in the midterms, did not find any sympathetic ears among Johnson or his top leadership allies in the final weeks.</p> 
<p>“They made their case,” one senior House Republican involved in the talks said of the centrists. Their last-minute push for a floor vote wouldn’t change party leaders’ belief that they didn’t have the votes to actually pass an extension of the subsidies, the senior Republican added — especially given divides within their conference over abortion coverage.</p> 
<p>Johnson said in a recent interview <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/mike-johnson-obamacare-dilemma-00687068" target="_blank">he understood the “dilemma”</a> facing some of the moderates who have since launched discharge petitions to try to force a vote on an extension. But privately Johnson’s leadership circle was always skeptical that those petitions would ever garner enough support to force the speaker’s hand.</p> 
<p>One big problem for the centrists: They were too late.</p> 
<p>By the time Fitzpatrick and Kiggans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/frustrated-republicans-move-to-force-obamacare-vote-as-warnings-mount-about-the-midterms-00685423" target="_blank">launched separate discharge petitions</a> aimed at extending the subsidies, there were not enough legislative days left to trigger a vote before the House adjourns for the year and the tax credits lapse. Notably, the Republican moderates mostly kept quiet during the entire 43-day government shutdown — and didn’t publicly pressure Johnson and fellow GOP leaders to negotiate as Democrats made the expiring tax credits the centerpiece of the fight.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, a co-chair of the bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus, vowed last week to keep pushing to extend the subsidies.</p> 
<p>“They can just dig themselves into an ideological corner all day long — it’s not fixing the problem,” Fitzpatrick said about party leaders in an interview. “We can agree that the current construct is flawed, but that letting them expire is not acceptable.”</p> 
<p>Late last week, he and other moderates pushed Johnson to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/house-will-vote-on-obamacare-extension-next-week-00689845" target="_blank">allow a vote on a floor amendment</a> to the GOP health care bill or another outlet that would allow skeptical members an opportunity to express support for extending the subsidies.</p> 
<p>But hammering out that amendment has proven intractable, with Johnson indicating directly to the group that he was trying to make something work while others in the leadership ranks remained skeptical they could.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick indicated Monday he plans to propose an amendment in the Rules Committee that would be modeled off his bipartisan bill that proposed a two-year subsidy extension with an income cap and other eligibility restrictions. But as of Monday there was no agreement to allow it to come to a vote, Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think the final decision’s been made” on the amendment, he told reporters.</p> 
<p>The group of moderates planned to huddle on the House floor Monday night to finalize their strategy for the Tuesday Rules meeting, according to two people granted anonymity to describe the private plans.</p> 
<p>Separately, Fitzpatrick will meet Wednesday with the Problem Solvers to discuss their next steps on health care, two other people said, and he's invited a bipartisan group of rank-and-file senators who have also been exploring a bipartisan deal.</p> 
<p>Valadao, a senior appropriator who heads the centrist-leaning Republican Governance Group caucus, was among dozens of Republicans who lost their seats in 2018 after Republicans tried to repeal Obamacare. He declined to say in an interview Monday how he would vote on the leadership-backed health bill.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see how the amendment plays out,” he said.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/43694" data-person-id="43694">Richard Hudson</a> of North Carolina, who heads the House GOP campaign arm, said in an interview Monday he hasn’t given vulnerable members any advice about how they should be talking about the expiring Obamacare subsidies in their districts.</p> 
<p>“What I’ve been saying to my colleagues is that we’ve all got to do a better job of talking about what we’re for,” Hudson said. “Because we have actual policies that would bring down premiums and make health care more affordable — we just need to be more vocal about it.”</p> 
<p>Asked if he was worried about the expiring subsidies costing House Republicans the majority next year, he said, “No.”</p> 
<p>“Premiums are high — we told them they would be high if Obamacare passed,” Hudson said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thune eyes spending package to tackle military helicopter safety issue</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/thune-eyes-spending-package-to-tackle-military-helicopter-safety-issue-00691645</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2444-d5c5-a7bf-6e5fe8e30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 18:10:34 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> suggested Monday that he wants to tackle a contentious provision on military helicopters in a separate spending package — and not by axing it from the annual defense policy bill that’s set to pass this week.</p> 
<p>That’s a blow to Senate Commerce Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175665" data-person-id="175665">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Texas) and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51160" data-person-id="51160">Maria Cantwell</a> (D-Wash.), the committee’s ranking member, who have been calling on their colleagues to help strip the language out of the National Defense Authorization Act. </p> 
<p>The nation’s top transportation accident investigator has complained that the NDAA language would allow certain military helicopters to fly without using an advanced location-broadcasting technology in the Washington area, a safety concern raised following the deadly January crash between a regional jet and an Army Black Hawk near Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport.</p> 
<p>Cruz and Cantwell have filed a pair of amendments to both nix the NDAA provision and attach their ROTOR Act, <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2503" data-bill-id="US_119_S_2503">S. 2503</a>, to the bill instead.</p> 
<p>Referencing the ROTOR Act, Thune said Monday he thinks the dispute over the NDAA language could be handled by holding a vote on attaching the Cruz-Cantwell legislation to a fiscal 2026 appropriations package.</p> 
<p>“I think we’ll get there on that. But, yeah, it’d be really hard to undo the defense authorization bill,” he said.</p> 
<p>During a separate news conference Monday, Cruz appeared to acknowledge that adding his bill to the NDAA could be a tall order, with only a few days left before Congress leaves for the holidays. Instead, he hinted that he was eyeing other landing spots.</p> 
<p>“I’m seeking a vote on the ROTOR Act as part of any appropriations measure before the current continuing resolution expires at the end of next month,” he said alongside Cantwell. Some relatives of victims from the disaster joined them.</p> 
<p>Cruz was referencing the stopgap funding bill that lapses at the end of January, which is not an annual appropriations package.</p> 
<p><b>What’s next:</b> It's unclear whether there will be votes on the two lawmakers’ NDAA amendments, but Thune’s comments suggest that’s unlikely.</p> 
<p>In response to a question from POLITICO about whether Thune has said if he will allow those amendments to get floor votes, Cruz replied, “We don’t have a firm commitment on that yet, but I’m hopeful that we will.”</p> 
<p>Cruz made the pitch that if senators cut the provision out of the NDAA, which is poised to pass this week, the House would be able to “easily” OK the measure again, given how lawmakers in that chamber recently passed it 312-112.</p> 
<p>When asked if he is focusing on the amendment to nix the NDAA language before then attempting to pass the ROTOR Act in early 2026, Cruz said the bottom line is he wants to “fix this problem, and so procedurally, there are multiple, multiple possibilities.”</p> 
<p>He said he’s discussing the subject with Thune, as well as Cantwell.</p> 
<p><b>Context: </b>Cruz and Cantwell have slammed the provision in question, as has Jennifer Homendy, chair of the National Transportation Safety Board, who says it would allow the military to resume flying certain helicopters in the Washington area without using the advanced location-broadcasting technology called Automatic Dependent Surveillance-Broadcast Out, or ADS-B Out.</p> 
<p>The House and Senate Armed Services committees have defended the language.</p> 
<p>Cruz told reporters he spoke about the topic with President Donald Trump’s team last week, and that Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth has committed to him that he won’t oppose the ROTOR Act.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Banking will not vote on crypto bill this week</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/senate-banking-will-not-vote-on-crypto-bill-this-week-00691505</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-23c4-d653-afff-67c44f2c0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 15:47:46 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> is abandoning a push to hold a committee vote on a major cryptocurrency bill this week, punting the issue to next year.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the South Carolina Republican said in a statement Monday that the panel “is continuing to negotiate and looks forward to a markup in early 2026.”</p> 
<p>“Chairman Scott and the Senate Banking Committee have made strong progress with Democratic counterparts on bipartisan digital asset market structure legislation,” said the spokesperson, Jeff Naft. “From the outset, Chairman Scott has been clear that this effort should be bipartisan. He has consistently and patiently engaged in good-faith discussions to produce a strong bipartisan product that provides clarity for the digital asset industry and also makes America the crypto capital of the world.”</p> 
<p>The move comes following a frantic week of negotiations between top Banking Committee Republicans and a group of Senate Democrats who are working to strike a deal on the legislation. Democrats have pushed for more time for the talks to play out.</p> 
<p>Scott's decision to punt was previously reported by Punchbowl News.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No. 2 House Democrat Katherine Clark gets primary challenger</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/katherine-clark-primary-00690707</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-22f2-d5ec-abbb-faf67dd00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:00:15 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Massachusetts Rep. Katherine Clark, the No. 2 House Democratic leader, will face a challenge from the left in 2026.</p> 
<p>Jonathan Paz, an organizer and former Waltham city councilor, announced his campaign against Clark, the Democratic whip, in <a href="https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=vTsVLm-JnGU" target="_blank">a video posted late Sunday night</a> emphasizing the need to “rebuild” the Democratic party.</p> 
<p>“I’m challenging one of the most powerful Democrats in the House because we need new leadership,” said Paz, whose family immigrated from Bolivia. “Let's just call it what it is: our Democratic leaders are failing us. They're not stopping Trump. They're not making life more affordable. They're not building a party for the working class.”</p> 
<p>Paz, who served for four years on the Waltham City Council, more recently founded Fuerza, a volunteer group that responds to ongoing Immigration and Customs Enforcement arrests in the region.</p> 
<p>Clark is likely to be the highest-ranking House Democrat to face a contested primary. Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries had faced a run by New York City Council Member Chi Ossé, but Ossé <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/05/chi-osse-ends-bid-to-challenge-jeffries-00679466" target="_blank">dropped the bid</a> earlier this month.</p> 
<p>Clark ran unopposed in 2024 and had more than $1.8 million in her campaign coffers as of the end of September. A spokesperson did not respond to requests for comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: House GOP at the Obamacare cliff</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-deadline-health-care-vote-00690377</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-200e-da65-a1bf-e7ff1a830000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans are set to mark their final session week of 2025 with a muddled health care message that’s poised to have a big impact — a nationwide spike in insurance costs after Obamacare subsidies expire in less than three weeks.</p> 
<p><b>— The plan:</b> GOP leaders are eyeing a Wednesday vote on a package of conservative-friendly health policies they released last Friday (Pro subscribers can read <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/whats-in-the-house-gops-new-health-bill-00689839" target="_blank">more of the specifics here</a>).</p> 
<p>The proposal — a narrowly-focused attempt at striking consensus in a divided GOP conference — doesn’t include an extension of Affordable Care Act tax credits that lapse on Dec. 31. Instead, leadership is expected to throw a bone to anxious rank-and-file members by giving them the chance to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/house-will-vote-on-obamacare-extension-next-week-00689845" target="_blank">vote on an amendment</a> that would continue the subsidies — a vote that’s almost guaranteed to fail.</p> 
<p>“I expect people are going to have an opportunity to vote their conscience and then go defend their votes back home like we always do,” House Budget Chair Jodey Arrington (R-Texas) said.</p> 
<p><b>— Mods scramble: </b>Moderate Republicans in the House and Senate are privately strategizing about how to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/gop-obamacare-message-muddled-00690145" target="_blank">pull off an unlikely last-minute deal</a> to avert a health care price shock that could have big ramifications for the midterms. A number of vulnerable Republicans have argued they will lose their seats if the ACA subsidies aren’t extended.</p> 
<p>The Obamacare amendment that GOP moderates are set to offer this week is expected to be a two-year extension of the subsidies with an income cap and other changes — a plan modeled after a proposal from Reps. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) and Jared Golden (D-Maine).</p> 
<p>House Democratic leaders are waiting to see what the final amendment looks like. They could try to tank the bill by helping adopt the amendment, though many Democrats have criticized the Fitzpatrick-Golden plan.</p> 
<p><b>— More unhappy campers:</b> Key GOP hard-liners are upset that Republican leaders are allowing an ACA vote at all, and they know they have leverage. They're pushing for more restrictive language in the Obamacare amendment and want commitments on conservative policy wins in health legislation early next year, in exchange for letting the bill proceed. To shore up support with conservatives, GOP leaders are pairing the health care package with two bills that would limit transgender surgeries for minors.</p> 
<p><b>— Why it matters for the midterms: </b>This week’s vote is clear evidence that the GOP is struggling to define an easily digestible message on health care costs heading into next year’s elections, as Democrats stay mostly unified around extending the ACA subsidies.</p> 
<p>Every Senate Democrat voted to advance an Obamacare tax credit extension last week, and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries has managed to keep most of his members from endorsing compromise proposals from purple-district Republicans.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders have been unwilling to rethink a 15-year-old party message that Obamacare is a costly disaster, despite growing anxiety from their members about the electoral consequences.</p> 
<p>The saga has left many House Republicans frustrated even if they share concerns about the cost of the subsidies and the legacy of the ACA.</p> 
<p>“A lot of people are receiving this health care — they don’t need the rug pulled out from under them,” Rep. Dan Meuser (R-Pa.) told POLITICO last week. “Definitely should have been done a ways back, we could say, because of the shutdown. But we’ve got to do everything we can and then do more.”</p> 
<p>“I don’t see how we just leave things in limbo.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House to take up permitting: </b>House GOP leaders are eyeing a Thursday morning vote on bipartisan legislation that would aim to speed up energy project permitting. Republicans are working to shore up their votes, with resistant hard-liners arguing the bill would undermine President Donald Trump’s authority to block offshore wind energy projects.</p> 
<p><b>— Thune’s busy week: </b>Senate Majority Leader John Thune is looking to wrap the NDAA and confirm dozens of nominees before Congress leaves town for the holidays. Potential bonus items include some appropriations action and a war powers vote.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Nicholas Wu and Josh Siegel contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Our message is simple’: Democrats unite as GOP again struggles to address health care</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/gop-obamacare-message-muddled-00690145</link>
      <description>Republicans are confronting old divisions as members clash over expiring insurance subsidies used by millions of Americans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1e31-d983-affb-dffb28860000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/55/a0/164a9ae64853a022cc2da8dd4c41/u-s-congress-21759.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas), left, said Republicans have lacked "the backbone and the will power" to tackle the Affordable Care Act as Speaker Mike Johnson, right, pushes a narrow package of health care bills.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/55/a0/164a9ae64853a022cc2da8dd4c41/u-s-congress-21759.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With key Obamacare tax credits <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/obamacare-congress-negotiations-health-care-00688191" target="_blank">set to expire within weeks</a>, Democrats have unified behind a simple message: extend the subsidies and keep health insurance premiums from spiking for more than 20 million Americans.</p> 
<p>Republicans, meanwhile, have engaged in a wide-ranging blame game while scrambling to coalesce behind an easily digestible plan to lower health care costs. That struggle comes to a head this week as House leaders move to put what they hope will be a consensus GOP plan up for a vote.</p> 
<p>House Republican leaders chose a narrow set of proposals to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/whats-in-the-gop-health-bill-00689950" target="_blank">include in that plan</a>, arguing they lacked broad agreement for a more comprehensive undertaking as they seek to satisfy competing GOP factions, including vulnerable Republicans who’ve argued they will lose their seats if the Affordable Care Act subsidies aren’t extended.</p> 
<p>The upshot is that there is no clear, unified GOP message on health care going into the year-end deadline when the tax credits expire — and no guarantee that Republicans will be able to pass anything this week to address the loss of beefed-up subsidies instituted under former President Joe Biden.</p> 
<p>“I expect people are going to have an opportunity to vote their conscience and then go defend their votes back home like we always do,” House Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259549" data-person-id="259549">Jodey Arrington</a> (R-Texas) told reporters about the GOP’s health care strategy.</p> 
<p>Across the Capitol, there are already clear signs of unease. While Senate Republicans mostly united behind a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3386" target="_blank">plan that would expand health savings accounts</a> as an alternative, four GOP senators <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/senate-rejects-health-care-bills-00686855" target="_blank">crossed party lines</a> to advance a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_3385" target="_blank">Democratic proposal</a> that would simply extend the Obamacare subsidies for three years.</p> 
<p>Now rank-and-file Republicans in both chambers are privately strategizing about how to pull off an unlikely 11th-hour deal to avert a health care price shock that has triggered significant anxiety throughout the party about the political blowback they could face in the 2026 midterms. House GOP moderates negotiated an amendment vote that could tack a subsidy extension onto the leadership-backed health bill, but that vote is expected to fail and only serve as political cover for the vulnerable House Republicans.</p> 
<p>That’s because top GOP leaders have resisted scrambling a 15-year-old message their party has been loath to abandon: Obamacare is a costly disaster, and Americans need better options.</p> 
<p>“There's a couple of [issues] that split our conference — that's one of them,” House Majority Leader<a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655"> Steve Scalise</a> said last week.</p> 
<p>The dissonance within the GOP ranks comes as Democrats remain confident their push to preserve the status quo will resonate with voters — especially after making it a central focus of the shutdown fight that ended last month.</p> 
<p>Party leaders have managed to keep Democrats largely unified behind a three-year extension of the expiring subsidies. Every Senate Democrat voted to advance that proposal Thursday. In the House, Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> has managed so far to keep the vast majority of his members from endorsing compromise extension proposals that purple-district Republicans have introduced.</p> 
<p>“Our message is simple: Republicans have created a health care crisis for American families who are seeing their health insurance <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/aca-marketplace-premium-payments-would-more-than-double-on-average-next-year-if-enhanced-premium-tax-credits-expire/" target="_blank">rise by 100 to 300 percent</a>, and the solution has been in front of us for a while,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198769" data-person-id="198769">Brad Schneider</a> (D-Ill.), chair of the centrist New Democrats.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump, the GOP’s master of viral messaging, has not been especially helpful when it comes to health care. Trump has repeatedly referred to Obamacare as a “disaster” and railed against insurance companies who collect the federal subsidies — echoing a favorite conservative talking point.</p> 
<p>But he has yet to lay out a specific alternative beyond giving “money to the people” directly to buy health care. Trump gave a nod to the issue during the annual Congressional Ball at the White House Thursday, addressing “Democrats” in the room: “We’re going to start working together on health care. I really predict that.”</p> 
<p>While some of the Republicans present took the comments to mean Trump might be open to striking a so-far elusive health care deal in January, many Democrats doubt he will be willing to come to the table and extend a framework he has railed against for a decade. Moreover, the party is preparing to use the issue — and Trump’s refusal to engage — to hammer Republicans in the midterms as they show vulnerability on cost-of-living concerns.</p> 
<p>“He doesn’t understand the hell that people are going through as they prepare to pay these hugely high health care costs,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a> of Connecticut, a member of Senate Democratic leadership.</p> 
<p>On Capitol Hill this week, familiar divides are likely to play out as Republicans come to terms with the impending expiration of the subsidies, which will mean a much smaller swath of Americans will be eligible for tax credits. The Congressional Budget Office projects millions will choose to drop their coverage rather than pay higher premiums.</p> 
<p>Already concerns about political blowback forced House GOP leaders to backtrack from their initial strategy of simply allowing the Obamacare subsidies to expire. As part of their efforts to pass a package of measures meant to erode insurance regulations enacted in the ACA, "the process will allow" for an <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/house-will-vote-on-obamacare-extension-next-week-00689845" target="_blank">amendment vote on extending the subsidies</a>, a Republican leadership aide said Friday.</p> 
<p>But that has rankled conservatives who have publicly criticized those Republicans who are supporting an extension, and top party leaders do not expect the amendment will be adopted.</p> 
<p>“My Democratic colleagues broke health care, and now they are down here saying we must give more money to insurance companies,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a> (R-Texas) said Friday on the House floor, “and any Republican who goes along with that needs to answer for doing the same thing.”</p> 
<p>Republicans have health care plans, he added, but “what we don’t have is the backbone and the will power to stand up and deliver.”</p> 
<p>Scores of Roy’s colleagues, however, have taken a more nuanced view — that even though they share concerns about the cost of the subsidies and the legacy of Obamacare, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/no-house-gop-health-plan-00684401" target="_blank">they are frustrated</a> their party appears to be confronting the issue only at the last minute with family budgets at stake for thousands of their constituents.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/306852" data-person-id="306852">Dan Meuser</a> (R-Pa.) said last week he wasn’t completely happy with the situation and that Republicans “need to move this along.”</p> 
<p>“A lot of people are receiving this health care — they don't need the rug pulled out from under them,” Meuser said. “Definitely should have been done a ways back, we could say, because of the shutdown. But we've got to do everything we can and then do more. “I don't see how we just leave things in limbo,” he added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shapiro backs Brooks in primary for top Dem target</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/shapiro-backs-brooks-in-key-pa-house-race-00690263</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1f67-da65-a1bf-ffffae960000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 19:44:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro is endorsing firefighter union head Bob Brooks in the state’s 7th Congressional District — the potential 2028 presidential contender putting his thumb on the scale in a crowded primary for a seat that’s among Democrats’ top targets to flip in the midterms.</p> 
<p>Shapiro’s endorsement, shared first with POLITICO, comes as the governor is plotting an aggressive push to help his party wrest back control of the House by turning as many as four Pennsylvania districts blue — throwing his weight behind candidates as other governors attempt to nab seats for their parties via redistricting. It’s a strategy that will serve as a major test of Shapiro’s coattails in a critical swing state in 2026, when he’s also up for reelection. And if successful, it could give him a launchpad for a 2028 White House bid.</p> 
<p>Shapiro helped recruit Brooks into the race and is headlining a <a href="https://x.com/JuliaTerruso/status/1993402862563737754?s=20" target="_blank"><u>fundraiser for Brooks’ campaign</u></a> Thursday in Philadelphia. Brooks is competing in a five-way primary as Democrats attempt to unseat GOP Rep. Ryan Mackenzie, who flipped the Lehigh Valley district last year by one of the narrowest margins in the country.</p> 
<p>“[Brooks] is the fighter our friends and neighbors all across the Lehigh Valley deserve in Washington. Throughout his career, Bob has worked hard for the men and women of organized labor — standing up for higher wages, better healthcare, and safer working conditions,” Shapiro said in a statement. “Bob has always had my back — and I am proud to endorse him in this race and stand with him in the fight to make life more affordable and get stuff done for our communities.”</p> 
<p>Brooks called Shapiro’s support “a powerful vote of confidence in our campaign.” Brooks, the head of the statewide Pennsylvania firefighters union, <a href="https://www.cityandstatepa.com/politics/2022/06/shapiro-picks-big-endorsement-statewide-firefighters-union/368357/" target="_blank"><u>backed Shapiro early</u></a> in his 2022 gubernatorial bid.</p> 
<p>It’s part of a broader undertaking by Shapiro to remake the state Democratic Party and spearhead its midterms efforts. Shapiro has <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-5285-dc40-a1bb-77e578660000" target="_blank"><u>installed allies atop the state party</u></a> and funneled cash into its coffers. He’s already endorsed Janelle Stelson in her repeat bid to unseat GOP Rep. Scott Perry in the state’s 10th District, after she lost by barely a percentage point last year. Formal endorsements of Scranton Mayor Paige Cognetti and Bucks County Commissioner Bob Harvie against vulnerable GOP Reps. Rob Bresnahan and Brian Fitzpatrick, respectively, are expected in the new year.</p> 
<p>Brooks has racked up endorsements from across the political spectrum — from the moderate Shapiro to progressives like Sen. Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.) and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.).</p> 
<p>But Shapiro’s endorsement is unlikely to clear a field that has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/democrats-2026-primaries-house-00670194" target="_blank"><u>divided Democratic special interest groups</u></a> and where another candidate, Ryan Crosswell, has so far been the fundraising leader.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump seems to wave the white flag on his US attorneys gambit</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/13/donald-trump-us-attorneys-senate-confirmation-00689692</link>
      <description>The president is pushing for an end to the so-called “blue slip” to solve for the disqualification of a handful of unconfirmed U.S. attorneys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1455-d983-affb-d5dfa93d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/23/0e/7aff57534eee8ff13dce3ff26285/trump-22183.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Brandon/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump speaks during a signing ceremony in the Oval Office on Dec. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/23/0e/7aff57534eee8ff13dce3ff26285/trump-22183.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erica Orden</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erica Orden</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For months, President Donald Trump has used unconventional tactics to install loyalists as top federal prosecutors across the country, and battled challenges to their authority. Now, he appears to be conceding defeat.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration has signaled in recent days that it may refocus its efforts on trying to eliminate a Senate procedural tool used to block U.S. attorney nominees, rather than continuing to challenge the disqualifications in court. The move comes after New Jersey U.S. Attorney Alina Habba <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/alina-habba-steps-down-as-new-jerseys-top-federal-prosecutor-00680823" target="_blank">resigned from her post</a> following a court ruling upholding <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/alina-habba-appeals-court-ruling-00671224" target="_blank">her disqualification</a> along with a handful of other U.S. attorneys who have been stripped of their positions by federal judges.</p> 
<p>On Friday, Delaware U.S. Attorney Julianne Murray also <a href="https://x.com/Murray4DE/status/1999475044494532645" target="_blank">left her post</a>, citing the Habba ruling.</p> 
<p>The administration’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/19/trump-us-attorneys-senate-confirmation-bypass-00515124?cid=apn" target="_blank">tactics with U.S. attorneys</a> — bypassing the Senate or sidestepping federal judges to keep unvetted prosecutors in place — are a crucial component of Trump’s effort to deploy the Justice Department against his perceived enemies. He has relied on loyalist U.S. attorneys to pursue what critics call baldly political investigations and prosecutions, including those against New York Attorney General Letitia James and former FBI Director James Comey.</p> 
<p>On Thursday, Trump called the so-called “blue slip” process, in which home-state senators can veto judicial or U.S. attorney nominees, a “scam.” It’s his latest attack after Trump has spent months <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/trump-us-attorneys-republicans-00617024" target="_blank">pressuring Senate Republicans</a> to review <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/25/grassley-trump-blue-slip-criticism-00522724" target="_blank">the practice</a>.</p> 
<p>“‘Blue Slips’ are making it impossible to get great Republican Judges and U.S. Attorneys approved to serve in any state where there is even a single Democrat Senator,” Trump wrote in <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115701239677984151" target="_blank">a social media post</a>. “So unfair to Republicans, and not Constitutional.” He directed Senate Majority Leader John Thune “to get something done, ideally the termination of Blue Slips.”</p> 
<p>Thune quickly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/b-00686585" target="_blank">rejected</a> that call, and Senate Judiciary Chair Chuck Grassley has indicated <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/25/grassley-trump-blue-slip-criticism-00522724" target="_blank">no interest</a> in scrapping the practice. Grassley also blamed the administration for failing to advance more U.S. attorney nominees, saying he has been “hamstrung waiting for background investigations and other paperwork from the administration.”</p> 
<p>Asked for comment, a White House spokesperson referred to Trump’s public statements.</p> 
<p>Earlier in the week, Trump appeared to acknowledge that the court rulings disqualifying his U.S. attorneys will ultimately force them out of their offices, even though many have remained there following the rulings.</p> 
<p>Trump-installed federal prosecutors in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/28/judge-los-angeles-top-federal-prosecutor-illegally-appointed-00626804" target="_blank">Los Angeles</a> area, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/30/us-attorney-nevada-cases-00589343" target="_blank">Nevada</a> and in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/james-comey-letitia-james-cases-lindsey-halligan-00666896" target="_blank">Eastern District of Virginia</a>, for example, have continued working in those offices despite being deemed disqualified. Trump, however, seemed to predict that may not continue.</p> 
<p>“We have about seven U.S. attorneys who are not going to be able to keep their jobs much longer because of the blue slip,” Trump <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rHBAMvZ-mc4" target="_blank">told reporters</a> Monday.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Next stop: SCOTUS?</h5> 
<p>Carl Tobias, a law professor at the University of Richmond, said the administration appears now to have only two options: continue to try to install temporary U.S. attorneys, only to repeatedly have those choices disqualified by courts, or attempt the traditional process of Senate confirmation.</p> 
<p>Tobias said he suspects the administration doesn’t want the U.S. attorney gambit to reach the Supreme Court. “I think the last thing they want is to have the Supreme Court say no, right? Because then the game is over.”</p> 
<p>That way, he said, “they can continue to do what they've been doing, and that is avoiding advice and consent, which is in the Constitution, which they've done in more than half the districts, and continue to play games with the system.”</p> 
<p>But other legal experts said it wasn’t clear how the Supreme Court might rule. Nina Mendelson, a professor at the University of Michigan Law School and an expert on acting officials, said she could envision the court leaning either way.</p> 
<p>“If [the administration] does appeal, the Supreme Court may, on the one hand, be interested in preserving the Senate's constitutional function of advice and consent and thus narrowly interpret the President's authority to appoint acting US Attorneys,” she wrote in an email. “On the other hand, the Supreme Court has, in a series of cases, expressed its concern for presidential control and flexibility, which might prompt it to more generously interpret the President's power.”</p> 
<p>Though the administration can appeal the rulings disqualifying the prosecutors, it hasn’t in two key instances. In the Habba case, the Justice Department has said publicly that it will pursue an appeal, but asked the 3rd Circuit Court of Appeals for an extension to decide how it will proceed. New Jersey’s Democratic senators, Cory Booker and Andy Kim, have urged the White House to <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/booker-kim-ask-white-house-to-discuss-suitable-habba-replacement-00686144" target="_blank">work with them</a> to select Habba’s replacement.</p> 
<p>In the case involving Lindsey Halligan in the Eastern District of Virginia, Attorney General Pam Bondi said in late November that it would pursue an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/james-comey-letitia-james-cases-next-00672339" target="_blank">“immediate”</a>appeal — but it hasn’t.</p> 
<p>Instead, it kept Halligan in place and attempted, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/letitia-james-indictment-grand-jury-00678079" target="_blank">but twice</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/letitia-james-indictment-fails-00687508" target="_blank">failed</a>, to re-indict James. On Thursday, in a sign the White House may be adopting a more traditional approach to installing U.S. attorneys, the administration began seeking Senate confirmation for Halligan by <a href="https://www.judiciary.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/halligan_sjq.pdf" target="_blank">submitting her questionnaire</a> to the Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the committee, however, noted that Halligan doesn’t have blue slips from Virginia’s senators, and “nominees without blue slips don’t have the votes to advance out of committee or get confirmed on the Senate floor.”</p> 
<p>The administration is appealing disqualification rulings in the Los Angeles area and Nevada. In the Northern District of New York, a federal judge appears <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/john-sarcone-letitia-james-subpoeanas-00677169" target="_blank">poised to disqualify</a>John Sarcone III, the Trump-aligned U.S. attorney whose office is pursuing a separate investigation of James.</p> 
<p>Despite Trump’s griping about having his choices blocked, he is on pace to match the Biden administration for the number of U.S. attorneys confirmed during its first year. To date, Trump has seen 13 U.S. attorneys confirmed by the Senate, up from <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/26/donald-trump-us-attorneys-senate-confirmation-00583005" target="_blank">just two in September,</a> and 18 more are expected to be confirmed next week, bringing the total to 31.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/ChuckGrassley/status/1999154682246144409?s=20" target="_blank">“ATTN WH; SEND MORE NOMS,”</a> Grassley wrote on social media on Thursday.</p> 
<p>Legal experts said the uptick in Senate-confirmed top federal prosecutors is a welcome development, even if they aren’t in some of the highest-impact districts.</p> 
<p>“That’s promising for the system,” Tobias said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inside Republicans’ new health bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/whats-in-the-gop-health-bill-00689950</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-152b-d7be-a79b-bd7f27d00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 19:54:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders plan to take a vote next week on conservative-friendly health policies they’ve pursued for years. It’s the latest GOP counter to Democrats’ push to extend expiring Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>Here is what’s in the bill, <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-149e-d5ec-abbb-dc9e1e070000" target="_blank">the text of which was released Friday</a>.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">CHOICE accounts</span><br>Oklahoma GOP Rep. Kevin Hern’s <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_118_HR_3799" target="_blank">CHOICE legislation</a> would allow employers to offer workers tax-advantaged funds to pay for individual health insurance, in lieu of offering a traditional group plan. It would also offer tax incentives for employers who adopt the arrangements.</p> 
<p>Both Republicans and Democrats like the concept because it promotes individual choice in health coverage while also encouraging Obamacare sign-ups.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Funding cost-sharing reductions</span><br>When Obamacare was first implemented in 2014, the federal government paid insurers directly to offset cost-sharing reductions, or discounts on deductibles that insurers must offer to people making between 100 and 250 percent of the federal poverty level.</p> 
<p>In response to a lawsuit filed by congressional Republicans, a federal judge in 2016 ruled the government’s payments were illegal because the funding wasn’t explicitly appropriated by Congress. The Obama administration appealed, but the first Trump administration dropped the case and stopped the payments.</p> 
<p>Insurers are still required to offer the cost-sharing reductions, they just no longer get reimbursed by the federal government.</p> 
<p>To make up for the loss of federal dollars, insurers substantially increased silver premiums, a process known as “silver loading.” That’s driven up the amount of federal premium subsidies the government pays insurers, because the subsidy amounts are tied to the second-lowest-cost silver plan in the marketplace.</p> 
<p>Republicans now want to put an end to that practice and start funding the cost-sharing reductions again, which is expected to lower premiums for silver plans, thus lowering the amount Obamacare enrollees receive in premium subsidies, regardless of what type of plan they’re enrolled in.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Association health plans</span><br>Association health plans enable several small businesses to band together to get health insurance. The framework includes <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_2528" target="_blank">a bill</a> from Education and Workforce Chair Tim Walberg (R-Mich.) that would permit self-employed people to buy an association health plan.</p> 
<p>Democrats oppose the idea. In addition to not guaranteeing essential benefits, the plans can distort the insurance market by drawing away healthy, young people, according to a statement from Virginia Rep. Bobby Scott, the top Democrat on the Education and Workforce Committee.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Stop-loss policy</span><br><a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_2571" target="_blank">The Self-Insurance Protection Act</a> from Rep. Bob Onder (R-Mo.) would expand access for employers to “stop-loss” policies that enable them to protect against catastrophic health costs from just a few employees.</p> 
<p>The bill would ensure that such policies are not classified as traditional health insurance by the federal government. But it has generated pushback from Democrats because it can also restrict states from regulating them.<br><span class="story-text__heading-medium"></span><span class="story-text__heading-medium">Pharmacy benefit managers</span><br>The bill aims to overhaul how pharmacy benefit managers operate. Those are companies that negotiate drug prices on behalf of insurers and large employers. Pharmaceutical companies and lawmakers have long blamed them for high drug prices.</p> 
<p>A push to change the rules governing the PBMs fell apart last year after Trump adviser Elon Musk tanked year-end legislation, but there continues to be overwhelming bipartisan interest in advancing changes that shed light on the PBMs’ business practices.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comer threatens the Clintons with contempt for refusing to be deposed in Epstein probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/comer-threatens-the-clintons-00689936</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1500-d5ec-abbb-dd960a880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 19:05:45 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Oversight Committee Chair James Comer has threatened to pursue contempt charges against former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton if they do not sit for depositions in Congress’ probe of the Jeffrey Epstein investigation.</p> 
<p>His warning Friday came after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/trump-clinton-gates-included-in-epstein-photo-trove-00688628" target="_blank">the committee released new photos</a> from the estate of the late convicted sex offender, including a signed photo depicting the former president smiling alongside Epstein and Ghislaine Maxwell, who is serving 20 years in prison for her role in his child sex trafficking operation.</p> 
<p>Comer excoriated the Clintons in a statement for apparently refusing to participate in the investigation. The House Oversight Committee subpoenaed the Clintons in August, and has requested they sit for depositions next week.</p> 
<p>“It has been more than four months since Bill and Hillary Clinton were subpoenaed to sit for depositions related to our investigation into Jeffrey Epstein and Ghislaine Maxwell’s horrific crimes. Throughout that time, the former President and former Secretary of State have delayed, obstructed, and largely ignored the Committee staff’s efforts to schedule their testimony,” Comer said.</p> 
<p>He said the House Oversight Committee will seek to hold both Clintons in contempt of Congress if they do not appear for depositions or reschedule in the coming weeks. Comer scheduled Bill Clinton’s deposition for Wednesday and Hillary Clinton’s deposition for Thursday.</p> 
<p>“If the Clintons fail to appear for their depositions next week or schedule a date for early January, the Oversight Committee will begin contempt of Congress proceedings to hold them accountable,” said the statement.</p> 
<p>Bill Clinton’s ties to Epstein have been publicly known for years. His association included traveling on Epstein’s private plane after he left office. A spokesperson for the former president has said he cut off ties with Epstein prior to his 2019 arrest and was unaware of Epstein’s alleged crimes.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-12T12:17:18-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House GOP leaders race to release health care package Friday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/house-health-plan-obamacare-00688701</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1368-d983-affb-d7fb921e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 11:34:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders are rushing to release a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/04/congress/johnson-house-gop-health-care-plan-00676661" target="_blank">new health care package</a> Friday, but a morning meeting with members of key GOP faction left unsettled whether to allow a floor vote on extending expiring Obamacare tax credits.</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and other members of his leadership team want to file text of the health care legislation as soon as possible in order to comply with House notice requirements and prepare it to be take up by the House Rules Committee early next week. But the matter has been held up as they negotiate with conservative hard-liners who are wary of teeing up a vote to extend the expiring insurance subsidies.</p> 
<p>“This is going to be a great piece of legislation that everyone will be united around," Johnson told reporters after the meeting.</p> 
<p>The core package is expected to include an expansion of health savings accounts and association health plans, as well as funding for cost-sharing reductions that help low-income Obamacare enrollees afford their plans. But moderate House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-republicans-weigh-vote-on-obamacare-extension-00688189" target="_blank">want an amendment vote</a> to add what is likely to be a two-year extension of the enhanced tax credits that were enacted by Democrats during the Covid-19 pandemic and are set to expire Dec. 31. </p> 
<p>GOP leaders had been planning to let the subsidies expire, but they are now inclined to allow a floor amendment on an extension, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the closed-door Friday morning meeting with Johnson and a swath of senior Republicans.</p> 
<p>The current thinking among House GOP leaders, three of the Republicans said, is that the amendment would fail on the floor. But the GOP moderates who support a subsidy extension would be likely to support the final package anyway, two other Republicans said, believing that voting for something to lower health care costs would be better than nothing.</p> 
<p>One possible wrinkle: Some Democrats could end up supporting the amendment, giving it enough backing for adoption. But that could lead some conservative Republicans to abandon the bill, and Democrats are not likely to support its other provisions — potentially tanking the final product.</p> 
<p>Conservatives, including Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259549" data-person-id="259549">Jodey Arrington</a> (R-Texas), have strongly objected to any attempt to continue the tax credits.</p> 
<p>"I pity the Republican that has to explain why they would propagate or perpetuate, I should say, a fraud-ridden subsidy from the Covid era to prop up a failed health care program," Arrington said Friday, saying it would make Republicans "complicit in propping up the very driver" of rising health care costs.</p> 
<p>But he suggested a vote on an extension would happen regardless: "I expect people are going to have an opportunity to vote their conscience and then go defend their votes back home like we always do."</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said the topic was “heavily discussed” in the meeting, which another senior House Republican described as “lively.” Leaving the session, Scalise said leaders would be "making final decisions shortly, because we have to file text later today.”</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-12T18:21:28-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump, Clinton, Gates included in Epstein photo trove</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/trump-clinton-gates-included-in-epstein-photo-trove-00688628</link>
      <description>The House Oversight Committee Democrats released photos from the Epstein estate linking powerful men to the late convicted sex offender.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-131a-d983-affb-d7db33b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 10:20:13 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ce/8c/8c777a6348e0b19f26453d2f47ac/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-018.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">House Oversight Committee</media:credit>
        <media:title>An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Donald Trump with unidentified women, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ce/8c/8c777a6348e0b19f26453d2f47ac/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-018.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Photos from the estate of Jeffrey Epstein tie the convicted sex offender to President Donald Trump, former President Bill Clinton, tech billionaire Bill Gates and former Treasury Secretary Larry Summers.</p> 
<p>These men and others are featured in the roughly 95,000 photos the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee has received from the Epstein estate as part of its ongoing investigation. House Democrats released batches of photos on Friday. </p> 
<p>“It is time to end this White House cover-up and bring justice to the survivors of Jeffrey Epstein and his powerful friends,” the Oversight Committee's top Democrat, Rep. Robert Garcia of California, said in a statement. “These disturbing photos raise even more questions about Epstein and his relationships with some of the most powerful men in the world. We will not rest until the American people get the truth. The Department of Justice must release all the files, NOW.”</p> 
<p>When asked about the latest photos, Trump said he had not seen them.</p> 
<p>"There are hundreds and hundreds of people that have photos with him. So that's no big deal," he told reporters Friday in the Oval Office. "I know nothing about it."</p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson in a statement accused Democrats of "selectively releasing cherry-picked photos with random redactions."</p> 
<p>"The Democrat hoax against President Trump has been repeatedly debunked and the Trump Administration has done more for Epstein’s victims than Democrats ever have by repeatedly calling for transparency, releasing thousands of pages of documents, and calling for further investigations into Epstein’s Democrat friends," she continued. "It’s time for the media to stop regurgitating Democrat talking points and start asking Democrats why they wanted to hang around Epstein after he was convicted.”</p> 
<p>Jackson also accused House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries (D-N.Y.) and Del. Stacey Plaskett, Democratic delegate for the Virgin Islands, of maintaining ties with Epstein following his sex trafficking charges. Plaskett was found in a recent release of Epstein emails to have been texting with Epstein during a congressional hearing to get information about the panel's witness, Trump's ex-fixer Michael Cohen.</p> 
<p>A Jeffries spokesperson pointed to a recent CNN interview where the leader said he had no knowledge of email outreach to Epstein, nor did he receive a donation.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Plaskett did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Other individuals in the photographs beyond Trump also did not respond to requests for comment Friday. </p> 
<p>The Justice Department is required to release the full tranche of Epstein-related documents by Dec. 19, per the terms of legislation Congress passed last month.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/0e/37/685cef5140028f8517d3b0951d0c/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-016.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Clinton, center, Ghislaine Maxwell, center right, and Epstein, far right, with two unidentified people, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Clinton, center, Ghislaine Maxwell, center right, and Epstein, far right, with two unidentified people, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p>Of the photos shared Friday, one features Trump alongside someone who appears to be a young woman (her face has been redacted). Another shows Trump standing beside Epstein — who died by suicide in his jail cell in 2019 — chatting with a woman, while a third has Trump grinning among a half-dozen women whose faces have also been redacted. In that shot, he appears to have his arm around one woman’s waist.</p> 
<p>There is another photo in the tranche showing pictures of "Trump condoms" being sold for $4.50 each, branded with the words, “I’M HUUUUGE!”</p> 
<p>There is a signed photo from Clinton depicting him smiling alongside Epstein and Epstein’s associate Ghislaine Maxwell, who is serving 20 years for her part in the sex trafficking scheme. While Clinton's association including travel on Epstein's plane after the former president left office is well-documented, Clinton has said he cut ties with Epstein before his 2019 arrest and had no knowledge of his crimes.</p> 
<p>The images underscore Epstein’s long and storied network of connections to powerful men across industries, from filmmaker Woody Allen to conservative strategist Steve Bannon. They were sent to Capitol Hill after a subpoena from the Oversight panel for materials from the late financier’s estate, separate from the documents demanded from the Justice Department by legislation.</p> 
<p>While Epstein’s connections with these public figures are far from new revelations, they highlight the extent to which Epstein reveled in his relationships with powerful people.</p> 
<p>Gates, the Microsoft founder, is seen smiling at Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, in one photo and grinning beside a pilot in front of a plane in another. That photo has been published previously.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/19/d4/d433a4794d03843cd6e2aa31900e/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-011.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Gates and Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Bill Gates and Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p>Summers, the former Treasury Secretary, is seen in one photo on what appears to be a small plane. He and Epstein forged a relationship during Summers' tenure as president of Harvard University, and he's the latest public figure to face fallout from his connections to the financier, including being <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/american-economic-association-imposes-lifetime-ban-on-larry-summers-00673686" target="_blank">banned from</a> the American Economic Association and forced to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/larry-summers-steps-back-from-harvard-responsibilities-00661238" target="_blank">step back from his roles</a> at Harvard.</p> 
<p>In a November statement, Summers said he took "full responsibility for my misguided decision to continue communicating with Mr. Epstein."</p> 
<p>Bannon, who served as Trump’s chief strategist during his first term, is seen in the photos talking with Epstein at a desk and standing beside Epstein in front of a mirror, posing for a selfie. </p> 
<p>In another photo, Bannon appears to be speaking with Allen. </p> 
<p>Bannon has not responded to requests for comment from various news outlets since appearing in some of the earlier Epstein file releases, but over the summer <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/07/14/maga-factions-epstein-fallout-reactions-00452358" target="_blank">told attendees at a Turning Point USA summit</a> that “Epstein is a key that picks the lock on so many things, not just individuals but also institutions.”</p> 
<p>Allen <a href="https://www.thetimes.com/culture/film/article/woody-allen-jeffery-epstein-prince-andrew-wife-jrkm02l6l" target="_blank">has said</a> he attended dinner parties with Epstein and said the financier "couldn't have been nicer." He also said he never saw Epstein with underage girls.</p> 
<p>One photo shows Epstein with a smiling Richard Branson, the billionaire businessman who founded the Virgin Group.</p> 
<p>Trump has maintained that he ended his relationship with Epstein years ago and called the efforts clamoring for the release of the files a “hoax.” In a pivot last month, he gave congressional Republicans his nod of approval to vote to release the Epstein files and swiftly signed the legislation into law.</p> 
<p>Those files are due in the coming days, after courts cleared the way for the Justice Department to release grand jury materials and the 30-day clock for Attorney General Pam Bondi to make the contents public is winding down. A Justice Department spokesperson did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Clinton, meanwhile, has been subpoenaed by the Oversight panel, but a date has not yet been announced for his testimony to congressional investigators. Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-epstein-investigation-department-of-justice-00651851" target="_blank">has ordered Bondi</a> to investigate Democrats with ties to Epstein, including Clinton and Summers. Bondi asked Jay Clayton, U.S. attorney in the Southern District of New York, to lead the charge.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/4a/a8/c17119e94ce886b523c1b2de0178/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-015.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Woody Allen, left, and Steve Bannon, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate of Woody Allen, left, and Steve Bannon, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p>It's not clear when the rest of the photos will be released, though a Garcia press release noted that Oversight Democrats would be released "to the public in the days and weeks ahead," while remaining "committed to protecting the identities of survivors."</p> 
<p>Speaking with reporters on Capitol Hill Friday, Garcia said his staff had only gone through a small portion of the materials and appropriate redactions would require days and weeks of committee work. Other photos turned over to lawmakers include depictions of women and Epstein's properties, he added.</p> 
<p>"Obviously, there are photos of powerful men and folks that we want to have an opportunity to speak with and ask questions of," said Garcia.</p> 
<p>"The so-called Department of Justice under the Trump administration needs to comply with the law," House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries said at his weekly press conference Friday. "We as Democrats, led by Robert Garcia ... are going to continue to make sure that we're holding this administration accountable."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for House Oversight Republicans blasted Democrats' unilateral release.</p> 
<p>“Once again, Ranking Member Robert Garcia and Oversight Committee Democrats are cherry-picking photos and making targeted redactions to create a false narrative about President Trump. We received over 95,000 photos and Democrats released just a handful," the spokesperson said in a statement. "Democrats’ hoax against President Trump has been completely debunked. Nothing in the documents we’ve received shows any wrongdoing. It is shameful Rep. Garcia and Democrats continue to put politics above justice for the survivors.”</p> 
<p>Oversight Committee Democrats released several dozen additional photos Friday evening showing what appears to be the Epstein property and a dental chair in a room surrounded by wall-mounted masks of men's faces, as well as a zoom-in of a "massage therapy system" and Epstein himself in a bathtub.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/7e/b1/7bc38c2b4f4d8fb07a85c45fc28b/embargo-holdforepsteindocs-019.JPG" alt="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate shows a massage therapy system, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files." data-portal-copyright="House Oversight Committee" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="House Oversight Committee" data-title="An undated photograph from Jeffrey Epstein's estate shows a massage therapy system, released on Dec. 12, 2025, by the House Oversight Committee as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files."/><p><i>Nicholas Wu, Sam Sutton, Lisa Kashinsky, Gregory Svirnovskiy and Faith Wardwell contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Johnson stares down another revolt — this time on energy permitting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/12/congress/mike-johnson-republicans-energy-permitting-reform-00688529</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1090-da65-a1bf-f7f915880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson is facing another intraparty revolt — one that has nothing to do with health care, defense policy or pay for college athletes.</p> 
<p>Johnson wants the House to vote on a bill next week from Natural Resources Chair Bruce Westerman (R-Ark.) that would accelerate the production and delivery of domestic energy. For Republicans, the energy permitting revamp would fulfill a yearslong legislative priority — and for President Donald Trump, his dreams of achieving U.S. energy dominance.</p> 
<p>But some conservatives want to speed up the federal permitting process only for fossil fuels. <a href="https://www.eenews.net/articles/conservatives-sound-alarm-about-westermans-nepa-bill/" target="_blank">And they’re furious</a> that Westerman’s measure, which advanced out of committee with bipartisan support last month, would ease the path for green energy projects, too.</p> 
<p>The GOP will likely need to supply all the votes on a procedural rule — as per usual in the majoritarian House — to tee up the measure for floor debate. Right now, the votes may not be there.</p> 
<p>“We’re taking in … whether [the legislation] goes far enough to free up all the constraints put on oil, gas and nuclear and whether it’s still promoting too much wind and solar,” said Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas), who sits on House Rules. </p> 
<p>The meltdown prompted Johnson to delay consideration of the bill from this week to next. But hard-liners have yet to budge, and Westerman told POLITICO Thursday there are no plans to remove some of the most controversial language to appease them.</p> 
<p>Freedom Caucus Chair Andy Harris (R-Md.) and Reps. Jeff Van Drew (R-N.J.) and Chris Smith (R-N.J.) <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/conservative-lawmakers-warn-trump-against-gop-led-nepa-overhaul-00684686" target="_blank">escalated their campaign against the measure</a> this week in a new letter to Trump and Interior Secretary Doug Burgum.</p> 
<p>“Your administration would have fewer tools to rightfully halt offshore wind development, and projects currently being blocked by successful court actions brought by your administration would see a second life,” they warned of the consequences of Westerman’s bill becoming law.</p> 
<p>Van Drew told POLITICO he plans to share his concerns directly with the White House in the coming days.</p> 
<p>For now, Johnson plans to plow ahead as GOP leadership aides work to resolve outstanding issues, three people close to negotiations told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“We are working through it,” Westerman said in an interview. “We’re just taking everybody’s input under consideration right now and focusing on the big picture of getting permitting reform done.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House moves on health care: </b>Moderate House Republicans are talking with leadership about possibly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-republicans-weigh-vote-on-obamacare-extension-00688189" target="_blank">setting up an amendment vote</a> that could add an extension of expiring Obamacare subsidies to a health care package expected on the floor next week, according to four people granted anonymity to describe internal conversations.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders will likely meet with a few more Republican groups Friday morning before finalizing the package. House Majority Leader Steve Scalise said Thursday he is hoping to file the bills Friday.</p> 
<p><b>— Speaking of health care: </b>The Republican Study Committee is hosting a briefing Friday morning on health care polling with the Foundation for Government Accountability, according to a copy of the event invitation obtained by POLITICO. The invite says the briefing will feature “critical polling showing what the American people really care about when it comes to health care.”</p> 
<p><i>Kelsey Brugger, Josh Siegel, Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘We don’t have a lot of time’: Congress comes to terms with an all-but-certain lapse in Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/obamacare-congress-negotiations-health-care-00688191</link>
      <description>Some Republicans are scrambling to see if a deal can come together in the final weeks of 2025, but most are skeptical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0fdb-d7be-a79b-afff5f860006</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 19:01:58 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f5/c1/5b4d275d4b529de761c972eecbc5/u-s-congress-44512.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) is among the senators trying to use Thursday's failed votes to spark new momentum toward compromise.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f5/c1/5b4d275d4b529de761c972eecbc5/u-s-congress-44512.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hopes for a quick patch saving millions of Americans from sharply higher health insurance premiums have given way to expectations of a long slog on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>It is now all but certain that enhanced Obamacare subsidies first implemented by Democrats as a Covid relief measure will expire Dec. 31 after the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/senate-rejects-health-care-bills-00686855" target="_blank">Senate voted down</a> competing partisan health plans Thursday and House GOP leaders indicated they had no plans to bring an extension up for a vote this year.</p> 
<p>Less certain is when lawmakers might begin to pick up the pieces — or if they have any hope of finding a solution. A bipartisan group of lawmakers continues to talk about a possible 11th-hour path forward, hoping that the failed votes this week can give them some badly needed momentum. But most of their colleagues are convinced the discussions won’t bear fruit until 2026.</p> 
<p>A major obstacle is that leaders in both parties are, at least so far, prioritizing plans that don't bridge existing political gaps. Top Republicans are putting forward proposals that would not extend the expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies, while Democrats are sticking to proposals that most in the GOP say they cannot accept.</p> 
<p>“We don’t have a lot of time,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a>, an Alaska Republican who voted for both parties’ proposals Thursday. She said she was “talking to people of good will and good faith about how we might be able to sketch” out a compromise.</p> 
<p>But Murkowski also said in a subsequent statement that Congress needs to reach an agreement by Jan. 15 — a concession talks are likely to slip into next year.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/221844" data-person-id="221844">Mike Rounds</a> (R-S.D.), who has been involved in loose bipartisan health care discussions for months, said he hoped the failed votes would lead negotiators to “bridge the impasses.” But asked if there was any way to prevent the subsidies from lapsing, he said, “I honestly don’t know.”</p> 
<p>The stakes for American families are considerable. Independent analysts say those who purchase insurance directly from the ACA exchanges could <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/aca-marketplace-premium-payments-would-more-than-double-on-average-next-year-if-enhanced-premium-tax-credits-expire/" target="_blank">see their premiums spike</a> by an average of about $1,000 a year. For some, it could be considerably more. The political stakes are also vast, with many moderate Republicans fretting that a lapse would threaten their reelection campaigns and endanger the GOP’s congressional majorities.</p> 
<p>That sense of panic has not trickled up to Republican leaders, who appear ready to send lawmakers home next week until Jan. 6. By that time, the enhanced subsidies will have lapsed — returning the tax credits to prepandemic levels that assist a much narrower swath of Americans. The Congressional Budget Office <a href="https://www.cbo.gov/publication/61734" target="_blank">has estimated millions of Americans</a> will go without insurance as people drop their plans to avoid having to pay higher premiums.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> left the door open Thursday to an 11th-hour deal but also acknowledged the obvious: They don't have a lot of time.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see where the discussions go,” Thune told reporters after the failed votes. “I think we’ll get a sense for that here pretty soon.”</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, meanwhile, is plowing forward with a plan to hold a vote next week on a House GOP-authored health care framework that, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal discussions, will not include a subsidy extension. Instead it is likely to mirror aspects of the Senate proposal that mostly united Republicans Thursday but failed to leapfrog the chamber’s 60-vote legislative threshold.</p> 
<p>Yet to weigh in is President Donald Trump. While he voiced support this week for giving federal money “to people,” not insurance companies, he also has avoided taking a firm stance for or against an extension of the subsidies.</p> 
<p>The White House appears to be tacitly on board with Johnson’s decision not to pursue an extension, with administration officials believing that path unifies the GOP.</p> 
<p>"The idea is to put together a package before Christmas that has unity with 218 Republican votes in the House," said a person familiar with health care discussions on the Hill and in the White House who was granted anonymity to discuss them.</p> 
<p>“The biggest threat these days is the discharge petition," the person said, adding that the only way to avoid it is to "put together a consensus plan" among House Republicans.</p> 
<p>It was a reference to ongoing bipartisan effort to circumvent leadership and force floor votes on legislation that would temporarily extend the expiring Obamacare subsidies while imposing new eligibility requirements. Two such petitions have been filed and received Republican sign-ons in recent days.</p> 
<p>Neither petition has yet to garner the sweeping support from Democrats needed to succeed, however. Instead, Democratic leaders are pushing to discharge a bill that would simply extend the current subsidy framework for three years — to the doorstep of the next presidential election.</p> 
<p>“Every single House Democrat is supportive of a straightforward extension of the Affordable Care Act tax credits,” House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> told reporters Thursday. “All we need are four Republicans to join us.”</p> 
<p>With nothing likely to make it to Trump’s desk by the end of the year, lawmakers are increasingly turning their attention to January. Many view the Jan. 30 government shutdown deadline as the real cutoff for a bipartisan health care deal.</p> 
<p>Some conservative Republicans are pushing their party to simply pursue a partisan health care bill under the budget reconciliation process, which can skirt the Senate’s 60-vote supermajority requirement. They argue that Democrats are not actually interested in compromising and instead want to run their midterm campaigns on the expired subsidies.</p> 
<p>“I know there are some on my side who say 60-vote bills stand the test of time, yadda yadda yadda,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said. “There are not going to be 60 votes. The Democrats think this is a great political issue for them.”</p> 
<p>But others are talking about paths to compromise, even as bipartisan negotiations have struggled to gain traction over months of attempts before, during and after the 43-day government shutdown where Democrats made extending the subsidies the centerpiece of their demands.</p> 
<p>One idea already floating around the Senate Thursday was to merge the GOP plan, which expands health savings accounts, with an extension of the subsidies accompanied by the kinds of restrictions contemplated in the House bills subject to discharge petitions. Thune said he is being kept in the loop on the bipartisan and bicameral conversations about how to quickly come up with a deal before the holidays.</p> 
<p>Few, however, thought that approach could come together that quickly.</p> 
<p>“It would be great if we could get it done next week, but realistically I think we’ve got to look at it as next week but also January,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151837" data-person-id="151837">John Hoeven</a> (R-N.D.).</p> 
<p>Among Republicans, the pressure posed by the subsidy cliff is rivaled by the anxiety they are feeling about the approaching midterms. GOP lawmakers in both chambers are warning that they are handing Democrats’ a political cudgel to use against them next year if the tax credits expire.</p> 
<p>Democrats will pick “sympathetic cases” to use against Republicans, retiring Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) predicted, “and there will be plenty of them.” Sen. Jim Justice (R-W.Va.) added that if Republicans are not concerned about the midterm implications, “then you're living in a cave.”</p> 
<p>But Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> warned it might already be too late.</p> 
<p>“The toothpaste is out of the tube,” he said Thursday. “Once Jan. 1 comes and everyone is locked into their insurance proposals, you can't put the toothpaste back in the tube.”</p> 
<p><i>Megan Messerly and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Republicans weigh vote on Obamacare extension</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-republicans-weigh-vote-on-obamacare-extension-00688189</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-0fd8-d983-affb-cfdbfe820004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 18:58:48 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Moderate House Republicans are talking with GOP leaders about possibly setting up an amendment vote that could add an extension of expiring Obamacare subsidies to a health care package expected to move across the floor next week, according to four people granted anonymity to describe internal conversations. </p> 
<p>GOP leaders have been skeptical of such a move. But they’re currently working through whether it could pass muster with other Republicans, and it’s under discussion as centrist House Republicans grow desperate to hold off the expiration of the subsidies that more than 20 million Americans use, the four people said. </p> 
<p>Those leadership conversations also include whether to include Texas Rep. August Pfluger’s bill redirecting the tax credits into health savings account contributions as part of the GOP health package next week. </p> 
<p>Other options are under consideration as GOP leaders continue working on a plan Thursday, with Majority Leader Steve Scalise saying in a brief interview he wants to file the bills Friday. </p> 
<p>Two of the GOP moderates, Rep. Jen Kiggans of Virginia and Brian Fitzpatrick of Pennsylvania, have launched discharge petitions to force an extension vote, but those are unlikely to succeed before the subsidies expire on Dec. 31. </p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick spoke to Johnson about the push during a meeting in his office Thursday, according to another person granted anonymity to describe the meeting. Fitzpatrick and Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.) also huddled with Johnson on the floor later Thursday. </p> 
<p>But Republican leaders are still working through what have so far been intractable issues over using the subsidies to fund abortion coverage, which risks the ire of at least some GOP hard-liners. There are fears adding it as an amendment could imperil the entire package, with key conservatives on the Rules Committee opposed to an ACA extension able to block its consideration. </p> 
<p>But many more House Republicans — even some conservatives — believe there needs to be some sort of subsidy extension as a bridge. “I think we have to have that,” one conservative granted anonymity to speak candidly about a possible amendment. </p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman (S.C.), one of the hard-liners on the Rules Committee, said he opposes the inclusion of a subsidy extension but would not say if he would move to block it from getting a vote.</p> 
<p>“I don't want the discharge petition where you won't have anything,” he said. “We'll see how it goes.”</p> 
<p>The House wrangling over an Obamacare patch comes after four Republican senators voted Thursday to advance a Democratic proposal for a three-year subsidy extension. There are ongoing bipartisan conversations among rank-and-file senators about how to get a deal across the finish line before they leave for the holidays. </p> 
<p>Senate Majority John Thune has left the door open to taking up a bill if it can get through the House but said in an interview Thursday evening that he was not personally encouraging House Republicans to send over a bill. </p> 
<p>“I’ve talked to the speaker, and I think he’s trying to gauge where his members are and see what the traffic will bear over there,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
