<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 09:00:00 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Forget Mamdani. New York’s real political shift happened everywhere else.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/28/new-york-upstate-blue-wave-mamdani-00668749</link>
      <description>Democrats flipped over 50 county legislative seats across the state. Republicans flipped one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bcd5-d49b-af9f-bcf507bd0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 09:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/03/f6/70eca5c8449e90fed1da5dc39a54/unlimiteduse-electionday-ny-11-04-2025-063.JPG">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Bing Guan for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A voter deposits their ballot into a ballot counting machine at a polling site inside P.S. 20 in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York, on Electio Day, Nov. 4, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/03/f6/70eca5c8449e90fed1da5dc39a54/unlimiteduse-electionday-ny-11-04-2025-063.JPG" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Bill Mahoney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Bill Mahoney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Zohran Mamdani’s decisive win in New York City — along with key victories in New Jersey and Virginia — suggested Democrats are headed into the midterms from a position of strength. But they didn’t capture how deep that strength ran.</p> 
<p>Across suburbs, rural counties and small towns in New York, Democrats posted electoral gains that rival — and in many cases surpass — the party’s 2017 “Blue Wave.” In a state with enough competitive House races to decide control of the chamber, the outcome amounts to a wakeup call for already-wary Republicans.</p> 
<p>New York Democrats once viewed the 2017 elections as among their best ever. The Blue Wave that year was driven by purple suburbs making a hard shift left. This year in New York, that tilt was felt even more widely — with Democrats in every corner of the state pointing to economic uncertainty exacerbated by President Donald Trump’s policies as voters’ top concern.</p> 
<p>“It was about peoples’ anxiety,” said Leslie Berliant, who ousted a Republican incumbent to win a seat in the Otsego County Legislature. “It definitely was a feeling that we don’t feel protected by what’s happening in the federal government, and we need to make sure we have people in place at the local level who care about our needs. Democrats ran on that, and I think it worked.”</p> 
<p>Much of the early narrative from this fall’s elections has cast Democrats’ gains as occurring mostly in places where they often win. An examination of every race on the ballot in New York shows the shift was far more widespread, with Democrats having their best-ever performances in numerous deep red towns and rural areas.</p> 
<p>There’s still plenty of time for conditions to change before the 2026 midterms. But a year out, this year’s contests offered very little solace for Republicans as they prep for seven battleground congressional races in New York and a gubernatorial election in which they hope to build on the rightward momentum of the 2022 and 2024 elections.</p> 
<p>A POLITICO review of results in 268 county, town and village executive branch races found an average 10 point increase in the Democratic margin.</p> 
<p>Democrats made gains in at least 18 different county legislative bodies in November, flipping over 50 seats across the Empire State. They gained five seats in Oswego County, which Trump won by 27 points in 2024. They picked up five in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history. And they flipped five in Onondaga and gained their first majority there since the 1970s.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/2e/42/1c9870ba4f8a91b982bf30d4b66a/ap9724584833457619.jpg" alt="Shown above, New Paltz in Ulster County. Democrats picked up five seats in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history" data-portal-copyright=" Historic Hotels of America and Mohonk Mountain House via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Shown above, New Paltz in Ulster County. Democrats picked up five seats in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history"/><p>For Republicans, the outcome painted a bleak picture: GOP candidates flipped one county legislative seat in the entire state.</p> 
<p>Democrats who won these local contests shared similar stories about what they saw on the ground. Trump voters didn’t necessarily throw their MAGA hats into bonfires. But economic anxiety persists in every corner of the state. And Republican voters feeling the pinch — whether over federal cuts, tariffs, or inflation — are now at least willing to hear a pitch from Democrats.</p> 
<p>In the town of Erwin, just north of the Pennsylvania border, Democrat Debbie Shannon ousted Republican Steuben County Legislator James Kuhl, the son of a former congressman.</p> 
<p>“I knocked on everyone’s door, and the economy is the big hot button issue,” Shannon said. “Especially for Republicans who said Trump ran on ‘I’m going to lower the price of eggs,’ and that isn’t happening. I think they’re breaking with the administration.”</p> 
<p>This November was only the second time since 1989 that Democrats won mayoral races in each of the state’s five largest cities. Sharon Owens was the first Democrat elected Syracuse’s mayor in 12 years, Sean Ryan received the most votes in a contested Buffalo race since 1981, and Mamdani received more votes than any Democratic nominee in New York City since at least 1965.</p> 
<p>Democratic performance in places that were once untouchable Republican strongholds is perhaps more notable when looking ahead to next year. Consider, for example, the Rochester suburbs: Penfield elected a Democratic supervisor for the first time in four decades, Greece for the first time in 120 years, and Perinton for the first time <a href="https://www.democratandchronicle.com/story/news/politics/elections/2025/11/05/monroe-county-ny-election-takeaways-from-2025/87098791007/" target="_blank">since the Civil War</a>.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/76/a4/2a3681d04783be8a1a4780c9a816/2024-election-61546.jpg" alt="Voters cast their ballots at the Susan B. Anthony Museum & House in Rochester in 2024." data-portal-copyright="Lauren Petracca/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Voters cast their ballots at the Susan B. Anthony Museum & House in Rochester in 2024."/><p>Democrats also flipped mayoral or supervisor offices in places like Tonawanda, Oneonta, Monroe, Rensselaer, Johnson City and Riverhead.</p> 
<p>All told, there were 118 municipal executive races outside of New York City this year that were contested in either 2021 or 2023. The number of ballots cast for Democrats grew from 1.3 million to 1.6 million, a 22 percent increase. The number for Republicans grew 1 percent to 1.6 million.</p> 
<p>That means that while the typical upstate or Long Island Democrat lost by 10 points in the last go-around, they received 50 percent of the vote this year.</p> 
<p>Even in places where Republicans had good nights, there’s little evidence of a broader rightward shift. Republicans made gains in Saratoga Springs, but not as many as Democrats made in the larger, neighboring town of Clifton Park. Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman won big in his reelection campaign. But Democrats improved on their performance in 17 of the other 21 executive offices on the ballot on Long Island. And in the other major suburban county, Westchester’s Ken Jenkins had the best performance by a Democratic county executive candidate in two decades.</p> 
<p>The Democratic gains were thus much broader than those in 2017. The following year, New York Democrats flipped three congressional seats, and the number of people voting for Andrew Cuomo in the gubernatorial contest grew 76 percent in 2018 compared with 2014.</p> 
<p>All of that is promising to Democrats like Gov. Kathy Hochul who are on the ballot in 2026. The Republican path to a statewide victory involves running up the numbers in red parts of the state, doing well in suburban towns and minimizing the Democratic margin in New York City. All three of those need to happen in 2026 for a GOP win to be plausible in statewide contests — and this November, none of them did.</p> 
<p>But there were also hints of an anti-establishment trend mixed in with the leftward shift — and certainly more than a glimmer of that in New York City. That trend makes forecasting Hochul’s fate a little less clear come next June or November.</p> 
<p>Not everybody who won said they did so by running on a Democratic platform. Candidates in the rural North Country, for example, attempted to outdo each other in criticizing Hochul’s handling of <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2025/02/25/kathy-hochul-prison-crisis-corrections-officers-00206033" target="_blank">a prison strike</a> earlier this year.</p> 
<p>Voters are looking “for leadership that kind of ignores traditional party stances,” said Lebanon Supervisor-elect Adam Carvell, who noted he wasn’t focused on purely partisan issues before receiving 63 percent of the vote as a Democrat in a town where Trump received 60 percent last year. The electorate, he said, wasn’t just bothered by the White House’s actions, but policies <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/05/democratic-lawmaker-readies-clean-car-delay-proposal-00336271" target="_blank">supported by</a> the sitting Democratic governor, such as an electric vehicle mandate.</p> 
<p>“The municipal electrical vehicle mandate that was coming down, it’s a Hochul thing,” said Carvell. “The boots-on-the-ground take on that here is that’s unworkable … The idea of introducing very expensive, hard to maintain [electric snow plows] scared a lot of people.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/96/8b/b891625e4ff8be183e7d56d48fd9/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2246393039" alt="New York Gov. Kathy Hochul speaks at a ribbon-cutting ceremony at the National Urban League's new headquarters in Harlem on Nov. 12, 2025, where she was joined by New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani." data-portal-copyright="Spencer Platt/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="New York Gov. Kathy Hochul speaks at a ribbon-cutting ceremony at the National Urban League's new headquarters in Harlem on Nov. 12, 2025, where she was joined by New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani."/><p>Yet even the candidates who eschewed strict partisanship repeatedly highlighted the federal government and its role in the economy as the top concern on voters’ minds.</p> 
<p>Don Dabiew, who won a seat in Franklin County’s Legislature, pointed to a hit to Canadian tourism.</p> 
<p>“Almost all the small towns around are seeing an impact of that because people aren’t coming across anymore,” Dabew said. “There’s some people that are upset with our country as a whole, and they don’t want to support us anymore.”</p> 
<p>In Canandaigua, mayor-elect Thomas Lyon highlighted federal cuts.</p> 
<p>“DOGE was eliminating jobs left and right,” he said. “The national veterans’ suicide hotline is located here in Canandaigua at our VA, and you had people losing their jobs, not being able to provide support to our veterans.”</p> 
<p>Even in local elections where partisanship wasn’t rampant, Democrats said the current frustrations about the country as a whole are opening doors that hadn’t been open before.</p> 
<p>“We listened and said, ‘We’re not talking about federal politics here; we’re talking about right here, right now, our town,’” said Lisa Moore, who won the South Bristol supervisor’s race.</p> 
<p>“A lot of people were just so sick and tired of the divisiveness at the federal level, and the sort of miserableness, that they were happy to not demonize Democrats, as Democrats have been demonized in our town in the past.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-26T21:55:06-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>White House presses Congress for drone powers ahead of World Cup, Olympics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/white-house-asks-congress-for-power-to-take-down-drones-00670564</link>
      <description>The administration is facing resistance from GOP leadership of the Senate Commerce Committee.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c2fc-d739-a3ba-defcd0910001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 20:46:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ad/c8afee09486f9e9a81622a73d0d8/white-house-80173.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump walks on the South Lawn of the White House after disembarking from Marine One Nov. 2, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ad/c8afee09486f9e9a81622a73d0d8/white-house-80173.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House is pressing lawmakers to give the administration more power to take down aerial drones in domestic airspace in advance of the U.S. hosting the 2026 World Cup and 2028 Olympic games, according to three people involved in ongoing negotiations.</p> 
<p>The push to attach the measure to a must-pass defense policy bill in the coming weeks is facing resistance on Capitol Hill, including from the Senate Commerce Committee led by Sen. Ted Cruz, amid concerns the proposal constitutes federal overreach. The Commerce panel has jurisdiction over aviation affairs.</p> 
<p>Draft <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-c28a-df0f-abfa-e3eabde50000" target="_blank"><u>legislation floated by the White House</u></a> and obtained by POLITICO would give agencies including the Departments of Homeland Security and Justice new authority to take counter-drone measures for “large scale public gatherings or events, critical infrastructure or correctional facilities.” The proposal would also broaden “counter-drone authority” for state and local law enforcement.</p> 
<p>Under current law, federal agencies are empowered to intervene against drone threats only when specific, high-risk facilities, including government operations and power plants, are deemed to be at risk.</p> 
<p>The push comes as the leaders of the House and Senate Armed Services Committees are trying to finalize the text of the defense bill by early next week. Spokespeople for the Republican chairs and top Democrats on the committees did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>The White House request of Congress is the administration’s latest move to ramp up security ahead of the World Cup and Olympic games. The administration announced earlier this month it was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/13/drone-defenses-world-cup-00606174" target="_blank"><u>launching a $500 million program</u></a> to help state and local governments develop anti-drone strategies ahead of the events as well as any celebrations that might take place around the 250th anniversary of the signing of the Declaration of Independence.</p> 
<p>“This is an important issue we must address as we prepare for global events such as the World Cup and the Olympics, and we need to ensure proper authorities are in place to protect the American people,” said a House GOP leadership aide granted anonymity to discuss the negotiations.</p> 
<p>A White House official granted anonymity to describe ongoing deliberations said the White House Office of Legislative Affairs has been working on legislative language and circulating related proposals among congressional offices since September. The administration has been working closely with Speaker Mike Johnson’s office on the legislative draft and has also engaged with Senate Majority Leader John Thune’s office, according to the official.</p> 
<p>“It’s something that the admin feels is extremely important given particularly all of the events of the next year,” the White House official said. “Having a strong strong event infrastructure and drone counter-measures is very important.”</p> 
<p>It’s unclear if Congress will adopt the plan. A person granted anonymity to discuss private negotiations said Senate Commerce views the draft provision as an “extremely problematic” power grab that would give federal security officials too much leeway in determining how best to “protect the public."</p> 
<p>Phoebe Keller, a spokesperson for Cruz on the Commerce Committee, said in a statement, “We are happy to work with the administration on this proposal and any suggestion to the contrary is simply untrue."</p> 
<p>Sen. Eric Schmitt, a Missouri Republican on Senate Commerce, also supports tougher counter-drone legislation. Kansas City, Mo., is scheduled to host six World Cup matches next year.</p> 
<p>“Unauthorized drones pose a clear risk to Americans and our homeland, and it’s time Congress acts and shows more urgency,” Schmitt spokesperson Rachel Dumke said in a statement. “Senator Schmitt looks forward to continuing to work with his colleagues to find a path forward.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Trump targeting these Democrats could backfire</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/democrats-trump-sedition-backfire-00670552</link>
      <description>The administration’s attacks have elevated the six moderate lawmakers who cut an anti-Trump video urging troops to disobey illegal orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c255-d49b-af9f-f6f549780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 18:03:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d8/77/689cf1054421aafa8a8228245780/main-wu-brakkton-demssedition.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Claudine Hellmuth/POLITICO (source images via AP)</media:credit>
        <media:title>From left to right: Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), Rep. Chris Deluzio (D-Pa.), Rep. Chrissy Houlahan (D-Pa.), Sen. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.), Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) and Rep. Maggie Goodlander (D-N.H.)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d8/77/689cf1054421aafa8a8228245780/main-wu-brakkton-demssedition.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump is going to war with Democrats over the military. It could backfire on him.</p> 
<p>The president’s attacks on six Democrats who recorded a video encouraging military members to buck unlawful orders are elevating members of a faction that just delivered big off-year wins for their party. Most hail from swing states or districts, identify as centrists and are leveraging their national security backgrounds to argue that Democrats can retake the patriotic lane.</p> 
<p>Trump is also boosting some potential 2028 presidential hopefuls, Arizona Sen. Mark Kelly and Michigan Sen. Elissa Slotkin, while further undercutting the GOP’s attempts to make New York progressives like Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani and Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez the face of the Democratic Party.</p> 
<p>“Pete Hegseth and Donald Trump are providing Mark Kelly with the kind of visibility that almost no amount of money could buy,” said Barrett Marson, an Arizona-based Republican strategist, referring to the Defense secretary who ordered an investigation of Kelly. “Every 2028 contender wishes they could be attacked like this by the Trump administration.”</p> 
<p>Since Trump accused the six of “sedition” and even suggested they could be executed, they’ve racked up millions of views on social media, done the cable news circuit and blasted out fundraising appeals highlighting the attacks.</p> 
<p>It’s heightened the stature of even those who have already been the subject of speculation about their 2028 aspirations. Kelly, who was on the short list to be Vice President Kamala Harris’ running mate last year, has already <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/west-wing-playbook-remaking-government/2025/07/23/reviews-are-in-on-the-first-2028-dem-hopefuls-00471732" target="_blank">visited a raft of early primary</a> and general-election battleground states this year. But only after Trump’s attack was he invited on “Jimmy Kimmel Live!” this week.</p> 
<p>In recent months, Slotkin has been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/24/slotkin-has-a-war-plan-to-beat-trump-dont-be-weak-and-woke-00308176" target="_blank">testing what she calls a “war plan”</a> to “contain and defeat Donald Trump” in speeches outside of her state, meeting with <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook/2025/11/14/slotkin-finds-dems-at-a-crossroads-00651647" target="_blank">low-propensity voters</a> and theorizing about what she calls “Project 2029.” Now she’s brought those themes to a series of interviews and public appearances over the past week.</p> 
<p>As Democrats debate how far to lean into themes of patriotism more often claimed by conservatives, a group of lawmakers organized by Slotkin released a <a href="https://x.com/ElissaSlotkin/status/1978930764692455430?s=20" target="_blank">video with anti-authoritarian themes</a> ahead of the “No Kings” protests last month. A <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2558895077819811" target="_blank">follow-up video last week</a> called on troops not to obey unlawful orders, prompting Trump’s explosion.</p> 
<p>The president posted on social media they were committing “SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL” by suggesting military members ignore their chain of command and shared a post calling for traitors to be hanged. The White House later denied Trump was threatening the lawmakers with death. Since then, the Pentagon has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894?" target="_blank">opened an investigation</a> into Kelly, who is a retired Navy captain, and the six lawmakers claim the FBI <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/democrats-fbi-trump-00668584" target="_blank">has made inquiries</a> through congressional authorities.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/9c/cc/3f39da1f4b4a8b675b81bf61bdc9/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2162570114" alt="Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), another Democrat with a military background, said " data-portal-copyright="Samuel Corum/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), another Democrat with a military background, said "/><p>Democrats, particularly those with military backgrounds, have leapt to their colleagues’ defense, echoing their message about following the law and accusing Trump of weaponizing the government against his political opponents.</p> 
<p>“Trump knows that we’re a threat” to Republicans’ grip on Washington, said Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), a military veteran whose Serve America PAC supports several of the Democrats in the video. “These are great leaders who can take the fight to Trump and MAGA.”</p> 
<p>“It’s classic Trump — he ratchets everything up to an 11 and it blows up in his face,” said Austin Cook, a Democratic strategist and former Slotkin spokesperson. “Not only did it reinforce everything swing voters have always hated about him, but it’s also given this group the biggest megaphone they’ve ever had.”</p> 
<p>But Tim Edson, a GOP strategist and former political director for the National Republican Senatorial Committee, said the video will only confirm the GOP base’s preconceived, negative views of Democratic officials.</p> 
<p>“Republicans believe these Democrats are deranged with hatred of Trump, and it’s just their latest attempt to undermine lawful policies simply because they’re Trump’s policies,” Edson said. “These embarrassing antics only rally Republicans to the president.”</p> 
<p>Some Democrats think it’s too early to tell how things will shake out for the “seditious six,” as some Trump officials are <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/video/6385589967112" target="_blank">calling the lawmakers</a>.</p> 
<p>“Whether it works or not will depend on what comes next, if an illegal order actually does come down they get to be leaders saying ‘I told you so,’” texted one strategist who has consulted for Democratic veterans and was granted anonymity to speak candidly. “If one doesn’t, they’ve simply made themselves victims to Trump’s latest attacks. Most Democrats fail at playing on his turf.”</p> 
<p>Kelly doubled down on the video’s message during his talk-show appearance Tuesday night and noted some of his Republican colleagues are expressing support: “People are starting to take a look at this and saying, ‘Wow, this is just nuts that he's going after U.S. senators and members of the House for something they said.’”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Nobody will ever believe it’: James Comer airs doubts about his own Epstein investigation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/james-comer-jeffrey-epstein-investigation-00669127</link>
      <description>The House Oversight chair fears “so many conspiracy theories” will haunt any findings he ultimately releases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bd22-d49b-af9f-bde6efbc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/bb/05/b27bf2c64e73a8775e84773b7496/u-s-congress-50847.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. James Comer said he is hopeful recent House document requests will turn up further notable revelations about the late convicted sex offender.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bb/05/b27bf2c64e73a8775e84773b7496/u-s-congress-50847.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Without James Comer’s House investigation into Jeffrey Epstein, the world might never have seen the “birthday book” full of lewd materials or the trove of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/here-are-9-of-the-most-shocking-revelations-in-the-latest-batch-of-epstein-documents-00649853" target="_blank">more than 20,000 documents</a> elucidating the late convicted sex offender’s dealings with global power players — including President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>It would have been a career-defining triumph for any House Oversight Committee chair. But not for Comer, who expressed deep ambivalence about the ongoing probe in a recent interview.</p> 
<p>That reflects the complicated and unpredictable fallout from the Epstein saga, which has helped derail the Republican congressional agenda and the opening year of Trump’s second term. It could also have implications for Comer’s own political ambitions — given his own belief that Americans’ minds might well be impervious to his panel’s conclusions.</p> 
<p>“I fear the report will be like the Warren Report,” he said. “Nobody will ever believe it.”</p> 
<p>Comer’s reference to the 1964 report on the assassination of President John F. Kennedy led by Chief Justice Earl Warren underscores how the Epstein case has enthralled legions of skeptics who say the federal government is intent on protecting powerful men involved in the exploitation of young women and girls.</p> 
<p>That was one big reason, Comer said, that he “wasn't excited about doing the investigation.” Even now, he has not fully committed to releasing a final report, saying it would happen “eventually, I would assume.”</p> 
<p>“There's so many conspiracy theories,” he said, leaving unspoken that his reputation and legacy are now entwined with the case.</p> 
<p>That’s a shift from where Comer had staked his political brand a year ago, as the top GOP investigator of Joe Biden. But his two-year effort to undermine the sitting president produced uneven results, with his impeachment probe focusing on Biden family business dealings <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/08/19/house-gop-biden-impeachment-00174711" target="_blank">never coming to a vote</a> and his investigation into the former president’s alleged mental decline <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/28/republican-trump-biden-autopen-investigation-00624187" target="_blank">failing to deliver any bombshells</a>.</p> 
<p>So as he eyes a 2027 run for Kentucky governor, with his relationship with Trump likely to be central to his prospects, it’s the Epstein investigation that could determine Comer’s future in politics.</p> 
<p>For months, House GOP leadership touted the Oversight probe as proof that Republicans were taking the Epstein case seriously — even as they fought efforts from within their own ranks to advance legislation that would force a complete release of the DOJ investigative files. In a twist last week, Trump gave up fighting the bill’s inevitable passage, signing the measure into law shortly after Congress approved it with just one dissenter.</p> 
<p>The administration now has fewer than 30 days to make materials available to the public, with redactions to protect victims’ names and respect ongoing criminal investigations. Comer, meanwhile, must find a way to shepherd his committee’s investigation to some conclusion.</p> 
<p>Asked what the logical end point of his probe would be, Comer was not quite sure.</p> 
<p>He said he remains hopeful the bank records he has subpoenaed will turn up something notable. The chair <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/comer-subpoenas-epsteins-financial-records-00657935" target="_blank">recently demanded Epstein-related records</a> from JPMorgan Chase and Deutsche Bank and asked the attorney general for the U.S. Virgin Islands, whose jurisdiction includes the two private islands that Epstein owned, for additional materials.</p> 
<p>Comer warned of various obstacles. Many of the crimes occurred decades ago, and evidence will be difficult to find. The key witness — Epstein — killed himself behind bars in 2019, while Ghislaine Maxwell, Epstein’s longtime co-conspirator now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in the sex trafficking crimes, has said she <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/ghislaine-maxwell-plead-fifth-house-oversight-00664640" target="_blank">will not cooperate</a> with the Oversight Committee’s questioning.</p> 
<p>In an effort to try to satisfy calls on both sides of the aisle for some kind of “list,” Comer said he has tasked Democratic and Republican women on the Oversight Committee to meet privately with victims to try to learn the identities of people complicit in Epstein’s criminal activities.</p> 
<p>“If there is no Epstein list, and the American people expect us to compose an Epstein list, if we don't get any names from the victims, it's going to be hard to do,” he said.</p> 
<p>Jennifer Freeman, an attorney representing some of Epstein’s accusers, warned that Comer's strategy could put the women at risk.</p> 
<p>“Why are we putting the burden on them?” she said in an interview.</p> 
<p>But the most significant challenge Comer faces is managing the political fallout for Trump and the GOP writ large.</p> 
<p>Comer’s targeting of the Epstein estate uncovered materials that connect the president to the late financier. But Comer has continued to downplay the significance of the revelations and insist they show no signs of wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Democrats publicized widely the revelations in<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/08/house-oversight-receives-epstein-estate-files-00550721" target="_blank">the birthday book</a>, with a racy drawing and message allegedly penned by Trump. They also blasted out a set of emails mentioning Trump, including one in which Epstein said that Trump “knew about the girls.”</p> 
<p>Comer rejects the narrative that his investigation has been damaging for Trump and blamed his panel’s minority for disregarding committee norms in selectively releasing certain information the panel had received.</p> 
<p>Speaking with reporters last week, Comer called the Oversight Committee’s top Democrat, Rep. Robert Garcia of California, “dishonest” and “awful,” among other personal attacks.</p> 
<p>“I'm done with Garcia, criticizing me. He played the gay card,” Comer said. “He just needs to do TikTok videos or something. … He's not a serious investigator. He’s like a TikTok video kind of guy.”</p> 
<p>Comer added that Garcia “had limited abilities to begin with, but he's burned his bridges with this.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Comer said the “gay card” comment referred to a September incident where <a href="https://x.com/RobertGarcia/status/1965471435914444928" target="_blank">Garcia invoked his sexuality</a> after Comer called him a “drama queen” to reporters.</p> 
<p>Garcia, who is gay, said in an interview it was “clear that Chairman Comer … and the committee Republicans have been outworked and outmaneuvered, and he’s clearly upset and panicking that we have been fighting every single day to release these files. … They’ve tried to bend the knee to Trump and coverup and be part of the White House cover-up.”</p> 
<p>If Trump is displeased with Comer’s handling of the Epstein investigation, he hasn’t said so publicly, and there aren’t apparent rumblings inside the administration about friction.</p> 
<p>“The president likes James Comer a lot,” a senior White House official who was granted anonymity to share private conversations said. “In fact, I spoke with [Trump] recently about [Comer] and he said he's always been good and with him all the way. There's no problems there."</p> 
<p>For Comer, there is another reason to endear himself to the president with this investigation: He’s eying a bid to succeed Gov. Andy Beshear in a state where Trump’s endorsement could have significant influence.</p> 
<p>Comer said in the interview people were encouraging him to run, and he has been traveling statewide ahead of the potential race. He suspects Epstein will not be a major issue in the campaign, but his frequent TV hits discussing his investigative work have given him the opportunity to speak to Kentucky voters, he noted.</p> 
<p>He said he has not spoken to the White House about the Epstein probe, and when asked how he suspects Trump views the probe, Comer said, “I don’t want to know, probably.”</p> 
<p><i>Diana Nerozzi contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans clash over drone crackdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/chinese-drones-defense-bill-fight-00669415</link>
      <description>Many Republicans fear the Chinese-made product is a major threat to national security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bdcb-d51c-a39e-bdcbe8460000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0f/cb/070e31334b0c8c765a780db44b66/u-s-congress-40828.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Elise Stefanik (R-N.Y.) is seen during a press conference outside the U.S. Capitol, on May 14, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0f/cb/070e31334b0c8c765a780db44b66/u-s-congress-40828.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A Capitol Hill push by GOP China hawks to impose new restrictions on Shenzhen-based aerial drone maker DJI is facing resistance from Republicans who warn the company’s products have become critical tools for U.S. farming and energy firms.</p> 
<p>The fight is playing out after Rep. Elise Stefanik of New York, a close ally of President Donald Trump, secured the crackdown in the House version of a must-pass defense policy bill. At stake for DJI are new restrictions on its ability to offer products in the U.S.</p> 
<p>Stefanik is making the case that the company’s products expose Americans’ data to the Chinese government — an allegation that the company denies as it lobbies hard to make the case that it operates independently of Chinese officials.</p> 
<p>But Stefanik and her allies are facing pushback in the Senate, which opted against including the provision in its version of the bill and where Republicans are raising concerns about potential negative impacts on U.S. businesses and law enforcement. The two chambers are working to resolve their differences in the sprawling defense bill so they can enact it by year’s end.</p> 
<p>“They are the primary drone maker in the United States at a reasonable price,” Senate Agriculture Chair John Boozman, an Arkansas Republican, said of DJI in an interview. “This technology is being used more and more. ... That’s the crux of the problem.”</p> 
<p>The battle over DJI marks the latest flash point among Republicans over how to counter China without sacrificing U.S. business interests. Trump, whose election in 2016 was a boon to the party’s China hawk wing, has himself sought to ease tensions with Beijing in recent months after initiating a trade war. It’s unclear that Stefanik and her allies will prevail with their campaign against DJI.</p> 
<p>DJI is the dominant global producer of commercial drones, which it markets to enterprise customers for uses in inspecting infrastructure, surveying land and public safety.</p> 
<p>“There are real cost ramifications for commercial enterprises, not just farming,” Sen. John Hoeven, a North Dakota Republican, said in an interview. “You’ve got the energy industry, where they’re tracking transmission lines, rescue and recovery, all these different other uses. It’s something we’ve got to figure out.”</p> 
<p>Boozman and Hoeven say they also have national security concerns about DJI, but Stefanik has been pushing provisions that would take an all-or-nothing approach, rejecting the notion that economic impacts should hold lawmakers back from immediately barring the sale of new DJI products in the U.S.</p> 
<p>“It is very important for us to have U.S. drones and not have that data be turned over to the CCP,” she said in an interview. “It has been an issue we’ve worked on for a number of years with traditional bipartisan support to protect our information, whether it’s the topography of their regions or on the installations … or potential troop movements.”</p> 
<p>The legislative language Stefanik and other China hawks are pursuing comes as DJI already faces potential restrictions on its ability to sell products in the U.S. after Dec. 23, thanks to an amendment Stefanik secured in last year’s defense authorization bill.</p> 
<p>That earlier provision requires federal agencies to audit DJI and another Chinese drone manufacturer, Autel, for national security risks. If no such audit is performed, a ban on domestic imports will go into effect. No national security agency has indicated it plans to conduct the audit in time to meet the deadline.</p> 
<p>The new proposal Republicans are now debating would require another federal audit of drone equipment, including software and spectrum band products, developed in countries that are “foreign adversaries.” The language once again targets DJI and Autel.</p> 
<p>DJI has spent nearly $3 million on federal lobbying this year, according to disclosures filed with Congress, in appeals to lawmakers from states and districts that rely on its drones to support critical sectors of their local economies – particularly agricultural and law enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>“The fundamental point is, this isn’t really about data security,” DJI global head of policy Adam Welsh said in an interview. “This is, frankly, about protectionism and trying to protect a U.S. industry.”</p> 
<p>Representatives of DJI’s enterprise customer base acknowledge national security concerns associated with the drones. But they are also warning against the repercussions of a full-out ban.</p> 
<p>“It would have a very significant level of repercussions, full stop,” National Sheriffs’ Association CEO Jonathan Thompson said in an interview. “It’s a little like taking cars out of a sheriff’s office and saying you can’t use any cars. These are ubiquitous.”</p> 
<p>Even the federal government has had trouble weaning itself off the Chinese-made drones.</p> 
<p>After the Interior Department prohibited the purchase of new DJI drones in 2020, the Government Accountability Office found in a follow-up review that the removal of foreign-made drone fleets had significantly impaired the operations of the Bureau of Land Management and National Park Service.</p> 
<p>“BLM and NPS do not have enough drones for their operations to manage or prevent wildland fires and have shifted some operations to riskier, more costly methods, such as helicopters,” the GAO said in the report.</p> 
<p>Sen. Rick Scott, a Florida Republican who is championing a proposal in his chamber that mirrors Stefanik’s language, said in an interview that he has run into resistance at the Senate Commerce Committee, which has jurisdiction over aviation and technology issues and is chaired by Sen. Ted Cruz of Texas.</p> 
<p>“Commerce did not oppose the inclusion of a DJI audit in the [defense bill],” said Phoebe Keller, a committee spokesperson for Cruz. “Staff provided edits to the text and engaged in good faith to clear the language. The sponsors ultimately chose not to engage further but we remain happy to work with the sponsors if and when they decide to reengage.”</p> 
<p>A person granted anonymity to share details of the negotiations said committee staff conveyed concerns to Scott’s team about the ramifications of banning drones relied upon by first responders</p> 
<p>Scott rejects concerns that there aren’t yet viable alternative drones being produced in the U.S.</p> 
<p>“There’s American companies, and there will be,” said Scott, a former Florida governor and health care CEO. “I’m a business guy. If you told me there was an opportunity, I could figure it out pretty fast.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The big sticking point in the White House’s health care proposal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/republicans-trump-obamacare-abortion-00669389</link>
      <description>For many GOP members, an expansion of abortion restrictions in Obamacare is a must-have in any tentative health care plan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bdbc-df0f-abfa-fdfe21640000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 20:18:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/2f/23/2a651e5a4d50acd022860cca97e0/white-house-14259.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump looks on with guests during an announcement about in vitro fertilization in the Oval Office at the White House on Oct. 16, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2f/23/2a651e5a4d50acd022860cca97e0/white-house-14259.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alice Miranda Ollstein, Jordain Carney and Cheyenne Haslett</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alice Miranda Ollstein, Jordain Carney and Cheyenne Haslett</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House's silence on how its health care plan deals with abortion is causing a headache for Republicans on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>For many GOP members, an expansion of abortion restrictions in Obamacare is a must-have. But the White House’s decision to leave the issue out of its tentative framework caught Republicans off guard, leaving them in the dark about whether the president would ultimately stake out a position publicly, according to two aides granted anonymity to disclose private discussions.</p> 
<p>The fight over the Hyde amendment, which bars federal funding for abortion, is just one of many landmines that need to be cleared before any health care deal to extend expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies can be reached. It also comes on top of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">GOP backlash to other aspects</a> of the White House’s health policy framework that leaked Sunday.</p> 
<p>“No Republican has voted for Obamacare or an Obamacare extension or expansion,” said a senior Senate Republican aide, granted anonymity to speak candidly. “Asking members to do that and not including Hyde would be impossible for many.”</p> 
<p>The White House did not respond to requests for comment on the president’s stance.</p> 
<p>The proposal the administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">had planned to roll out this week</a> consisted of a two-year extension of the ACA’s enhanced subsidies with new limitations favored by conservatives, such as a cutoff for people with higher incomes and a requirement that everyone pay a minimum monthly premium. But the White House gave no indication of whether it endorsed GOP lawmakers’ demand to also prohibit any insurance plan that receives a federal subsidy from covering abortion services.</p> 
<p>Gavin Oxley, a spokesperson with Americans United for Life, said it would be helpful for the White House to publicly lay out its position on the Hyde question to give lawmakers an idea of how to proceed.</p> 
<p>Not weighing in now, or proceeding with a plan without abortion restrictions, “would ultimately fracture the wide-reaching coalition that got President Trump re-elected,” Oxley said.</p> 
<p>“We believe the Administration and pro-life leaders in Congress will come to the table in good faith with a plan that includes Hyde,” he continued. “But should it not, we will be prepared to reject such a plan.”</p> 
<p>House and Senate Republicans, as well as dozens of anti-abortion groups that have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/24/congress-republicans-abortion-health-00577631" target="_blank">spent months lobbying Congress</a> and the White House, oppose any extension of the subsidies that doesn’t bar all insurance plans in the individual market from covering abortion. One of the people granted anonymity to speak candidly said that including the abortion funding restrictions was a “red line" for a broad swath of Republicans.</p> 
<p>“We don’t have any details on this plan, but Senator Young supports Hyde protections and believes they should apply to any taxpayer funded health care spending,” said Leah Selk, spokesperson for Republican Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/52983" data-person-id="52983">Todd Young</a> of Indiana.</p> 
<p>The hard line for Republicans creates a narrow window for bipartisan agreement, if any, before the end of the year, when the subsidies are set to expire and cause premiums to skyrocket. Democrats, whose votes are needed to clear the filibuster in the Senate to advance most legislation, have declared that abortion restrictions would be a non-starter in ongoing negotiations.</p> 
<p>“Instead of working with Democrats to fix the health care crisis they created, Republicans now want to hold women’s health care hostage and force their radical agenda on the American people,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51247" data-person-id="51247">Ron Wyden</a> of Oregon, the top Democrat on the Finance Committee that has jurisdiction over much of the sprawling U.S. health system, in a recent floor speech. “I have one thing to say to that: not on my watch.”</p> 
<p>Likely cognizant of this political reality, the White House’s decision to sidestep the abortion question was intended to allow the administration to avoid drawing attention to an issue that could have immediately jeopardized the plan’s viability, said a Republican aide with knowledge of the discussions — even if its silence has actually had the opposite effect. </p> 
<p>“Look, it's no secret that this administration is not rushing to put a lot of political capital on the issue of abortion if they can avoid it,” said Patrick Brown, a fellow with the conservative think tank Ethics and Public Policy Center, which has been part of the roiling debate over abortion restrictions in Obamacare. “It's not something I think they have any interest in highlighting.”</p> 
<p>The abortion standoff is just one of many factors complicating a proposed deal to extend insurance subsidies. Deep divisions remain around who should qualify for such subsidies, how generous they should be, and what kind of health services are covered.</p> 
<p>Any agreement would need Trump's blessing, giving Republicans political cover to vote for an extension of the health reform law they have raged against for more than a decade. But given this difficult landscape, conservative lobbyists are skeptical that passage is possible even if Trump endorsed abortion restrictions. Those in close contact with lawmakers say it’s unlikely an extension of the subsidies could win 60 votes in the Senate — or even 50.</p> 
<p>“It'd be very difficult, even if they do it through reconciliation,” said Tom McClusky, the director of government affairs for Catholic Vote. “On the subsidies alone, I think you have a large enough contingent on the Republican side that don't want them renewed at all — regardless of if you can somehow miraculously figure out the protections of Hyde.”</p> 
<p>Since its inception more than a decade ago, the Affordable Care Act has barred federal subsidies from paying for abortions, but left it up to states whether health insurance plans in the individual market could cover abortion using other funding.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/state-policies-on-abortion-coverage-in-medicaid-private-insurance-and-aca-exchange-plans-2025/" target="_blank">Half of states</a> have opted to ban all coverage of abortion on their Obamacare markets, including some where abortion itself is legal, like Pennsylvania and Arizona. In the remaining 25 states, abortion coverage through Obamacare is either allowed or required, though any claims paid out involving the termination of a pregnancy come from a separate account that doesn’t use any federal subsidies.</p> 
<p>If Congress passes an Obamacare subsidy extension that includes the abortion restrictions conservatives are demanding, it would force roughly a dozen states where abortion coverage is mandatory to make a tough decision: change their laws or risk losing billions of dollars. In the states where abortion coverage is allowed but not required, it would be up to individual insurance plans whether to lose federal funding or drop abortion coverage.</p> 
<p>After nearly a year of the Trump administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/01/28/trump-gop-leaders-congress-power-assault-00002129" target="_blank">clawing power away from Capitol Hill</a> and dictating everything from spending to military action, some anti-abortion advocates are baffled by the lack of a firm message on how the Hyde amendment’s ban on abortion funding applies to Obamacare.</p> 
<p>“It’s in tension with this administration's broader approach to dealing with Congress, which has been very heavy handed — sort of, ‘We are calling the shots. Sit back and let us drive,’” said Brown. “But it would be their preference to sit in the back seat on that issue specifically.”</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-25T16:30:24-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democrats say they are subjects of FBI probe after filming anti-Trump video</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/democrats-fbi-trump-00668584</link>
      <description>Six lawmakers with nation security backgrounds are being criticized by the Trump administration for telling troops to disobey illegal orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bc69-d51c-a39e-bd690bee0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 15:04:06 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/38/1c/95a9d09c49c8b305ee0cb3501b93/task-force-on-the-attempted-assassination-of-donald-trump-75904.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Angelina Katsanis/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) speaks to the press at the first hearing from the Task Force on the attempted assassination of Donald Trump in Washington on Sept. 26, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/38/1c/95a9d09c49c8b305ee0cb3501b93/task-force-on-the-attempted-assassination-of-donald-trump-75904.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Kyle Cheney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Kyle Cheney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Several congressional Democrats said Tuesday they might be under investigation by the FBI after filming an anti-Trump video urging military troops not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p><br>“President Trump is using the FBI as a tool to intimidate and harass Members of Congress. Yesterday, the FBI contacted the House and Senate Sergeants at Arms requesting interviews," wrote Democratic Reps. Jason Crow of Colorado and Maggie Goodlander of New Hampshire, alongside Chris Deluzio and Chrissy Houlahan of Pennsylvania, in a joint statement. "No amount of intimidation or harassment will ever stop us from doing our jobs and honoring our Constitution."</p> 
<p>"The President directing the FBI to target us is exactly why we made this video in the first place. He believes in weaponizing the federal government against his perceived enemies and does not believe laws apply to him or his Cabinet," Sen. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.) posted on social media. </p> 
<p>The lawmakers, who all have national security or military backgrounds, appeared in a video encouraging members of the military not to obey orders they believe are unlawful, saying, "Don't give up the ship." This message prompted a furious response from President Donald Trump, who called the video "SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL” and also shared a post calling for traitors to be hanged — though White House later said Trump was not threatening the lawmakers with death. </p> 
<p>The House Sergeant at Arms office was contacted by the FBI Monday about setting up interviews related to the six members of Congress, according to a person granted anonymity to speak freely about the matter. The request was forwarded to the House Office of General Counsel to interact with the Justice Department, the person said. </p> 
<p>Typically, investigations related to members of Congress are handled between the Office of General Counsel and the main Justice Department, not the FBI, making the outreach somewhat unusual. </p> 
<p>The Pentagon announced Monday it <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894?utm_campaign=mb&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_source=morning_brew" target="_blank">would investigate another one</a> of the lawmakers in the video, Democratic Sen. Mark Kelly of Arizona, for “serious allegations of misconduct" which could result in recalling him to active duty to face a court martial on alleged crimes.</p> 
<p>The Senate and House Sergeants at Arms offices did not immediately respond to a request for comment. A spokesperson for the FBI declined to comment.</p> 
<p><i>Cheyanne M. Daniels contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marjorie Taylor Greene is staying out of the election to replace her</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/marjorie-taylor-greene-election-replacement-00667787</link>
      <description>The Georgia Republican said she won’t endorse in next year’s special election, avoiding a proxy war with Trump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b827-df0f-abfa-f96fc30c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:44:36 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/43/7c/bdf82ab248118cdcbe355509ef36/congress-epstein-88278.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Julia Demaree Nikhinson/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene, (R-Ga.), speaks during a news conference on the Epstein Files Transparency Act, Nov. 18, 2025, outside the U.S. Capitol in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/43/7c/bdf82ab248118cdcbe355509ef36/congress-epstein-88278.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Marjorie Taylor Greene said she won’t make any endorsement in the special election race to replace her in Congress — avoiding a potential clash between her preferred candidate and a candidate aligned with President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Greene said in a social media post Monday that she will remain neutral in the special election in Georgia’s 14th Congressional District after she steps away from Congress in January.</p> 
<p>“Looking ahead towards the Special Election for my Congressional seat, I will not be endorsing anyone out of respect to my district. I truly support the wonderful people of Georgia 14 and want them to pick their Representative,” she <a href="https://x.com/mtgreenee/status/1993081407418118423?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. “So anyone claiming they have my endorsement would not be telling the truth.”</p> 
<p>Her neutrality paves the way for Trump’s allies to elevate a candidate of their choosing in a heavily-Republican district that Greene won in 2024 by 28 points.</p> 
<p>In announcing her sudden decision to leave Congress, Greene, who has become estranged from the president, said she was partly inspired to step down to avoid a “hateful and hurtful primary” against a Trump-backed candidate.</p> 
<p>Trump, following her announcement, <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115593179521083607" target="_blank">said Greene would have</a> “no chance of winning” in a primary against a candidate with his endorsement.</p> 
<p>The special election won’t be scheduled until Greene leaves her post. Georgia law stipulates the election must occur at least 30 days after it’s been ordered. A Georgia Republican official told Atlanta News First the special election will <a href="https://www.atlantanewsfirst.com/2025/11/22/metro-atlanta-gop-chair-march-special-election-likely-fill-marjorie-taylor-greenes-seat/" target="_blank">likely occur in March</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump was going to roll out a health care plan. Then Republicans weighed in.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751</link>
      <description>Lawmakers just have a few weeks left to reach a deal to avoid a massive premium spike for ACA enrollees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b835-d739-a3ba-fcfd62480000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:32:04 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ab/74/53112bc746aca107df3185b51063/white-house-65365.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump stands near a sign on lowering drug prices for Americans as he announces a drug-pricing deal with Pfizer in the Oval Office at the White House Sept. 30, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ab/74/53112bc746aca107df3185b51063/white-house-65365.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Cheyenne Haslett, Benjamin Guggenheim and Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Cheyenne Haslett, Benjamin Guggenheim and Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">health care plan</a> is in limbo after pushback from Republicans who were caught off guard by the president’s forthcoming proposal — questioning, in particular, whether it would include additional abortion restrictions.</p> 
<p>Trump had been expected to unveil a new policy framework Monday afternoon, said two people familiar with the plan and granted anonymity to describe deliberations around it. That framework was expected to center around a two-year extension of Affordable Care Act subsidies with income caps and other new limits backed by conservatives.</p> 
<p>But while White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Monday that Trump remained focused on “unveiling a health care proposal,” she declined to get into specifics about subsidy extensions or a timeline for the rollout: “I’ll let the president speak for himself."</p> 
<p>A White House official separately noted Trump’s daily schedule never listed plans for a Monday rollout.</p> 
<p>The uncertainty around the timing of the announcement comes as Hill Republicans remain sharply divided over whether to extend the enhanced tax credits to prevent premiums from skyrocketing next year or to let them expire at the end of the year and coalesce around an alternative approach to keep health care costs down.</p> 
<p>One House Republican granted anonymity to speak freely said in an interview Monday they needed to see “what structural changes” Trump might float, adding that GOP lawmakers should demand “reforms … in exchange for extending the subsidies.”</p> 
<p>According to three additional people granted anonymity to share details of the plan ahead of its release, Trump was preparing to place new income caps on individuals receiving the subsidies and require minimum premium payments for Obamacare enrollees. He also was expected to propose an option for enrollees to receive part of their tax credit in a tax-advantaged savings account if they downgrade to a lower-premium health plan.</p> 
<p>These policy changes <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/cassidy-fund-hsas-trump-aca-subsidies-00655213" target="_blank">align with what many conservatives</a> have been seeking. But it wasn’t clear Monday whether the plan would also include <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/24/congress-republicans-abortion-health-00577631" target="_blank">expanded restrictions under the so-called Hyde amendment</a>, which bans federal funds from being used for abortions.</p> 
<p>One of the people who described the tentative plan and two other people granted anonymity to disclose private discussions said congressional Republicans still didn’t know how Trump’s proposal would deal with that thorny issue.</p> 
<p>The ACA has always barred federal subsidies from paying for abortions but left it up to states to determine whether health insurance plans in the individual market could cover abortion using other funding.</p> 
<p>Marjorie Dannenfelser, the president of Susan B. Anthony Pro-Life America, reiterated in a statement Monday her anti-abortion group will penalize any lawmaker who votes for a subsidies extension without additional abortion guardrails that ban coverage nationwide.</p> 
<p>“We oppose any health care plan that fails to include this safeguard,” she said. “Our position is consistent and will not change.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s plan to extend the ACA credits — even with changes sought by conservatives — also <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2025/11/24/trumps-obamacare-move-blindsides-conservatives-00666700" target="_blank">blindsided some Hill Republicans</a> who have dug in against any bipartisan deal to extend the credits.</p> 
<p>"I know that we've got different ideas in our conference," House Majority Whip Tom Emmer (R-Minn.) said in a Monday morning interview on Fox Business Network. "I think you're going to hear more from the White House.”</p> 
<p>House GOP leadership last week gave a presentation to the House Republican Conference slamming the subsidies for perpetuating what they dubbed the “Unaffordable Care Act,” a moniker Emmer repeated Monday.</p> 
<p>Not all Republicans reacted negatively to the news of a forthcoming health policy announcement from Trump. Rep. Tim Burchett in an interview Monday credited the president with having “some guts” to get lawmakers “to the table.” Trump’s forthcoming framework, Burchett added, “starts the negotiating.”</p> 
<p>“I don’t like the subsidies,” the Tennessee Republican continued, “but everybody griping about it doesn’t have a plan, so get some guts, put up a plan … or get the heck out of the way.”</p> 
<p>Burchett also said the White House will now roll out the plan Tuesday, underscoring confusion and mixed messaging around the forthcoming presentation.</p> 
<p>Leavitt left open a broad array of possibilities for the final White House plan Monday, including that it might not ultimately include a subsidy extension. Asked specifically if that provision would be included, she told reporters, "As you all know, sometimes you report things and then President Trump comes out with an announcement and those things are not always true."</p> 
<p>Some Democrats expressed cautious optimism upon learning that Trump was preparing to embrace an extension of the ACA credits.</p> 
<p>Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.), who has been heavily involved in the bipartisan negotiations on health care, said in a statement Monday that she has had “constructive conversations” with Republicans about extending the enhanced tax credits.</p> 
<p>“If the reports are true and the President is considering coming to the table in good faith, I believe we can find a path forward that can earn broad bipartisan support in Congress,” Shaheen said.</p> 
<p>She added that anything Trump puts out on the issue could signal “a serious proposal to begin negotiations.”</p> 
<p>Democrats, including Shaheen, have been discussing what their strategy should be ahead of a floor vote in mid-December on a proposal to extend the subsidies, which was promised to Democrats by Senate Majority Leader John Thune in exchange for their votes to end the government shutdown. Democrats will get to decide what proposal they want a vote on, though Republicans are expected to offer their own alternative unless there is a bipartisan deal.</p> 
<p>One provision that had been included in Trump’s tentative plan — pegging the eligibility cap for the subsidies at 700 percent of the federal poverty line — is among the ideas being mulled by Shaheen and her colleagues.</p> 
<p>But other Democrats slammed the proposal outright, further casting doubt on how Trump’s opening salvo would land on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>In a statement Monday afternoon, the three top House Democrats on committees with jurisdiction over health care — Reps. Richard Neal of Massachusetts, Frank Pallone of New Jersey and Bobby Scott of Virginia — panned the White House’s forthcoming proposal, calling it the “greatest hits of Republican health care ideas the people have rejected for years.”</p> 
<p>They continued, “At this point, anything short of a clean extension is unworkable and won’t avoid the price hikes people are now facing.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Mike Johnson is losing control of the House</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/house-discharge-petitions-mike-johnson-00666557</link>
      <description>Thanks to a coalition of Democrats and disgruntled Republicans, more discharge petitions have succeeded in the past two years than the prior three decades combined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b2d0-df0f-abfa-f3fac5600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d4/7f/42e62ed44ab997b2bde70893baf5/u-s-congress-89936.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Speaker Mike Johnson railed against the discharge petition on releasing the Epstein files at a Nov. 18 news conference. His efforts were to no avail.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d4/7f/42e62ed44ab997b2bde70893baf5/u-s-congress-89936.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over the course of decades, House lawmakers had succeeded only a few times in triggering votes on bills the chamber’s leaders refused to call up.</p> 
<p>Then Mike Johnson became speaker.</p> 
<p>On the Louisiana Republican’s watch, the “discharge petition” has caught fire. Rank-and-file lawmakers have managed five times since he won his gavel two years ago to circumvent Johnson’s wishes by getting the 218 signatures needed to force votes on legislation he had blocked — more than in the prior 30 years combined.</p> 
<p>Most recently, a bipartisan group used the maneuver to advance a long-stalled bill requiring President Donald Trump’s administration to release information about the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>It’s members of Johnson’s own party who have most effectively wielded the tool in recent years. Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) masterminded the Epstein push, while Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) engineered an effort to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/04/01/congress/proxy-voting-rule-vote-fails-00263621" target="_blank">seek voting accommodations</a> for House members with newborn babies. Before that, then-Rep. Garret Graves (R-La.) used the gambit to enact a bill to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/12/20/congress/social-security-bill-passes-senate-00195786" target="_blank">expand Social Security payments</a> for millions of public sector workers.</p> 
<p>“They try to say that discharge petitions are a tool of the minority, but that's actually only the perspective of people that want to consolidate power within leadership,” Luna said in an interview, adding that she would protect the maneuver “with every bone in my body.”</p> 
<p>The upshot for Johnson is that the arcane legislative mechanism once known only to Capitol Hill obsessives is now a routine part of life in the Republican House majority. Beyond Epstein, Johnson is now facing several new drumbeats for action, with lawmakers looking to force votes on banning member stock trading, sanctioning Russia and extending health care subsidies that are set to expire at year’s end.</p> 
<p>The GOP’s slim majority is an obvious contributor to the burgeoning popularity of the maneuver. The discharge process is set into motion when 218 members sign on to a petition, meaning only a handful of Republicans need to cross leadership if Democrats are united in support.</p> 
<p>But the recent spate of successful discharges also reflects careful groundwork Democrats laid to quickly seize on the procedure, along with a sentiment among many Republicans that Johnson is stifling the will of the House to appease Trump and small GOP factions — including hard-liners who successfully ousted Johnson’s predecessor, Kevin McCarthy.</p> 
<p>“I would encourage you to ask Mike Johnson why he repeatedly refused to bring my bill to the floor,” Rep. Greg Steube (R-Fla.) said in an interview.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">‘Toxic political environment’</h5> 
<p>Steube is still bitter about how Johnson hindered passage last year of his legislation to provide tax relief to disaster survivors, even after the measure was unanimously approved in committee. Once Steube <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/05/21/congress/discharge-petition-passes-in-house-disaster-relief-00159184" target="_blank">got the signatures</a> he needed to compel floor action, the measure passed the House in a 382-7 vote before clearing the Senate and earning then-President Joe Biden’s signature.</p> 
<p>That first victory — seven months into Johnson’s tenure as speaker — showed how the maneuver can be successful “in a toxic political environment,” said Steube, a MAGA-hat-wearing, fourth-term member who has consistently won his southwest Florida district by a landslide. “It’s got to be something that is very bipartisan and is important enough that the body says, Yeah, this warrants overriding the speaker.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/e5/6f/f58ac8944faca95bba470d9c0429/white-house-87594.jpg" alt="Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) completed one discharge petition and is now threatening another." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) completed one discharge petition and is now threatening another."/><p>The discharge petition dates back to 1910, when it was created in response to the “overreaching, overbearing, overcontrolling” style of then-Speaker Joseph Cannon — aka “Czar Cannon” — according to Sarah Binder, a George Washington University professor who focuses on legislative politics.</p> 
<p>Now, she said, it serves as a “pressure valve” for a chamber designed to reflect the majority’s will.</p> 
<p>In some cases, discharge petitions can help solve thorny political problems for the speaker. Philip Wallach, who studies the roots of congressional dysfunction at the right-leaning American Enterprise Institute, said Johnson is “using this idea of getting forced” as a way to keep his job.</p> 
<p>“He’s actually kind of deft at the coalition management problem and at staying on side with Trump,” Wallach said. “If he acted some other way, I really do think there's a good chance that he would find himself on the wrong side of Trump and get thrown out.”</p> 
<p>That was certainly the case with the Epstein vote, though Johnson protested mightily against the bill Massie and his ally Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) sought to discharge, arguing until the moment Trump signed it that it did not do enough to protect Epstein’s victims from invasions of privacy.</p> 
<p>But as the 427-1 vote demonstrated, there was a deep groundswell for transparency that Johnson had been holding off at Trump’s behest.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">‘The fuse in the fuse box’</h5> 
<p>Massie said members of both parties are now “brainstorming” other bills they might be able to catapult to the floor.</p> 
<p>“It's the fuse in the fuse box when everything gets jammed up and the wires get crossed and nothing can get done,” he told reporters last week.</p> 
<p>In discouraging Republicans from signing on to discharge petitions, House GOP leaders argue that the tactic undermines the party in power and circumvents Congress’ “regular order” system of debate, where legislation is meant to advance through committees with special expertise.</p> 
<p>“Typically it’s when somebody either doesn't want to go through the committee process or doesn't get what they want out of the committee process,” House Majority Leader Steve Scalise (R-La.) said in an interview.</p> 
<p>But it’s not just committee calendars and floor scheduling that has chafed many House Republicans. GOP leaders have taken more overt steps this year to thwart the chamber’s ability to work the majority’s will — including by <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/04/09/congress/house-gop-leaders-move-to-quash-vote-on-trumps-global-tariffs-00280922" target="_blank">preemptively blocking efforts</a> to force votes on canceling some of Trump’s tariffs.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/54/ff/fff17c344819af3398fa862426ba/unlimiteduse-11-12-2025-capitol-hill-anna-rose-layden-0044.jpg" alt="After success with the Epstein bill, Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) says he's brainstorming other bipartisan measures to discharge." data-portal-copyright="Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO" data-title="After success with the Epstein bill, Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) says he's brainstorming other bipartisan measures to discharge."/><p>Even before Johnson’s tenure, House leaders of both parties have chipped away at the “open rule” practice of allowing lawmakers to debate any amendments they wanted on the floor. Now they nearly always pick and choose the amendments allowed — if they allow them at all.</p> 
<p>On the Epstein bill, the House’s top Republicans characterized the decision to sign Massie’s petition as a loyalty test.</p> 
<p>“They made it pretty clear that if you get on the discharge petition, you've declared war on the president, in so many words,” Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) said in an interview, adding that he sympathized with Johnson’s need to keep Trump and “prima donnas” in the House GOP happy.</p> 
<p>“He tries his best,” Bacon said.</p> 
<p>But Bacon, who is retiring after his term ends, has signed on to several discharge petitions, including one to sanction Russia and aid Ukraine, which is just a few signatures shy of 218. Bacon reasons that gesture is a way to show Trump that there’s rising support for helping Ukraine while affording Johnson some political cover.</p> 
<p>“I feel like I’m helping him out by doing the discharge on Ukraine, in a way,” Bacon said of Johnson. “Because I'm trying to force the hand. He's going to say, ‘I didn't have any choice on this.’”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">‘Zombie’ legislation</h5> 
<p>Democrats, to be sure, have done their share to contribute to the dizzying pace of discharges. Just last week, another petition succeeded, setting up a vote on a measure sponsored by Rep. Jared Golden (D-Maine) that would nullify an executive order Trump issued in March scrapping the collective bargaining rights of more than 1 million federal employees.</p> 
<p>The party’s leaders, in fact, have quietly plotted for months to take full advantage of the tool. Under House rules, it typically takes well over a month to force a vote once a petition gets the requisite 218 signatures. So Massachusetts Rep. Jim McGovern, the top Democrat on the House Rules Committee, coordinated the filing of “zombie” measures containing placeholder language allowing members to jump-start the procedural countdown before they finalize the substance of the legislation they want to propel to the floor.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/99/18/306f2cfb4baba6d55961b8d31eb4/congress-defense-spending-38430.jpg" alt="Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) engineered a strategy to use discharge petitions more quickly." data-portal-copyright="J. Scott Applewhite/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) engineered a strategy to use discharge petitions more quickly."/><p>McGovern acknowledged in an interview that none of that spade work pays off unless at least a few members of the majority are disgruntled enough to buck their leaders.</p> 
<p>“It takes a lot of courage for Republicans to sign on to a discharge petition when they're in charge,” he said. “But I think it's a reflection of their frustration with their own leadership.”</p> 
<p>Off the Hill, congressional observers who know the history of the seldom-used gambit are stunned, if not necessarily surprised, by its recent success.</p> 
<p>“Despite the fact that it doesn't succeed very often, it's out there for an ambitious, organized minority — and, in this case, also disgruntled or concerned majority members, who feel their leadership's not on the right side of the issue,” Binder said. “So beware the discharge.”</p> 
<p><i>Cassandra Dumay contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House to pitch a Trump Obamacare extension with limits</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701</link>
      <description>Republicans have been eager for Trump to reveal his preferences on expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b3c7-df0f-abfa-f3ef41570000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 21:53:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fe/f8/23c0463140cab5f1c43278cc53d4/white-house-21565.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump speaks with reporters as he departs on the South Lawn of the White House to board Marine One on Oct. 24, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fe/f8/23c0463140cab5f1c43278cc53d4/white-house-21565.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House expects to soon unveil a health policy framework that includes a two-year extension of Obamacare subsidies due to expire at the end of next month and new limits on eligibility, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the unannounced plans.</p> 
<p>The proposal would mark President Donald Trump’s foray into Capitol Hill negotiations over how to address health care premium spikes set to hit Affordable Care Act enrollees if Congress lets the premium subsidies expire.</p> 
<p>A White House official declined to confirm the details of the plan, saying, “Until President Trump makes an announcement himself, any reporting about the administration’s healthcare positions is mere speculation.” MS NOW <a href="https://www.ms.now/news/trump-health-care-plan-obamacare-aca-subsidies" target="_blank">first reported</a> news of Trump’s intent to announce a new health care framework as soon as Monday to address spikes in ACA insurance premiums.</p> 
<p>As part of a deal to reopen the government earlier this month, Senate Republicans agreed to give Democrats a vote on the ACA tax credits in December. But GOP lawmakers across the Capitol <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/aca-obamacare-subsidies-extension-00655842" target="_blank">have been divided</a> over how to respond to the subsidy deadline, leaving many eager for Trump to reveal his preferences. Hard-line conservatives have been pushing to let the subsidies expire while moderate Republicans have been pressing for an extension. Some Republicans are angling for a health care overhaul to replace the credits.</p> 
<p>The White House plan is expected to include new income caps for enrollees to qualify for the ACA tax credits as well as minimum premium payments, according to the two people with direct knowledge of the proposal.</p> 
<p>The planned eligibility cap would limit the subsidies to individuals with income up to 700 percent of the federal poverty line — aligning with what a bipartisan group of senators have been discussing separately, according to a fourth person granted anonymity to share knowledge of the negotiations.</p> 
<p>Enrollees would also pay a minimum premium payment — a nod to concerns from conservatives that millions of Americans pay nothing in premiums while being unaware they are enrolled in ACA insurance plans.</p> 
<p>The White House’s plan would call on Congress to appropriate funds for cost-sharing reductions, which would reduce out-of-pocket health costs for ACA plans.</p> 
<p>The administration is also set to propose an option for enrollees to receive part of their tax credit in a tax-advantaged savings account if they move down to a lower-premium health plan. Many Republicans lawmakers favor the idea as a way to provide funds directly to people, as opposed to relying on indirect subsidies to insurance companies to drive down health costs. Trump himself has publicly endorsed the concept.</p> 
<p>Democratic lawmakers want Republicans to negotiate with them on an extension, but it remains to be seen whether they would settle for a short-term fix with restrictions attached. It’s also not clear how House GOP leaders would react to the plan after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-gop-leaders-pitch-members-on-unaffordable-care-act-00656362" target="_blank">presenting their members last week</a> with a pitch against what they dubbed the “Unaffordable Care Act.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crockett: MTG couldn’t ’take the heat’ from Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/jasmine-crocket-marjorie-taylor-greene-trump-00666306</link>
      <description>Rep. Jasmine Crockett mocked GOP Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene’s decision to resign from Congress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b142-d49b-af9f-b5e633d50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 11:01:05 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e4/cf/64f4d6654153a90be03a9d97882a/u-s-congress-65232.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Jasmine Crockett (D-Texas) noted that she had long been the target of President Donald Trump's ire.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e4/cf/64f4d6654153a90be03a9d97882a/u-s-congress-65232.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Jasmine Crockett on Sunday appeared to show little sympathy for her colleague Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene after the Georgia Republican announced her upcoming resignation from Congress.</p> 
<p>In an interview with CNN’s Jake Tapper on “State of the Union,” the Texas Democrat, long a foe of President Donald Trump, said Greene’s decision came after she was on “the opposite side of the president” for only one week.</p> 
<p>“You're on the other side of the president for one week, and you can't take the heat?” Crockett said. “Imagine what it is to sit in my shoes, to not only be on the opposite side of him, but to have people like her who are constantly fanning the flames of hate and imagine what those threats look like when you literally are someone like me.” </p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972" target="_blank">Greene announced Friday</a> she would resign from Congress early in 2026 following a fallout between herself and Trump.</p> 
<p>Greene, once a loyal ally of Trump, had become a sharp critic of both the president and her own party over disagreements on the Epstein files, health care and the government shutdown. Greene alleged she had begun to face threats after Trump called her “a traitor.”</p> 
<p>But Crockett on Sunday pointed out that multiple other Republicans, notably Reps. Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Lauren Boebert of Colorado, have also faced the president’s ire in light of their support to release the files on the disgraced, deceased financier.</p> 
<p>“I mean, listen, he's upset with Thomas Massie, and so he's gone after him. He's upset with Boebert, he's upset with any Republican that actually signed the discharge petition,” Crockett said. “But somehow they were able to weather the storm. Why is everyone else able to stand and you can’t?”</p> 
<p>Crockett and Greene’s relationship has long been tense, at one point <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/house-committee-meeting-devolves-chaos-personal-insults-marjorie-taylo-rcna152698" target="_blank">culminating in a confrontation</a> between the two during a House Oversight and Accountability Committee hearing last year.</p> 
<p>Still, Crockett had appeared to be showing some sympathy toward her congressional foe after Trump withdrew his support for Greene.</p> 
<p>“I’m here for you girl … I told you not to trust him … all he cares about is HIMself (and protecting pedos) he never loved you,” <a href="https://x.com/jasmineforus/status/1989520641729466618?s=46" target="_blank">Crockett tweeted at the time</a>.</p> 
<p>It is unclear what Greene’s future plans will be, but Crockett is expected to decide this week if she will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/30/crockett-texas-senate-run-00628699" target="_blank">launch a bid to challenge</a> GOP Sen. John Cornyn.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marjorie Taylor Greene resigns from Congress after clash with Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972</link>
      <description>The former Trump loyalist said she will step down Jan. 5.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a927-d49b-af9f-bde7834a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 20:31:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0e/b0/f9ff8c3e401c944363eaab591391/u-s-congress-45616.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene speaks alongside victims of convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a press conference outside the U.S. Capitol on Nov. 18.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0e/b0/f9ff8c3e401c944363eaab591391/u-s-congress-45616.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Marjorie Taylor Greene, the MAGA firebrand who rose to prominence as a combative supporter of President Donald Trump, announced late Friday she is resigning from Congress after a public feud with him.</p> 
<p>Greene, who was elected to Congress in 2020 from a rural northwestern Georgia district, made the surprise announcement in a surprise video address that referenced her falling out with Trump. The president branded her a “traitor” and withdrew his endorsement for supporting an effort he opposed to release files from the criminal investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“Standing up for American women who were raped at 14, trafficked and used by rich powerful men, should not result in me being called a traitor and threatened by the President of the United States, whom I fought for,” she said in a <a href="https://x.com/mtgreenee/status/1992037226415554642?s=20" target="_blank">statement posted on X</a>.</p> 
<p>Her resignation reflects increasing divisions within the MAGA movement that propelled Trump to power on a populist agenda that Greene had aggressively supported.</p> 
<p>The Republican lawmaker’s relationship with Trump soured after she joined calls from Democrats to release the Epstein files, criticized the president’s focus on foreign affairs and called for action on the expiring Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>“Loyalty should be a two-way street and we should be able to vote our conscience and represent our district’s interest because our job title is literally representative,’' she said.</p> 
<p>Greene said she will step down from office on Jan. 5.</p> 
<p>She did not provide advance notice to to anyone in House Republican leadership, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal matters.</p> 
<p>Her resignation threatens to further tighten Speaker Mike Johnson’s Republican majority early next year.</p> 
<p>The GOP holds a 219-213 advantage following Democrat Mikie Sherrill’s resignation this week after her election as New Jersey governor. That means Johnson can lose no more than two Republicans on a party-line vote.</p> 
<p>Greene highlighted her record of supporting Trump since she entered Congress, noting that she only disagreed in a "few areas” with some of the president’s recent proposals on immigration, artificial intelligence and foreign policy along with her stance on the Epstein documents.</p> 
<p>The White House had no immediate comment and appeared to be caught off-guard by her resignation. </p> 
<p>“It is surprising to absolutely no one that she would exit in the most selfish way possible,” an administration official, who was granted anonymity to discuss the resignation before a statement had been released. </p> 
<p>Rachel Scott, a senior political correspondent for ABC, <a href="https://x.com/rachelvscott/status/1992056507953754215?t=YE1da1BAx7NV3wFu_EzpSA&amp;s=19" target="_blank">said on X</a> that she spoke with Trump and he was surprised but pleased with the resignation. "I think it's great news for the country. It's great," he said.</p> 
<p>The growing divide between Trump and Greene came to a head last week when the president revoked his endorsement of Green in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-mtg-aca-epstein-massie-00653412" target="_blank"><u>scathing social media post</u></a> in which he labeled her “wacky” and a “ranting lunatic.” Days later, he reversed his position on the Epstein case files and encouraged House Republicans to support a bill that would for the Department of Justice to release the documents.</p> 
<p>Johnson later tried to paper over the rift between the Georgia Republican and Trump. The speaker acknowledged the dispute over the Epstein documents but said it was important that the party hold together.</p> 
<p>“But look, I work on unity in the party, and my encouragement of everybody is to get together,” he said. “We’ve got to do all that in order to deliver for the people.”</p> 
<p>Greene suggested in her statement that a looming primary challenge from a candidate aligned with the president factored into her decision — referring to the pro-Trump super PAC MAGA Inc. as one of the actors pushing her aside.</p> 
<p>“I have too much self respect and dignity, love my family way too much, and do not want my sweet district to have to endure a hurtful and hateful primary against me by the President we all fought for, only to fight and win my election while Republicans will likely lose the midterms,” she said.</p> 
<p>Her resignation brings a stunning conclusion to a tumultuous tenure that included promoting outlandish conspiracy theories. In 2021, the House voted to strip her of her committee assignments for social media posts promoting violence towards prominent Democrats.</p> 
<p>She also earned a reputation as a wild card among the House Republican caucus. In 2024, she attempted to remove Johnson from his position as the party was still recovering from a protracted fight that led to the ouster of former Speaker Kevin McCarthy.</p> 
<p>Days after being sworn into office for the first time, she joined a group of Republican members of Congress seeking to block the certification of Joe Biden’s presidential election victory over Trump on Jan. 6., 2021.</p> 
<p>Greene did not rule out a future run for office, suggesting she might run as an independent if she returned to politics. </p> 
<p>"When the common American people finally realize and understand that the political industrial complex of both parties is ripping this country apart, that not one elected leader like me is able to stop Washington's machine from gradually destroying our country, and instead the reality is that they, common Americans, the people, possess the real power over Washington," she said, "then I'll be here by their side to rebuild it." </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-21T15:23:14-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House members move to force Russia sanctions vote as Trump pushes peace deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/russia-sanctions-discharge-petition-00665210</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a7f6-df0f-abfa-e7fe1e3a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 14:52:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan coalition of pro-Ukraine lawmakers will seek to force a House vote to impose crippling sanctions on Russia, even as President Donald Trump is moving to swiftly clinch a peace deal between the two warring nations.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) <a href="https://x.com/RepBrianFitz/status/1991940517584666907?s=20" target="_blank">said in an X post Friday</a> that he and his allies have “officially notified both the Clerk of the House and House leadership of our discharge petition to force a vote on crushing Russian sanctions immediately upon our return” from the Thanksgiving holiday recess.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick was responding to news that Trump wants the Ukrainian government to approve the draft peace deal <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/witkoff-back-channel-push-ukraine-alarms-allies-00660247" target="_blank">assembled by his envoy Steve Witkoff</a> no later than Thursday. The plan would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/trump-plan-to-end-ukraine-war-cedes-donbas-to-russia-00664204" target="_blank">cede vast portions of eastern Ukraine</a> to Russia in exchange for a security guarantee from western nations.</p> 
<p>Trump appeared to be putting pressure on Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy with his Thanksgiving ultimatum, but the House lawmakers have their eye on Russian President Vladimir Putin — and they believe they have Trump’s blessing.</p> 
<p>House and Senate GOP leaders have held off for months, awaiting a clear signal from Trump, but with the president more determined to impose a peace plan than ever, rank-and-file members are determined to act.</p> 
<p>“The President’s appeasement plan to Russia is forcing our hand," said Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.).</p> 
<p>A discharge petition can circumvent the majority leadership if 218 House members sign it; it has been used to pressure Speaker Mike Johnson multiple times this year — most recently to pass legislation on the so-called Epstein files.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and other members of the Ukraine Caucus have offered sanctions legislation alongside Sens. Richard Blumenthal (D-Conn.) and Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.). Fitzpatrick <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/house-resolution/438?s=1&amp;r=3" target="_blank">filed a resolution</a> earlier this year setting up a possible effort to discharge that bill but did not immediately trigger it.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers could also force a vote on a bill from Reps. Gregory Meeks (D-N.Y.) and Steny Hoyer (D-Md.) that would pair Russia sanctions with assistance for Ukraine. The bipartisan Ukraine Caucus is set to hold a virtual meeting Monday to “talk about what the best strategy is to get something done quickly,” Fitzpatrick said in an interview Friday.</p> 
<p>“We’re talking about potentially moving them together if the sanctions are not brought to the floor in short order,” Fitzpatrick said ahead of his social media post.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick said he has been talking to Johnson about the sanctions bill and believes the speaker is supportive of the legislation. Noticing his intention to force a vote now, with the House leaving for a weeklong recess, effectively gives Johnson until early December to find an off-ramp.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ghislaine Maxwell will plead Fifth in House Epstein probe, Comer says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/ghislaine-maxwell-plead-fifth-house-oversight-00664640</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a785-d739-a3ba-fffd93bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:26:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ghislaine Maxwell, the convicted co-conspirator of the late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, will refuse to answer questions in the House Oversight Committee's probe into Epstein and the Justice Department’s handling of the case, Oversight Chair James Comer said.</p> 
<p>Maxwell's legal team said she would invoke her Fifth Amendment rights if she sat with congressional investigators, the Kentucky Republican said in an interview. He also suggested it would be unlikely that his staff or lawmakers would sit down with Maxwell, who is in a federal prison camp in Texas, under the circumstances.</p> 
<p>“Her lawyers have replied that she's not going to answer any questions," Comer said. "She's only going to plead the Fifth. I mean, I could spend a bunch of taxpayer dollars to send staff and members down there, and if she's going to plead the Fifth, I don’t know that that's a good investment.”</p> 
<p>Comer <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/23/congress/epstein-james-comer-subpoena-ghislaine-maxwell-testify-00471644" target="_blank">issued a subpoena</a> in July for Maxwell’s testimony, and her legal team initially suggested that she would be willing to answer questions <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/29/congress/maxwell-makes-demands-00481769" target="_blank">under certain conditions</a>, including that her appeals had been resolved. The Supreme Court recently rejected a request to revisit her conviction.</p> 
<p>In return for her cooperation, Maxwell requested immunity from further criminal proceedings and to receive questions in advance. Comer said both immunity and advanced notice was a nonstarter.</p> 
<p>An attorney for Maxwell, David Oscar Markus, did not immediately return a message seeking comment. He signed a July letter saying Maxwell "will have no choice but to invoke her Fifth Amendment rights" unless her demands were met.</p> 
<p>Maxwell was sentenced to 20 years in prison in 2022 on child sex trafficking charges. In the context of government investigations, the Fifth Amendment protects against witnesses from being forced to give testimony that would potentially incriminate themselves.</p> 
<p>Maxwell sat for a two-day interview with the Justice Department in July and shortly afterward was transferred to the minimum security facility in Texas. Critics have argued she has received favorable treatment from the administration. Maxwell is also preparing a commutation application for President Donald Trump's consideration.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This House GOP centrist is plotting a new health care bill aimed at winning over Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635</link>
      <description>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick wants to pair an extension of Obamacare subsidies with new flexibility for health savings accounts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a779-d739-a3ba-fffd33380000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 12:33:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/89/1f/76c377164f26953c2731101ac4a9/u-s-congress-94407.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“We’re going to have to move quickly,” Fitzpatrick said.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/89/1f/76c377164f26953c2731101ac4a9/u-s-congress-94407.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A key House Republican moderate is drafting a new bill that would extend soon-to-expire Obamacare subsidies and offer a carrot to try to win over more-conservative GOP colleagues and President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.), who co-chairs the bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus, outlined in an interview Friday several elements he is eyeing for the new proposal: an extension of the Affordable Care Act tax credits, with income limits and required minimum premium payments; new flexibility for health savings accounts, a conservative priority aimed at wooing Trump and conservatives; and potentially a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2025/09/08/can-congress-revive-pbm-reform-00549936" target="_blank">stalled bipartisan package</a> overhauling the role of pharmaceutical benefit managers.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, who has been working with fellow GOP centrists who are desperate to address the subsidy cliff, said it was “our hope” that they would soon introduce a bill encompassing those provisions.</p> 
<p>“We’re going to have to move quickly,” he said.</p> 
<p>The proposal would be <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/rick-scott-releases-obamacare-subsidy-alternative-00664146" target="_blank">competing with</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/cassidy-fund-hsas-trump-aca-subsidies-00655213" target="_blank">multiple alternatives</a> from conservative Republicans who are proposing to at least partially end the federal subsidies for plans purchased on Affordable Care Act exchanges, replacing them with individual accounts that they say would give Americans more flexibility to purchase health care.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and his allies are open to moving toward more flexibility for HSAs, but they don’t want to allow the Obamacare tax credits to expire as well. Some in the group strongly believe they need to focus on extending the existing subsidies first, then develop a broader health care overhaul.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and several other Republicans in the Problem Solvers group spoke about their health care plans during a private dinner Thursday night. Bacon <a href="http://politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/house-denounces-horrors-of-socialism-00664412" target="_blank">rolled out a separate bipartisan plan</a> Friday with GOP Rep. Jeff Hurd of Colorado and Democratic Reps. Tom Suozzi of New York and Josh Gottheimer of New Jersey that would extend the subsidies for two years, albeit with new restrictions on eligibility.</p> 
<p>But Fitzpatrick said that, based on conversations with colleagues, more than an extension will need to be included in order to attract a critical mass of GOP votes. Trump and top House GOP leaders have signaled they are opposed to continuing the ACA tax credits, and scores of House Republicans have signaled the same.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise, asked about the centrist Republicans’ aims in an interview Friday, said GOP leaders had other plans. He indicated Republicans are planning to bring legislation dealing with HSA flexibility, the PBM overhaul, cost-sharing reductions and other conservative policies to the floor in the coming weeks — but not an ACA tax-credit extension.</p> 
<p>“There are a lot of really good ideas that we're going to be bringing to the floor for votes that lower premiums for families, bring more transparency and more options for families,” he said.</p> 
<p>When asked if GOP leaders believe it’s tenable to allow the subsidies to expire, letting those other policies fill the gap, he replied: “We don't have all the final things agreed upon, and we will work through it with our whole conference.”</p> 
<p>The House GOP centrists feel left in the lurch by their own leaders, who have followed the lead of more conservative factions in advocating for the subsidies to expire. But they’ve also been angered by moderate Democrats, who they say are insisting on first sketching out a larger “framework” for negotiations.</p> 
<p>Democrats have been cool to the GOP proposals that would substitute individual spending accounts for the existing subsidies, arguing that they would not fully fill the financial gap for many Americans and could <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/11/obamacare-could-collapse-under-trumps-new-plan-policy-experts-say-00647246" target="_blank">destabilize health insurance markets</a>.</p> 
<p>One House Republican who was at the Thursday night dinner said colleagues spent a large portion of the evening kvetching about Democrats, whom they remain angry at after the lengthy government shutdown.</p> 
<p>“We’re past talking about frameworks,” said another House Republican, who was granted anonymity to speak candidly about the internal discussions. “This is an emergency.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jordan seeks info from banks in probe of Jack Smith</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/jordan-writes-to-banks-00664520</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a744-df0f-abfa-e76e57d70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 12:00:19 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan is asking major banks to hand over communications and materials related to former special counsel Jack Smith’s far-reaching investigations into President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Bank of America, JPMorgan Chase, Citigroup and Morgan Stanley are among more than a dozen financial institutions receiving letters from the Ohio Republican, who wants documents relating to requests for financial data from federal law enforcement officials.</p> 
<p>“During the Biden-Harris Administration, the Department of Justice subpoenaed financial institutions … for financial records of private customer data in its politicized investigations into President Trump,” Jordan wrote in the letters obtained by POLITICO. “We write to request relevant materials in [your] possession.”</p> 
<p>Smith was appointed by then-President Joe Biden to investigate Trump’s retention of classified documents and efforts to subvert the results of the 2020 election — the latter of which has prompted renewed outrage among Republicans after revelations that Smith’s office requested GOP senators’ private phone data without their knowledge. Republicans see that move as an overreach and the investigation itself as a politicization of the Justice Department.</p> 
<p>Jordan was already conducting his own investigation into Smith’s work, including asking Smith to sit for a transcribed interview with his committee. Smith has countered he will answer lawmakers’ questions in a public forum, after he has the opportunity to view his records from the Justice Department. The two men have not yet reached an agreement.</p> 
<p>In the meantime, Jordan has just recently discovered that two years worth of his own phone records were also subpoenaed by the Biden DOJ — though the legal document showing the seizure was dated before Smith’s appointment in 2022.</p> 
<p>“The thing that got me was the length of time,” Jordan said in an interview Friday. “It's just creepy, and it's ridiculous … I want to know who signed off on it.”</p> 
<p>He said he had not yet decided if he would call Biden’s attorney general, Merrick Garland, to sit for an interview with his committee, too.</p> 
<p>"We do not share client account information with the government voluntarily — we were compelled to do so by law," said a spokesperson for JPMorgan Chase in a statement. "Responding to subpoenas is a legal obligation, not a choice or a sign of collusion."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson with Morgan Stanley did not immediately return a request for comment about Jordan’s Friday letter, while spokespeople for Bank for America and Citigroup declined to comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House votes to denounce ‘horrors’ of socialism ahead of Mamdani-Trump meeting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/house-denounces-horrors-of-socialism-00664412</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a724-d739-a3ba-fffca88b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 11:03:52 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House voted 285-98 to approve a resolution condemning the “horrors of socialism” Friday morning, just hours before President Donald Trump is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/mamdanis-meeting-with-trump-comes-with-a-power-disadvantage-00664265" target="_blank">set to meet</a> with New York’s incoming democratic socialist mayor Zohran Mamdani.</p> 
<p>Eighty-six Democrats joined with Republicans to approve the measure. Two others voted present. No Republican voted to oppose it.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson and House GOP leaders have decried Mamdani’s election as the next mayor of the country’s largest city, citing his far-left politics and arguing he is the new, radical face of the Democratic Party. They’ve vowed to make him a centerpiece of their attacks against Democrats ahead of the 2026 midterm elections.</p> 
<p>Democrats on Capitol Hill have dismissed the Republicans broadsides over Mamdani, and party leaders criticized the GOP-written measure ahead of Friday’s vote, saying it “selectively lists certain despotic leaders and the harms of totalitarian regimes self-labeled as ‘socialist.’”</p> 
<p>They did not, however, formally recommend a no vote. A swath of moderate Democrats, especially from New York, are uncomfortable with Mamdani’s rise in their party.</p> 
<p>The debate over the symbolic measure was derailed for about 10 minutes after Rep. Maria Salazar (R-Fla.) verbally attacked Rep. Maxine Waters (D-Calif.) on the floor, accusing her of being a “friend” of the late Cuban dictator Fidel Castro despite traveling to the country and seeing the abuses of his regime.</p> 
<p>Waters asked for Salazar’s words to be taken down, but Salazer instead withdrew her remarks, allowing the debate to continue.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warren Davidson slams Lindsey Graham over Senate data payout provision</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/davidson-slams-graham-over-data-payout-measure-00664369</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a6ef-df0f-abfa-e7efc8760000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 10:18:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Warren Davidson on Friday denounced Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.) for his plans to capitalize on a new measure that allows senators — but not House members or the general public — to sue the federal government for accessing their electronic data without proper notice.</p> 
<p>The provision, inserted by Senate Majority Leader John Thune in last week’s shutdown-ending continuing resolution, was written for senators targeted in former special counsel Jack Smith’s investigation into President Donald Trump’s efforts to overturn the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>“This Senator wants the Constitution to protect him (Senators), but no one else,” <a href="https://x.com/warrendavidson/status/1991820152032363006?s=46" target="_blank">Davidson (R-Ohio) wrote Friday morning on X</a>. “Literally no one other than a United States Senator could sue for damages. The House unanimously opposed this corrupt carve out for Senators. Protect every American citizen. End 3rd party doctrine.”</p> 
<p>Senate Judiciary Chair Chuck Grassley (R-Iowa) <a href="https://x.com/chuckgrassley/status/1975297712712262100" target="_blank">disclosed records in October</a> that Smith’s investigation obtained phone records of nine GOP members of Congress. The eight senators on the list would be eligible to sue under the current provision, but Rep. Mike Kelly (R-Pa.), the lone House member, is not.</p> 
<p>The House on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-votes-to-overturn-thunes-controversial-subpoena-measure-00661169" target="_blank">Wednesday voted 426-0 to reverse the provision language</a>, but it is unlikely to be taken up further in the Senate, where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/thune-phone-records-payout-jack-smith-00658393" target="_blank">Thune doesn’t appear bothered by</a> the discord within the GOP.</p> 
<p>Graham’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment. But the longtime South Carolina senator has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">proposed expanding the class of people given standing to sue</a> under the provision to “any private group” targeted by Smith over the course of his investigation.</p> 
<p>“All of us who were wronged need to have a remedy to that wrong,” he said in a speech at the Capitol on Thursday. “And we’re creating a chance to go to court for what happened to us in a fashion to make sure it never happens again.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Things are not normal on the Hill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/house-censure-votes-bacon-beyer-trump-threats-00664290</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a4af-d49b-af9f-b4ef9fd80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After a seven-week recess, Speaker Mike Johnson was optimistic about making progress on urgent priorities like government funding and rising health care costs. Instead, the House used hours of floor time to vote five times this week on measures rebuking other members.</p> 
<p>“The only thing we can apparently do is condemn each other,” says Rep. Mark Pocan (D-Wis.). “I’ve not seen the House hit this low of a point since I’ve been here.”</p> 
<p>Once a rare tactic, censures have become commonplace partly for their use as a political rallying cry and a fundraising boon. Concerned lawmakers are now scrambling to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/house-censure-death-spiral-00663655" target="_blank">stop the censure wars from escalating</a>.</p> 
<p>Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and Don Beyer (D-Va.) introduced bipartisan legislation Thursday that would require 60 percent of the House — rather than the current simple majority — to approve a censure of a member, disapprove their conduct or remove them from committee assignments.</p> 
<p>“The institution needs some protection,” Bacon said in an interview.</p> 
<p>House leaders seem open to curbing the personal brawling. Johnson called the general suggestion of a rule change “an intriguing idea” and said he’d be “open to having that conversation.” Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries also said he is “open-minded about what the possibilities are in terms of getting the Congress out of this repeated effort by Republicans to censure members.”</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump added fuel to the fire when he declared Thursday morning that six Democratic lawmakers are engaged in “<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOUR, punishable by DEATH!</a>” The Democrats — Sens. Elissa Slotkin (Mich.) and Mark Kelly (Ariz.) and Reps. Jason Crow (Colo.), Chrissy Houlahan (Pa.), Maggie Goodlander (N.H.) and Chris Deluzio (Pa.) — shared a video Tuesday encouraging U.S. military members to disobey unlawful orders.</p> 
<p>Johnson initially <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/mike-johnson-trump-sedition-00662754" target="_blank">defended Trump</a>, saying it was the Democrats who were acting “wildly inappropriate.” He later conceded “the words that the president chose are not the ones I would use.” Senate Majority Leader John Thune said of Trump’s suggestion of executions: “I don’t agree with that.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Russia sanctions action: </b>Some Republicans are prepared to introduce a discharge petition as soon as Friday to force a vote on stalled Russia sanctions legislation if House leaders don’t take action. Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) told POLITICO he huddled with Johnson on the House floor Wednesday night and that Johnson “shares the sense of urgency” but “doesn’t necessarily” agree with Thune’s assessment that the bill must start in the House.</p> 
<p><b>— Another discharge petition threat: </b>House Republicans interested in forcing a vote to ban congressional stock trading say they’re ready to kick off the process Friday if leaders continue to stall. Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) told POLITICO she’s first waiting to see whether House Administration Chair Bryan Steil (R-Wis.) will mark up and offer an amendment process Friday on a potential separate bill related to stock trading.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu, Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mourning Dick Cheney — and the US House</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/11/20/mourning-dick-cheney-and-the-us-house-00663709</link>
      <description>The former vice president’s funeral marked the end of a certain kind of Congress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a35e-d739-a3ba-fffe57c30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 19:04:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e9/16/9f4e81564e3e86874ad8a1499920/aptopix-cheney-funeral-44262.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Rep. Liz Cheney, R-Wyoming, walks past her fathers casket after speaking a tribute, during the funeral for former Vice President Dick Cheney, at the Washington National Cathedral, Thursday, Nov. 20, 2025 in Washington. (AP Photo/Matt Rourke)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e9/16/9f4e81564e3e86874ad8a1499920/aptopix-cheney-funeral-44262.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jonathan Martin</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jonathan Martin</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was just another Thursday in Washington.</p> 
<p>Donald Trump was threatening to <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/white-house/trump-democrats-death-penalty-sedition-military-orders-rcna245003" target="_blank">execute congressional Democrats</a>, House members were mounting <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/house-censure-death-spiral-00663655" target="_blank">gangland-style political reprisals</a> on one another and the following people sat next to each in the same pew at Washington’s National Cathedral to remember the life of Dick Cheney: Anthony Fauci, Rachel Maddow, Ken Mehlman and James Carville.</p> 
<p><br>The former vice-president, who died earlier this month after modern medicine and a new heart let him see his grandkids become adults, would have been appalled at Trump’s conduct, amused by his coalition of the willing (mourners) and depressed by what has become of the House, where he represented Wyoming for a decade.</p> 
<p>Cheney’s service was fittingly held the first full week his beloved House was back in session after a 54-day absence following the government shutdown. The dispiriting part is that after they reopened the government, lawmakers quickly turned on one another. Resolutions of disapproval and even expulsion were teed up, with the usual tribal, red-vs.-blue targeting of the other party — but also intra-party warfare between rival factions.</p> 
<p>It was enough to make the bipartisan vote on the release of the Jeffrey Epstein files look like a historic triumph of Article I power and legislative branch independence.</p> 
<p>Now a decade into the Trump era, it’s easy to focus on his aberrant and indefensible behavior. In fact, we should — it’s important to not be inured to how he acts. Calling a female reporter “piggy,” treating visiting autocrats like they’re former Canadian Prime Minister Brian Mulroney, and saying of the Federal Reserve chair: “I’d love to fire his ass.” Which was all before he went on social media to say “Hang Them” of those Democratic lawmakers who recorded a video urging military service members to refuse illegal orders.</p> 
<p>And that was all just this week.</p> 
<p>Yet what’s disheartening about the breakdown of the House is it illustrates that the political rot runs deeper than just one man. Yes, Trump sets the example and has modeled the worst behavior. But we know who he is. This year makes clear, however, that the institutional decay in Washington may outlast his presidency.</p> 
<p><br>Republicans have full control of the government, yet there have been more resolutions of disapproval or censure (three) voted on individual lawmakers than there have been votes on major bills (one). It has gotten so bad that a bipartisan duo is introducing legislation to raise the vote threshold to censure a member, to “raise the level of sanity in the House.”</p> 
<p>Yes, the lack of legislative activity is in part because House members wrapped many of their priorities in legislation formerly known as the “one big, beautiful bill.”</p> 
<p>But would any student of Congress really say this has been a productive year for the House? And could anyone tell you what their legislative priorities for the rest of this session have been since the BBB was signed in July?</p> 
<p><br>And then there’s that pesky Article I language, the power distributed to Congress by the Constitution. There’s not a single member of Congress who could argue with a straight face, at least in private, that they’re acting the part of a co-equal branch.</p> 
<p><br>Arriving for Cheney’s service, I encountered a former Republican congressional and White House aide, a conservative, dejected by Congress’s abdication of its authority. Had I seen, he asked, the clip of House Speaker Mike Johnson earlier this month in which the speaker says he’s “cheering for the president” to win the Supreme Court case challenging Trump’s power to levy tariffs without congressional approval? “I say that as a jealous guardian of the legislative branch of government,” Johnson added, irony unintended.</p> 
<p>Not far away was John Thune, the Senate GOP Leader and a House member himself at the turn of the century. “It’s a different era,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>“It’s a different era,” he said again, and without taking pleasure in the observation as he surveyed a sanctuary full of old guard Republicans and the Democrats doing their duty, whether out of obligation or respect for the Cheney family’s opposition to Trump after January 6.</p> 
<p>The audience reflected the end of Cheney’s career, and the eulogists spoke of Cheney the father, grandfather, boss and heart patient more than they did the controversial vice-president, 30-something presidential chief of staff or Desert Storm-era defense secretary.</p> 
<p>But there were reminders of the post that Cheney cherished so much, serving as Wyoming’s sole House member between 1979 and 1989.</p> 
<p><br>There were a handful of his colleagues from that era, including the few still left in Congress such as Nancy Pelosi and Steny Hoyer, as well as those who also ascended to higher office, like Al Gore and Dan Quayle.</p> 
<p>And the man who, had he won, would have been Cheney’s classmate in the House class of ’78 couldn’t help but stand in the pulpit and recall his own defeat that year.</p> 
<p>“The Republican wave didn’t reach West Texas that year,” said George W. Bush, recounting his only loss while generously noting that Cheney was undefeated.</p> 
<p>More telling, though, were the descriptions of Cheney’s mind and curiosity. Nobody dared say it outright in such a solemn setting, but I couldn’t help but think of what has been lost in today’s House. There’s not many Dick Cheneys walking through that door (at Cannon) and the few who are soon look to run for the Senate, governor or walk away entirely.</p> 
<p>Liz Cheney, his eldest daughter and the former congresswoman, recalled her father as a college dropout, working on power lines in Wyoming by day but reading Churchill’s history of World War II in a sleeping bag at night. She and her sister, Mary, would grudgingly go along with him as young girls as he took them to museums and battlefields, reading every word on every plaque to their consternation.</p> 
<p>And then in the winter of his life, as Liz recalled, she and her father went back to some of those same historic sites. And even as he declined, he would still come armed with that day’s newspapers, the latest issue of <i>The Economist</i> and a book.</p> 
<p>He was, Bush noted, “a serious man.”</p> 
<p>If only the same could be said for so many in today’s House.</p> 
<p>This isn’t to bask in blind nostalgia — those beneath the gravestones at Section 60 in Arlington and even more Iraqis should have their say in any full appraisal of Cheney’s career.</p> 
<p>Yet nobody would argue that the current Congress and particularly this House are worthy of a great country.</p> 
<p>There are still members who would’ve flourished in Cheney’s day, but even they are sober about the state of the institution.</p> 
<p><br>“This is one of those eras in which you read Kipling’s classic <a href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems/46473/if---" target="_blank">poem</a>, ‘If—’ over and over and then get up and go to work every day,” Rep. Tom Cole (R-Okla.), the House Appropriations Chair, told me. “The aim isn’t to rebuild Rome in a day. It is just to make things a bit better every day.”</p> 
<p><br>Liz Cheney can’t because, unlike most all of her former GOP colleagues, she couldn’t and wouldn’t get over what Trump did on January 6 — and her state rejected her because of it three years ago.</p> 
<p>I thought Thursday about that 2022 primary and recalled what stood out to me about an interview I conducted with Liz shortly before her inevitable defeat that summer.</p> 
<p>She inveighed against Trump and the danger he posed, but she said something more about her party and the institution in which she then served.</p> 
<p>“What the country needs are serious people who are willing to engage in debates about policy,” Cheney told me then, wishing Americans would “vote for the serious candidate.”</p> 
<p>Then she went further.</p> 
<p><br>“I would much rather serve with Mikie Sherrill and Chrissy Houlahan and Elissa Slotkin than Marjorie Taylor Greene and Lauren Boebert,” she said, adding of her then-House Democratic colleagues with national security backgrounds: “They love this country, they do their homework and they’re people who are trying to do the right thing for the country.”</p> 
<p>Cheney’s father had just recorded an ad for her, calling Trump “a coward,” and she was thrilled to have him by her side in her final House campaign.</p> 
<p>“I talk to him every day,” she said. “He’s just a source of tremendous wisdom across the board, he’s such a student of American history.”</p> 
<p>I reminded her that he co-wrote a <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=691f9749a909714d3fa60d34&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoFwkEKgCAQAMAX6UpKSLfoEnTpC4uaCrqKGkKvj5kwRu0bwJyTY8avEDclwxXJd3bGlNhdpmvPm9gRkLyzbM-uRYMEtoJYtdKLVEL-2qQZEA%3D%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.amazon.com" target="_blank">book</a> with his wife, Lynne, on House greats — <i>Kings of the Hill</i> – and she laughed for one of the few times that day. “Well, my mother wrote that — a sore subject,” she joked.</p> 
<p>Would you have stayed in the House had your dad not so revered the body? I asked.</p> 
<p>She dodged the question but turned more serious, explaining she was “so glad” she stayed — even though her career was nearly over.</p> 
<p>“Having the opportunity to help make sure that we protect any future January 6ths, it’s the right thing to be doing,” Cheney said.</p> 
<p>Her father also left the House without becoming one of those <i>Kings of the Hill</i>.</p> 
<p>Had he not been appointed Defense Secretary under George H.W. Bush, the taciturn Wyomingite may well have become speaker. Cheney was House Minority Whip when he left Congress in 1989, the back-up plan for Bush after John Tower’s Pentagon nomination was rejected by the Senate.</p> 
<p>He was a man of the House and relished that his daughter, Liz, followed him there and was even happier when she declined to run for the Senate in 2020. She seemed in that moment poised to eventually claim the post that eluded her father once he left Congress.</p> 
<p>But five years later Liz Cheney was out of Congress, honoring her father’s fidelity to the Constitution over party and then, in a moment that spoke louder than words, stopping on her way down the aisle as his funeral ended to hug Pelosi.</p> 
<p>It was a poignant moment, the two mothers of five and daughters of House members who rose to the leadership as political opposites but bonded when duty called.</p> 
<p>Former Rep. Richard B. Cheney (R-Wyo.) would’ve liked it.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The House is scrambling to avoid a censure death spiral</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/house-censure-death-spiral-00663655</link>
      <description>In their first full week back after the shutdown, lawmakers voted five times on measures to rebuke colleagues, eating up hours of floor time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a344-d49b-af9f-b7e45d090000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 17:03:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/87/62/d6a902ed4833b3966ab117f38b10/u-s-congress-38283.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“Most of us know this isn’t good for the institution," Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) said about the escalating tit-for-tat.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/87/62/d6a902ed4833b3966ab117f38b10/u-s-congress-38283.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As he reconvened the House this month after a seven-week recess, Speaker Mike Johnson promised to recommit lawmakers to making laws — adding session days and keeping them voting into the night to catch up on lost time.</p> 
<p>His members instead spent much of their first full week back after the shutdown sniping at each other and using the House floor to carry out attacks on colleagues. Lawmakers voted five times on measures to rebuke other members, eating up hours of floor time.</p> 
<p>The spasms of personal pique crossed party lines, with Democrats targeting Democrats and Republicans targeting Republicans in some cases. It left at least a few lawmakers fuming about the depths of the House’s dysfunction and looking for ways to address it.</p> 
<p>“The only thing we can apparently do is condemn each other,” said Rep. Mark Pocan (D-Wis.), slamming the legislative agenda. “I’ve not seen the House hit this low of a point since I’ve been here.”</p> 
<p>An effort by a fellow Democrat to rebuke Rep. Jesus “Chuy” Garcia (D-Ill.) over his apparent scheme to install his top aide as his successor <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/house-rebukes-garcia-00657309" target="_blank">succeeded Tuesday</a>. A Republican effort targeting Del. Stacey Plaskett (D-V.I.) over her communications with the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-escapes-censure-vote-epstein-texts-00658334" target="_blank">narrowly failed</a>, as did a GOP-led effort to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-punts-mills-censure-attempt-to-the-ethics-committee-00661242" target="_blank">censure Rep. Cory Mills</a>(R-Fla.) over various alleged ethical misdeeds.</p> 
<p>The Plaskett and Mills measures failed in part because of a small but vocal group of lawmakers determined to put a stop to the tit-for-tat floor antics before they spiraled into something even more disruptive.</p> 
<p>Two of them — Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and Don Beyer (D-Va.) — <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HRES_906?activeTabs=overview" target="_blank">introduced legislation</a> Thursday that would change House rules to make it harder for members to target colleagues, warning that the chamber is at risk of devolving into an irreparable cycle of caustic personal brawling.</p> 
<p>“The institution needs some protection,” Bacon said in an interview.</p> 
<p>The Bacon-Beyer proposal would require 60 percent of the House to approve the censure of a lawmaker, disapprove of their conduct or remove them from their committee assignments — up from the current simple majority threshold.</p> 
<p>“The censure process in the House is broken — all of us know it,” the two wrote in a letter to colleagues, saying the back-and-forth battles “impair our ability to work together for the American people, pull our focus away from problems besetting the country, and inflict lasting damage on this institution.”</p> 
<p>Johnson called the general suggestion of rules changes “an intriguing idea” this week. He made no commitments to act but said he’d be “open to having that conversation.”</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries also told reporters he was “open-minded about what the possibilities are in terms of getting the Congress out of this repeated effort by Republicans to censure members.”</p> 
<p>In addition to the five votes on Garcia, Plaskett and Mills, House leaders also worked to try and fend off an effort to censure or expel Rep. Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick (D-Fla.), who was indicted Wednesday on federal fraud charges. She has called the indictment an “unjust, baseless sham.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Greg Steube (R-Fla.), who publicly teased the effort to sideline his indicted colleague, said in an interview Thursday that he would hold off until the House Ethics Committee releases its report on Cherfilus-McCormick.</p> 
<p>That’s at least a nod to how things used to be done in the House, where members were given a chance to make their case in court or to an effective jury of their peers on the Ethics panel before being subjected to public discipline.</p> 
<p>Steube said he was ready to follow a more recent precedent: the House’s 2023 ouster of then-Rep. George Santos over claims of fraud and campaign finance irregularities.</p> 
<p>Efforts to punish the New York Republican erupted soon after revelations of his checkered personal history emerged following his 2022 election. But it was only following the release of a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/11/16/santos-ethics-reports-finds-substantial-evidence-of-criminal-wrongdoing-00127527" target="_blank">scathing Ethics report</a> that members acted overwhelmingly to expel him.</p> 
<p>“If [Cherfilus-McCormick] does not resign by the time the Ethics Committee releases its report detailing their investigation, then I’ll move forward," Steube said.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers now expect that report to be released in a matter of weeks, according to two people granted anonymity to describe internal House conversations.</p> 
<p>Extreme cases involving allegations of criminal conduct like Santos and Sherfilus-McCormick are not primarily what Bacon and Beyer are seeking to curtail.</p> 
<p>Instead, they are registering more concern about a recent spate of censures that have been doled out across party lines to lawmakers who have engaged in behavior that is crude, distasteful or simply objectionable to their political enemies.</p> 
<p>Rep. Paul Gosar (R-Ariz.), for instance, was censured in 2021 under a Democratic majority for posting an animated video depicting the murder of Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez (D-N.Y.). When Republicans retook the chamber, GOP members targeted Rep. Adam Schiff (D-Calif.) for his role in investigating President Donald Trump’s alleged connections to Russia and Rep. Rashida Tlaib (D-Mich.) for comments about Israel, among others.</p> 
<p>Once a rare and embarrassing rebuke, censure has <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-nightly/2025/09/19/how-censure-lost-its-bite-00574046" target="_blank">now become commonplace</a> — in no small part because it has become a political rallying cry and fundraising boon for the lawmakers who lead the disciplinary efforts as well as those they target.</p> 
<p>Without new protections, lawmakers fear the censure wars will continue to escalate.</p> 
<p>“It's an easy way for an individual member to elevate his or her profile, throw a rock at the other side and force your way onto the floor,” said one House Democrat granted anonymity to speak candidly about his colleagues’ motivations. “There doesn't appear to be any kind of mutually assured destruction kind of deterrence on this. So my guess is, it'll just keep going and going and going.“</p> 
<p>A handful of members have stood against that trend. Bacon was among six House Republicans who saved Plaskett from censure and removal from the House Intelligence Committee this week by voting no or present on the resolution targeting her.</p> 
<p>That sparked <a href="https://x.com/RepMTG/status/1991141316978155732" target="_blank">accusations from some colleagues</a> that they had struck a corrupt bargain to protect Mills. But Bacon said there were larger principles at stake and many more than six who wanted to avoid a doom spiral of retribution.</p> 
<p>Several Republicans told Bacon they “were voting yes but hoping I was a no,” he said. “Most of us know this isn’t good for the institution.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Thune offers to tweak controversial phone records language</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/john-thune-phone-records-tweak-00663527</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a313-d51c-a39e-af1bec840000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 16:27:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune offered Thursday to amend the controversial provision he slipped into last week's government funding package that could award GOP senators hundreds of thousands of dollars for having their phone records seized without their knowledge as part of an investigation into President Donald Trump's effort to overturn the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>Thune's proposal, presented on the Senate floor Thursday afternoon, would clarify that any payout to senators seeking damages would be directed back to the U.S. Treasury and would not personally enrich lawmakers. </p> 
<p>It comes less than 24 hours after the House voted unanimously to repeal the legislative language. It also follows a tense GOP lunch meeting Wednesday, where Thune got an earful from his own members upset they had no advance warning about the provision.</p> 
<p>Republicans discussed how to change the legislative language during the closed-door meeting and spent much of Thursday working to nail down the changes before Sen. Martin Heinrich (D-N.M.) came to the floor seeking unanimous consent to pass the House repeal measure.</p> 
<p>The provision passed last week would allow lawmakers to be personally awarded at least $500,000, which could have resulted in millions of dollars transferred to several GOP senators who were singled out by former special counsel Jack Smith's investigation into Trump's activities following the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>There was no agreement on the floor Thursday to move forward with Thune's proposed measure, which would not have changed the underlying statutory language. He instead offered a resolution that would have been binding only in the Senate and would not require House approval.</p> 
<p>Heinrich, the ranking member of the legislative branch appropriations subcommittee, objected to Thune's offer, saying the law itself needs to be changed and that both parties should keep talking about addressing the retroactivity of the provision.</p> 
<p>“Frankly, this is just outrageous to me,” said Heinrich. “This is at the exact same time as 22 million Americans could see their health insurance premiums skyrocket because Republicans refuse to extend the [Affordable Care Act] tax credits.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), who was among the lawmakers Smith subpoenaed, objected to Heinrich's unanimous consent request and made clear he wasn't interested in anything that would prevent him from filing a lawsuit.</p> 
<p>“What did we do to justify having Jack Smith issue a subpoena for the phone records of a branch of government — the Senate — where all of us had to decide whether or not to certify the election?” Graham asked on the Senate floor. “We’re not going to let the Democratic Party decide my fate. We’re going to let a judge decide my fate.”</p> 
<p>Graham also thanked Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, who negotiated the language with Thune. Schumer told reporters yesterday he supported a repeal.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-20T21:41:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Mike Johnson defends Trump's 'sedition' attacks on Democrats</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/mike-johnson-trump-sedition-00662754</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a24d-d49b-af9f-b6ed635f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 12:42:03 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson defended Donald Trump's declaration Thursday that <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">some congressional Democrats engaged in "sedition</a>" after the president suggested those Democrats should be executed Thursday.</p> 
<p>Johnson said it was the Democrats who were acting “wildly inappropriate” by suggesting that military members should disobey unlawful orders from Trump. By post "SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR, punishable by DEATH," according to Johnson, Trump was simply “defining the crime of sedition."</p> 
<p>"That is a factual statement," Johnson said, adding attorneys would have to "parse" the language in the criminal act.</p> 
<p>Trump had previously reposted another Truth Social user, who wrote, "HANG THEM GEORGE WASHINGTON WOULD!!"</p> 
<p>Johnson said he did not see the full scope of Trump's comments and reposts, but he joined in Trump's attacks on the six House and Senate Democrats who posted a video addressing military members.</p> 
<p>“For a senator like Mark Kelly or any member of the House or Senate to behave in that kind of talks is to me so just beyond the pale,” Johnson said, before telling reporters, “I’m not going to say anything more on it.”</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune pushed back on Trump's suggestion of executions, saying, "I don't agree with that." But he, too, criticized Democrats: "Obviously everybody has a First Amendment right [but] what they did was ill-advised and provocative and unnecessary."</p> 
<p>Later in the day — after White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt clarified that Trump did not actually want to execute members of Congress — Johnson softened his remarks, saying that “the words that the president chose are not the ones that I would use.”</p> 
<p>“Obviously, I don't think that ... these are crimes punishable by death or any of that," Johnson said. "But what the point [that] we need to emphasize here is that members of Congress in the Senate [and] House should not be telling troops to disobey orders. It is dangerous.”</p> 
<p>Speaking in a morning floor speech, Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer denounced Trump's comments, saying the president "is lighting a match in a country soaked with political gasoline."</p> 
<p>"Every senator, every representative, every American regardless of party should condemn this immediately and without qualification," he said. " Because if we don't draw a line here, there is no line left to draw."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-20T14:22:36-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump calls for Democratic lawmakers to face trial for ‘seditious behavior’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a1de-df0f-abfa-e1feb7990000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 10:42:12 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Thursday called for six Democratic lawmakers to face arrest and trial after they made a video encouraging U.S. service members and members of the intelligence community to refrain from following orders if they broke the law.</p> 
<p>“It’s called SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115582417825161974" target="_blank">Trump charged in a post on Truth Social</a>. “Each one of these traitors to our Country should be ARRESTED AND PUT ON TRIAL. Their words cannot be allowed to stand - We won’t have a Country anymore!!! An example MUST BE SET.”</p> 
<p>The president then reposted 16 Truth Social posts, <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@P78/115580255469225519" target="_blank">including one that advocated for hanging the Democrats</a>, like “GEORGE WASHINGTON WOULD.”</p> 
<p>“This is really bad, and Dangerous to our Country,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115582451169685243" target="_blank">he wrote later</a>. </p> 
<p>“SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR, punishable by DEATH!” he said in a separate post. </p> 
<p>Sens. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.) and Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), as well as Reps. Jason Crow (D-Colo.), Chrissy Houlahan (D-Pa.), Maggie Goodlander (D-N.H.) and Chris Deluzio (D-Pa.) were featured in the Tuesday video. They are all either military veterans or worked in national security-focused roles before taking office.</p> 
<p>“We know you are under enormous stress and pressure right now,” <a href="https://www.facebook.com/SenElissaSlotkin/videos/2558895077819811/" target="_blank">they said</a>. “Americans trust their military. But that trust is at risk. This administration is pitting our uniformed military and intelligence community professionals against American citizens. Like us, you all swore an oath to protect and defend this Constitution. Right now, the threats to our constitution aren’t just coming from abroad, but from right here at home. Our laws are clear, you can refuse illegal orders.”</p> 
<p>As part of a stated push to crack down on street crime and bolster deportations, Trump has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/30/national-guard-dc-deployment-extended-00629725" target="_blank">federalized National Guard troops in American cities</a>, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/02/trump-chicago-national-guard-00540357" target="_blank">Washington, Chicago</a> and Portland. Democratic officials have argued the president’s deployments constitute an illegal overreach of federal power and have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/06/lawsuits-national-guard-cities-trump-00595430" target="_blank">sued to stop them</a>.</p> 
<p>White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt in a Thursday briefing defended Trump's comments, saying the media had unfairly focused exclusively on his Truth Social posts, "but not what brought the president to responding in this way."</p> 
<p>But in a joint statement Thursday, House Democratic leadership condemned Trump’s “disgusting and dangerous death threats” and called for him to delete the posts, urging their Republican colleagues to say the same.</p> 
<p>The statement — co-signed by Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, Minority Whip Katherine Clark and Caucus Chair Pete Aguilar — said House leadership had been in contact with the House sergeant at arms and the United States Capitol Police to "ensure the safety" of the members mentioned in Trump's posts.</p> 
<p>“Donald Trump incited a violent attack on the Capitol on January 6th as part of a treacherous attempt to overturn the results of the 2020 presidential election,” they wrote. “The President’s violent and unhinged rhetoric against American patriots is consistent with his well-documented history of attacking prisoners of war, Gold Star families and war heroes. There is no bottom when it comes to Donald Trump.”</p> 
<p>The six Democrats later panned Trump's reaction, <a href="https://x.com/SenatorSlotkin/status/1991568438804763103" target="_blank">writing in a joint statement</a> that "no threat, intimidation, or call for violence" would deter them from defending the Constitution.</p> 
<p>“What’s most telling is that the President considers it punishable by death for us to restate the law," they said. "Our servicemembers should know that we have their backs as they fulfill their oath to the Constitution and obligation to follow only lawful orders. It is not only the right thing to do, but also our duty."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-20T11:54:32-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Indicted House Dem will step down from committee leadership position</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/jeffries-on-cherfilus-mccormick-00661418</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a1aa-d49b-af9f-b5eecd1e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 09:52:12 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Indicted Democratic Rep. Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick of Florida will step aside from her leadership position on a House Foreign Affairs subcommittee "while the matter is ongoing," House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries' office said Thursday morning.</p> 
<p>Democratic Caucus <a href="https://democrats.house.gov/imo/media/doc/democratic_caucus_rules_119th.pdf" target="_blank">rules require</a> indicted lawmakers to relinquish committee leadership slots. </p> 
<p>"Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick has proudly represented the people of Palm Beach and Broward Counties since 2022. Consistent with the United States Constitution, she is entitled to her day in court and the presumption of innocence," Jeffries spokesperson Christie Stephenson said in a statement. </p> 
<p>These are the first comments from the New York Democrats' team since news broke Wednesday night of the new allegations against the lawmaker. </p> 
<p>Cherfilus-McCormick has been charged with <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/florida-democrat-indicted-on-federal-fraud-charges-00661162" target="_blank">stealing federal disaster relief funds</a> and using the money to support her campaign for Congress, using straw donors to funnel FEMA funds to friends and having them contribute to her campaign, and conspiring to file a false tax return.</p> 
<p>In a statement Thursday, Cherfilus-McCormick called her indictment "an unjust, baseless, sham" and insisted "and I am innocent." </p> 
<p>She added, "The timing alone is curious and clearly meant to distract from far more pressing national issues. From day one, I have fully cooperated with every lawful request, and I will continue to do so until this matter is resolved."</p> 
<p>The Florida Democrat has also been the subject of an ethics investigation into campaign finance issues and requesting community project funding, known as earmarks, to a for-profit entity, potentially in violation of House rules. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Where health care talks stand</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/health-care-obamacare-extension-premium-hsa-00661368</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9fac-d739-a3ba-dffcba900000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate’s leaving Thursday for Thanksgiving recess without clear bipartisan agreement on how to address expiring Obamacare subsidies. But after a busy week of talks across the Capitol, we’re starting to get some clarity on what will or won’t pass muster in a year-end health care deal.</p> 
<p>Here’s what we’ve learned:</p> 
<p>— Sen. Bill Cassidy’s (R-La.) plan to redirect funds into health savings accounts isn’t going to fly with Democrats. Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer told reporters Wednesday his party only wants an extension of the Affordable Care Act credits that expire next month, and that “Cassidy’s proposal, as I understand it, replaces them.”</p> 
<p>“It’s privatizing health insurance, and it looks like it’s really problematic,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Health experts say Cassidy’s plan, which aligns with a proposal floated by President Donald Trump, also won’t necessarily do much to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/cassidys-obamacare-plan-will-not-lower-skyrocketing-premiums-democrats-and-policy-experts-say-00660894" target="_blank">offset looming premium spikes</a>. Those talking points could bolster Democrats’ opposition as they argue for a clean extension of the subsidies.</p> 
<p>— More Republicans are acknowledging it might be too late to enact major new health care policy before Dec. 31.</p> 
<p>“It’s a welcome discussion,” Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) told POLITICO. “But we’re not gonna get that done by Dec. 31.”</p> 
<p>When asked about the timeline on Wednesday, Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said there’s not enough time to make “major changes.”</p> 
<p>That could give a boost to Democrats who were promised a standalone vote on an ACA extension bill next month in exchange for reopening the government.</p> 
<p>But it could also embolden conservatives who are eager to ditch bipartisan talks and go their own way on a health care-focused, party-line reconciliation package, as White House deputy chief of staff James Blair teased Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Senate Budget Chair Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.) said Wednesday he plans to pursue a new budget reconciliation bill. However such a move would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">likely have to happen next year if at all</a>.</p> 
<p>— There’s one area of bipartisan promise on health care. Senate Finance Chair Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) and ranking member Ron Wyden (D-Ore.) say they’ll soon unveil a proposal to crack down on the health intermediaries known as pharmacy benefit managers — a longtime priority for the panel.</p> 
<p>Wyden told POLITICO he’s hopeful the Senate will advance a bill by the end of the year. When he chaired Senate Finance in 2023, the committee approved a PBM bill in a 26-0 vote.</p> 
<p>Committee Republicans are eager for the bill to hitch a ride on a must-pass legislative vehicle. One Senate aide involved in the negotiations tells POLITICO the package is likely to be in the mix in January as Congress approaches the next government funding deadline.</p> 
<p>Sen. Steve Daines (R-Mont.) told reporters Wednesday there could be a “window” to put it on the floor as a standalone measure.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p>— <b>More censures?</b> Look out for <a href="https://x.com/repgregsteube/status/1991317294870392922?s=46" target="_blank">whether there’s a move</a> to censure Rep. Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick (D-Fla.) after she was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/florida-democrat-indicted-on-federal-fraud-charges-00661162" target="_blank">indicted on federal fraud charges</a> Wednesday. This week has been heavy on censure efforts in the House, with Rep. Chuy García (D-Ill.) formally rebuked Tuesday and derailed attempts against Democratic Del. Stacey Plaskett of the Virgin Islands and GOP Rep. Cory Mills of Florida.</p> 
<p><b>— Next steps on permitting talks:</b> Key negotiators regard Thursday morning’s House Natural Resources Committee markup as an important step in reaching a comprehensive permitting reform deal this Congress. Chair Bruce Westerman’s (R-Ark.) bill would ease permitting reviews and limit legal challenges for projects under the National Environmental Policy Act, a bedrock environmental protection law many conservatives believe is mired in too much red tape.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA down to the wire:</b> The “Big Four” leaders of House and Senate Armed Services are racing to reach a compromise defense bill just a week before their self-imposed deadline. The lawmakers are hoping to drop the bill text the day they return from Thanksgiving break and are targeting an early December vote on the House and Senate floors.</p> 
<p><i>Robert King, Calen Razor, Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Josh Siegel and Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thune and Johnson suffer rare split over Epstein, Jack Smith fallout</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/thune-johnson-epstein-jack-smith-00660066</link>
      <description>The two men meet regularly and enjoy a good rapport, but the House speaker and Senate majority leader have found themselves caught up in intraparty drama.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9f35-d739-a3ba-dffd1fa10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5c/00/8438b9014c40aad978463feec8df/main-dumain-johnsonvthune-illustration.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Jade Cuevas/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.Dumain.JohnsonvThune.Illustration</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5c/00/8438b9014c40aad978463feec8df/main-dumain-johnsonvthune-illustration.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> have largely worked in lockstep since January. This week, they hit a rough patch.</p> 
<p>The two men are known for rising above whatever theatrics are embroiling their respective conferences. But in recent days they became enmeshed in just that, when they publicly split and shadowboxed over a pair of internal GOP dilemmas over politically toxic issues.</p> 
<p>The fissure emerged when Johnson trashed a measure that Thune tucked into last week’s <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_5371" target="_blank">government funding deal</a> to allow senators to sue the government and reap damages for electronic records seizures. With the Louisiana Republican calling the provision “a bad look,” the House on Wednesday unanimously passed a bill to repeal it in a major rebuke.</p> 
<p>Johnson suffered his own loss at the hands of Thune this week when the South Dakota Republican rebuffed the speaker’s calls to amend the House’s Jeffrey Epstein disclosure bill to include more protections for victims and whistleblowers. The Senate passed the bill by unanimous consent, after months of Johnson trying to slow it down in the House and ultimately succumbing to an end-run by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.).</p> 
<p>In an interview Wednesday, Thune downplayed the episodes, calling the phone records provision a “Senate issue” to work through and noting the congressional debate over the Epstein files “took on a life of its own” in the final stages.</p> 
<p>“We work very well together. Communicate regularly. There are always going to be hiccups along the way,” Thune said. “And I’ve served in the House. They are very different institutions and different cultures and ways of doing things but we make it work.”</p> 
<p>The split marked an unexpected round of turbulence for the mild-mannered GOP leaders, who meet weekly when both chambers are in session and are generally viewed as having a good working rapport.</p> 
<p>Now they face two huge challenges they will need to navigate together: Obamacare subsidies are set to expire at the end of next month, threatening health insurance premium hikes for millions of Americans, and the leaders face competing factions in both chambers when it comes to how to respond. In January, Thune and Johnson will once again have to rally their members around a bill to avoid another government shutdown. At stake in all the fights is how the GOP’s handling goes over with voters ahead of next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>The friction points reflect a well-worn dynamic of congressional life — the House and Senate operate at times in split-screen political realities despite Thune, Johnson and their conferences belonging to the same party.</p> 
<p>Thune, like most of the Senate, didn’t know Johnson before the low-key House member ascended to the speakership in the fall of 2023. But the two men developed a rapport before Thune took over as GOP leader in January. They are viewed as more aligned in their day-to-day operations and temperament than some of their predecessor pairings, including former Senate GOP leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51216" data-person-id="51216">Mitch McConnell</a> and the House’s former top Republican Kevin McCarthy.</p> 
<p>“They work well together. And they get along well,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151837" data-person-id="151837">John Hoeven</a> (R-N.D.), a close Thune ally, said of the two GOP leaders. “They not only have a professional relationship, they like each other.”</p> 
<p>Another Republican senator who knows Thune and Johnson said they had “worked very well together” so far, adding that some tension between the two chambers is “probably healthy.”</p> 
<p>“They’re very similar,” said the senator, who was granted anonymity to speak candidly about the leaders.</p> 
<p>That doesn’t change the fact that senior House Republicans, including some Johnson allies, are still smarting over the inclusion of the payout language for senators in last week’s funding package. It was designed to give special recourse to Senate Republicans who had their phone records seized during Jack Smith’s investigation into Trump’s 2020 election interference. House Republicans have said they didn’t learn about it until after the Senate passed the bill and it was the House’s turn to act on reopening the government.</p> 
<p>For an angry swath of House Republicans, the episode reinforced their long-standing anxieties about being jammed by the Senate and painted Johnson — who also said he didn't find out about the provision until after Senate passage — as embarrassingly out of the loop.</p> 
<p>Johnson quickly promised the House would vote on separate legislation to repeal it, and the House passed the rollback Wednesday night with zero opposition. Thune <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">also got an earful</a> from his own members during a closed-door lunch Wednesday, including from typical leadership allies like Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine).</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a> (R-Texas), a former Senate staffer, said Wednesday as he made the case for repealing the provision ahead of the vote that the House needed to “hip check” the Senate.</p> 
<p>Johnson, meanwhile, told reporters that Thune was “a trustworthy, honest broker, and that's why I was so surprised when we found out about that [phone records] provision.”</p> 
<p>Across the Capitol, Senate Republicans believe Johnson dropped a hot potato in their lap in the form of the bill to release the Epstein files. Johnson presided over bitter infighting for months over the bipartisan push to force a vote on the matter. By the time Johnson agreed to it, he was on the verge of being on the losing side of an open rebellion within his ranks and seemingly at odds with Trump, who suddenly urged Republicans to support it Sunday night.</p> 
<p>Johnson framed his pivot around a hope the Senate would alter the bill before clearing it for Trump’s signature.</p> 
<p>“I talked to John Thune over the weekend. I just texted him. We’re going to get together. We’ll talk about this,” Johnson told reporters as he left the House floor Tuesday following the 427-1 vote to release the files.</p> 
<p>But Senate Republicans, including members of leadership, never had an appetite for making changes. Many GOP senators privately made clear they didn’t want Thune to drag out the Epstein discussion as Johnson had, and Thune never publicly opened the door to amending the bill.</p> 
<p>Two people granted anonymity to discuss private party dynamics said that if Thune had bowed to Johnson’s push for changes, it would have risked keeping Republicans mired in the Epstein issue for weeks.</p> 
<p>"What was [Thune] supposed to do with a bill that passed the House 427-1 ... had no objections in the Senate and the president said he'd sign?" one of the people said.</p> 
<p>“That is House drama,” said another GOP senator granted anonymity to speak candidly about the situation. “We don’t need that over here.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House unanimously rebukes Thune on data seizure payouts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-votes-to-overturn-thunes-controversial-subpoena-measure-00661169</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9f00-d739-a3ba-dffc61f40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 21:03:46 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House unanimously voted 426-0 Wednesday night to <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6019" target="_blank">claw back language</a> in last week's government funding bill that could award some GOP senators hundreds of thousands of dollars in damages for having their phone records unknowingly obtained by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>The language, which was quietly slipped into the shutdown-ending package last week by Senate Majority Leader John Thune, drove bipartisan outrage in the House. Even outspoken critics of Smith — including House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio), who is leading an investigation into the Biden-era probe — supported the effort to repeal a politically toxic measure that was quickly branded as a taxpayer-funded windfall for a select few.</p> 
<p>“That policy, in my opinion — in the opinion I think of all the members of this institution — is unacceptable,” said House Administration Committee chair Bryan Steil (R-Wis.), during floor debate. “No one should be able to enrich themselves because the federal government wronged them, no elected official should be able to.”</p> 
<p>The provision would allow senators to sue the federal government for $500,000 or more if their electronic data was subpoenaed without proper notification. But there are concerns over the language’s retroactivity — which would extend protections to at least eight Republican senators whose records were obtained as part of Smith’s investigation into Donald Trump’s attempts to subvert the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>There are no guarantees the bill to repeal the language will get a vote in the Senate.</p> 
<p>The revelations that Smith obtained lawmakers’ private data has enraged Republican senators, who argue his probe amounted to a politicization of the Justice Department. But Smith’s subpoena was narrowly tailored for data around the Jan. 6 Capitol attack, and investigators did not receive the contents of their calls.</p> 
<p>Several GOP lawmakers whose phone data was subpoenaed have distanced themselves from the provision. But it may be too late. Thune hasn’t shown any interest in bringing the bill to the Senate floor, even amid the pushback from his members over his quiet decision to include it in the funding package.</p> 
<p>Thune told reporters Wednesday that additional conversations are necessary to reach a consensus about how to change the provision.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), who has indicated he intends to sue for a significant monetary reward, has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">proposed expanding who can sue</a> under the legislative language.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Ethics Committee establishes panel to investigate Cory Mills</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/ethics-investigates-mills-00660582</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9e3e-d51c-a39e-bf3ff0ef0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 17:37:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Ethics Committee launched a formal investigation Wednesday into myriad allegations against the embattled Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398811" data-person-id="398811">Cory Mills</a>, with the House poised to vote on whether to censure the Florida Republican later tonight.</p> 
<p>The bipartisan panel responsible for adjudicating accusations against House members has stood up an investigative subcommittee to review various allegations against Mills. It will be responsible for evaluating whether Mills broke House rules, laws or other standards in violating campaign finance rules; engaging in sexual misconduct or dating violence; or misusing his position or House resources; among other potential charges.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Mills did not immediately return a request for comment.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/06/cory-millis-threats-allegations-gop-00496518" target="_blank">Outside allegations against Mills</a> are numerous. He has been accused of stolen valor, benefiting from federal contracts while in office and assaulting a onetime girlfriend in his Washington apartment. That woman has since denied being assaulted, and Mills was never charged.</p> 
<p>More recently, another ex-girlfriend <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/05/gop-rep-mills-accused-of-threatening-to-release-nude-videos-of-ex-girlfriend-00495059" target="_blank">accused Mills of threatening</a> to release explicit videos of her. Last month, a judge in Florida <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/cory-mills-restraining-order-florida-00608307" target="_blank">granted the woman a restraining order</a> against the lawmaker.</p> 
<p>The announcement from the Ethics Committee Wednesday afternoon said members will also consider whether Mills “failed to properly disclose required information on statements required to be filed with the House;” “improperly solicited and/or received gifts, including in connection with privately sponsored officially-connected travel;” or “received special favors by virtue of his position.”</p> 
<p>The panel had already been looking at some allegations against Mills, after a referral from what was then the Office of Congressional Ethics. The nonpartisan watchdog found “substantial reason to believe” Mills may have violated campaign finance rules, benefited from federal contracts while in office, or misreported his financial information.</p> 
<p>The Ethics Committee's announcement comes on the same day that Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/282851" data-person-id="282851">Nancy Mace</a> (R-S.C.) introduced a resolution to censure Mills and strip him of his committee assignments. Republican leaders are expected to attempt to refer the matter to the Ethics Committee as a way of tabling the matter on the House floor, and the disclosure of the panel's investigative steps could help provide political cover to GOP conference members who might have otherwise felt pressure to formally admonish Mills.</p> 
<p>Still, the allegations against Mills have become a growing headache for House GOP leaders. Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, asked about the restraining order against Mills last month, replied: “I have not heard or looked into any of the details of that.”</p> 
<p>He added: “I’ve been a little busy. We have a House Ethics Committee. If it warrants that, I’m sure they’ll look into that.”</p> 
<p>Mills did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
