<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 21:38:16 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Dems fall short of flipping deep-red House seat in surprisingly competitive Tennessee special election</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/republican-matt-van-epps-wins-tn-special-election-00673966</link>
      <description>Republican Matt Van Epps won after both parties spent significant effort in a district Trump won by more than 20 points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e17e-da2c-af9f-fb7f333a0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 21:38:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0b/b0/cea3df124b91ba1add94bfab16b4/van-epps-02708.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Republican Matt Van Epps won the special election for Tennessee’s 7th Congressional District.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0b/b0/cea3df124b91ba1add94bfab16b4/van-epps-02708.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican Matt Van Epps won a Tennessee House special election on Tuesday, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/tennessee-aftyn-behn-matt-van-epps-democrats-00674118" target="_blank">Democrat Aftyn Behn significantly cut into GOP margins in the district</a>, continuing a streak of overperformances this year.</p> 
<p>National outside groups poured millions into the race, as Republicans grew concerned about a potential upset.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump carried the district by 22 points last fall, but voters’ dissatisfaction with cost of living helped Behn trim that margin.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elise Stefanik is Johnson’s latest challenge as he struggles to keep control of the House</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/elise-stefanik-mike-johnson-feud-00674030</link>
      <description>The New York Republican took remarkable public shots at the speaker Tuesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e1ba-db69-a9fb-e5fb91270000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 20:04:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b1/ab/516c363b4e3b80e772cfe092dd55/u-s-congress-03347.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Stefanik, left, is getting backup from House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan, right, in her battle to get her pet provision in a must-pass bill.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b1/ab/516c363b4e3b80e772cfe092dd55/u-s-congress-03347.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Even by the high standards of chaos for the 119th Congress, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> being accused Tuesday by a member of his own leadership team of protecting the “deep state” was a remarkable development.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227481" data-person-id="227481">Elise Stefanik</a>’s rare move to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/stefanik-accuses-johnson-lying-00672634" target="_blank">publicly accuse the speaker</a> of being a liar and then, in a separate provocation, signing on to an effort to force a vote on legislation Johnson has kept bottled up is the latest symptom of a House Republican Conference seemingly on a razor’s edge.</p> 
<p>Increasingly, rank-and-file House Republicans are bringing their spats with Johnson into the open, suggesting the speaker is losing further control over his restive members as his already slim majority threatens to narrow further and potentially devastating midterm elections loom.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260571" data-person-id="260571">Kevin Kiley </a>(R-Calif.), who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/kevin-kiley-shutdown-gop-critic-00608517" target="_blank">openly challenged Johnson’s decision</a> to keep the House out of session for seven weeks this fall and criticized him for not pushing back on the GOP’s mid-decade redistricting campaign, said in a brief interview Tuesday that he saw Stefanik’s anger as part of broader trend.</p> 
<p>“I do think that there's a lot of frustration right now in the House with the effectiveness or lack thereof of this body in recent months,” he said. “The House has … in some cases ceded its own authority, hasn't taken the lead on a lot of important policy measures and has even taken steps now to limit the agency of individual members.”</p> 
<p>For much of his two-year tenure, Johnson has been able to keep a handle on the infighting thanks to President Donald Trump’s stranglehold on the Republican Party, with the president personally intervening at key points this year to settle internecine disputes.</p> 
<p>But many sense that is changing as the speaker suffers public setbacks — such as his recent failure to prevent passage of a bill mandating the release of Justice Department files related to the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein. Things could fray further depending on how the GOP fares in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/house-republicans-tennessee-special-election-00672582" target="_blank">Tuesday’s special election in Tennessee</a>.</p> 
<p>"That model only works if no one challenges him and gets away with it," said one senior House Republican granted anonymity to speak frankly about conference dynamics. "And that's not what's happening now. … People are less willing to stay quiet.”</p> 
<p>In particular, several high-profile GOP women have clashed with the speaker over various issues in recent months. Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/337881" data-person-id="337881">Marjorie Taylor Greene</a> of Georgia, Nancy Mace of South Carolina and Lauren Boebert of Colorado were instrumental in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/epstein-files-bill-congress-00655286" target="_blank">pushing through the Epstein bill</a>. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> of Florida filed her second discharge petition of the year Tuesday, seeking to force a vote on a bill banning member stock trading that the speaker has so far declined to advance. And several women in the House GOP raised concerns about leaders’ handling of Rep. Cory Mills (R-Fla.), who is facing multiple accusations regarding his conduct and ethics.</p> 
<p>Stefanik is in another category altogether. A year ago, she was the No. 4 House GOP leader before relinquishing her post in anticipation of her confirmation as ambassador to the United Nations. But Trump withdrew her nomination amid concerns about the thin GOP majority — a move for which Stefanik has privately faulted Johnson.</p> 
<p>Johnson granted her an unelected junior leadership role as a consolation prize, but she has decided her political future will not lie in the House, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/07/elise-stefanik-new-york-governor-campaign-launch-00641679" target="_blank">launching a campaign for New York governor</a> instead of seeking re-election. And now she appears to be all-in on a scorched earth campaign against the speaker.</p> 
<p>"Elise is running for governor and frankly does not give a fuck anymore about playing nice," said a second House Republican granted anonymity to speak frankly about the dispute.</p> 
<p>The precipitating cause for Stefanik’s public outburst, in her telling, was a leadership-level decision to exclude legislation requiring that Congress be informed of counterintelligence probes into candidates for federal offices from the annual defense policy bill — a must-pass measure to which lawmakers are keen to attach their personal priorities.</p> 
<p>After Stefanik <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/stefanik-accuses-johnson-lying-00672634" target="_blank">posted her displeasure</a> to her X account, Johnson tried to tamp down the furor Tuesday. The speaker, who sometimes jokes he’s more of a mental health counselor, told reporters he couldn’t understand why Stefanik “didn’t just call me” and that the two could have handled the dispute in private.</p> 
<p>“Just more lies from the Speaker,” Stefanik retorted, <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995886289527214190" target="_blank">again on X</a>, mocking Johnson’s claims of ignorance. “This is his preferred tactic to tell Members when he gets caught torpedoing the Republican agenda.”</p> 
<p>House Republicans close to Stefanik argue there are more GOP members who are upset about the congressional notice provision falling out of the Pentagon bill. Notably, House Judiciary Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51745" data-person-id="51745">Jim Jordan</a> (R-Ohio) said he had not yet thought about whether he would join Stefanik in withholding his support for the bill over its exclusion.</p> 
<p>“We want this protection in there,” he told reporters. “I think it makes sense.”</p> 
<p>Just hours after Stefanik’s comments, Johnson faced down a brief revolt over a procedural measure on the House floor led by hard-line Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and other incensed Republicans that would have derailed GOP leaders’ floor plans for the week.</p> 
<p>As that crisis was still unfolding, Luna launched her <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/house-discharge-petitions-mike-johnson-00666557" target="_blank">discharge petition</a> to force a vote on a congressional stock trading ban — and Stefanik quickly announced she was signing on to the move undermining the speaker’s authority.</p> 
<p>Members of Johnson’s leadership circle and other senior Republicans were privately shocked by Stefanik’s sharp public criticism of the speaker — and that she didn’t later decide to delete them — according to three people granted anonymity to describe conversations that unfolded Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s staff have reached out to Stefanik’s team and are seeking to resolve the spat privately, according to two other people with direct knowledge of the matter.</p> 
<p>The speaker’s allies argue the disgruntled Republicans are just that — people with axes to grind against Johnson.</p> 
<p>But Stefanik is getting backup from other malcontents inside the House GOP, including Greene, who was once seen as being on the opposite pole of the Republican conference. Both women were kept in close consultation by the previous speaker, Kevin McCarthy, and have since fallen out with Johnson.</p> 
<p>After helping to engineer the successful Epstein files vote, Greene <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972" target="_blank">announced her imminent resignation</a> — itself a slap at Johnson, given the tight GOP majority — and publicly railed against the House’s diminished power and Johnson’s speakership. She weighed in again Tuesday after Stefanik aired her accusations about the Pentagon bill.</p> 
<p>“No surprises here,” Greene said in her <a href="https://x.com/RepMTG/status/1995869033590321660" target="_blank">own X post</a>. “As usual from the Speaker, promises made promises broken. We all know it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans want a health care plan. They don’t know what will go in it.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/republicans-want-a-health-care-plan-they-dont-know-what-will-go-in-it-00673969</link>
      <description>House and Senate Republicans need to build consensus around a health care proposal by the end of next week if they want to compete with a Democratic plan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e18c-da2c-af9f-fbeda5ed0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 19:11:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/51/4e/e45f580c4d7d9885a212a944121d/u-s-congress-07906.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) is seen at the U.S. Capitol Oct. 1, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/51/4e/e45f580c4d7d9885a212a944121d/u-s-congress-07906.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican lawmakers are looking to craft their own health care policy overhauls by the end of next week, when Senate Democrats get a vote on expiring Obamacare subsidies. So far they don’t agree on what their competing plan should look like.</p> 
<p>In separate closed-door meetings Tuesday, House and Senate Republicans debated what they could put forth as they face the reality that health insurance premiums will skyrocket if enhanced Affordable Care Act tax credits lapse after Dec. 31. Speaker Mike Johnson for the first time definitively promised his anxious members he would put forward some kind of health care blueprint in the coming days, while Senate Republicans discussed how to lower health care costs including through a revamp of health savings accounts. </p> 
<p>But GOP leaders in both chambers face deep divisions within their ranks about how to proceed, including whether to extend the credits at all and force Republicans to vote for the first time to affirm Obamacare. With Tuesday’s conversations producing little clarity, GOP lawmakers said they are still far away from a plan they could unite behind by the end of next week.</p> 
<p>“Have you ever heard of a Rorschach test? Let’s smear it all over the wall,” Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) said about the state of the GOP’s health care discussions. </p> 
<p>Some Republicans on Capitol Hill worry that the failure to come up with any plan in the coming days could be a political nightmare heading into the 2026 midterms, with GOP candidates being dogged by questions about increased health care costs. </p> 
<p>Retiring Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) Tuesday warned of a potential backlash during the midterms if the subsidies expire, predicting Democrats would pummel Republicans in 2026 by highlighting a “number of sympathetic cases” where Americans have seen their health insurance costs go up.</p> 
<p>“There’s a lot of harmonization that needs to be done,” he said about the GOP’s health care talks. </p> 
<p>During their weekly lunch Tuesday, Senate Republicans heard from Finance Chair Mike Crapo and HELP Chair Bill Cassidy about their progress in developing a Republican proposal that could be put on the floor alongside the Democratic plan. Senate Majority Leader John Thune is giving Democrats a vote as part of a deal he struck to re-open the government.</p> 
<p>As part of the lunch, Republicans discussed providing more flexibility for how health savings accounts are used, imposing income caps on ACA subsidies and requiring ACA enrollees to make minimum payments on premiums, according to senators in attendance. </p> 
<p>Cassidy, a physician, has been an evangelist for boosting health savings accounts as an alternative to extending the tax credits. He’s poised to use a HELP Committee hearing on the topic Wednesday to tout this proposal.</p> 
<p>Thune is facing competing pressures within his conference over whether the ACA subsidies should be extended or allowed to sunset. Some GOP senators said after Tuesday’s lunch they expected there would be a vote on some kind of Republican health care measure next week, but Thune wouldn’t commit to that timeline, telling reporters only that his members would continue to discuss ideas. </p> 
<p>Crapo, in an interview, said it would be a “collective decision” from the Senate GOP Conference about whether his proposal with Cassidy would get a vote next week. </p> 
<p>Republicans are also still waiting to see what the Democratic proposal will be. Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer told reporters after a closed-door lunch with his own caucus that they discussed the idea and to “stay tuned” on where they would land. Democrats are likely to offer a clean extension of the subsidies, but haven’t said how long that extension would be. </p> 
<p>Across the Capitol, Johnson pledged Tuesday for the first time that House Republicans will put forward a health care plan soon. Many House Republicans left a closed-door conference meeting with the sense that GOP leaders could produce a framework by the end of this week. </p> 
<p>But House GOP leaders are confronting their own internal squabbling, with one person close to leadership, granted anonymity to speak candidly, describing that goal as “ambitious.” </p> 
<p>Leaders of the House Republican Conference have also pushed to omit any ACA subsidy extension from their upcoming health care plan, alarming GOP moderates who worry their reelection prospects hinge on the subsidies’ survival.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise got an earful on the concerns about proceeding without an ACA extension during a lunch meeting with the centrist Republican Governance Group, according to four Republicans in the room. </p> 
<p>One of the Republicans, granted anonymity to discuss the private conversation, said that nearly every member of that caucus complained to Scalise that “something needs to be done” on health care before the end of the year. Many of the members present advocated for an ACA subsidy extension. </p> 
<p>Scalise didn’t make any promises but said the “will of the conference” would decide whether Republicans could back health care provisions like an extension of the ACA subsidies — though a majority of House Republicans don’t support it. </p> 
<p>“We had a good conversation about all the work that's been done by the three committees of jurisdiction,” Scalise said in an interview after the meeting, referring to House Energy and Commerce, Ways and Means and Education and the Workforce.</p> 
<p>“Of course, members that aren't on those committees, you know, haven't been aware of some of the things that have come out, but we also wanted to get their feedback,” Scalise added.</p> 
<p>Some Republicans are holding out hope for a bipartisan breakthrough, as GOP leaders pursue what would likely be party-line options.</p> 
<p>House Problem Solvers Co-Chair Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) is working on a bill that reflects the leaked health care framework the White House was planning to reveal last week but held back amid conservative backlash. He told reporters Tuesday he has discussed the bill with the White House and it is “not addressing” abortion restrictions — a bid to entice Democrats.</p> 
<p>"We're trying to get a bill that can get 218,” Fitzpatrick said. "I think it's the most serious attempt out there."</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rep. Ayanna Pressley will run for reelection, foregoing Senate race</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/pressley-seeks-reelection-00673538</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e0ed-da2c-af9f-fbede9820000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 16:33:10 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Ayanna Pressley won’t challenge Sen. Ed Markey for his Senate seat and instead plans to seek reelection to her House seat, she announced today, ending weeks of speculation about the progressive Democrat’s political future.</p> 
<p>“Hearing from so many people from throughout our Commonwealth encouraging me to run for the United States Senate was deeply humbling and a testament to the strength of our movement. It would be an honor to serve the whole Commonwealth—but with our daughter in her last year at home before college and a district that has been in the crosshairs of this White House, I am certain that the Massachusetts 7th is where I belong in this moment,” Pressley said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Markey, who will be 80 when he’s up for reelection next year, is already facing a challenge from Rep. Seth Moulton. The Salem Democrat has centered his campaign on a call for generational change in the wake of the 2024 elections.</p> 
<p>Pressley <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/04/congress/ayanna-pressley-for-senate-00636295" target="_blank">was considering her own bid for Senate</a>, and a recent <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2025/11/25/metro/full-poll-results-massachusetts-voters/?p1=Article_Inline_Related_Link" target="_blank">Suffolk University/Boston Globe poll</a> showed her neck-and-neck with Markey in a three-way Democratic primary. But polling also showed her entrance into the race would narrow Markey’s lead over Moulton, raising concern among progressives in the state that a three-way race could open a lane for the more moderate congressman.</p> 
<p>“Now, more than ever, is the time to dig deep, to lean into mutual aid, and to use every tool available to stand in the gap in defense of our neighbors and our democracy,” Pressley said.</p> 
<p>In a statement responding to Pressley’s announcement, Moulton called her “a powerful advocate for justice and opportunity in Massachusetts,” and Markey described the Squad member as “a champion for the 7th Congressional District, for Massachusetts, and for our nation.”</p> 
<p>“I share her commitment to the fight against authoritarianism, to take back the House and the Senate in 2026, and I am deeply grateful for her continued partnership,” Markey said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Luna pushes to force a vote banning congressional stock trading</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/anna-paulina-luna-congressional-stock-trading-ban-00673180</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e08e-dbbc-a3fa-f2eed7d90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 14:56:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Anna Paulina Luna is pushing forward with a discharge petition to circumvent Speaker Mike Johnson and force a vote on a <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/house-resolution/725" target="_blank">congressional stock trading ban</a>, she said in an interview Tuesday.</p> 
<p>The politically explosive topic is still divisive among House Republicans, but broadly popular with the public. Luna (R-Fla.) said she's done with waiting around for accountability on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Rep. Tim Burchett (R-Tenn.), who is working on the effort with Luna, agreed many Republicans are “tired” of GOP leaders pushing off the legislation.</p> 
<p>It’s just the latest internal GOP fight Johnson has to deal with. At the same time Luna and Burchett formally launched their discharge petition effort Tuesday afternoon, Johnson faced a revolt among his members on the House floor over a procedural move involving legislation to regulate name, image and likeness compensation in college sports.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thune says abortion language a sticking point in health care talks</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/thune-abortion-language-health-care-00672635</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-e002-d51c-a39e-ed0bb5e30005</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 12:02:27 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said Tuesday that while bipartisan discussions are ongoing around the fate of soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies, abortion restrictions are a major sticking point.</p> 
<p>“There are conversations that continue, but as you know the Hyde issue is a difficult and challenging one on both sides,” Thune told reporters.</p> 
<p>The fight over the so-called Hyde Amendment, which bars federal funding for abortion, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/24/congress-republicans-abortion-health-00577631" target="_blank">has been looming over any potential deal</a> to extend the enhanced Obamacare tax credits. And GOP lawmakers, not to mention a cadre of influential anti-abortion groups, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/republicans-trump-obamacare-abortion-00669389" target="_blank">quickly noticed the White House’s framework was silent</a> on the issue.</p> 
<p>The White House ultimately held off on releasing that framework as it faced a mountain of GOP criticism from conservatives who felt caught off guard that Trump would back a two-year extension of the subsidies — even when paired with new income caps and other restrictions.</p> 
<p>The Senate is expected to vote next week on a proposal from Democrats to extend the ACA subsidies, but Democrats haven’t yet detailed what bill they will put on the chamber floor.</p> 
<p>Republicans are separately working on a potential counterproposal that would come from Sens. Mike Crapo and Bill Cassidy, chairs of the Senate Finance and HELP Committees, respectively. GOP senators also have yet to decide whether they’ll roll out that plan in time for a vote next week, though, and the substance remains in flux.</p> 
<p>Sens. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) and Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said Monday night that while efforts to reach a bipartisan agreement persist, many lawmakers believe they are ultimately headed toward a failed vote next week. Some senators are already looking at Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cut-off for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think we’re close to a 60-vote threshold yet,” Thune said of bipartisan health care talks.</p> 
<p>There’s also uncertainty on the other side of the Capitol about how Republicans will respond to the looming expiration of the subsidies, which could cause premiums to skyrocket in the new year. Speaker Mike Johnson told reporters at his weekly press conference that he “didn’t commit to” a short-term extension during a closed-door House GOP members’ meeting Tuesday morning but that “there will be a Republican response to this.”</p> 
<p>“What I’ve got to do is build consensus deliberately around the best ideas,” Johnson said. “We’re pulling those ideas together … I can’t project in advance what that will be because I don’t know what the consensus is in that room.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stefanik accuses Johnson of lying, ‘blocking’ her defense bill provision</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/stefanik-accuses-johnson-lying-00672634</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dff1-d49b-af9f-fff50d260000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 11:43:07 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Elise Stefanik is taking aim directly at Speaker Mike Johnson over signals a provision she has championed won’t be included in the annual defense policy bill the House wants to pass next week — marking a notable and unusual split inside the House GOP leadership team.</p> 
<p>Stefanik, a New York Republican who serves as a member of Johnson’s leadership team, said in <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995856738994565416" target="_blank">a social media post</a> Tuesday morning she would help tank the National Defense Authorization Act if it doesn’t incorporate her provision that would require the FBI to notify Congress when it opens investigations into candidates running for federal office.</p> 
<p>“This is an easy one,” the New York Republican posted on social media Tuesday morning. “This bill is DOA unless this provision gets added in as it was passed out of committee.”</p> 
<p>Stefanik also blamed Johnson for the expected omission.</p> 
<p>“[T]he Speaker is blocking my provision to root out the illegal weaponization that led to Crossfire Hurricane, Arctic Frost, and more,” she wrote on X. “He is siding with Jamie Raskin against Trump Republicans to block this provision to protect the deep state.”</p> 
<p>Stefanik’s proposal, which would require the public disclosure of all “FBI counterintelligence investigations into presidential and federal candidates seeking office,” is designed to combat what many Republicans consider politically motivated investigations related to Russian interference in the 2016 election and former special counsel Jack Smith’s probe into President Donald Trump’s efforts to subvert the election in 2020.</p> 
<p>Asked about whether he thwarted the provision’s inclusion in the NDAA, Johnson said Stefanik’s retelling of events is “false.” He said he supported the provision and that there could still be a path for its passage in some other legislative vehicle.</p> 
<p>“I don’t exactly know why Elise just won’t call me,” he said, recalling that he told his colleague over text, “What are you talking about? This hasn’t even made it to my level.”</p> 
<p>Johnson explained the bipartisan leaders of the House and Senate Judiciary Committees, who he suspected have jurisdiction over this issue, had not agreed to include the language, leading to the provision being dropped from the defense bill. A spokesperson for Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary panel, deferred to Johnson’s explanation.</p> 
<p>Stefanik quickly responded in <a href="https://x.com/EliseStefanik/status/1995886289527214190" target="_blank">another post on X</a>, “Just more lies from the Speaker,” while insisting the Intelligence Committee, on which Stefanik sits, has jurisdiction over her provision.</p> 
<p>Leaders of the House and Senate Armed Services Committees have been negotiating the NDAA for weeks and could roll out a compromise package as soon as Thursday; Stefanik said in her social media post that she got early details of that package in an Intelligence Committee briefing.</p> 
<p>The narrow GOP majority in the House means that Johnson can barely afford to lose any Republican support if Democrats reject the legislation en masse, but it’s far from guaranteed Stefanik’s opposition will doom the NDAA on its own.</p> 
<p>While most Democrats opposed the hard-right version of the Pentagon bill the House passed in September, more Democrats might come on board to support a compromise measure and make up for a shortfall of votes on the Republican side of the aisle. The NDAA is typically a broadly bipartisan package.</p> 
<p><i>Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Republicans sweat Tennessee election, despite Hudson’s assurances</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/house-republicans-tennessee-special-election-00672582</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dfa5-d51c-a39e-ffad95540000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 10:20:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders are trying to steady their restive conference as they seek to avert disaster in a Tennessee special election for a ruby-red GOP-controlled seat on Tuesday night.</p> 
<p>NRCC Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/43694" data-person-id="43694">Richard Hudson</a> told House Republicans in their closed-door meeting Tuesday morning that Republican Matt Van Epps will win the race. But he also said members need to remember special elections are special, according to four people in the room, all of whom were granted anonymity to discuss the private meeting.</p> 
<p>National Republicans have had to intervene to attempt to rescue Van Epps from a potential defeat in Tennessee's 7th Congressional District, a conservative stronghold President Donald Trump won by more than 20 points.</p> 
<p>The race between Van Epps and Democrat Aftyn Behn has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/a-nationalized-tennessee-special-election-has-both-parties-on-edge-00671736" target="_blank">attracted millions in outside spending</a> from both sides, despite the typically uncompetitive nature of the district.</p> 
<p>Republicans in the room for Hudson's remarks Tuesday morning, however, did not feel much better about the state of the conference and the special election ahead of next year's midterms.</p> 
<p>"It was not overly comforting," one House Republican who attended the meeting said, noting that some GOP members quietly glanced over at each other as the North Carolina congressman argued a win is a win.</p> 
<p>Another House Republican predicted the GOP conference would spend some time reeling from the fallout of the race, given that it shouldn't have been competitive in the first place.</p> 
<p>“If our victory margin is single digits, the conference may come unhinged,” one senior House Republican said. A loss would be catastrophic and the conference would "explode," the Republican added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: The health care talks to watch</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/02/congress/health-care-obamacare-bipartisan-deal-talks-murkowski-thune-00672353</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dd5d-d739-a3ba-ddfd49340000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senators will be voting on health care in about a week. Their chances of success are not good.</p> 
<p>The most likely outcome: Two failed votes on competing partisan proposals and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/senate-barrels-toward-failure-on-health-care-00672273" target="_blank">no certain solution</a> to the Affordable Care Act subsidy cliff.</p> 
<p>But that doesn’t mean all is said and done. Senate Republicans and Democrats head into their respective party lunches Tuesday with lots of competing options to discuss. And even after the likely-to-fail Senate votes, talks will continue — with many lawmakers now viewing the Jan. 30 government funding deadline as the real drop-dead date.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said there’s “groundwork being laid that could end up in actually something getting done.”</p> 
<p>Here are the multiple tracks to keep an eye on:</p> 
<p><b>— The Senate Democratic proposal:</b> Expect Democrats to discuss Tuesday what they plan to offer up next week. Most likely is a “clean” extension of the ACA subsidies that few Republicans support, though they could offer GOP-favored eligibility restrictions as an olive branch to conservatives.</p> 
<p><b>— The Senate GOP alternative:</b> Most Republicans expect a “side-by-side” vote with a GOP alternative to the Democratic bill. GOP Sens. Mike Crapo of Idaho and Bill Cassidy of Louisiana are preparing that counterproposal, though it’s unclear what that might include or when it would be introduced.</p> 
<p><b>— The House GOP framework:</b> House leaders have tasked three committees with assembling a package of bills which they are tentatively looking to put on the floor before the chamber’s scheduled Dec. 18 departure for the holiday recess. Don’t expect this to get any Democratic buy-in.</p> 
<p><b>— The House centrists’ plan:</b> Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) told POLITICO Monday he has talked with the White House about a bill he is working on and shopping with like-minded moderates that would largely mirror Presdient Donald Trump’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635" target="_blank">unreleased framework</a>: “It’s one of those things where nobody’s going to love it. But hopefully enough people are okay with it.”</p> 
<p><b>— The Senate bipartisan talks:</b> If a passable product is ever going to emerge, it’s probably coming out of this effort dating back to before the government shutdown involving the likes of Sens. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) and Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska). They are looking to forge compromise on an extension of the subsidies, but there’s not much time left.</p> 
<p>“The calendar is not necessarily our friend right now,” Murkowski said in a brief interview.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Special election fight in Tennessee: </b>Speaker Mike Johnson spent valuable time Monday boosting a Republican candidate in Tuesday’s Tennessee special election as the GOP hopes to shore up its slim House majority. Polling shows Republican Matt Van Epps leading Democrat Aftyn Behn by only single-digit margins, catching the attention of the president and national Republicans as they scramble to hang onto what should be a deep-red district.</p> 
<p><b>— Children’s internet safety hearing: </b>A partisan fight is brewing over whether to include state AI laws in legislation to protect kids’ safety online. A House Energy and Commerce subcommittee will hold a hearing Tuesday on the issue, fulfilling a promise made by committee Chair Brett Guthrie (R-Ky.) to advance kids’ safety legislation.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA text coming Thursday: </b>House Armed Services plans to release text for the National Defense Authorization Act on Thursday, Chair Mike Rogers (R-Ala.) and ranking member Adam Smith (D-Wash.) said Monday night. Rogers said he believes a moratorium on state AI regulation will not make it into the final version of the NDAA, despite an effort from Trump and some GOP leaders to include the language.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Calen Razor, Meredith Lee Hill, Katherine Long and Alfred Ng contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate barrels toward failure on health care</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/senate-barrels-toward-failure-on-health-care-00672273</link>
      <description>A bipartisan breakthrough appears unlikely ahead of next week's scheduled votes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dcd5-d739-a3ba-dcfddb530000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 21:15:29 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/99/93/4b04ee3c4ab39ed43bdb08b353a0/u-s-congress-82476.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) walks to a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 1, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/99/93/4b04ee3c4ab39ed43bdb08b353a0/u-s-congress-82476.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Calen Razor and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Calen Razor and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senators have about a week before they're set to vote on soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies. Most of them already believe the chances for a bipartisan breakthrough by then are roughly zero.</p> 
<p>There’s no clear momentum for any plan that would avoid a lapse in tax credits that could raise insurance premiums for 20 million Americans. House and Senate members involved in the talks said Monday they are still trading ideas, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-health-care-subsidies-congress-00671172" target="_blank">Congress is in the dark</a> about whether President Donald Trump will roll out an 11th-hour framework for an extension, which could help provide a needed boost.</p> 
<p>“Right now, it’s not on a fast track,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198817" data-person-id="198817">Markwayne Mullin</a> (R-Okla.) said about the chances for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>Instead, the most likely outcome is that Senate Democrats put up a bill that has little GOP support for a vote, if any, while Republicans offer a competing bill of their own. And even those partisan proposals remained in flux as lawmakers returned to Washington from a weeklong recess.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), who has been a key figure in the bipartisan negotiations over a potential extension, said that while she still believes there is time to craft a compromise proposal before the vote, it “remains to be seen” if people are willing to move that quickly.</p> 
<p>On a separate track, GOP Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> of Idaho and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana are working behind the scenes on a bill meant to serve as the Republican counterproposal to whatever Democrats offer, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss private deliberations. Aside from the unsettled substance of the bill, when it might be unveiled remains in question.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and two other people familiar with internal conference discussions didn’t rule out a vote on a GOP health care plan next week but would not commit to that timing.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see what the Dems want to put up,” Thune said Monday. “There’s obviously something that we could put up as a side-by-side, neither of which would probably get 60 [votes to advance], but I think in the end you would like to see if there’s a path forward on something that could merge.”</p> 
<p>Some Senate Republicans don’t see the point in forcing a symbolic vote on a GOP counterproposal.</p> 
<p>“I don’t want to take a vote just for the heck of it,” said Mullin, who spoke with Trump about health care last week. ”If we’re going to vote, let’s make sure we do something that’s going to be productive.”</p> 
<p>Health care is expected to be the dominant topic at both Senate party lunches Tuesday. Democrats will use the closed-door meeting to talk through their options, which include offering a “clean” extension of the ACA subsidies — which few Republicans support — or an extension paired with GOP-favored eligibility restrictions as an olive branch to conservatives.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are facing their own dilemma — and internal divisions — over which approach to take. Some, like Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> of Maine and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska, have backed an extension of the subsidies, but a chunk of the Senate GOP conference, to say nothing of their counterparts in the House, want to end the subsidies cold turkey.</p> 
<p>Many Republicans, including Cassidy, are focused on alternatives that would structure federal health care subsidies around health savings accounts, an idea that Trump has also endorsed. But lawmakers agree there is virtually no time to develop and implement such a system before the existing subsidies expire, leading some Republicans to favor a temporary extension.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she is “very hopeful” about the bipartisan talks underway but acknowledged the time pressure: “The calendar is not necessarily our friend right now.”</p> 
<p>Nor, for now, is Trump, who appears to be sitting on the sidelines even as some congressional Republicans are begging him to get involved and sketch out a health care plan that could help unite and energize GOP factions in the House and Senate.</p> 
<p>The president appeared <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">poised to roll out a plan</a> late last month that would extend the ACA subsidies with an income cap and other eligibility restrictions. But the White House scuttled that plan amid a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">mountain of GOP backlash</a>.</p> 
<p>“I think without White House leadership, we're not going to have a well received product,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.), who has backed a temporary extension. “If we produce something in the Senate, it won't be well received in the house unless the president works his magic, which he's very capable of doing.”</p> 
<p>Thune said Monday he doesn’t believe the White House is “advocating for advancing anything at the moment,” while making the point that health care talks could continue past next week’s votes. Lawmakers increasingly view Jan. 30 — the next government funding deadline — as the real cutoff for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>“I think there’s, you know, groundwork being laid that could end up in actually something getting done,” he said. “I just don’t know if it can get done by next week. That’d be a pretty heavy lift.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, House Republicans are on a separate track altogether, with party leaders looking to assemble a suite of health care bills from three committees — Ways and Means, Energy and Commerce, and Education and Workforce. Their plan is less about making law, which would require buy-in from Senate Democrats, and more about showing voters that Republicans have plans to address rising health care costs.</p> 
<p>Under pressure from unhappy GOP centrists, House leaders are tentatively planning to put legislation on the floor before the chamber’s scheduled Dec. 18 departure for the holiday recess. But that could change. The Ways and Means and Energy and Commerce panels are holding listening sessions with Republican members this week, indicating their plans remain in development.</p> 
<p>“We want to get it done as soon as we are ready to get it passed,” Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said in a brief interview Monday.</p> 
<p>Some GOP chairs raised questions and made messaging suggestions on health care during a leadership meeting Monday with Scalise, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the private conversation. One of the people added that there’s still “not a lot of direction” from Republican leaders on the topic, and even conservative Republicans are rankled that no firm proposals are being circulated widely inside the conference with just 11 scheduled session days remaining in the year.</p> 
<p>“We’re nowhere on health care,” said one senior House Republican who was granted anonymity to candidly describe the situation.</p> 
<p>Republican leaders are also under pressure from some House GOP centrists who are threatening to use a discharge petition to effectively force a subsidy extension bill to the floor.</p> 
<p>One of those centrists, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> of Pennsylvania, said Monday he has spoken with the White House about a bill he is working on and shopping around to colleagues, which would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635" target="_blank">largely mirror Trump’s unreleased framework</a>.</p> 
<p>“It's one of those things where nobody's going to love it,” Fitzpatrick said. “But hopefully enough people are okay with it.”</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schumer says his NY offices received 'MAGA' bomb threats</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/01/congress/chuck-schumer-maga-bomb-threats-00671737</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-dba0-d51c-a39e-ffa92bbf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 15:51:50 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said Monday his offices in three New York cities received bomb threats via an e-mail titled "MAGA."</p> 
<p>Schumer in a statement said the threats were made against offices in Rochester, Binghamton and Long Island. In addition to the "MAGA" subject line, the emails alleged that the 2020 election was "rigged," the top Senate Democrat said.</p> 
<p>"Everyone is safe, and I am grateful for their quick and professional response to ensure these offices remain safe and secure for all New Yorkers," Schumer said, reporting "full security sweeps" from local and federal law enforcement.</p> 
<p>“As I have said many times, these kinds of violent threats have absolutely no place in our political system. No one—no public servant, no staff member, no constituent, no citizen—should ever be targeted for simply doing their job," he added.</p> 
<p>A U.S. Capitol Police spokesperson declined to comment, saying the department "cannot discuss member security.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Health deal hinges on Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/01/congress/health-care-obamacare-deal-trump-fitzpatrick-00671204</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-d7db-d51c-a39e-ffdb43c30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is back. Welcome to the December of Hellth.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers now have a mere 30 days to address expiring Obamacare tax credits and prevent health insurance hikes for millions of Americans. Republicans and Democrats agree success hangs on one question: Will President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-health-care-subsidies-congress-00671172" target="_blank">figure out what he wants</a>?</p> 
<p>Interpreting Trump’s intentions has gotten tougher since lawmakers left Washington. Early in the break, Trump appeared to be on the brink of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">announcing a framework</a> to extend the Affordable Care Act subsidies with new eligibility restrictions, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">only to pull back</a> after GOP criticism. He then <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/trump-obamacare-subsidy-extension-aca-00669491" target="_blank">said he doesn’t want</a> to extend the subsidies but understands it might be necessary.</p> 
<p>Capitol Hill factions are trying to figure out what Trump wants and how to entice him to their side.</p> 
<p>“The president has got to sign whatever we do, otherwise it’s a legislative exercise,” says Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick, the Pennsylvania Republican who is drafting what he describes as a bipartisan proposal that would largely align with last week’s leaked White House framework.</p> 
<p><b>The timeline as we know it — </b>Though the ACA tax credits expire at month’s end, some lawmakers are looking at Jan. 30, the next shutdown deadline, as the real cutoff for a health care deal.</p> 
<p>The Senate will vote as soon as Dec. 9 on an undefined health care proposal, the fulfillment of the bipartisan deal to reopen the government.</p> 
<p><b>What’s in the works — </b>Fitzpatrick and other centrists are looking to build bipartisan support for an extension of the subsidies with new income restrictions and other safeguards. Their efforts have loose backing from the Republican Main Street Caucus, whose chair Rep. Mike Flood (Neb.) endorsed the contours of the leaked White House health plan.</p> 
<p>A coalition of House and Senate Republicans that includes key committee chairs are working behind the scenes on a range of possible proposals, but there’s no guarantee the GOP will fall in line or the lawmakers will produce a bill this year.</p> 
<p>Senate Finance Chair Mike Crapo (R-Idaho) says he is “working to try to find a pathway to get some bipartisan solution” — not a budget reconciliation bill.</p> 
<p>As a fail-safe, centrist House Republicans are prepared to launch a discharge petition to force a floor vote on a subsidy extension. But they’re also trying to give space to the Senate to see if a bipartisan deal can be reached.</p> 
<p>Democrats have yet to reach a consensus.</p> 
<p>A group of Democrats including Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (N.H.) and Rep. Tom Suozzi (N.Y.) has been in close contact with Republicans including Fitzpatrick and Sen. Lisa Murkowski (Alaska) about what could get bipartisan support. But others, including independent Sen. Bernie Sanders of Vermont, want Democrats to embrace a sweeping health care plan that could be a rallying cry for the midterms but has no chance of winning GOP votes.</p> 
<p>There’s widespread skepticism that Republicans will agree to any plan that isn’t fully endorsed by Trump. A significant swath of GOP lawmakers will simply never vote to extend anything related to Obamacare, according to three GOP aides granted anonymity to discuss internal dynamics.</p> 
<p>“That’s the trouble today,” says Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.). “You can have good-faith negotiations with Republicans, but it just doesn’t matter until Donald Trump weighs in.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— What’s next for appropriations: </b>House GOP appropriators aren’t yet ready to advance the two biggest outstanding funding bills — Defense and Labor-HHS-Education — and are instead rooting for a cross-chamber compromise on several smaller funding measures, with sights on enactment by month’s end.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans are also looking for a smaller group of bills that could get signed into law as they continue to pursue a separate minibus that would pair defense funding with Labor-HHS-Education and other bills, according to two aides granted anonymity to disclose internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>Any appropriations bills finalized in the next three weeks would be ripe for hitching to a year-end agreement on health insurance subsidies, should one materialize.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA deal incoming:</b> Lawmakers plan to release the final text of a compromise version of the National Defense Authorization Act this week and tee up a House floor vote as soon as next week, though House and Senate leaders still need to sign off on the final product.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Record-setting personnel issues are marring Trump’s second term</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-nominations-withdrawals-record-00669890</link>
      <description>The president has nearly doubled Joe Biden’s mark for nominees withdrawn from the Senate in the first year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c161-d49b-af9f-f5e52ba40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/09/b2/b66eac514788ac0a8c7d4937bf8f/unlimiteduse-11-10-2025-wh-009.JPG">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Craig Hudson for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Some GOP insiders trace the record pace of nominee withdrawals to the influence of Sergio Gor, left, the former White House personnel chief.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/09/b2/b66eac514788ac0a8c7d4937bf8f/unlimiteduse-11-10-2025-wh-009.JPG" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Alex Gangitano and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Alex Gangitano and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On the surface, President Donald Trump’s second-term personnel operation has been a smoothly running machine. The Senate has confirmed more than 300 civilian nominees since January, even changing the chamber’s rules to move them faster.</p> 
<p>But there are clear signs of breakdowns behind the scenes. Trump has withdrawn a record number of nominees for a president’s first year in office as he faces a combination of GOP pushback against some picks, vetting issues, White House infighting and, in some cases, the president’s own mercurial views.</p> 
<p>Trump has withdrawn 57 nominations, <a href="https://www.congress.gov/quick-search/nominations?wordsPhrases=&amp;wordVariants=on&amp;congressGroups%5B0%5D=0&amp;congresses%5B0%5D=119&amp;nomCivil=on&amp;nomOther=on&amp;pnNumbers=&amp;nomineeNames=&amp;positions=&amp;organizations=&amp;stateTerritories%5B0%5D=any&amp;nominationAction=97&amp;dates=datesReceivedInSenate&amp;dateOperator=after&amp;startDate=01%2F19%2F2025&amp;endDate=&amp;dateIsOption=yesterday" target="_blank">according to Senate data</a> — roughly double the 22 nominations he withdrew during the first year of his first administration and the 29 his immediate predecessor, Joe Biden, withdrew during his first year.</p> 
<p>The pace of withdrawals, the highest since at least the Ronald Reagan presidency, has flown below the radar in the day-to-day churn on Capitol Hill, with many Republican senators expressing surprise at the data in interviews. But they also acknowledged the obvious: In some instances, the White House just isn’t making sure Trump’s nominees can get the votes.</p> 
<p>“It would appear that some nominees haven’t been vetted, and … somebody says, ‘Go with them anyways,’” Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Perhaps the most vivid example was the monthslong intraparty drama over Paul Ingrassia’s nomination to lead the Office of Special Counsel.</p> 
<p>After POLITICO reported he made racist comments in a group chat, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/trump-pulls-ingrassia-nomination-racist-texts-00617041" target="_blank">Ingrassia withdrew</a> despite telling senators he had “no recollection of these alleged chat leaks, and do not concede their authenticity.” But Senate Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/23/how-senate-republican-finally-said-no-to-ingrassia-00619273" target="_blank">had already privately telegraphed</a> to the Trump administration for months that his nomination was in serious peril.</p> 
<p>Asked about the withdrawals, a person close to the White House granted anonymity to speak candidly about internal dynamics pointed to Ingrassia as a key example.</p> 
<p>“Would I say some vetting has been questionable? One thousand percent,” the person said, adding of Ingrassia: “That was a vetting nightmare that was only allowed to happen based on certain relationships and acquaintances with people that are making the decisions.”</p> 
<p>Trump faced similar pushback from Republican senators over Ed Martin’s nomination to be the U.S. attorney in Washington. Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), a key vote on the Judiciary Committee, essentially killed Martin’s nomination after he told the White House that he couldn’t support him over his past defense of accused Capitol rioters. But even before that, Martin <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/ed-martin-senate-confirmation-woes-00322346" target="_blank">was on thin ice</a> with GOP senators.</p> 
<p>A Senate aide who was granted anonymity to speak frankly about White House personnel issues said that in several cases the nominees were being withdrawn not because of issues with GOP senators but intra-administration snags. A White House official, granted anonymity because they were not authorized to speak publicly about the withdrawals, acknowledged the presidential personnel office had recently strengthened its background checks for nominees.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/97/a2/f060e99048ea8979d006c39400bd/trump-washington-prosecutor-23335.jpg" alt="Ed Martin was pulled after it became clear his U.S. attorney nomination would fail in the Senate Judiciary Committee." data-portal-copyright="Amanda Andrade-Rhoades/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Ed Martin was pulled after it became clear his U.S. attorney nomination would fail in the Senate Judiciary Committee."/><p>The person close to the White House said that “not all of these nominations were done so in good faith” under Sergio Gor, who served as the director of the White House Presidential Personnel Office until his confirmation as ambassador to India. The person suggested Gor’s successor as personnel chief, longtime Trump loyalist Dan Scavino, would oversee fewer withdrawals.</p> 
<p>“I think Dan is a little bit wiser and less inclined to give out jobs like candy to people who haven’t earned them or would not pass vetting,” the person added.</p> 
<p>Gor and the U.S. Embassy in India did not return messages seeking comment. The White House official said the 57 withdrawals, which include instances where the same nominee was put forward for multiple positions, were done “for a variety of reasons — clerical changes, new positions or adding new responsibilities to their original role.”</p> 
<p>Frank Bisignano’s nomination for Social Security commissioner, for example, was withdrawn and immediately resubmitted to the Senate in January.</p> 
<p>The official added that Trump is nominating new individuals at a “record pace” and noted he has gotten more nominees confirmed at this point than he did during his first term or than Biden did by this point.</p> 
<p>Republicans were already confirming Trump nominees at a faster clip than in his first administration. But in September they enacted a party-line rules change, allowing most nominees to now be confirmed in groups of unlimited size. One <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/senate-resolution/377/text" target="_blank">group of 108</a> was confirmed in September; a <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/senate-resolution/412/text" target="_blank">group of 48 more</a> followed in October.</p> 
<p>Tillis, who described himself as surprised by the total number of nominees withdrawn, pointed to Trump’s fast pace in making nominations as one possible reason for the sloppy vetting.</p> 
<p>“Obviously, when you move more quickly and you’ve got new folks in play, then you are going to run into people who have lifestyle issues,” Tillis said, adding that he believes only “outliers” have run into issues in the Senate.</p> 
<p>Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.), who like Tillis expressed surprise at the number of nominees withdrawn, added that “part of our responsibility is advise and consent.”</p> 
<p>“And sometimes the advice is to maybe reconsider something,” Rounds said. “You don't have to make a big deal out of it, but you can share that with the administration. And sometimes they take a second look at the nominee, and they say, ‘You know, yeah, you're right.’”</p> 
<p>Asked about the withdrawals, White House spokesperson Liz Huston said in a statement that Trump is “nominating the most talented patriots to successfully carry out his America First agenda.”</p> 
<p>“Under President Trump’s leadership, these appointees are delivering on his core campaign promises in record time from securing the border, ending Joe Biden’s inflation crisis, unleashing American energy, and restoring common sense policies,” she added.</p> 
<p>While Martin and Ingrassia are two high-profile examples of nominees running aground in the Senate, there have been other quieter examples — including Joel Rayburn, who had been nominated to be an assistant secretary of State but <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/27/us/politics/trump-middle-east-state-department-nominee-rayburn.html" target="_blank">faced fierce public opposition</a> from Sen. Rand Paul (R-Ky.).<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ec/57/c909c49844a598c4338397a8e547/prosecutor-firings-93313.jpg" alt="Activist Laura Loomer took credit for Trump's recent backtrack on his pick for IRS chief counsel." data-portal-copyright="Chris Szagola/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Activist Laura Loomer took credit for Trump's recent backtrack on his pick for IRS chief counsel."/><p>Trump has also withdrawn nominees for his own reasons. He abruptly withdrew Rep. Elise Stefanik’s nomination to be the U.S. ambassador to the United Nations earlier this year amid concerns about how the New York Republican’s departure would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/13/elise-stefanik-united-nations-delay-00204172" target="_blank">trim the House majority</a>. He later pulled Jared Isaacman's nomination to lead NASA over his "prior associations," <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/trump-nominates-isaacman-nasa-administrator-00636497" target="_blank">only to renominate him</a> five months later.</p> 
<p>Late last month, he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-pulls-nominee-for-top-irs-post-who-drew-conservative-activists-ire-00652355" target="_blank">withdrew Donald Korb’s nomination</a> as top IRS lawyer after a pressure campaign led by right-wing activist Laura Loomer. She publicly boasted that Korb had been “Loomered” after Trump’s announcement.</p> 
<p>Others have been snagged by the blue-slip precedent, which allows home-state senators to effectively block district court and U.S. attorney nominees. For instance, Democratic Sens. Cory Booker and Andy Kim refused to return a blue slip for Alina Habba, who was nominated to be U.S. attorney for New Jersey. Trump withdrew her nomination and attempted to place her in the role as an acting U.S. attorney, which sparked a legal battle.</p> 
<p>Trump is so far standing by other nominees subject to blue-slip objections, and he is pressuring Senate Judiciary Committee Chair Chuck Grassley to get rid of the practice altogether. Republicans did away with it for appeals court judicial nominees during Trump’s first term, but Grassley and many other GOP senators remain opposed to a wholesale elimination.</p> 
<p>Trump told Senate Republicans last month that he ousted one official after finding out that he had been backed by Virginia’s Democratic senators. Trump recently withdrew nominations for Todd Gilbert, whom he had nominated to be U.S. attorney for the Western District of Virginia, and Erik Siebert, who had been nominated to be U.S. attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia.</p> 
<p>“I had one Republican who got two great letters, but it turned out that he was a RINO,” Trump said during a White House breakfast with senators. “When I saw that the two senators from Virginia gave him glowing remarks … I said let me see this, I read the most beautiful letters I’ve ever seen. I called him up; I said, ‘Sorry, you’re fired — get the hell out of here.’”</p> 
<p><i>Dasha Burns contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Time is not our friend’: Health care scramble begins amid mixed signals from Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/01/trump-health-care-subsidies-congress-00671172</link>
      <description>The president injected more uncertainty last week, saying he doesn’t want to extend key insurance subsidies but understands it might be necessary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-d704-d51c-a39e-ff0db51a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8a/f5/3990712f4fe78084f263da013241/house-of-representatives-19187.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) said President Donald Trump has to endorse any health plan Congress pursues, "otherwise it’s a legislative exercise."</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8a/f5/3990712f4fe78084f263da013241/house-of-representatives-19187.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress returns to session Monday and kicks off a December sprint to address expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies and prevent health insurance premium hikes for millions of Americans.</p> 
<p>Members of both parties acknowledge success hangs on one question: Will President Donald Trump ever figure out what he wants?</p> 
<p>Since lawmakers left town 10 days ago, the picture has only grown foggier. Early in their holiday break, Trump appeared to be on the precipice of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">announcing a framework</a> to temporarily extend the Obamacare subsidies with new eligibility restrictions, only to pull back after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">mountain of internal GOP criticism</a>.</p> 
<p>In his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/trump-obamacare-subsidy-extension-aca-00669491" target="_blank">only comments on the matter</a>, Trump injected more uncertainty last week, saying he doesn’t want to extend the subsidies but understands it might be necessary.</p> 
<p>The mixed signals have left the various factions on Capitol Hill trying to figure out where Trump will ultimately come down — and how to entice the president to back their side in a thorny policy fight that could have major political consequences in next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>“The president has got to sign whatever we do, otherwise it’s a legislative exercise,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.), who is drafting what he describes as a bipartisan proposal that would largely align with the leaked White House framework.</p> 
<p>But Fitzpatrick and other lawmakers are quickly running out of time to pin Trump down. The Senate will vote next week, as soon as Dec. 9, on a health care proposal. It’s unclear what will be in the bill, but it’s the fulfillment of a promise Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> made to Democrats as part of a deal to end the 43-day government shutdown.</p> 
<p>“The question is, how quickly can something come together?” Thune said before leaving Washington for Thanksgiving.</p> 
<p>Or as Fitzpatrick put it: “Time is not our friend.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and other centrists are looking to build bipartisan support for an extension of the subsidies, a priority for Democrats, with new income restrictions and other safeguards, which are a priority for Republicans. Their efforts have loose backing from the Republican Main Street Caucus, whose chair, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196030" data-person-id="196030">Mike Flood</a> of Nebraska, quickly endorsed the contours of the leaked White House framework last week.</p> 
<p>But others in the GOP want to pursue a more radical overhaul of Obamacare, with Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> of Florida pitching the president on plans centered around individual spending accounts. Scott even termed his vision as “Trump Health Freedom Accounts.”</p> 
<p>Trump has kept Congress in limbo as lawmakers try to figure out what he will support. Republicans spent much of November thinking the president was turning away from extending the tax credits, only to be blindsided by news that the White House framework would do just that.</p> 
<p>Most House and Senate Republicans, including senior members of leadership, learned details of the tentative White House proposal — and how quickly it could be rolled out — from media reports, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">including POLITICO’s</a>. Their objections prompted the White House to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">scuttle the rollout</a>.</p> 
<p>A House Republican granted anonymity to discuss internal conference thinking acknowledged that it would have been “wiser” if the Trump administration had consulted directly with Hill GOP leaders before word of the framework leaked out.</p> 
<p>The GOP lawmaker added that Trump “cannot please everyone” with any health plan.</p> 
<p>“Most took it as a good sign that the [White House] initially accepted a modified extension,” the lawmaker said. “Yes, a subset complained, but I think they’re in the minority.”</p> 
<p>Getting an extension of the subsidies through the House and Senate, not to mention Trump, will require navigating a political obstacle course.</p> 
<p>For one, the framework was silent on new abortion restrictions, which are a key demand for many Republicans and a deal-break for many Democrats.</p> 
<p>“We’re not going to allow public funds to be used for funding abortion,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/221844" data-person-id="221844">Mike Rounds</a> (R-S.D.) told reporters before Thanksgiving.</p> 
<p>While much of the GOP backlash to Trump’s unreleased framework was about how lawmakers found out about it, there’s a significant swath of Republicans who will simply never vote to extend anything related to Obamacare, according to three GOP aides granted anonymity to discuss internal dynamics.</p> 
<p>In addition to the Scott and Cassidy plans, a coalition of House and Senate Republicans that includes key committee chairs are working behind the scenes on a range of possible health care proposals, but there’s no guarantee the GOP will fall in line behind the plans or whether the lawmakers will even produce a bill this year.</p> 
<p>As a fail-safe, House GOP centrists are preparing to launch a discharge petition to force a floor vote on a subsidy extension. But they are also trying to give space to the Senate to see if a bipartisan deal can be reached, according to two Republicans granted anonymity to discuss the talks.</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers are already looking at Jan. 30, the next government funding deadline, as the real cutoff for a health care deal, even though the credits would have expired by then. And some hard-liners want GOP leaders to embrace a party-line approach <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">amid widespread skepticism</a> among their colleagues that’s even doable.</p> 
<p>Senate Finance Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> (R-Idaho), whose committee shares oversight of the ACA, said he is “working to try to find a pathway to get some bipartisan solution” — not a partisan, filibuster-skirting bill Republicans could pursue under the budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>“There are a lot of things going on,” he said. Crapo added that even if the promised Senate vote fails, “We will need to be continuing to work … with our colleagues on both sides of the aisle to try to find some broader health care solutions.”</p> 
<p>Democrats were initially buoyed by news that Trump was preparing to endorse an extension of the subsidies, despite the eligibility restrictions, believing that it was a good sign that he was even thinking about it. But that optimism faded after witnessing the Republican backlash.</p> 
<p>They have their own internal divisions over what their own strategy should be as the clock ticks. Senate Democrats, as part of the agreement with Thune, will get to decide what proposal they vote on. But they haven’t yet come to consensus and are expected to use a Tuesday caucus lunch to discuss their options.</p> 
<p>A group of Democrats, including Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> of New Hampshire and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259491" data-person-id="259491">Tom Suozzi</a> of New York, has been in close contact with Republican lawmakers including Fitzpatrick and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska about what could get bipartisan support. But others, such as independent Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51605" data-person-id="51605">Bernie Sanders</a> of Vermont, want Democrats to instead embrace a sweeping health care plan that would have no chance of winning GOP votes but would give them a rallying point heading into the midterm elections.</p> 
<p>That divide has haunted congressional Democrats since January as they’ve repeatedly struggled to unify at key moments. There’s also widespread skepticism that Republicans will ever agree to any health care plan that isn’t fully endorsed by Trump.</p> 
<p>“That’s the trouble today: You can have good-faith negotiations with Republicans, but it just doesn’t matter until Donald Trump weighs in,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a> (D-Conn.). “The pollsters have obviously told them that they are going to get their clocks cleaned if they don’t fix the health care mess they created. They may hate the ACA and Barack Obama so much they are willing to lose an election.”</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forget Mamdani. New York’s real political shift happened everywhere else.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/28/new-york-upstate-blue-wave-mamdani-00668749</link>
      <description>Democrats flipped over 50 county legislative seats across the state. Republicans flipped one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bcd5-d49b-af9f-bcf507bd0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 09:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/03/f6/70eca5c8449e90fed1da5dc39a54/unlimiteduse-electionday-ny-11-04-2025-063.JPG">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Bing Guan for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A voter deposits their ballot into a ballot counting machine at a polling site inside P.S. 20 in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York, on Electio Day, Nov. 4, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/03/f6/70eca5c8449e90fed1da5dc39a54/unlimiteduse-electionday-ny-11-04-2025-063.JPG" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Bill Mahoney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Bill Mahoney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Zohran Mamdani’s decisive win in New York City — along with key victories in New Jersey and Virginia — suggested Democrats are headed into the midterms from a position of strength. But they didn’t capture how deep that strength ran.</p> 
<p>Across suburbs, rural counties and small towns in New York, Democrats posted electoral gains that rival — and in many cases surpass — the party’s 2017 “Blue Wave.” In a state with enough competitive House races to decide control of the chamber, the outcome amounts to a wakeup call for already-wary Republicans.</p> 
<p>New York Democrats once viewed the 2017 elections as among their best ever. The Blue Wave that year was driven by purple suburbs making a hard shift left. This year in New York, that tilt was felt even more widely — with Democrats in every corner of the state pointing to economic uncertainty exacerbated by President Donald Trump’s policies as voters’ top concern.</p> 
<p>“It was about peoples’ anxiety,” said Leslie Berliant, who ousted a Republican incumbent to win a seat in the Otsego County Legislature. “It definitely was a feeling that we don’t feel protected by what’s happening in the federal government, and we need to make sure we have people in place at the local level who care about our needs. Democrats ran on that, and I think it worked.”</p> 
<p>Much of the early narrative from this fall’s elections has cast Democrats’ gains as occurring mostly in places where they often win. An examination of every race on the ballot in New York shows the shift was far more widespread, with Democrats having their best-ever performances in numerous deep red towns and rural areas.</p> 
<p>There’s still plenty of time for conditions to change before the 2026 midterms. But a year out, this year’s contests offered very little solace for Republicans as they prep for seven battleground congressional races in New York and a gubernatorial election in which they hope to build on the rightward momentum of the 2022 and 2024 elections.</p> 
<p>A POLITICO review of results in 268 county, town and village executive branch races found an average 10 point increase in the Democratic margin.</p> 
<p>Democrats made gains in at least 18 different county legislative bodies in November, flipping over 50 seats across the Empire State. They gained five seats in Oswego County, which Trump won by 27 points in 2024. They picked up five in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history. And they flipped five in Onondaga and gained their first majority there since the 1970s.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/2e/42/1c9870ba4f8a91b982bf30d4b66a/ap9724584833457619.jpg" alt="Shown above, New Paltz in Ulster County. Democrats picked up five seats in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history" data-portal-copyright=" Historic Hotels of America and Mohonk Mountain House via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Shown above, New Paltz in Ulster County. Democrats picked up five seats in Ulster by making inroads in towns that have been Republican for generations, winning their largest majority in county history"/><p>For Republicans, the outcome painted a bleak picture: GOP candidates flipped one county legislative seat in the entire state.</p> 
<p>Democrats who won these local contests shared similar stories about what they saw on the ground. Trump voters didn’t necessarily throw their MAGA hats into bonfires. But economic anxiety persists in every corner of the state. And Republican voters feeling the pinch — whether over federal cuts, tariffs, or inflation — are now at least willing to hear a pitch from Democrats.</p> 
<p>In the town of Erwin, just north of the Pennsylvania border, Democrat Debbie Shannon ousted Republican Steuben County Legislator James Kuhl, the son of a former congressman.</p> 
<p>“I knocked on everyone’s door, and the economy is the big hot button issue,” Shannon said. “Especially for Republicans who said Trump ran on ‘I’m going to lower the price of eggs,’ and that isn’t happening. I think they’re breaking with the administration.”</p> 
<p>This November was only the second time since 1989 that Democrats won mayoral races in each of the state’s five largest cities. Sharon Owens was the first Democrat elected Syracuse’s mayor in 12 years, Sean Ryan received the most votes in a contested Buffalo race since 1981, and Mamdani received more votes than any Democratic nominee in New York City since at least 1965.</p> 
<p>Democratic performance in places that were once untouchable Republican strongholds is perhaps more notable when looking ahead to next year. Consider, for example, the Rochester suburbs: Penfield elected a Democratic supervisor for the first time in four decades, Greece for the first time in 120 years, and Perinton for the first time <a href="https://www.democratandchronicle.com/story/news/politics/elections/2025/11/05/monroe-county-ny-election-takeaways-from-2025/87098791007/" target="_blank">since the Civil War</a>.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/76/a4/2a3681d04783be8a1a4780c9a816/2024-election-61546.jpg" alt="Voters cast their ballots at the Susan B. Anthony Museum & House in Rochester in 2024." data-portal-copyright="Lauren Petracca/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Voters cast their ballots at the Susan B. Anthony Museum & House in Rochester in 2024."/><p>Democrats also flipped mayoral or supervisor offices in places like Tonawanda, Oneonta, Monroe, Rensselaer, Johnson City and Riverhead.</p> 
<p>All told, there were 118 municipal executive races outside of New York City this year that were contested in either 2021 or 2023. The number of ballots cast for Democrats grew from 1.3 million to 1.6 million, a 22 percent increase. The number for Republicans grew 1 percent to 1.6 million.</p> 
<p>That means that while the typical upstate or Long Island Democrat lost by 10 points in the last go-around, they received 50 percent of the vote this year.</p> 
<p>Even in places where Republicans had good nights, there’s little evidence of a broader rightward shift. Republicans made gains in Saratoga Springs, but not as many as Democrats made in the larger, neighboring town of Clifton Park. Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman won big in his reelection campaign. But Democrats improved on their performance in 17 of the other 21 executive offices on the ballot on Long Island. And in the other major suburban county, Westchester’s Ken Jenkins had the best performance by a Democratic county executive candidate in two decades.</p> 
<p>The Democratic gains were thus much broader than those in 2017. The following year, New York Democrats flipped three congressional seats, and the number of people voting for Andrew Cuomo in the gubernatorial contest grew 76 percent in 2018 compared with 2014.</p> 
<p>All of that is promising to Democrats like Gov. Kathy Hochul who are on the ballot in 2026. The Republican path to a statewide victory involves running up the numbers in red parts of the state, doing well in suburban towns and minimizing the Democratic margin in New York City. All three of those need to happen in 2026 for a GOP win to be plausible in statewide contests — and this November, none of them did.</p> 
<p>But there were also hints of an anti-establishment trend mixed in with the leftward shift — and certainly more than a glimmer of that in New York City. That trend makes forecasting Hochul’s fate a little less clear come next June or November.</p> 
<p>Not everybody who won said they did so by running on a Democratic platform. Candidates in the rural North Country, for example, attempted to outdo each other in criticizing Hochul’s handling of <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2025/02/25/kathy-hochul-prison-crisis-corrections-officers-00206033" target="_blank">a prison strike</a> earlier this year.</p> 
<p>Voters are looking “for leadership that kind of ignores traditional party stances,” said Lebanon Supervisor-elect Adam Carvell, who noted he wasn’t focused on purely partisan issues before receiving 63 percent of the vote as a Democrat in a town where Trump received 60 percent last year. The electorate, he said, wasn’t just bothered by the White House’s actions, but policies <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/05/democratic-lawmaker-readies-clean-car-delay-proposal-00336271" target="_blank">supported by</a> the sitting Democratic governor, such as an electric vehicle mandate.</p> 
<p>“The municipal electrical vehicle mandate that was coming down, it’s a Hochul thing,” said Carvell. “The boots-on-the-ground take on that here is that’s unworkable … The idea of introducing very expensive, hard to maintain [electric snow plows] scared a lot of people.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/96/8b/b891625e4ff8be183e7d56d48fd9/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2246393039" alt="New York Gov. Kathy Hochul speaks at a ribbon-cutting ceremony at the National Urban League's new headquarters in Harlem on Nov. 12, 2025, where she was joined by New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani." data-portal-copyright="Spencer Platt/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="New York Gov. Kathy Hochul speaks at a ribbon-cutting ceremony at the National Urban League's new headquarters in Harlem on Nov. 12, 2025, where she was joined by New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani."/><p>Yet even the candidates who eschewed strict partisanship repeatedly highlighted the federal government and its role in the economy as the top concern on voters’ minds.</p> 
<p>Don Dabiew, who won a seat in Franklin County’s Legislature, pointed to a hit to Canadian tourism.</p> 
<p>“Almost all the small towns around are seeing an impact of that because people aren’t coming across anymore,” Dabew said. “There’s some people that are upset with our country as a whole, and they don’t want to support us anymore.”</p> 
<p>In Canandaigua, mayor-elect Thomas Lyon highlighted federal cuts.</p> 
<p>“DOGE was eliminating jobs left and right,” he said. “The national veterans’ suicide hotline is located here in Canandaigua at our VA, and you had people losing their jobs, not being able to provide support to our veterans.”</p> 
<p>Even in local elections where partisanship wasn’t rampant, Democrats said the current frustrations about the country as a whole are opening doors that hadn’t been open before.</p> 
<p>“We listened and said, ‘We’re not talking about federal politics here; we’re talking about right here, right now, our town,’” said Lisa Moore, who won the South Bristol supervisor’s race.</p> 
<p>“A lot of people were just so sick and tired of the divisiveness at the federal level, and the sort of miserableness, that they were happy to not demonize Democrats, as Democrats have been demonized in our town in the past.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-26T21:55:06-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>White House presses Congress for drone powers ahead of World Cup, Olympics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/white-house-asks-congress-for-power-to-take-down-drones-00670564</link>
      <description>The administration is facing resistance from GOP leadership of the Senate Commerce Committee.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c2fc-d739-a3ba-defcd0910001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 20:46:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ad/c8afee09486f9e9a81622a73d0d8/white-house-80173.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump walks on the South Lawn of the White House after disembarking from Marine One Nov. 2, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ad/c8afee09486f9e9a81622a73d0d8/white-house-80173.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House is pressing lawmakers to give the administration more power to take down aerial drones in domestic airspace in advance of the U.S. hosting the 2026 World Cup and 2028 Olympic games, according to three people involved in ongoing negotiations.</p> 
<p>The push to attach the measure to a must-pass defense policy bill in the coming weeks is facing resistance on Capitol Hill, including from the Senate Commerce Committee led by Sen. Ted Cruz, amid concerns the proposal constitutes federal overreach. The Commerce panel has jurisdiction over aviation affairs.</p> 
<p>Draft <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-c28a-df0f-abfa-e3eabde50000" target="_blank"><u>legislation floated by the White House</u></a> and obtained by POLITICO would give agencies including the Departments of Homeland Security and Justice new authority to take counter-drone measures for “large scale public gatherings or events, critical infrastructure or correctional facilities.” The proposal would also broaden “counter-drone authority” for state and local law enforcement.</p> 
<p>Under current law, federal agencies are empowered to intervene against drone threats only when specific, high-risk facilities, including government operations and power plants, are deemed to be at risk.</p> 
<p>The push comes as the leaders of the House and Senate Armed Services Committees are trying to finalize the text of the defense bill by early next week. Spokespeople for the Republican chairs and top Democrats on the committees did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>The White House request of Congress is the administration’s latest move to ramp up security ahead of the World Cup and Olympic games. The administration announced earlier this month it was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/13/drone-defenses-world-cup-00606174" target="_blank"><u>launching a $500 million program</u></a> to help state and local governments develop anti-drone strategies ahead of the events as well as any celebrations that might take place around the 250th anniversary of the signing of the Declaration of Independence.</p> 
<p>“This is an important issue we must address as we prepare for global events such as the World Cup and the Olympics, and we need to ensure proper authorities are in place to protect the American people,” said a House GOP leadership aide granted anonymity to discuss the negotiations.</p> 
<p>A White House official granted anonymity to describe ongoing deliberations said the White House Office of Legislative Affairs has been working on legislative language and circulating related proposals among congressional offices since September. The administration has been working closely with Speaker Mike Johnson’s office on the legislative draft and has also engaged with Senate Majority Leader John Thune’s office, according to the official.</p> 
<p>“It’s something that the admin feels is extremely important given particularly all of the events of the next year,” the White House official said. “Having a strong strong event infrastructure and drone counter-measures is very important.”</p> 
<p>It’s unclear if Congress will adopt the plan. A person granted anonymity to discuss private negotiations said Senate Commerce views the draft provision as an “extremely problematic” power grab that would give federal security officials too much leeway in determining how best to “protect the public."</p> 
<p>Phoebe Keller, a spokesperson for Cruz on the Commerce Committee, said in a statement, “We are happy to work with the administration on this proposal and any suggestion to the contrary is simply untrue."</p> 
<p>Sen. Eric Schmitt, a Missouri Republican on Senate Commerce, also supports tougher counter-drone legislation. Kansas City, Mo., is scheduled to host six World Cup matches next year.</p> 
<p>“Unauthorized drones pose a clear risk to Americans and our homeland, and it’s time Congress acts and shows more urgency,” Schmitt spokesperson Rachel Dumke said in a statement. “Senator Schmitt looks forward to continuing to work with his colleagues to find a path forward.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Trump targeting these Democrats could backfire</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/democrats-trump-sedition-backfire-00670552</link>
      <description>The administration’s attacks have elevated the six moderate lawmakers who cut an anti-Trump video urging troops to disobey illegal orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-c255-d49b-af9f-f6f549780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 18:03:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d8/77/689cf1054421aafa8a8228245780/main-wu-brakkton-demssedition.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Claudine Hellmuth/POLITICO (source images via AP)</media:credit>
        <media:title>From left to right: Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), Rep. Chris Deluzio (D-Pa.), Rep. Chrissy Houlahan (D-Pa.), Sen. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.), Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) and Rep. Maggie Goodlander (D-N.H.)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d8/77/689cf1054421aafa8a8228245780/main-wu-brakkton-demssedition.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump is going to war with Democrats over the military. It could backfire on him.</p> 
<p>The president’s attacks on six Democrats who recorded a video encouraging military members to buck unlawful orders are elevating members of a faction that just delivered big off-year wins for their party. Most hail from swing states or districts, identify as centrists and are leveraging their national security backgrounds to argue that Democrats can retake the patriotic lane.</p> 
<p>Trump is also boosting some potential 2028 presidential hopefuls, Arizona Sen. Mark Kelly and Michigan Sen. Elissa Slotkin, while further undercutting the GOP’s attempts to make New York progressives like Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani and Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez the face of the Democratic Party.</p> 
<p>“Pete Hegseth and Donald Trump are providing Mark Kelly with the kind of visibility that almost no amount of money could buy,” said Barrett Marson, an Arizona-based Republican strategist, referring to the Defense secretary who ordered an investigation of Kelly. “Every 2028 contender wishes they could be attacked like this by the Trump administration.”</p> 
<p>Since Trump accused the six of “sedition” and even suggested they could be executed, they’ve racked up millions of views on social media, done the cable news circuit and blasted out fundraising appeals highlighting the attacks.</p> 
<p>It’s heightened the stature of even those who have already been the subject of speculation about their 2028 aspirations. Kelly, who was on the short list to be Vice President Kamala Harris’ running mate last year, has already <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/west-wing-playbook-remaking-government/2025/07/23/reviews-are-in-on-the-first-2028-dem-hopefuls-00471732" target="_blank">visited a raft of early primary</a> and general-election battleground states this year. But only after Trump’s attack was he invited on “Jimmy Kimmel Live!” this week.</p> 
<p>In recent months, Slotkin has been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/24/slotkin-has-a-war-plan-to-beat-trump-dont-be-weak-and-woke-00308176" target="_blank">testing what she calls a “war plan”</a> to “contain and defeat Donald Trump” in speeches outside of her state, meeting with <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook/2025/11/14/slotkin-finds-dems-at-a-crossroads-00651647" target="_blank">low-propensity voters</a> and theorizing about what she calls “Project 2029.” Now she’s brought those themes to a series of interviews and public appearances over the past week.</p> 
<p>As Democrats debate how far to lean into themes of patriotism more often claimed by conservatives, a group of lawmakers organized by Slotkin released a <a href="https://x.com/ElissaSlotkin/status/1978930764692455430?s=20" target="_blank">video with anti-authoritarian themes</a> ahead of the “No Kings” protests last month. A <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2558895077819811" target="_blank">follow-up video last week</a> called on troops not to obey unlawful orders, prompting Trump’s explosion.</p> 
<p>The president posted on social media they were committing “SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL” by suggesting military members ignore their chain of command and shared a post calling for traitors to be hanged. The White House later denied Trump was threatening the lawmakers with death. Since then, the Pentagon has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894?" target="_blank">opened an investigation</a> into Kelly, who is a retired Navy captain, and the six lawmakers claim the FBI <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/democrats-fbi-trump-00668584" target="_blank">has made inquiries</a> through congressional authorities.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/9c/cc/3f39da1f4b4a8b675b81bf61bdc9/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2162570114" alt="Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), another Democrat with a military background, said " data-portal-copyright="Samuel Corum/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), another Democrat with a military background, said "/><p>Democrats, particularly those with military backgrounds, have leapt to their colleagues’ defense, echoing their message about following the law and accusing Trump of weaponizing the government against his political opponents.</p> 
<p>“Trump knows that we’re a threat” to Republicans’ grip on Washington, said Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.), a military veteran whose Serve America PAC supports several of the Democrats in the video. “These are great leaders who can take the fight to Trump and MAGA.”</p> 
<p>“It’s classic Trump — he ratchets everything up to an 11 and it blows up in his face,” said Austin Cook, a Democratic strategist and former Slotkin spokesperson. “Not only did it reinforce everything swing voters have always hated about him, but it’s also given this group the biggest megaphone they’ve ever had.”</p> 
<p>But Tim Edson, a GOP strategist and former political director for the National Republican Senatorial Committee, said the video will only confirm the GOP base’s preconceived, negative views of Democratic officials.</p> 
<p>“Republicans believe these Democrats are deranged with hatred of Trump, and it’s just their latest attempt to undermine lawful policies simply because they’re Trump’s policies,” Edson said. “These embarrassing antics only rally Republicans to the president.”</p> 
<p>Some Democrats think it’s too early to tell how things will shake out for the “seditious six,” as some Trump officials are <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/video/6385589967112" target="_blank">calling the lawmakers</a>.</p> 
<p>“Whether it works or not will depend on what comes next, if an illegal order actually does come down they get to be leaders saying ‘I told you so,’” texted one strategist who has consulted for Democratic veterans and was granted anonymity to speak candidly. “If one doesn’t, they’ve simply made themselves victims to Trump’s latest attacks. Most Democrats fail at playing on his turf.”</p> 
<p>Kelly doubled down on the video’s message during his talk-show appearance Tuesday night and noted some of his Republican colleagues are expressing support: “People are starting to take a look at this and saying, ‘Wow, this is just nuts that he's going after U.S. senators and members of the House for something they said.’”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans clash over drone crackdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/chinese-drones-defense-bill-fight-00669415</link>
      <description>Many Republicans fear the Chinese-made product is a major threat to national security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bdcb-d51c-a39e-bdcbe8460000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0f/cb/070e31334b0c8c765a780db44b66/u-s-congress-40828.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Elise Stefanik (R-N.Y.) is seen during a press conference outside the U.S. Capitol, on May 14, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0f/cb/070e31334b0c8c765a780db44b66/u-s-congress-40828.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A Capitol Hill push by GOP China hawks to impose new restrictions on Shenzhen-based aerial drone maker DJI is facing resistance from Republicans who warn the company’s products have become critical tools for U.S. farming and energy firms.</p> 
<p>The fight is playing out after Rep. Elise Stefanik of New York, a close ally of President Donald Trump, secured the crackdown in the House version of a must-pass defense policy bill. At stake for DJI are new restrictions on its ability to offer products in the U.S.</p> 
<p>Stefanik is making the case that the company’s products expose Americans’ data to the Chinese government — an allegation that the company denies as it lobbies hard to make the case that it operates independently of Chinese officials.</p> 
<p>But Stefanik and her allies are facing pushback in the Senate, which opted against including the provision in its version of the bill and where Republicans are raising concerns about potential negative impacts on U.S. businesses and law enforcement. The two chambers are working to resolve their differences in the sprawling defense bill so they can enact it by year’s end.</p> 
<p>“They are the primary drone maker in the United States at a reasonable price,” Senate Agriculture Chair John Boozman, an Arkansas Republican, said of DJI in an interview. “This technology is being used more and more. ... That’s the crux of the problem.”</p> 
<p>The battle over DJI marks the latest flash point among Republicans over how to counter China without sacrificing U.S. business interests. Trump, whose election in 2016 was a boon to the party’s China hawk wing, has himself sought to ease tensions with Beijing in recent months after initiating a trade war. It’s unclear that Stefanik and her allies will prevail with their campaign against DJI.</p> 
<p>DJI is the dominant global producer of commercial drones, which it markets to enterprise customers for uses in inspecting infrastructure, surveying land and public safety.</p> 
<p>“There are real cost ramifications for commercial enterprises, not just farming,” Sen. John Hoeven, a North Dakota Republican, said in an interview. “You’ve got the energy industry, where they’re tracking transmission lines, rescue and recovery, all these different other uses. It’s something we’ve got to figure out.”</p> 
<p>Boozman and Hoeven say they also have national security concerns about DJI, but Stefanik has been pushing provisions that would take an all-or-nothing approach, rejecting the notion that economic impacts should hold lawmakers back from immediately barring the sale of new DJI products in the U.S.</p> 
<p>“It is very important for us to have U.S. drones and not have that data be turned over to the CCP,” she said in an interview. “It has been an issue we’ve worked on for a number of years with traditional bipartisan support to protect our information, whether it’s the topography of their regions or on the installations … or potential troop movements.”</p> 
<p>The legislative language Stefanik and other China hawks are pursuing comes as DJI already faces potential restrictions on its ability to sell products in the U.S. after Dec. 23, thanks to an amendment Stefanik secured in last year’s defense authorization bill.</p> 
<p>That earlier provision requires federal agencies to audit DJI and another Chinese drone manufacturer, Autel, for national security risks. If no such audit is performed, a ban on domestic imports will go into effect. No national security agency has indicated it plans to conduct the audit in time to meet the deadline.</p> 
<p>The new proposal Republicans are now debating would require another federal audit of drone equipment, including software and spectrum band products, developed in countries that are “foreign adversaries.” The language once again targets DJI and Autel.</p> 
<p>DJI has spent nearly $3 million on federal lobbying this year, according to disclosures filed with Congress, in appeals to lawmakers from states and districts that rely on its drones to support critical sectors of their local economies – particularly agricultural and law enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>“The fundamental point is, this isn’t really about data security,” DJI global head of policy Adam Welsh said in an interview. “This is, frankly, about protectionism and trying to protect a U.S. industry.”</p> 
<p>Representatives of DJI’s enterprise customer base acknowledge national security concerns associated with the drones. But they are also warning against the repercussions of a full-out ban.</p> 
<p>“It would have a very significant level of repercussions, full stop,” National Sheriffs’ Association CEO Jonathan Thompson said in an interview. “It’s a little like taking cars out of a sheriff’s office and saying you can’t use any cars. These are ubiquitous.”</p> 
<p>Even the federal government has had trouble weaning itself off the Chinese-made drones.</p> 
<p>After the Interior Department prohibited the purchase of new DJI drones in 2020, the Government Accountability Office found in a follow-up review that the removal of foreign-made drone fleets had significantly impaired the operations of the Bureau of Land Management and National Park Service.</p> 
<p>“BLM and NPS do not have enough drones for their operations to manage or prevent wildland fires and have shifted some operations to riskier, more costly methods, such as helicopters,” the GAO said in the report.</p> 
<p>Sen. Rick Scott, a Florida Republican who is championing a proposal in his chamber that mirrors Stefanik’s language, said in an interview that he has run into resistance at the Senate Commerce Committee, which has jurisdiction over aviation and technology issues and is chaired by Sen. Ted Cruz of Texas.</p> 
<p>“Commerce did not oppose the inclusion of a DJI audit in the [defense bill],” said Phoebe Keller, a committee spokesperson for Cruz. “Staff provided edits to the text and engaged in good faith to clear the language. The sponsors ultimately chose not to engage further but we remain happy to work with the sponsors if and when they decide to reengage.”</p> 
<p>A person granted anonymity to share details of the negotiations said committee staff conveyed concerns to Scott’s team about the ramifications of banning drones relied upon by first responders</p> 
<p>Scott rejects concerns that there aren’t yet viable alternative drones being produced in the U.S.</p> 
<p>“There’s American companies, and there will be,” said Scott, a former Florida governor and health care CEO. “I’m a business guy. If you told me there was an opportunity, I could figure it out pretty fast.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Nobody will ever believe it’: James Comer airs doubts about his own Epstein investigation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/james-comer-jeffrey-epstein-investigation-00669127</link>
      <description>The House Oversight chair fears “so many conspiracy theories” will haunt any findings he ultimately releases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bd22-d49b-af9f-bde6efbc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/bb/05/b27bf2c64e73a8775e84773b7496/u-s-congress-50847.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. James Comer said he is hopeful recent House document requests will turn up further notable revelations about the late convicted sex offender.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bb/05/b27bf2c64e73a8775e84773b7496/u-s-congress-50847.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Without James Comer’s House investigation into Jeffrey Epstein, the world might never have seen the “birthday book” full of lewd materials or the trove of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/here-are-9-of-the-most-shocking-revelations-in-the-latest-batch-of-epstein-documents-00649853" target="_blank">more than 20,000 documents</a> elucidating the late convicted sex offender’s dealings with global power players — including President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>It would have been a career-defining triumph for any House Oversight Committee chair. But not for Comer, who expressed deep ambivalence about the ongoing probe in a recent interview.</p> 
<p>That reflects the complicated and unpredictable fallout from the Epstein saga, which has helped derail the Republican congressional agenda and the opening year of Trump’s second term. It could also have implications for Comer’s own political ambitions — given his own belief that Americans’ minds might well be impervious to his panel’s conclusions.</p> 
<p>“I fear the report will be like the Warren Report,” he said. “Nobody will ever believe it.”</p> 
<p>Comer’s reference to the 1964 report on the assassination of President John F. Kennedy led by Chief Justice Earl Warren underscores how the Epstein case has enthralled legions of skeptics who say the federal government is intent on protecting powerful men involved in the exploitation of young women and girls.</p> 
<p>That was one big reason, Comer said, that he “wasn't excited about doing the investigation.” Even now, he has not fully committed to releasing a final report, saying it would happen “eventually, I would assume.”</p> 
<p>“There's so many conspiracy theories,” he said, leaving unspoken that his reputation and legacy are now entwined with the case.</p> 
<p>That’s a shift from where Comer had staked his political brand a year ago, as the top GOP investigator of Joe Biden. But his two-year effort to undermine the sitting president produced uneven results, with his impeachment probe focusing on Biden family business dealings <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/08/19/house-gop-biden-impeachment-00174711" target="_blank">never coming to a vote</a> and his investigation into the former president’s alleged mental decline <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/28/republican-trump-biden-autopen-investigation-00624187" target="_blank">failing to deliver any bombshells</a>.</p> 
<p>So as he eyes a 2027 run for Kentucky governor, with his relationship with Trump likely to be central to his prospects, it’s the Epstein investigation that could determine Comer’s future in politics.</p> 
<p>For months, House GOP leadership touted the Oversight probe as proof that Republicans were taking the Epstein case seriously — even as they fought efforts from within their own ranks to advance legislation that would force a complete release of the DOJ investigative files. In a twist last week, Trump gave up fighting the bill’s inevitable passage, signing the measure into law shortly after Congress approved it with just one dissenter.</p> 
<p>The administration now has fewer than 30 days to make materials available to the public, with redactions to protect victims’ names and respect ongoing criminal investigations. Comer, meanwhile, must find a way to shepherd his committee’s investigation to some conclusion.</p> 
<p>Asked what the logical end point of his probe would be, Comer was not quite sure.</p> 
<p>He said he remains hopeful the bank records he has subpoenaed will turn up something notable. The chair <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/comer-subpoenas-epsteins-financial-records-00657935" target="_blank">recently demanded Epstein-related records</a> from JPMorgan Chase and Deutsche Bank and asked the attorney general for the U.S. Virgin Islands, whose jurisdiction includes the two private islands that Epstein owned, for additional materials.</p> 
<p>Comer warned of various obstacles. Many of the crimes occurred decades ago, and evidence will be difficult to find. The key witness — Epstein — killed himself behind bars in 2019, while Ghislaine Maxwell, Epstein’s longtime co-conspirator now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in the sex trafficking crimes, has said she <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/ghislaine-maxwell-plead-fifth-house-oversight-00664640" target="_blank">will not cooperate</a> with the Oversight Committee’s questioning.</p> 
<p>In an effort to try to satisfy calls on both sides of the aisle for some kind of “list,” Comer said he has tasked Democratic and Republican women on the Oversight Committee to meet privately with victims to try to learn the identities of people complicit in Epstein’s criminal activities.</p> 
<p>“If there is no Epstein list, and the American people expect us to compose an Epstein list, if we don't get any names from the victims, it's going to be hard to do,” he said.</p> 
<p>Jennifer Freeman, an attorney representing some of Epstein’s accusers, warned that Comer's strategy could put the women at risk.</p> 
<p>“Why are we putting the burden on them?” she said in an interview.</p> 
<p>But the most significant challenge Comer faces is managing the political fallout for Trump and the GOP writ large.</p> 
<p>Comer’s targeting of the Epstein estate uncovered materials that connect the president to the late financier. But Comer has continued to downplay the significance of the revelations and insist they show no signs of wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Democrats publicized widely the revelations in<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/08/house-oversight-receives-epstein-estate-files-00550721" target="_blank">the birthday book</a>, with a racy drawing and message allegedly penned by Trump. They also blasted out a set of emails mentioning Trump, including one in which Epstein said that Trump “knew about the girls.”</p> 
<p>Comer rejects the narrative that his investigation has been damaging for Trump and blamed his panel’s minority for disregarding committee norms in selectively releasing certain information the panel had received.</p> 
<p>Speaking with reporters last week, Comer called the Oversight Committee’s top Democrat, Rep. Robert Garcia of California, “dishonest” and “awful,” among other personal attacks.</p> 
<p>“I'm done with Garcia, criticizing me. He played the gay card,” Comer said. “He just needs to do TikTok videos or something. … He's not a serious investigator. He’s like a TikTok video kind of guy.”</p> 
<p>Comer added that Garcia “had limited abilities to begin with, but he's burned his bridges with this.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Comer said the “gay card” comment referred to a September incident where <a href="https://x.com/RobertGarcia/status/1965471435914444928" target="_blank">Garcia invoked his sexuality</a> after Comer called him a “drama queen” to reporters.</p> 
<p>Garcia, who is gay, said in an interview it was “clear that Chairman Comer … and the committee Republicans have been outworked and outmaneuvered, and he’s clearly upset and panicking that we have been fighting every single day to release these files. … They’ve tried to bend the knee to Trump and coverup and be part of the White House cover-up.”</p> 
<p>If Trump is displeased with Comer’s handling of the Epstein investigation, he hasn’t said so publicly, and there aren’t apparent rumblings inside the administration about friction.</p> 
<p>“The president likes James Comer a lot,” a senior White House official who was granted anonymity to share private conversations said. “In fact, I spoke with [Trump] recently about [Comer] and he said he's always been good and with him all the way. There's no problems there."</p> 
<p>For Comer, there is another reason to endear himself to the president with this investigation: He’s eying a bid to succeed Gov. Andy Beshear in a state where Trump’s endorsement could have significant influence.</p> 
<p>Comer said in the interview people were encouraging him to run, and he has been traveling statewide ahead of the potential race. He suspects Epstein will not be a major issue in the campaign, but his frequent TV hits discussing his investigative work have given him the opportunity to speak to Kentucky voters, he noted.</p> 
<p>He said he has not spoken to the White House about the Epstein probe, and when asked how he suspects Trump views the probe, Comer said, “I don’t want to know, probably.”</p> 
<p><i>Diana Nerozzi contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The big sticking point in the White House’s health care proposal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/republicans-trump-obamacare-abortion-00669389</link>
      <description>For many GOP members, an expansion of abortion restrictions in Obamacare is a must-have in any tentative health care plan.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bdbc-df0f-abfa-fdfe21640000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 20:18:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/2f/23/2a651e5a4d50acd022860cca97e0/white-house-14259.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump looks on with guests during an announcement about in vitro fertilization in the Oval Office at the White House on Oct. 16, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2f/23/2a651e5a4d50acd022860cca97e0/white-house-14259.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alice Miranda Ollstein, Jordain Carney and Cheyenne Haslett</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alice Miranda Ollstein, Jordain Carney and Cheyenne Haslett</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House's silence on how its health care plan deals with abortion is causing a headache for Republicans on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>For many GOP members, an expansion of abortion restrictions in Obamacare is a must-have. But the White House’s decision to leave the issue out of its tentative framework caught Republicans off guard, leaving them in the dark about whether the president would ultimately stake out a position publicly, according to two aides granted anonymity to disclose private discussions.</p> 
<p>The fight over the Hyde amendment, which bars federal funding for abortion, is just one of many landmines that need to be cleared before any health care deal to extend expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies can be reached. It also comes on top of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">GOP backlash to other aspects</a> of the White House’s health policy framework that leaked Sunday.</p> 
<p>“No Republican has voted for Obamacare or an Obamacare extension or expansion,” said a senior Senate Republican aide, granted anonymity to speak candidly. “Asking members to do that and not including Hyde would be impossible for many.”</p> 
<p>The White House did not respond to requests for comment on the president’s stance.</p> 
<p>The proposal the administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751" target="_blank">had planned to roll out this week</a> consisted of a two-year extension of the ACA’s enhanced subsidies with new limitations favored by conservatives, such as a cutoff for people with higher incomes and a requirement that everyone pay a minimum monthly premium. But the White House gave no indication of whether it endorsed GOP lawmakers’ demand to also prohibit any insurance plan that receives a federal subsidy from covering abortion services.</p> 
<p>Gavin Oxley, a spokesperson with Americans United for Life, said it would be helpful for the White House to publicly lay out its position on the Hyde question to give lawmakers an idea of how to proceed.</p> 
<p>Not weighing in now, or proceeding with a plan without abortion restrictions, “would ultimately fracture the wide-reaching coalition that got President Trump re-elected,” Oxley said.</p> 
<p>“We believe the Administration and pro-life leaders in Congress will come to the table in good faith with a plan that includes Hyde,” he continued. “But should it not, we will be prepared to reject such a plan.”</p> 
<p>House and Senate Republicans, as well as dozens of anti-abortion groups that have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/24/congress-republicans-abortion-health-00577631" target="_blank">spent months lobbying Congress</a> and the White House, oppose any extension of the subsidies that doesn’t bar all insurance plans in the individual market from covering abortion. One of the people granted anonymity to speak candidly said that including the abortion funding restrictions was a “red line" for a broad swath of Republicans.</p> 
<p>“We don’t have any details on this plan, but Senator Young supports Hyde protections and believes they should apply to any taxpayer funded health care spending,” said Leah Selk, spokesperson for Republican Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/52983" data-person-id="52983">Todd Young</a> of Indiana.</p> 
<p>The hard line for Republicans creates a narrow window for bipartisan agreement, if any, before the end of the year, when the subsidies are set to expire and cause premiums to skyrocket. Democrats, whose votes are needed to clear the filibuster in the Senate to advance most legislation, have declared that abortion restrictions would be a non-starter in ongoing negotiations.</p> 
<p>“Instead of working with Democrats to fix the health care crisis they created, Republicans now want to hold women’s health care hostage and force their radical agenda on the American people,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51247" data-person-id="51247">Ron Wyden</a> of Oregon, the top Democrat on the Finance Committee that has jurisdiction over much of the sprawling U.S. health system, in a recent floor speech. “I have one thing to say to that: not on my watch.”</p> 
<p>Likely cognizant of this political reality, the White House’s decision to sidestep the abortion question was intended to allow the administration to avoid drawing attention to an issue that could have immediately jeopardized the plan’s viability, said a Republican aide with knowledge of the discussions — even if its silence has actually had the opposite effect. </p> 
<p>“Look, it's no secret that this administration is not rushing to put a lot of political capital on the issue of abortion if they can avoid it,” said Patrick Brown, a fellow with the conservative think tank Ethics and Public Policy Center, which has been part of the roiling debate over abortion restrictions in Obamacare. “It's not something I think they have any interest in highlighting.”</p> 
<p>The abortion standoff is just one of many factors complicating a proposed deal to extend insurance subsidies. Deep divisions remain around who should qualify for such subsidies, how generous they should be, and what kind of health services are covered.</p> 
<p>Any agreement would need Trump's blessing, giving Republicans political cover to vote for an extension of the health reform law they have raged against for more than a decade. But given this difficult landscape, conservative lobbyists are skeptical that passage is possible even if Trump endorsed abortion restrictions. Those in close contact with lawmakers say it’s unlikely an extension of the subsidies could win 60 votes in the Senate — or even 50.</p> 
<p>“It'd be very difficult, even if they do it through reconciliation,” said Tom McClusky, the director of government affairs for Catholic Vote. “On the subsidies alone, I think you have a large enough contingent on the Republican side that don't want them renewed at all — regardless of if you can somehow miraculously figure out the protections of Hyde.”</p> 
<p>Since its inception more than a decade ago, the Affordable Care Act has barred federal subsidies from paying for abortions, but left it up to states whether health insurance plans in the individual market could cover abortion using other funding.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.kff.org/womens-health-policy/state-policies-on-abortion-coverage-in-medicaid-private-insurance-and-aca-exchange-plans-2025/" target="_blank">Half of states</a> have opted to ban all coverage of abortion on their Obamacare markets, including some where abortion itself is legal, like Pennsylvania and Arizona. In the remaining 25 states, abortion coverage through Obamacare is either allowed or required, though any claims paid out involving the termination of a pregnancy come from a separate account that doesn’t use any federal subsidies.</p> 
<p>If Congress passes an Obamacare subsidy extension that includes the abortion restrictions conservatives are demanding, it would force roughly a dozen states where abortion coverage is mandatory to make a tough decision: change their laws or risk losing billions of dollars. In the states where abortion coverage is allowed but not required, it would be up to individual insurance plans whether to lose federal funding or drop abortion coverage.</p> 
<p>After nearly a year of the Trump administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/01/28/trump-gop-leaders-congress-power-assault-00002129" target="_blank">clawing power away from Capitol Hill</a> and dictating everything from spending to military action, some anti-abortion advocates are baffled by the lack of a firm message on how the Hyde amendment’s ban on abortion funding applies to Obamacare.</p> 
<p>“It’s in tension with this administration's broader approach to dealing with Congress, which has been very heavy handed — sort of, ‘We are calling the shots. Sit back and let us drive,’” said Brown. “But it would be their preference to sit in the back seat on that issue specifically.”</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-25T16:30:24-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democrats say they are subjects of FBI probe after filming anti-Trump video</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/democrats-fbi-trump-00668584</link>
      <description>Six lawmakers with nation security backgrounds are being criticized by the Trump administration for telling troops to disobey illegal orders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-bc69-d51c-a39e-bd690bee0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 15:04:06 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/38/1c/95a9d09c49c8b305ee0cb3501b93/task-force-on-the-attempted-assassination-of-donald-trump-75904.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Angelina Katsanis/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) speaks to the press at the first hearing from the Task Force on the attempted assassination of Donald Trump in Washington on Sept. 26, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/38/1c/95a9d09c49c8b305ee0cb3501b93/task-force-on-the-attempted-assassination-of-donald-trump-75904.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Kyle Cheney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Kyle Cheney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Several congressional Democrats said Tuesday they might be under investigation by the FBI after filming an anti-Trump video urging military troops not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p><br>“President Trump is using the FBI as a tool to intimidate and harass Members of Congress. Yesterday, the FBI contacted the House and Senate Sergeants at Arms requesting interviews," wrote Democratic Reps. Jason Crow of Colorado and Maggie Goodlander of New Hampshire, alongside Chris Deluzio and Chrissy Houlahan of Pennsylvania, in a joint statement. "No amount of intimidation or harassment will ever stop us from doing our jobs and honoring our Constitution."</p> 
<p>"The President directing the FBI to target us is exactly why we made this video in the first place. He believes in weaponizing the federal government against his perceived enemies and does not believe laws apply to him or his Cabinet," Sen. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.) posted on social media. </p> 
<p>The lawmakers, who all have national security or military backgrounds, appeared in a video encouraging members of the military not to obey orders they believe are unlawful, saying, "Don't give up the ship." This message prompted a furious response from President Donald Trump, who called the video "SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL” and also shared a post calling for traitors to be hanged — though White House later said Trump was not threatening the lawmakers with death. </p> 
<p>The House Sergeant at Arms office was contacted by the FBI Monday about setting up interviews related to the six members of Congress, according to a person granted anonymity to speak freely about the matter. The request was forwarded to the House Office of General Counsel to interact with the Justice Department, the person said. </p> 
<p>Typically, investigations related to members of Congress are handled between the Office of General Counsel and the main Justice Department, not the FBI, making the outreach somewhat unusual. </p> 
<p>The Pentagon announced Monday it <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894?utm_campaign=mb&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_source=morning_brew" target="_blank">would investigate another one</a> of the lawmakers in the video, Democratic Sen. Mark Kelly of Arizona, for “serious allegations of misconduct" which could result in recalling him to active duty to face a court martial on alleged crimes.</p> 
<p>The Senate and House Sergeants at Arms offices did not immediately respond to a request for comment. A spokesperson for the FBI declined to comment.</p> 
<p><i>Cheyanne M. Daniels contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marjorie Taylor Greene is staying out of the election to replace her</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/marjorie-taylor-greene-election-replacement-00667787</link>
      <description>The Georgia Republican said she won’t endorse in next year’s special election, avoiding a proxy war with Trump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b827-df0f-abfa-f96fc30c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:44:36 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/43/7c/bdf82ab248118cdcbe355509ef36/congress-epstein-88278.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Julia Demaree Nikhinson/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene, (R-Ga.), speaks during a news conference on the Epstein Files Transparency Act, Nov. 18, 2025, outside the U.S. Capitol in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/43/7c/bdf82ab248118cdcbe355509ef36/congress-epstein-88278.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Marjorie Taylor Greene said she won’t make any endorsement in the special election race to replace her in Congress — avoiding a potential clash between her preferred candidate and a candidate aligned with President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Greene said in a social media post Monday that she will remain neutral in the special election in Georgia’s 14th Congressional District after she steps away from Congress in January.</p> 
<p>“Looking ahead towards the Special Election for my Congressional seat, I will not be endorsing anyone out of respect to my district. I truly support the wonderful people of Georgia 14 and want them to pick their Representative,” she <a href="https://x.com/mtgreenee/status/1993081407418118423?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. “So anyone claiming they have my endorsement would not be telling the truth.”</p> 
<p>Her neutrality paves the way for Trump’s allies to elevate a candidate of their choosing in a heavily-Republican district that Greene won in 2024 by 28 points.</p> 
<p>In announcing her sudden decision to leave Congress, Greene, who has become estranged from the president, said she was partly inspired to step down to avoid a “hateful and hurtful primary” against a Trump-backed candidate.</p> 
<p>Trump, following her announcement, <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115593179521083607" target="_blank">said Greene would have</a> “no chance of winning” in a primary against a candidate with his endorsement.</p> 
<p>The special election won’t be scheduled until Greene leaves her post. Georgia law stipulates the election must occur at least 30 days after it’s been ordered. A Georgia Republican official told Atlanta News First the special election will <a href="https://www.atlantanewsfirst.com/2025/11/22/metro-atlanta-gop-chair-march-special-election-likely-fill-marjorie-taylor-greenes-seat/" target="_blank">likely occur in March</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump was going to roll out a health care plan. Then Republicans weighed in.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/trump-health-care-subsidies-backlash-00667751</link>
      <description>Lawmakers just have a few weeks left to reach a deal to avoid a massive premium spike for ACA enrollees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b835-d739-a3ba-fcfd62480000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 18:32:04 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ab/74/53112bc746aca107df3185b51063/white-house-65365.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump stands near a sign on lowering drug prices for Americans as he announces a drug-pricing deal with Pfizer in the Oval Office at the White House Sept. 30, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ab/74/53112bc746aca107df3185b51063/white-house-65365.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Cheyenne Haslett, Benjamin Guggenheim and Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Cheyenne Haslett, Benjamin Guggenheim and Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701" target="_blank">health care plan</a> is in limbo after pushback from Republicans who were caught off guard by the president’s forthcoming proposal — questioning, in particular, whether it would include additional abortion restrictions.</p> 
<p>Trump had been expected to unveil a new policy framework Monday afternoon, said two people familiar with the plan and granted anonymity to describe deliberations around it. That framework was expected to center around a two-year extension of Affordable Care Act subsidies with income caps and other new limits backed by conservatives.</p> 
<p>But while White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Monday that Trump remained focused on “unveiling a health care proposal,” she declined to get into specifics about subsidy extensions or a timeline for the rollout: “I’ll let the president speak for himself."</p> 
<p>A White House official separately noted Trump’s daily schedule never listed plans for a Monday rollout.</p> 
<p>The uncertainty around the timing of the announcement comes as Hill Republicans remain sharply divided over whether to extend the enhanced tax credits to prevent premiums from skyrocketing next year or to let them expire at the end of the year and coalesce around an alternative approach to keep health care costs down.</p> 
<p>One House Republican granted anonymity to speak freely said in an interview Monday they needed to see “what structural changes” Trump might float, adding that GOP lawmakers should demand “reforms … in exchange for extending the subsidies.”</p> 
<p>According to three additional people granted anonymity to share details of the plan ahead of its release, Trump was preparing to place new income caps on individuals receiving the subsidies and require minimum premium payments for Obamacare enrollees. He also was expected to propose an option for enrollees to receive part of their tax credit in a tax-advantaged savings account if they downgrade to a lower-premium health plan.</p> 
<p>These policy changes <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/cassidy-fund-hsas-trump-aca-subsidies-00655213" target="_blank">align with what many conservatives</a> have been seeking. But it wasn’t clear Monday whether the plan would also include <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/24/congress-republicans-abortion-health-00577631" target="_blank">expanded restrictions under the so-called Hyde amendment</a>, which bans federal funds from being used for abortions.</p> 
<p>One of the people who described the tentative plan and two other people granted anonymity to disclose private discussions said congressional Republicans still didn’t know how Trump’s proposal would deal with that thorny issue.</p> 
<p>The ACA has always barred federal subsidies from paying for abortions but left it up to states to determine whether health insurance plans in the individual market could cover abortion using other funding.</p> 
<p>Marjorie Dannenfelser, the president of Susan B. Anthony Pro-Life America, reiterated in a statement Monday her anti-abortion group will penalize any lawmaker who votes for a subsidies extension without additional abortion guardrails that ban coverage nationwide.</p> 
<p>“We oppose any health care plan that fails to include this safeguard,” she said. “Our position is consistent and will not change.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s plan to extend the ACA credits — even with changes sought by conservatives — also <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2025/11/24/trumps-obamacare-move-blindsides-conservatives-00666700" target="_blank">blindsided some Hill Republicans</a> who have dug in against any bipartisan deal to extend the credits.</p> 
<p>"I know that we've got different ideas in our conference," House Majority Whip Tom Emmer (R-Minn.) said in a Monday morning interview on Fox Business Network. "I think you're going to hear more from the White House.”</p> 
<p>House GOP leadership last week gave a presentation to the House Republican Conference slamming the subsidies for perpetuating what they dubbed the “Unaffordable Care Act,” a moniker Emmer repeated Monday.</p> 
<p>Not all Republicans reacted negatively to the news of a forthcoming health policy announcement from Trump. Rep. Tim Burchett in an interview Monday credited the president with having “some guts” to get lawmakers “to the table.” Trump’s forthcoming framework, Burchett added, “starts the negotiating.”</p> 
<p>“I don’t like the subsidies,” the Tennessee Republican continued, “but everybody griping about it doesn’t have a plan, so get some guts, put up a plan … or get the heck out of the way.”</p> 
<p>Burchett also said the White House will now roll out the plan Tuesday, underscoring confusion and mixed messaging around the forthcoming presentation.</p> 
<p>Leavitt left open a broad array of possibilities for the final White House plan Monday, including that it might not ultimately include a subsidy extension. Asked specifically if that provision would be included, she told reporters, "As you all know, sometimes you report things and then President Trump comes out with an announcement and those things are not always true."</p> 
<p>Some Democrats expressed cautious optimism upon learning that Trump was preparing to embrace an extension of the ACA credits.</p> 
<p>Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.), who has been heavily involved in the bipartisan negotiations on health care, said in a statement Monday that she has had “constructive conversations” with Republicans about extending the enhanced tax credits.</p> 
<p>“If the reports are true and the President is considering coming to the table in good faith, I believe we can find a path forward that can earn broad bipartisan support in Congress,” Shaheen said.</p> 
<p>She added that anything Trump puts out on the issue could signal “a serious proposal to begin negotiations.”</p> 
<p>Democrats, including Shaheen, have been discussing what their strategy should be ahead of a floor vote in mid-December on a proposal to extend the subsidies, which was promised to Democrats by Senate Majority Leader John Thune in exchange for their votes to end the government shutdown. Democrats will get to decide what proposal they want a vote on, though Republicans are expected to offer their own alternative unless there is a bipartisan deal.</p> 
<p>One provision that had been included in Trump’s tentative plan — pegging the eligibility cap for the subsidies at 700 percent of the federal poverty line — is among the ideas being mulled by Shaheen and her colleagues.</p> 
<p>But other Democrats slammed the proposal outright, further casting doubt on how Trump’s opening salvo would land on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>In a statement Monday afternoon, the three top House Democrats on committees with jurisdiction over health care — Reps. Richard Neal of Massachusetts, Frank Pallone of New Jersey and Bobby Scott of Virginia — panned the White House’s forthcoming proposal, calling it the “greatest hits of Republican health care ideas the people have rejected for years.”</p> 
<p>They continued, “At this point, anything short of a clean extension is unworkable and won’t avoid the price hikes people are now facing.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Mike Johnson is losing control of the House</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/house-discharge-petitions-mike-johnson-00666557</link>
      <description>Thanks to a coalition of Democrats and disgruntled Republicans, more discharge petitions have succeeded in the past two years than the prior three decades combined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b2d0-df0f-abfa-f3fac5600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d4/7f/42e62ed44ab997b2bde70893baf5/u-s-congress-89936.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Speaker Mike Johnson railed against the discharge petition on releasing the Epstein files at a Nov. 18 news conference. His efforts were to no avail.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d4/7f/42e62ed44ab997b2bde70893baf5/u-s-congress-89936.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over the course of decades, House lawmakers had succeeded only a few times in triggering votes on bills the chamber’s leaders refused to call up.</p> 
<p>Then Mike Johnson became speaker.</p> 
<p>On the Louisiana Republican’s watch, the “discharge petition” has caught fire. Rank-and-file lawmakers have managed five times since he won his gavel two years ago to circumvent Johnson’s wishes by getting the 218 signatures needed to force votes on legislation he had blocked — more than in the prior 30 years combined.</p> 
<p>Most recently, a bipartisan group used the maneuver to advance a long-stalled bill requiring President Donald Trump’s administration to release information about the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>It’s members of Johnson’s own party who have most effectively wielded the tool in recent years. Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) masterminded the Epstein push, while Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) engineered an effort to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/04/01/congress/proxy-voting-rule-vote-fails-00263621" target="_blank">seek voting accommodations</a> for House members with newborn babies. Before that, then-Rep. Garret Graves (R-La.) used the gambit to enact a bill to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/12/20/congress/social-security-bill-passes-senate-00195786" target="_blank">expand Social Security payments</a> for millions of public sector workers.</p> 
<p>“They try to say that discharge petitions are a tool of the minority, but that's actually only the perspective of people that want to consolidate power within leadership,” Luna said in an interview, adding that she would protect the maneuver “with every bone in my body.”</p> 
<p>The upshot for Johnson is that the arcane legislative mechanism once known only to Capitol Hill obsessives is now a routine part of life in the Republican House majority. Beyond Epstein, Johnson is now facing several new drumbeats for action, with lawmakers looking to force votes on banning member stock trading, sanctioning Russia and extending health care subsidies that are set to expire at year’s end.</p> 
<p>The GOP’s slim majority is an obvious contributor to the burgeoning popularity of the maneuver. The discharge process is set into motion when 218 members sign on to a petition, meaning only a handful of Republicans need to cross leadership if Democrats are united in support.</p> 
<p>But the recent spate of successful discharges also reflects careful groundwork Democrats laid to quickly seize on the procedure, along with a sentiment among many Republicans that Johnson is stifling the will of the House to appease Trump and small GOP factions — including hard-liners who successfully ousted Johnson’s predecessor, Kevin McCarthy.</p> 
<p>“I would encourage you to ask Mike Johnson why he repeatedly refused to bring my bill to the floor,” Rep. Greg Steube (R-Fla.) said in an interview.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">‘Toxic political environment’</h5> 
<p>Steube is still bitter about how Johnson hindered passage last year of his legislation to provide tax relief to disaster survivors, even after the measure was unanimously approved in committee. Once Steube <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/05/21/congress/discharge-petition-passes-in-house-disaster-relief-00159184" target="_blank">got the signatures</a> he needed to compel floor action, the measure passed the House in a 382-7 vote before clearing the Senate and earning then-President Joe Biden’s signature.</p> 
<p>That first victory — seven months into Johnson’s tenure as speaker — showed how the maneuver can be successful “in a toxic political environment,” said Steube, a MAGA-hat-wearing, fourth-term member who has consistently won his southwest Florida district by a landslide. “It’s got to be something that is very bipartisan and is important enough that the body says, Yeah, this warrants overriding the speaker.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/e5/6f/f58ac8944faca95bba470d9c0429/white-house-87594.jpg" alt="Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) completed one discharge petition and is now threatening another." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) completed one discharge petition and is now threatening another."/><p>The discharge petition dates back to 1910, when it was created in response to the “overreaching, overbearing, overcontrolling” style of then-Speaker Joseph Cannon — aka “Czar Cannon” — according to Sarah Binder, a George Washington University professor who focuses on legislative politics.</p> 
<p>Now, she said, it serves as a “pressure valve” for a chamber designed to reflect the majority’s will.</p> 
<p>In some cases, discharge petitions can help solve thorny political problems for the speaker. Philip Wallach, who studies the roots of congressional dysfunction at the right-leaning American Enterprise Institute, said Johnson is “using this idea of getting forced” as a way to keep his job.</p> 
<p>“He’s actually kind of deft at the coalition management problem and at staying on side with Trump,” Wallach said. “If he acted some other way, I really do think there's a good chance that he would find himself on the wrong side of Trump and get thrown out.”</p> 
<p>That was certainly the case with the Epstein vote, though Johnson protested mightily against the bill Massie and his ally Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) sought to discharge, arguing until the moment Trump signed it that it did not do enough to protect Epstein’s victims from invasions of privacy.</p> 
<p>But as the 427-1 vote demonstrated, there was a deep groundswell for transparency that Johnson had been holding off at Trump’s behest.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">‘The fuse in the fuse box’</h5> 
<p>Massie said members of both parties are now “brainstorming” other bills they might be able to catapult to the floor.</p> 
<p>“It's the fuse in the fuse box when everything gets jammed up and the wires get crossed and nothing can get done,” he told reporters last week.</p> 
<p>In discouraging Republicans from signing on to discharge petitions, House GOP leaders argue that the tactic undermines the party in power and circumvents Congress’ “regular order” system of debate, where legislation is meant to advance through committees with special expertise.</p> 
<p>“Typically it’s when somebody either doesn't want to go through the committee process or doesn't get what they want out of the committee process,” House Majority Leader Steve Scalise (R-La.) said in an interview.</p> 
<p>But it’s not just committee calendars and floor scheduling that has chafed many House Republicans. GOP leaders have taken more overt steps this year to thwart the chamber’s ability to work the majority’s will — including by <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/04/09/congress/house-gop-leaders-move-to-quash-vote-on-trumps-global-tariffs-00280922" target="_blank">preemptively blocking efforts</a> to force votes on canceling some of Trump’s tariffs.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/54/ff/fff17c344819af3398fa862426ba/unlimiteduse-11-12-2025-capitol-hill-anna-rose-layden-0044.jpg" alt="After success with the Epstein bill, Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) says he's brainstorming other bipartisan measures to discharge." data-portal-copyright="Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO" data-title="After success with the Epstein bill, Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) says he's brainstorming other bipartisan measures to discharge."/><p>Even before Johnson’s tenure, House leaders of both parties have chipped away at the “open rule” practice of allowing lawmakers to debate any amendments they wanted on the floor. Now they nearly always pick and choose the amendments allowed — if they allow them at all.</p> 
<p>On the Epstein bill, the House’s top Republicans characterized the decision to sign Massie’s petition as a loyalty test.</p> 
<p>“They made it pretty clear that if you get on the discharge petition, you've declared war on the president, in so many words,” Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) said in an interview, adding that he sympathized with Johnson’s need to keep Trump and “prima donnas” in the House GOP happy.</p> 
<p>“He tries his best,” Bacon said.</p> 
<p>But Bacon, who is retiring after his term ends, has signed on to several discharge petitions, including one to sanction Russia and aid Ukraine, which is just a few signatures shy of 218. Bacon reasons that gesture is a way to show Trump that there’s rising support for helping Ukraine while affording Johnson some political cover.</p> 
<p>“I feel like I’m helping him out by doing the discharge on Ukraine, in a way,” Bacon said of Johnson. “Because I'm trying to force the hand. He's going to say, ‘I didn't have any choice on this.’”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">‘Zombie’ legislation</h5> 
<p>Democrats, to be sure, have done their share to contribute to the dizzying pace of discharges. Just last week, another petition succeeded, setting up a vote on a measure sponsored by Rep. Jared Golden (D-Maine) that would nullify an executive order Trump issued in March scrapping the collective bargaining rights of more than 1 million federal employees.</p> 
<p>The party’s leaders, in fact, have quietly plotted for months to take full advantage of the tool. Under House rules, it typically takes well over a month to force a vote once a petition gets the requisite 218 signatures. So Massachusetts Rep. Jim McGovern, the top Democrat on the House Rules Committee, coordinated the filing of “zombie” measures containing placeholder language allowing members to jump-start the procedural countdown before they finalize the substance of the legislation they want to propel to the floor.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/99/18/306f2cfb4baba6d55961b8d31eb4/congress-defense-spending-38430.jpg" alt="Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) engineered a strategy to use discharge petitions more quickly." data-portal-copyright="J. Scott Applewhite/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) engineered a strategy to use discharge petitions more quickly."/><p>McGovern acknowledged in an interview that none of that spade work pays off unless at least a few members of the majority are disgruntled enough to buck their leaders.</p> 
<p>“It takes a lot of courage for Republicans to sign on to a discharge petition when they're in charge,” he said. “But I think it's a reflection of their frustration with their own leadership.”</p> 
<p>Off the Hill, congressional observers who know the history of the seldom-used gambit are stunned, if not necessarily surprised, by its recent success.</p> 
<p>“Despite the fact that it doesn't succeed very often, it's out there for an ambitious, organized minority — and, in this case, also disgruntled or concerned majority members, who feel their leadership's not on the right side of the issue,” Binder said. “So beware the discharge.”</p> 
<p><i>Cassandra Dumay contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House to pitch a Trump Obamacare extension with limits</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/white-house-to-propose-new-health-care-framework-00666701</link>
      <description>Republicans have been eager for Trump to reveal his preferences on expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b3c7-df0f-abfa-f3ef41570000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 21:53:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fe/f8/23c0463140cab5f1c43278cc53d4/white-house-21565.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump speaks with reporters as he departs on the South Lawn of the White House to board Marine One on Oct. 24, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fe/f8/23c0463140cab5f1c43278cc53d4/white-house-21565.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House expects to soon unveil a health policy framework that includes a two-year extension of Obamacare subsidies due to expire at the end of next month and new limits on eligibility, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the unannounced plans.</p> 
<p>The proposal would mark President Donald Trump’s foray into Capitol Hill negotiations over how to address health care premium spikes set to hit Affordable Care Act enrollees if Congress lets the premium subsidies expire.</p> 
<p>A White House official declined to confirm the details of the plan, saying, “Until President Trump makes an announcement himself, any reporting about the administration’s healthcare positions is mere speculation.” MS NOW <a href="https://www.ms.now/news/trump-health-care-plan-obamacare-aca-subsidies" target="_blank">first reported</a> news of Trump’s intent to announce a new health care framework as soon as Monday to address spikes in ACA insurance premiums.</p> 
<p>As part of a deal to reopen the government earlier this month, Senate Republicans agreed to give Democrats a vote on the ACA tax credits in December. But GOP lawmakers across the Capitol <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/aca-obamacare-subsidies-extension-00655842" target="_blank">have been divided</a> over how to respond to the subsidy deadline, leaving many eager for Trump to reveal his preferences. Hard-line conservatives have been pushing to let the subsidies expire while moderate Republicans have been pressing for an extension. Some Republicans are angling for a health care overhaul to replace the credits.</p> 
<p>The White House plan is expected to include new income caps for enrollees to qualify for the ACA tax credits as well as minimum premium payments, according to the two people with direct knowledge of the proposal.</p> 
<p>The planned eligibility cap would limit the subsidies to individuals with income up to 700 percent of the federal poverty line — aligning with what a bipartisan group of senators have been discussing separately, according to a fourth person granted anonymity to share knowledge of the negotiations.</p> 
<p>Enrollees would also pay a minimum premium payment — a nod to concerns from conservatives that millions of Americans pay nothing in premiums while being unaware they are enrolled in ACA insurance plans.</p> 
<p>The White House’s plan would call on Congress to appropriate funds for cost-sharing reductions, which would reduce out-of-pocket health costs for ACA plans.</p> 
<p>The administration is also set to propose an option for enrollees to receive part of their tax credit in a tax-advantaged savings account if they move down to a lower-premium health plan. Many Republicans lawmakers favor the idea as a way to provide funds directly to people, as opposed to relying on indirect subsidies to insurance companies to drive down health costs. Trump himself has publicly endorsed the concept.</p> 
<p>Democratic lawmakers want Republicans to negotiate with them on an extension, but it remains to be seen whether they would settle for a short-term fix with restrictions attached. It’s also not clear how House GOP leaders would react to the plan after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-gop-leaders-pitch-members-on-unaffordable-care-act-00656362" target="_blank">presenting their members last week</a> with a pitch against what they dubbed the “Unaffordable Care Act.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crockett: MTG couldn’t ’take the heat’ from Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/23/jasmine-crocket-marjorie-taylor-greene-trump-00666306</link>
      <description>Rep. Jasmine Crockett mocked GOP Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene’s decision to resign from Congress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-b142-d49b-af9f-b5e633d50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 11:01:05 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e4/cf/64f4d6654153a90be03a9d97882a/u-s-congress-65232.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Jasmine Crockett (D-Texas) noted that she had long been the target of President Donald Trump's ire.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e4/cf/64f4d6654153a90be03a9d97882a/u-s-congress-65232.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Jasmine Crockett on Sunday appeared to show little sympathy for her colleague Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene after the Georgia Republican announced her upcoming resignation from Congress.</p> 
<p>In an interview with CNN’s Jake Tapper on “State of the Union,” the Texas Democrat, long a foe of President Donald Trump, said Greene’s decision came after she was on “the opposite side of the president” for only one week.</p> 
<p>“You're on the other side of the president for one week, and you can't take the heat?” Crockett said. “Imagine what it is to sit in my shoes, to not only be on the opposite side of him, but to have people like her who are constantly fanning the flames of hate and imagine what those threats look like when you literally are someone like me.” </p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972" target="_blank">Greene announced Friday</a> she would resign from Congress early in 2026 following a fallout between herself and Trump.</p> 
<p>Greene, once a loyal ally of Trump, had become a sharp critic of both the president and her own party over disagreements on the Epstein files, health care and the government shutdown. Greene alleged she had begun to face threats after Trump called her “a traitor.”</p> 
<p>But Crockett on Sunday pointed out that multiple other Republicans, notably Reps. Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Lauren Boebert of Colorado, have also faced the president’s ire in light of their support to release the files on the disgraced, deceased financier.</p> 
<p>“I mean, listen, he's upset with Thomas Massie, and so he's gone after him. He's upset with Boebert, he's upset with any Republican that actually signed the discharge petition,” Crockett said. “But somehow they were able to weather the storm. Why is everyone else able to stand and you can’t?”</p> 
<p>Crockett and Greene’s relationship has long been tense, at one point <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/house-committee-meeting-devolves-chaos-personal-insults-marjorie-taylo-rcna152698" target="_blank">culminating in a confrontation</a> between the two during a House Oversight and Accountability Committee hearing last year.</p> 
<p>Still, Crockett had appeared to be showing some sympathy toward her congressional foe after Trump withdrew his support for Greene.</p> 
<p>“I’m here for you girl … I told you not to trust him … all he cares about is HIMself (and protecting pedos) he never loved you,” <a href="https://x.com/jasmineforus/status/1989520641729466618?s=46" target="_blank">Crockett tweeted at the time</a>.</p> 
<p>It is unclear what Greene’s future plans will be, but Crockett is expected to decide this week if she will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/30/crockett-texas-senate-run-00628699" target="_blank">launch a bid to challenge</a> GOP Sen. John Cornyn.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marjorie Taylor Greene resigns from Congress after clash with Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972</link>
      <description>The former Trump loyalist said she will step down Jan. 5.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a927-d49b-af9f-bde7834a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 20:31:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0e/b0/f9ff8c3e401c944363eaab591391/u-s-congress-45616.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene speaks alongside victims of convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a press conference outside the U.S. Capitol on Nov. 18.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0e/b0/f9ff8c3e401c944363eaab591391/u-s-congress-45616.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Marjorie Taylor Greene, the MAGA firebrand who rose to prominence as a combative supporter of President Donald Trump, announced late Friday she is resigning from Congress after a public feud with him.</p> 
<p>Greene, who was elected to Congress in 2020 from a rural northwestern Georgia district, made the surprise announcement in a surprise video address that referenced her falling out with Trump. The president branded her a “traitor” and withdrew his endorsement for supporting an effort he opposed to release files from the criminal investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“Standing up for American women who were raped at 14, trafficked and used by rich powerful men, should not result in me being called a traitor and threatened by the President of the United States, whom I fought for,” she said in a <a href="https://x.com/mtgreenee/status/1992037226415554642?s=20" target="_blank">statement posted on X</a>.</p> 
<p>Her resignation reflects increasing divisions within the MAGA movement that propelled Trump to power on a populist agenda that Greene had aggressively supported.</p> 
<p>The Republican lawmaker’s relationship with Trump soured after she joined calls from Democrats to release the Epstein files, criticized the president’s focus on foreign affairs and called for action on the expiring Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>“Loyalty should be a two-way street and we should be able to vote our conscience and represent our district’s interest because our job title is literally representative,’' she said.</p> 
<p>Greene said she will step down from office on Jan. 5.</p> 
<p>She did not provide advance notice to to anyone in House Republican leadership, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal matters.</p> 
<p>Her resignation threatens to further tighten Speaker Mike Johnson’s Republican majority early next year.</p> 
<p>The GOP holds a 219-213 advantage following Democrat Mikie Sherrill’s resignation this week after her election as New Jersey governor. That means Johnson can lose no more than two Republicans on a party-line vote.</p> 
<p>Greene highlighted her record of supporting Trump since she entered Congress, noting that she only disagreed in a "few areas” with some of the president’s recent proposals on immigration, artificial intelligence and foreign policy along with her stance on the Epstein documents.</p> 
<p>The White House had no immediate comment and appeared to be caught off-guard by her resignation. </p> 
<p>“It is surprising to absolutely no one that she would exit in the most selfish way possible,” an administration official, who was granted anonymity to discuss the resignation before a statement had been released. </p> 
<p>Rachel Scott, a senior political correspondent for ABC, <a href="https://x.com/rachelvscott/status/1992056507953754215?t=YE1da1BAx7NV3wFu_EzpSA&amp;s=19" target="_blank">said on X</a> that she spoke with Trump and he was surprised but pleased with the resignation. "I think it's great news for the country. It's great," he said.</p> 
<p>The growing divide between Trump and Greene came to a head last week when the president revoked his endorsement of Green in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-mtg-aca-epstein-massie-00653412" target="_blank"><u>scathing social media post</u></a> in which he labeled her “wacky” and a “ranting lunatic.” Days later, he reversed his position on the Epstein case files and encouraged House Republicans to support a bill that would for the Department of Justice to release the documents.</p> 
<p>Johnson later tried to paper over the rift between the Georgia Republican and Trump. The speaker acknowledged the dispute over the Epstein documents but said it was important that the party hold together.</p> 
<p>“But look, I work on unity in the party, and my encouragement of everybody is to get together,” he said. “We’ve got to do all that in order to deliver for the people.”</p> 
<p>Greene suggested in her statement that a looming primary challenge from a candidate aligned with the president factored into her decision — referring to the pro-Trump super PAC MAGA Inc. as one of the actors pushing her aside.</p> 
<p>“I have too much self respect and dignity, love my family way too much, and do not want my sweet district to have to endure a hurtful and hateful primary against me by the President we all fought for, only to fight and win my election while Republicans will likely lose the midterms,” she said.</p> 
<p>Her resignation brings a stunning conclusion to a tumultuous tenure that included promoting outlandish conspiracy theories. In 2021, the House voted to strip her of her committee assignments for social media posts promoting violence towards prominent Democrats.</p> 
<p>She also earned a reputation as a wild card among the House Republican caucus. In 2024, she attempted to remove Johnson from his position as the party was still recovering from a protracted fight that led to the ouster of former Speaker Kevin McCarthy.</p> 
<p>Days after being sworn into office for the first time, she joined a group of Republican members of Congress seeking to block the certification of Joe Biden’s presidential election victory over Trump on Jan. 6., 2021.</p> 
<p>Greene did not rule out a future run for office, suggesting she might run as an independent if she returned to politics. </p> 
<p>"When the common American people finally realize and understand that the political industrial complex of both parties is ripping this country apart, that not one elected leader like me is able to stop Washington's machine from gradually destroying our country, and instead the reality is that they, common Americans, the people, possess the real power over Washington," she said, "then I'll be here by their side to rebuild it." </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-21T15:23:14-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House members move to force Russia sanctions vote as Trump pushes peace deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/russia-sanctions-discharge-petition-00665210</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a7f6-df0f-abfa-e7fe1e3a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 14:52:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan coalition of pro-Ukraine lawmakers will seek to force a House vote to impose crippling sanctions on Russia, even as President Donald Trump is moving to swiftly clinch a peace deal between the two warring nations.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) <a href="https://x.com/RepBrianFitz/status/1991940517584666907?s=20" target="_blank">said in an X post Friday</a> that he and his allies have “officially notified both the Clerk of the House and House leadership of our discharge petition to force a vote on crushing Russian sanctions immediately upon our return” from the Thanksgiving holiday recess.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick was responding to news that Trump wants the Ukrainian government to approve the draft peace deal <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/witkoff-back-channel-push-ukraine-alarms-allies-00660247" target="_blank">assembled by his envoy Steve Witkoff</a> no later than Thursday. The plan would <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/trump-plan-to-end-ukraine-war-cedes-donbas-to-russia-00664204" target="_blank">cede vast portions of eastern Ukraine</a> to Russia in exchange for a security guarantee from western nations.</p> 
<p>Trump appeared to be putting pressure on Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy with his Thanksgiving ultimatum, but the House lawmakers have their eye on Russian President Vladimir Putin — and they believe they have Trump’s blessing.</p> 
<p>House and Senate GOP leaders have held off for months, awaiting a clear signal from Trump, but with the president more determined to impose a peace plan than ever, rank-and-file members are determined to act.</p> 
<p>“The President’s appeasement plan to Russia is forcing our hand," said Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.).</p> 
<p>A discharge petition can circumvent the majority leadership if 218 House members sign it; it has been used to pressure Speaker Mike Johnson multiple times this year — most recently to pass legislation on the so-called Epstein files.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and other members of the Ukraine Caucus have offered sanctions legislation alongside Sens. Richard Blumenthal (D-Conn.) and Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.). Fitzpatrick <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/house-resolution/438?s=1&amp;r=3" target="_blank">filed a resolution</a> earlier this year setting up a possible effort to discharge that bill but did not immediately trigger it.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers could also force a vote on a bill from Reps. Gregory Meeks (D-N.Y.) and Steny Hoyer (D-Md.) that would pair Russia sanctions with assistance for Ukraine. The bipartisan Ukraine Caucus is set to hold a virtual meeting Monday to “talk about what the best strategy is to get something done quickly,” Fitzpatrick said in an interview Friday.</p> 
<p>“We’re talking about potentially moving them together if the sanctions are not brought to the floor in short order,” Fitzpatrick said ahead of his social media post.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick said he has been talking to Johnson about the sanctions bill and believes the speaker is supportive of the legislation. Noticing his intention to force a vote now, with the House leaving for a weeklong recess, effectively gives Johnson until early December to find an off-ramp.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ghislaine Maxwell will plead Fifth in House Epstein probe, Comer says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/ghislaine-maxwell-plead-fifth-house-oversight-00664640</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a785-d739-a3ba-fffd93bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 13:26:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ghislaine Maxwell, the convicted co-conspirator of the late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, will refuse to answer questions in the House Oversight Committee's probe into Epstein and the Justice Department’s handling of the case, Oversight Chair James Comer said.</p> 
<p>Maxwell's legal team said she would invoke her Fifth Amendment rights if she sat with congressional investigators, the Kentucky Republican said in an interview. He also suggested it would be unlikely that his staff or lawmakers would sit down with Maxwell, who is in a federal prison camp in Texas, under the circumstances.</p> 
<p>“Her lawyers have replied that she's not going to answer any questions," Comer said. "She's only going to plead the Fifth. I mean, I could spend a bunch of taxpayer dollars to send staff and members down there, and if she's going to plead the Fifth, I don’t know that that's a good investment.”</p> 
<p>Comer <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/23/congress/epstein-james-comer-subpoena-ghislaine-maxwell-testify-00471644" target="_blank">issued a subpoena</a> in July for Maxwell’s testimony, and her legal team initially suggested that she would be willing to answer questions <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/29/congress/maxwell-makes-demands-00481769" target="_blank">under certain conditions</a>, including that her appeals had been resolved. The Supreme Court recently rejected a request to revisit her conviction.</p> 
<p>In return for her cooperation, Maxwell requested immunity from further criminal proceedings and to receive questions in advance. Comer said both immunity and advanced notice was a nonstarter.</p> 
<p>An attorney for Maxwell, David Oscar Markus, did not immediately return a message seeking comment. He signed a July letter saying Maxwell "will have no choice but to invoke her Fifth Amendment rights" unless her demands were met.</p> 
<p>Maxwell was sentenced to 20 years in prison in 2022 on child sex trafficking charges. In the context of government investigations, the Fifth Amendment protects against witnesses from being forced to give testimony that would potentially incriminate themselves.</p> 
<p>Maxwell sat for a two-day interview with the Justice Department in July and shortly afterward was transferred to the minimum security facility in Texas. Critics have argued she has received favorable treatment from the administration. Maxwell is also preparing a commutation application for President Donald Trump's consideration.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This House GOP centrist is plotting a new health care bill aimed at winning over Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-bill-00664635</link>
      <description>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick wants to pair an extension of Obamacare subsidies with new flexibility for health savings accounts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-a779-d739-a3ba-fffd33380000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 12:33:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/89/1f/76c377164f26953c2731101ac4a9/u-s-congress-94407.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“We’re going to have to move quickly,” Fitzpatrick said.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/89/1f/76c377164f26953c2731101ac4a9/u-s-congress-94407.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A key House Republican moderate is drafting a new bill that would extend soon-to-expire Obamacare subsidies and offer a carrot to try to win over more-conservative GOP colleagues and President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.), who co-chairs the bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus, outlined in an interview Friday several elements he is eyeing for the new proposal: an extension of the Affordable Care Act tax credits, with income limits and required minimum premium payments; new flexibility for health savings accounts, a conservative priority aimed at wooing Trump and conservatives; and potentially a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2025/09/08/can-congress-revive-pbm-reform-00549936" target="_blank">stalled bipartisan package</a> overhauling the role of pharmaceutical benefit managers.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, who has been working with fellow GOP centrists who are desperate to address the subsidy cliff, said it was “our hope” that they would soon introduce a bill encompassing those provisions.</p> 
<p>“We’re going to have to move quickly,” he said.</p> 
<p>The proposal would be <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/rick-scott-releases-obamacare-subsidy-alternative-00664146" target="_blank">competing with</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/cassidy-fund-hsas-trump-aca-subsidies-00655213" target="_blank">multiple alternatives</a> from conservative Republicans who are proposing to at least partially end the federal subsidies for plans purchased on Affordable Care Act exchanges, replacing them with individual accounts that they say would give Americans more flexibility to purchase health care.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and his allies are open to moving toward more flexibility for HSAs, but they don’t want to allow the Obamacare tax credits to expire as well. Some in the group strongly believe they need to focus on extending the existing subsidies first, then develop a broader health care overhaul.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and several other Republicans in the Problem Solvers group spoke about their health care plans during a private dinner Thursday night. Bacon <a href="http://politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/21/congress/house-denounces-horrors-of-socialism-00664412" target="_blank">rolled out a separate bipartisan plan</a> Friday with GOP Rep. Jeff Hurd of Colorado and Democratic Reps. Tom Suozzi of New York and Josh Gottheimer of New Jersey that would extend the subsidies for two years, albeit with new restrictions on eligibility.</p> 
<p>But Fitzpatrick said that, based on conversations with colleagues, more than an extension will need to be included in order to attract a critical mass of GOP votes. Trump and top House GOP leaders have signaled they are opposed to continuing the ACA tax credits, and scores of House Republicans have signaled the same.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise, asked about the centrist Republicans’ aims in an interview Friday, said GOP leaders had other plans. He indicated Republicans are planning to bring legislation dealing with HSA flexibility, the PBM overhaul, cost-sharing reductions and other conservative policies to the floor in the coming weeks — but not an ACA tax-credit extension.</p> 
<p>“There are a lot of really good ideas that we're going to be bringing to the floor for votes that lower premiums for families, bring more transparency and more options for families,” he said.</p> 
<p>When asked if GOP leaders believe it’s tenable to allow the subsidies to expire, letting those other policies fill the gap, he replied: “We don't have all the final things agreed upon, and we will work through it with our whole conference.”</p> 
<p>The House GOP centrists feel left in the lurch by their own leaders, who have followed the lead of more conservative factions in advocating for the subsidies to expire. But they’ve also been angered by moderate Democrats, who they say are insisting on first sketching out a larger “framework” for negotiations.</p> 
<p>Democrats have been cool to the GOP proposals that would substitute individual spending accounts for the existing subsidies, arguing that they would not fully fill the financial gap for many Americans and could <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/11/obamacare-could-collapse-under-trumps-new-plan-policy-experts-say-00647246" target="_blank">destabilize health insurance markets</a>.</p> 
<p>One House Republican who was at the Thursday night dinner said colleagues spent a large portion of the evening kvetching about Democrats, whom they remain angry at after the lengthy government shutdown.</p> 
<p>“We’re past talking about frameworks,” said another House Republican, who was granted anonymity to speak candidly about the internal discussions. “This is an emergency.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
