<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 19:00:36 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Insurers point to providers, drugmakers for driving up health costs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/insurers-point-to-providers-drugmakers-for-driving-up-health-costs-00740427</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e2f9-d9a8-a7bf-e6fb0d7a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 19:00:36 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Health insurance CEOs testifying before Congress about whether they're to blame for soaring health care costs have a plan: pass the buck.</p> 
<p>Five CEOs of major insurers will make the case that the health care premiums they set are rising because of prices charged by other health care players — like hospitals and drugmakers — according to their prepared testimony.</p> 
<p>The insurer blueprint comes as the industry is under immense public and political pressure to address rising health care costs, especially after enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies expired last year, sending Obamacare premiums skyrocketing for millions.</p> 
<p>The well-heeled CEOs of some of America's biggest insurance companies aren’t used to groveling, but want to keep lawmakers on their side and avoid any viral moment under cross-examination. The questioning could be tough, considering President Donald Trump called their firms “money sucking Insurance Companies” this month on Truth Social.</p> 
<p>The CEOs will testify before the Energy and Commerce Health Subcommittee Thursday morning, before facing the Ways and Means panel later in the day. In their testimonies, they'll attempt to reverse the narrative that they're at fault for how unaffordable American health care has become.</p> 
<p>“The cost of health insurance is driven by the cost of health care. It is a symptom, not a cause,” said UnitedHealth Group CEO Stephen Hemsley in his prepared testimony. “Premium rates are based on two key factors: how much care is used and how much is charged for that care. When the price of care goes up and care activity increases, the cost of health coverage necessarily follows.”</p> 
<p>Whether the administration buys that is a different story.</p> 
<p>Trump has applied pressure, calling on the companies to slash prices and saying he’d convene the CEOs to secure commitments similar to ones he’s received from the pharmaceutical industry to reduce drug prices.</p> 
<p>In their testimony, the CEOs will highlight affordability-related policies they hope Congress will take up — from reforming how providers are paid to digitizing Americans' health records. The insurers plan to emphasize steps they’ve taken, including commitments to the Trump administration last year to speed up their processes for approving treatments.</p> 
<p>Hemsley, CEO of UnitedHealth Group, the nation’s largest insurer, <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/unitedhealth-return-obamacare-profits-to-customers-00738928" target="_blank">pledged in his testimony</a> to return any profits the company makes on Obamacare plans in 2026 to customers.</p> 
<p>“Our message as an industry is that we're advocates for affordability,” Mike Tuffin, CEO of health insurance trade group AHIP, told POLITICO. “We're the only part of the system that gets up every day working to lower costs. We're doing everything we can to shield consumers from high and rising health care costs.”</p> 
<p>Elevance Health CEO Gail Boudreaux plans to point out that hospital care, doctor services and prescription drugs “have been the largest contributors” to rising U.S. health care spending, <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/national-health-spending-soars-in-2024-00728963" target="_blank">which grew 7.2 percent to $5.3 trillion in 2024</a>. Cigna CEO David Cordani will highlight data showing hospital prices surged in recent decades — a trend he says has been compounded by hospital acquisitions and private-equity ownership of provider practices.</p> 
<p>Some of the executives plan to compare insurers' thin profit margins to other health care industries’. Insurer profit margins were about 1.8 percent in 2025, according to the National Association of Insurance Commissioners. Drug companies' margins are between 20 to 40 percent, Cordani plans to point out.</p> 
<p>Hospitals and drug companies have long made the case that insurers aren’t so innocent. The American Hospital Association, in <a href="https://www.aha.org/system/files/media/file/2026/01/AHA-Statement-to-House-E-C-Subcommittee-for-Hearing-on-Lowering-Health-Care-Costs.pdf" target="_blank">a statement submitted</a> ahead of the hearing, said “actions by many commercial insurers erect barriers that make it more difficult for patients to receive timely access to needed medical care.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jeffries urged opposition to contempt recommendation for the Clintons</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/jeffries-urged-opposition-to-clintons-contempt-resolution-00740222</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e2b1-dabb-ad9f-fffd88690000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 17:36:30 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries urged opposition to a contempt recommendation for Bill and Hillary Clinton before the House Oversight panel ultimately voted to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/9-democrats-vote-to-hold-bill-clinton-in-contempt-of-congress-for-evading-epstein-testimony-00739940" target="_blank">send the measures to the floor</a> Wednesday, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss the whipping efforts.</p> 
<p>Nine Democrats joined Republicans in supporting the measure to hold former President Bill Clinton in contempt of Congress for defying a congressional subpoena over Jeffrey Epstein. Three Democrats joined Republicans in supporting the measure for former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Jeffries pointed to earlier remarks from the minority leader in which he suggested the Justice Department should instead be held in contempt for failing to hand over the Epstein documents by their December deadline.</p> 
<p>The spokesperson declined to provide further comment.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin (D-Md.) spoke with Democrats on the Oversight panel this morning at the behest of the minority leader, according to one of the two people.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-21T18:51:08-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Ethanol deal in sight as GOP leaders haggle over funding bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/ethanol-deal-funding-bill-00740048</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e29c-dabb-ad9f-fffda94e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 17:12:30 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>GOP leaders are nearing a potential compromise with farm-state Republicans that will allow a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">$1.2 trillion government funding package</a>to move forward Thursday after a key ethanol provision was omitted, according to four people granted anonymity to comment on private negotiations.</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> is discussing whether to include the provision allowing year-round sales of E15 fuel in a supplemental spending bill the Senate is working on moving this year to help farmers with tariff impacts or passing a separate House measure in the coming weeks. Separately, GOP leaders are working through issues with House Freedom Caucus members over possible amendment votes, according to two of the people and three other people granted anonymity to describe the deliberations.</p> 
<p>About a dozen House Republicans <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/farm-groups-appeal-to-trump-to-add-on-e15-in-fragile-government-funding-package-00739259" target="_blank">met with Johnson about the matter</a> late Wednesday morning, some of whom had threatened to oppose a procedural move vote to advance the funding package Thursday unless Johnson added on the E15 provision. Key farm and energy groups also pushed for the measure to be included at a meeting with White House officials Wednesday.</p> 
<p>But those groups came away from the meeting with no commitments from the Trump administration, according to two other people granted anonymity to describe the private meeting. White House officials told the groups that including E15 in the supplemental package would be a better option for ethanol proponents than the funding bill now headed for passage, explaining the administration did not want to risk a government shutdown over the issue.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> told reporters Wednesday evening he did not expect the base text of the bill to change before it is called up on the floor Thursday, meaning the ethanol provision would have to find another path to enactment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>9 Democrats vote to hold Bill Clinton in contempt of Congress for evading Epstein testimony</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/9-democrats-vote-to-hold-bill-clinton-in-contempt-of-congress-for-evading-epstein-testimony-00739940</link>
      <description>The House will now have to decide on whether to refer contempt charges against the ex-president, and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton, to the DOJ.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e25b-d1ea-a5df-f2dfaeee0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:06:27 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/81/40/0d91caa84f0dbecf279d093c4f41/u-s-congress-06213.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Oversight Committee Ranking Member Robert Garcia (D-Calif.) and Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) preside over a markup on holding Bill Clinton and Hillary Clinton in contempt of Congress on Jan. 21, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/81/40/0d91caa84f0dbecf279d093c4f41/u-s-congress-06213.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nine Democrats on the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee voted with Republicans Wednesday to recommend holding former President Bill Clinton in contempt of Congress for defying a subpoena to testify as part of the panel's investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>Three Democrats sided with Republicans in voting for a separate measure to recommend also holding former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in contempt.</p> 
<p>Their votes underscore the continued pressure Democrats are under to remain consistent in their calls for transparency and accountability in the Epstein case — no matter the person or the party affiliation or the dire consequences.</p> 
<p>The contempt reports now head to the House floor. Assuming the measures advance, the administration could choose to prosecute the former first couple, which could lead to potential jail time for one or both.</p> 
<p>For Hillary Clinton especially, it could mark the culmination of President Donald Trump’s decadelong hostility towards his 2016 political rival, who he repeatedly called to be put behind bars for using a private email server while leading the State Department.</p> 
<p>“No witness – not a former president or a private citizen — may willfully defy a duly issued congressional subpoena without consequence,” said House Oversight Committee chair James Comer (R-Ky.). “But that is what the Clintons did, and that is why we are here today.”</p> 
<p>Reps. Maxwell Frost of Florida, Raja Krishnamoorthi of Illinois, Summer Lee of Pennsylvania, Emily Randall of Washington, Lateefah Simon of California, Melanie Stansbury of New Mexico and Rashida Tlaib of Michigan, alongside Reps. Stephen Lynch and Ayanna Pressley of Massachusetts, joined Republicans in voting in favor of holding Bill Clinton in contempt. Two Democrats — Yassamin Ansari of Arizona and Dave Min of California — voted “present.”</p> 
<p>Lee, Stansbury and Tlaib voted in favor of holding Hillary Clinton in contempt, with one Democrat, Min, recording himself as “present.”</p> 
<p>Comer issued subpoenas to the Clintons as part of his committee’s Epstein probe. Though Bill Clinton has not been implicated in any illegal activity, he had a well-documented relationship with the late disgraced financier and lawmakers on both sides of the aisle have been eager for information about what he might know.</p> 
<p>But Republicans have sought to position Epstein as an alternative bogeyman to Trump, who also has not been accused of coordination in Epstein’s sex trafficking scheme but has been at the center of Democrats’ focus in demanding all federal case files related to Epstein be released.</p> 
<p>The Clintons have maintained that Comer’s subpoenas are not tied to a legitimate legislative purpose and are therefore invalid. They have also accused Comer of pursuing partisan antics designed to put them in prison.</p> 
<p>Like other public figures who received subpoenas from the Oversight panel in the Epstein probe, the Clintons submitted sworn declarations to the panel. In their written statements, the former first couple attested to their lack of knowledge about the criminal activities of both Epstein and his associate, Ghislaine Maxwell.</p> 
<p>The Clintons also, through their legal team, negotiated with the panel for months to determine terms for an appearance before lawmakers and staff investigators. Bill Clinton had offered to sit down for an interview with Comer and his staff, but Comer rejected the proposed conditions.</p> 
<p>In a statement on social media Wednesday morning before the contempt vote, <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/2013982202443292796" target="_blank"><u>a Clinton spokesperson said</u></a>, “We have offered to help, we have helped, and to this very moment we are ready to help. But the Republicans REFUSE to say YES.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia (D-Calif.), the committee’s top Democrat, voted against the contempt resolutions, saying he also wanted Bill Clinton to answer his panel’s questions but arguing Comer was applying different standards to witnesses.</p> 
<p>“Where is the pressure to get [Attorney General] Pam Bondi to release the files?” Garcia said. “Instead, you are focusing the committee's focus on whoever you perceive to be you, your enemies and the enemies of Donald Trump.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘I’m for it’: Johnson endorses impeachment for judges who rule against Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/johnson-backs-judicial-impeachment-00739286</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e1d7-d36f-a99b-efdf39080000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:39:45 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson now supports the push inside his party to bring impeachment articles against judges perceived as antagonistic of President Donald Trump’s agenda — a notable shift for the Louisiana Republican who over the summer sought to squelch such effort.</p> 
<p>"I'm for it," Johnson told reporters at his weekly news conference Wednesday, responding to the question of whether he would endorse impeaching judges who have ruled against the administration.</p> 
<p>A symbol of this ongoing effort has been James Boasberg, a U.S. district judge who ruled last year that the Trump administration's abrupt deportation of 137 men violated their due process rights and defied court orders to keep them in U.S. custody.</p> 
<p>Trump allies and Hill conservatives have argued Boasberg is an activist who ought to be ousted from the bench. Johnson, over the summer, tried to tamp down the enthusiasm among hard-liners to remove him.</p> 
<p>But judicial impeachment cries among House and Senate Republicans have flared up again in recent weeks. Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas) has written to Johnson urging him to take up impeachment proceedings against Boasberg, while the Judiciary committees of both chambers have held hearings on the matter broadly.</p> 
<p>Judicial activist Mike Davis also spoke with the Republican Study Committee earlier this month about the mechanics of impeaching Boasberg. Though he acknowledged that the party does not have the votes to impeach or remove Boasberg or others, Davis advised lawmakers to put the judge through the process as a punishment.</p> 
<p>Johnson also acknowledged Wednesday that "impeachment" would be "an extreme measure” and “we’ll see where it goes.”</p> 
<p>He added, however, that “some of these judges have gotten so far outside the bounds of where they're supposed to operate [that] it would not be, in my view, a bad thing for Congress to lay down the law, so to speak, and … make an example of some of the egregious abuses.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Democrats come out en masse against DHS funding bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/house-democrats-dhs-funding-00738894</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e16c-d887-a39b-f77e25790000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:40:15 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Only a handful of House Democrats are expected to back a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">DHS funding bill</a> this week after top party leaders spoke out against it during a closed-door caucus meeting Wednesday, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the meeting.</p> 
<p>Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" target="_blank" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> was among the many Democrats who spoke out against the bill, two of the people said. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/226960" target="_blank" data-person-id="226960">Pete Aguilar</a> of California, the No. 3 Democratic leader, later told reporters he was against the bill and that leaders heard “overwhelmingly” from members that this bill did not do enough to rein in ICE following recent clashes in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“We'll be voting no unless there are any substantive changes or amendments,” Aguilar said, confirming that other members of leadership also spoke out against the bill.</p> 
<p>One of the few House Democrats openly defending the bill is Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" target="_blank" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a> of Texas, who helped negotiate the legislation as the lead Democrat on the Homeland Security Appropriations subcommittee.</p> 
<p>He told reporters he understands his colleagues’ concerns about reported ICE abuses but cautioned that the alternative was worse — a continuing resolution for the department that he characterized as a “blank check.” The negotiated bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/congress-clinches-funding-deal-for-dhs-pentagon-domestic-agencies-00735698" target="_blank">includes $20 million for body cameras</a> and guardrails to prevent the transfer of funds between agencies, among other modest restrictions.</p> 
<p>“I'd rather have some provisions and no provisions at all,” he said, noting that the agency separately received billions of dollars under the GOP megabill last year. “The alternative would be a blank check, and I don't want to give them a blank check.”</p> 
<p>But many of Cuellar’s fellow appropriators view the matter differently. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307305" target="_blank" data-person-id="307305">Lauren Underwood</a> (D-Ill.), another member of the DHS subcommittee, said <a href="https://x.com/RepUnderwood/status/2013742968792834400" target="_blank">in a post on X</a> that she would be voting against it.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/134505" target="_blank" data-person-id="134505">Glenn Ivey</a> (D-Md.) also said he plans to vote against the bill and predicted a majority of fellow Democratic appropriators would join him. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51325" target="_blank" data-person-id="51325">Jim Clyburn</a> (D-S.C.), a senior appropriator and former party leader, said he is leaning no, while Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/381227" target="_blank" data-person-id="381227">Frank Mrvan</a> (D-Ind.) said he was undecided.</p> 
<p>Republicans should have the votes to pass the DHS funding measure without Democratic help, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/embarrassing-floor-meltdown-has-house-republicans-questioning-their-leaders-00730119" target="_blank">attendance has been an issue</a> for House GOP leaders in recent weeks. They warned in their own closed-door party meeting Wednesday that Thursday’s planned vote could be close and that they needed to immediately share any concerns they might have about the bill, according to two people granted anonymity to describe the private comments.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-21T10:55:07-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Judge denies lawmaker request for ‘independent monitor’ to oversee Epstein files release</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/epstein-files-release-request-00738707</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e13b-d36f-a99b-efbb3f060000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:49:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A federal judge on Wednesday <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.nysd.539612/gov.uscourts.nysd.539612.844.0.pdf" target="_blank">denied a request</a> by Reps. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) and Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) to appoint an <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/massie-khanna-jeffrey-epstein-files-release-00717659" target="_blank">independent monitor</a> to oversee the Justice Department’s disclosure of files related to Jeffrey Epstein, while conceding the lawmakers have raised “legitimate concerns” about the department’s compliance with the law.</p> 
<p>In a 7-page opinion, U.S. District Judge Paul Engelmayer wrote that his supervision of the criminal case against Epstein’s co-conspirator Ghislaine Maxwell doesn’t grant him <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.nysd.539612/gov.uscourts.nysd.539612.844.0.pdf" target="_blank">“any charter to supervise”</a> whether the Justice Department meets its legal obligation to disclose the files.</p> 
<p>But he noted that his order didn’t foreclose the lawmakers’ right to sue over the matter. And Engelmayer, an Obama appointee, added that both the lawmakers and victims “raise legitimate concerns about whether DOJ is faithfully complying with federal law.”</p> 
<p>Khanna said in a brief interview that they were considering filing their own lawsuit to ensure that the materials were released."We're looking at all the options," he said.</p> 
<p>Massie and Khanna authored the law Congress passed late last year mandating the department to make millions of pages of materials related to the late convicted sex offender public by Dec. 19. Instead, the department released a few tranches of material in late December but has disclosed in court filings that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/doj-epstein-files-timing-delays-00712169" target="_blank">millions of additional pages</a> remain unreleased.</p> 
<p>In addition to the disclosure delays, the lawmakers have complained that the Justice Department has improperly redacted certain information from the files.</p> 
<p><i>Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this post misspelled Paul Engelmayer's name.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-21T11:28:00-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House Oversight to depose Ghislaine Maxwell</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/maxwell-to-be-deposed-00738705</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e131-d887-a39b-f77315af0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:36:33 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ghislaine Maxwell, the longtime co-conspirator of Jeffrey Epstein, will sit for a deposition before the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee on Feb. 9, Chair James Comer said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The announcement came during a markup of contempt measures for Bill and Hillary Clinton, who refused to comply with subpoenas to sit for scheduled depositions last week as part of the panel's Epstein probe.</p> 
<p>Comer, a Kentucky Republican, had previously said he did not intend to send his staff to interview Maxwell, who is now serving a 20-year sentence at a prison camp in Texas for her part in Epstein's trafficking scheme. Maxwell's legal team had indicated she would plead her Fifth Amendment rights in declining to cooperate with lawmakers' questioning.</p> 
<p>The deposition is expected to be virtual.</p> 
<p>In a letter to Comer dated Jan. 20, however, Maxwell's attorneys maintained that her posture had not changed regarding her Fifth Amendment rights. The lawyers also requested that the deposition be delayed until Maxwell's legal proceedings had resolved.</p> 
<p>"Put plainly, proceeding under these circumstances would serve no other purpose than pure political theater and a complete waste of taxpayer monies," the attorneys wrote. "The Committee would obtain no testimony, no answers, and no new facts."</p> 
<p>They added that Maxwell would testify in a public forum if she were to receive clemency — a presidential power that President Donald Trump has not ruled out.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Lawmakers nearly at the funding finish line</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/21/congress/appropriations-shutdown-deadline-rule-vote-00738537</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-defc-d22e-a1db-dffd798b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is on track to avoid another shutdown, but it needs to clear several hurdles in a short amount of time in order to beat its month-end deadline.</p> 
<p>The pressure is on the House to pass four of the most challenging spending bills Thursday — to fund the departments of Defense, HHS, Labor, HUD, Transportation, Education and Homeland Security — then bundle them up with the two-bill package the chamber previously passed to fund Financial Services and State-Foreign Operations.</p> 
<p>Senators will then have one week to take a big swing at passing all six bills before sending them to President Donald Trump’s desk.</p> 
<p>Passing all 12 annual appropriations bills would be a stunning feat for lawmakers and leadership — especially in such a bitterly divided Congress. Here’s what they’ll have to deal with first:</p> 
<p><b>— Spotty attendance:</b> Speaker Mike Johnson’s barely-there majority could pose a problem come Thursday, when the House is expected to vote along party lines to tee up the rule vote allowing the final package of spending bills to come to the floor.</p> 
<p>This dynamic could be further complicated by the fact that House GOP leaders will allow a passage vote for the Homeland measure that’s separate from that of the other funding bills in recognition of its divisiveness.</p> 
<p>Rep. Rosa DeLauro (Conn.), the House’s top Democratic appropriator, said the legislation does not include some of the broader policy changes Democrats proposed, like preventing DHS from detaining and deporting U.S. citizens or from deploying personnel from other agencies to conduct immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>While Republican leaders expect the other bills to pass with broad bipartisan support, Homeland will likely be a tight vote. House Democrats plan to discuss their position on the DHS bill during their closed-door caucus meeting Wednesday morning.</p> 
<p><b>— Any hard-liner opposition:</b> House Freedom Caucus members told POLITICO Tuesday night they are combing through all the earmarks included in this funding package after previously vowing to work vigilantly to block money for projects they don’t like.</p> 
<p>“There’s always trepidation when it comes to earmarks,” Rep. Andrew Clyde (R-Ga.) said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Conservatives are also digging through the details on the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/20/congress/congress-clinches-health-deal-to-crack-down-on-drug-intermediaries-00736680" target="_blank">health care legislation</a> that bipartisan, bicameral leadership hopes will sail through as part of this funding measure. Many Republicans who worked on the deal feel confident that the policies designed to crack down on pharmacy benefit managers, and the extension of several public health programs, will make it across the finish line. But don’t rule out complaints from fiscal hawks at the last minute.</p> 
<p>“I’m fine largely,” Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) told reporters Tuesday night. “But I don’t know, I got to look, see if there’s anything objectionable.”</p> 
<p><b>— Time crunch in the Senate: </b>The Senate is in recess this week, but it is due to return Monday — if travel back to Washington isn’t <a href="https://x.com/capitalweather/status/2013791098133512241?s=20" target="_blank">derailed by snow</a> this weekend. At that point, there will be just five days until the Jan. 30 deadline, and leaders will need to get all 100 senators on board with fast-tracking passage of the final six-bill package. That’s assuming the House, which is scheduled to be in recess next week, passes it without incident.</p> 
<p>Senate leaders may have to offer amendment votes to get holdouts on both sides of the aisle to come on board, which could quickly become a slippery political slope — or they risk dragging out procedural votes beyond the funding cliff.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Clinton contempt vote: </b>The House Oversight Committee votes on two measures at 10 a.m. Wednesday over whether to recommend holding Bill and Hillary Clinton in contempt of Congress for defying subpoenas to testify in the panel’s Jeffrey Epstein investigation. Keep an eye on Democrats, who will have to decide whether they will side with Republicans to advance the contempt resolutions to the chamber floor — where, if adopted by the full House, the consequences for the Clintons could be as dire as imprisonment by the Trump DOJ. One person granted anonymity to share internal party dynamics said it was looking like most Oversight Democrats will vote “yes.”</p> 
<p><b>— House vote on mining CRA: </b>The House will consider a resolution Wednesday afternoon that would overturn the Biden administration’s ban on new mining near Minnesota’s Boundary Waters under the Congressional Review Act. A House aide granted anonymity to discuss the dynamics said to expect a nail-biter.</p> 
<p><b>— New crypto text landing: </b>Senate Agriculture Chair John Boozman (R-Ark.) is preparing to release an updated draft of his panel’s portion of a major cryptocurrency bill Wednesday. It comes after the senator postponed a previously planned markup to allow bipartisan discussions to continue around the so-called market structure measure.</p> 
<p><i>Katherine Tully-McManus, Benjamin Guggenheim, Jordain Carney, Josh Siegel, Hailey Fuchs, Meredith Lee Hill and Jasper Goodman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump’s Greenland tariffs could squeeze Hill Republicans</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-greenland-tariffs-congress-00738472</link>
      <description>Democrats plan to force House and Senate votes within weeks that stand to put GOP lawmakers on the spot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-de6e-dd3c-a5df-fe7eabca0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:44:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/6a/ff/62d854104c0fb56a443744648156/u-s-congress-81395.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) walks to a vote at the U.S. Capitol on Dec. 15, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/6a/ff/62d854104c0fb56a443744648156/u-s-congress-81395.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump’s threat to weaponize steep new tariffs as part of his bid to acquire Greenland could soon put queasy Republicans on the spot.</p> 
<p>House and Senate Democrats plan to force votes as soon as next month to block the European tariffs Trump announced over the weekend, according to two aides granted anonymity to disclose private scheduling. That, for now, is likely to be the main avenue of congressional accountability as the president amps up his campaign targeting the icy Danish territory.</p> 
<p>Democrats are waiting for Trump to file his executive order, but once he does, a resolution would ripen about 20 days later, according to one Senate aide granted anonymity to describe internal planning.</p> 
<p>While some lawmakers have floated using the spending legislation now moving through Congress ahead of next week’s government funding deadline as a way to block Trump, leaders of both parties are wary of taking any steps that could lead to a government shutdown. And, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/denmark-greenland-vote-congress-00735132" target="_blank">as POLITICO first reported</a>, Danish officials have privately urged against forcing a vote on a separate war powers authorization unless it has overwhelming bipartisan support.</p> 
<p>But the 10 percent tariffs threatened against Denmark, France, Germany, the U.K. and four other countries that recently sent a small contingent of troops to Greenland offer a clear opportunity for congressional pushback from Republicans uneasy about the geopolitics of Trump’s audacious demands, their own free-trade views or a combination of both.</p> 
<p>The Greenland reckoning comes as the House prepares to come off the sidelines on the gamut of Trump’s second-term tariffs. Speaker Mike Johnson has so far been able to shield Trump — and his own GOP members — from a direct confrontation over the president's aggressive levies, which have sparked private heartburn among some Republicans.</p> 
<p>But that appears to be coming to an end. A procedural maneuver that blocked efforts to cancel prior Trump tariffs expires next week, and Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/01/16/funding-crunch-threatens-house-recess-00733035" target="_blank">no firm plan to extend</a> the protections for the president. Already one House Republican — Rep. Don Bacon of Nebraska — says he is likely to oppose any effort by Johnson to block a cancellation of the Greenland-related tariffs from coming to the floor.</p> 
<p>“It's crazy — they're an ally, and we’ve alienated our good friends,” Bacon said Tuesday about Trump’s move targeting the Danes and other NATO countries that have backed them.</p> 
<p>With Republicans holding a threadbare House majority, and Democrats outnumbering them on some days, even one or two GOP defectors might be able to quash any effort to prevent a tariff vote.</p> 
<p>Three Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/16/congress/house-again-votes-to-surrender-tariff-powers-to-trump-00566975" target="_blank">voted in September against Johnson’s last effort</a> to block tariff votes: Reps. Kevin Kiley of California, Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Victoria Spartz of Indiana, who could be likely allies of Bacon.</p> 
<p>Rep. Tom McClintock (R-Calif.) also said he would oppose any effort to prevent tariff votes and doesn't support the president's plan to impose new trade levies on European countries over Greenland.</p> 
<p>“I think that the Trump economic policies overall are having a tremendous positive effect on the economy. I think the tariffs are hurting. And when you're trying to accelerate, it doesn't make much sense to tap on the brakes,” McClintock said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) said Trump’s plan to slap financial penalties on European allies over Greenland is a “bad idea” and that he wants to know the rationale for preventing a vote on blocking them. Fitzpatrick didn’t say how he would vote if he had the chance.</p> 
<p>“My sense is that he’s trying to gain leverage, but I still don’t support the rhetoric,” Fitzpatrick said. “Denmark has given us full access to the country, they’re a NATO ally. There’s no reason for any of this.”</p> 
<p>Republicans are already on edge as they await a ruling from the Supreme Court about Trump’s ability to use emergency powers to implement tariffs at will. The justices skipped an opportunity to issue a decision Tuesday, and it could be a month or more before they rule.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) said the legality of Trump’s latest tariff threat over Greenland is “a question that I have not seen answered yet.” He said he was wary of allowing a president to deploy tariffs as a way to secure new territory.</p> 
<p>“I think if it’s to address trade imbalances or trade abuses … then that’s the sort of thing where tariffs are certainly appropriate," Hurd said. “Outside of that context, I think it gets more problematic.”</p> 
<p>Johnson largely sidestepped a question Tuesday night on Trump’s threat to use tariffs as the latest salvo in his bid to acquire Greenland. He downplayed the odds of a conflict, saying that the U.S. has “great allies” and “everybody there wants to work towards a solution together.”</p> 
<p>The Senate is likely to pass a resolution to block the Greenland-related tariffs when it comes up for a vote. Already three Republicans — Sens. Rand Paul of Kentucky, Lisa Murkowski of Alaska and Thom Tillis of North Carolina — have publicly bashed Trump’s tariffs and urged Congress to take back its institutional prerogatives. Democrats would only need to pick up four GOP votes, and Sens. Susan Collins (R-Maine) and Mitch McConnell (R-Ky.) have both been publicly critical of Trump’s Greenland threats and previously supported resolutions targeting Trump’s other tariffs.</p> 
<p>“The way we are going about projecting power in the Arctic is costly, divisive and unnecessary,” Tillis said during a POLITICO panel Tuesday at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.</p> 
<p>The House and Senate both voting to block Trump’s tariffs would be a significant moment — marking the first time both chambers have moved to check Trump's most controversial trade tactic. But the president would surely veto such an effort, and there are no signs he is yet facing the type of GOP jailbreak that would allow Congress to override him.</p> 
<p>But forcing a vote stands to make things uncomfortable for those in the GOP who have tried to telegraph their discomfort with the Greenland push without fully breaking with Trump.</p> 
<p>Sen. John Barrasso (R-Wyo.), for instance, sidestepped weighing in directly on Trump’s latest tariff threat Tuesday, instead saying that the president has “been a strong supporter of tariffs.”</p> 
<p>“We've had a great relationship with them in the past, and there's a significant military presence,” Barrasso added on Greenland. “We need to build on that.”</p> 
<p>House Democrats, meanwhile, are seizing on the momentum to try to squeeze their GOP counterparts.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.), the top Democrat on the Rules Committee, recited Tillis’ and Murkowski’s remarks during a meeting of the panel Tuesday. He pressed Rep. Adrian Smith of Nebraska, a tariff-skeptical Republican who was testifying on an unrelated bill, whether he would support an effort by Johnson to block a vote on the Greenland-related tariffs.</p> 
<p>Smith said he would “prefer to vote on tariffs, certainly,” while adding he would need to look over any new language before making a commitment.</p> 
<p>“I wasn’t expecting to have this discussion,” Smith said, later adding: “I’ve been on the record for saying I’m not a fan of tariffs.”</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congress clinches bipartisan health deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/20/congress/congress-clinches-health-deal-to-crack-down-on-drug-intermediaries-00736680</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-dc32-d22e-a1db-df3721690000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:17:39 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congressional leaders reached a bipartisan, bicameral health care deal early Tuesday morning they hope lawmakers will pass later this week as part of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">four-bill government spending package</a>. </p> 
<p>Alongside funding for the departments of Defense, Transportation, Labor, Health and Human Services and Homeland Security through Sept. 30, senior appropriators are proposing a crackdown on drug intermediates known as pharmacy benefit managers, or PBMs. </p> 
<p>Lawmakers in both parties and chambers have been working toward reaching a compromise in this policy area for months after a PBM overhaul fell out of the December 2024 government funding bill amid criticism from then-President-elect Donald Trump and billionaire ally Elon Musk.</p> 
<p>The health care agreement would extend several public health programs, including major telehealth flexibilities, through the end of 2027. It also would fund, through the end of the fiscal year in 2030, a program run through the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services that reimburses facilities for offering hospital-level care in the home.</p> 
<p>In a major win for Democrats, the deal would boost funding for community health centers to $4.6 billion for fiscal year 2026. Another provision in the package would allow Medicare coverage for multi-cancer early detection screening tests.</p> 
<p>It's not clear whether conservatives in the House will allow the health care deal to go through. Fiscal hawks are due to balk at the spending increases for various programs, and the framework is silent on many of the policies called for last week by President Donald Trump's “Great Healthcare Plan" — including expansions to tax-advantaged health savings accounts and certain policies mandating lower drug prices.</p> 
<p>In a continued blow for members on both sides of the aisle, the agreement also would not revive enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies that lapsed at the end of last year and are causing premiums to spike for individuals on Obamacare insurance plans.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Movement on a health plan, but not Trump’s</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/20/congress/health-care-policy-plan-congress-trump-appropriations-00736100</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-d9dd-d6ec-a99b-dbfd3c320000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawmakers are eyeing a health care deal this week, but it’s far from the “Great Healthcare Plan” that President Donald Trump outlined last Thursday.</p> 
<p>Here’s a rundown of the latest developments and why Trump’s grander ambitions are looking DOA on Capitol Hill:</p> 
<p><b>— The deal Republicans could get:</b> After weeks of committee-level negotiations, congressional leadership and top appropriators on both sides of the aisle have clinched a deal on a smaller and far less contentious health care proposal that could hitch a ride on the next government funding package. Most ideas in the plan had a shot at becoming law in December 2024, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/12/18/congress/musk-opposes-funding-bill-00195021" target="_blank">were torpedoed</a> by Elon Musk and Trump.</p> 
<p>The deal released early Tuesday morning as part of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/congress-clinches-funding-deal-for-dhs-pentagon-domestic-agencies-00735698" target="_blank">$1.2 trillion funding package</a> includes a crackdown on drug intermediaries known as pharmacy benefit managers, renewals of several public health programs and $4.6 billion in funding this fiscal year for community health centers.</p> 
<p>The inclusion of the health agreement has swelled the bill to over 1,000 pages, so keep an eye on House conservatives who have balked in the past over being asked to vote within days on such jam-packed legislation.</p> 
<p><b>— The deal they probably can't clinch: </b>Trump’s broader health care affordability pitch from last week appears to be <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-health-plan-congress-00734445" target="_blank">largely doomed on the Hill</a>, underscoring the extreme difficulty around uniting Republicans on any health plan.</p> 
<p>Among the reasons: Democrats are in no mood to help after a series of health care fights with Republicans this past year, and key parts of Trump’s proposal likely wouldn’t meet the strict Senate rules for party-line legislation that could skirt a Democratic filibuster. Republicans also face major divisions over whether to even pursue more health initiatives using the budget reconciliation process in the first place.</p> 
<p>One House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly about conference dynamics described the appetite among GOP moderates for another major party-line bill — especially a health-focused one — as “not good.”</p> 
<p>“You’re going to need 218 votes, which means you’re going to need to build consensus across the conference on what it is we’re pursuing,” said Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.).</p> 
<p>Another big complication: Many senior Republicans oppose a key part of Trump’s plan — codifying “most favored nation” deals to link some U.S. drug payments to the lower prices paid abroad. Speaker Mike Johnson said last year he was “<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/johnson-not-a-big-fan-of-drug-policy-white-house-wants-for-trumps-megabill-00320974" target="_blank">not a big fan</a>” of the policy when White House officials attempted to squeeze it into the first GOP megabill.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Funding bill finalized: </b>POLITICO reporters will continue to scrub the freshly released <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-db15-dd3c-a5df-fb7f1c4a0000" target="_blank">bipartisan, bicameral text</a> for the Defense, Transportation-HUD, Labor-HHS-Education and Homeland Security bills through the day. The House aims to pass the shutdown-averting bill by Friday, with the Senate acting next week — just ahead of the Jan. 30 deadline.</p> 
<p><b>— Voter registration action:</b> House Majority Leader Steve Scalise is eyeing a vote on revamped legislation that would require proof of citizenship when registering to vote, potentially putting pressure on Senate Majority Leader John Thune to follow suit.</p> 
<p>The House passed the so-called SAVE Act in April with the help of a few Democrats, but it died in the Senate. Scalise in a Fox News Sunday interview this weekend talked up a new version of the bill, which would add a photo ID requirement.</p> 
<p><b>— Expanding the CRA’s reach: </b>Republicans are attempting to use the Congressional Review Act this week to overturn mining protections on public lands for the first time. The House Rules Committee will consider a resolution related to Minnesota’s Boundary Waters wilderness at 3 p.m. Tuesday.</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim, Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Calen Razor and James Bikales contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans will be hard-pressed to pass Trump’s ‘Great Healthcare Plan’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-health-plan-congress-00734445</link>
      <description>A lack of Democratic cooperation and strict Senate rules threaten the legislative viability of the White House framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c886-dd3c-a5df-eafeeecd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/56/39/c94961af4efaa7191bf9c538f540/u-s-congress-46690.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Mike Lawler of New York is among the Republicans questioning a party-line health care push this year.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/56/39/c94961af4efaa7191bf9c538f540/u-s-congress-46690.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Benjamin Guggenheim and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Benjamin Guggenheim and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump announced his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/trump-health-outline-00730933" target="_blank">“Great Healthcare Plan”</a> to little fanfare on Capitol Hill last week.</p> 
<p>The question now is how willing and able congressional Republicans will be to actually pass any of it into law after stumbling for years over politically toxic plans to undo Obamacare. The prognosis is not encouraging for the White House.</p> 
<p>Key parts of the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/The-Great-Healthcare-Plan.pdf" target="_blank">light-on-details proposal</a> likely won’t meet the strict Senate rules for party-line legislation that could skirt a Democratic filibuster. Similar cost-reduction proposals from Republicans ran into problems on that count in last year's tax-cuts-focused megabill.</p> 
<p>White House officials argue the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/trump-health-plan-insurance-pharma-obamacare-00732557" target="_blank">new health care plan features initiatives</a> that should garner bipartisan support, but Democrats are already balking. They’re in no mood to help Republicans out after Trump's megabill slashed Medicaid funding, and they’re still fighting to revive the expired Obamacare subsidies that the Trump plan rejects.</p> 
<p>“Time and again, Donald Trump has made empty promises to the American people about lowering their health care costs, and today’s announcement is no different,” Senate Finance ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51247" data-person-id="51247">Ron Wyden</a> (D-Ore.) said in a statement following the release of the White House framework.</p> 
<p>Even without the procedural hurdles, uniting Republicans behind a health care plan has repeatedly proven next to impossible. The fate of the enhanced Obamacare subsidies roiled the party for months before they lapsed Jan. 1, and now <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698" target="_blank">there are major divisions</a> over whether to pursue more health initiatives using the partisan budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>One key House faction, the conservative Republican Study Committee, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/rsc-reconciliation-framework-megabill-00724594" target="_blank">released a blueprint last week</a> for a party-line bill that included health care provisions, and its leaders now argue Trump’s plan mirrors key parts of it. They are among a significant GOP bloc that sees reconciliation as the only way the party can pass health legislation — or any other substantive policy — ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>“Our framework for a second reconciliation bill includes many of these historic reforms, because that's how we're going to secure real wins for the people who sent us here,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> (R-Texas), who leads the group of nearly 200 House Republicans, said in a statement to POLITICO.</p> 
<p>But vulnerable incumbents have much less of a stomach for taking up a new health care package before Election Day — especially <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/06/republican-medicaid-cuts-midterms-big-beautiful-bill-00440023" target="_blank">after the bruising Medicaid</a> and Obamacare subsidy fights.</p> 
<p>One House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly about conference dynamics described the appetite among GOP moderates for another major party-line bill — especially a health-focused one — as “not good.”</p> 
<p>"You're going to need 218 votes, which means you're going to need to build consensus across the conference on what it is we're pursuing,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.), a centrist in a tough reelection fight who said the RSC’s plans are “not reflective of the entirety of the conference.”</p> 
<p>There’s also major skepticism among Senate Republicans, including some top Trump allies, who understand that many of their ideas don’t qualify under reconciliation rules, which generally allow only for initiatives that are primarily fiscal in nature. Senators have long <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/26/congress/john-thune-senate-parliamentarian-overrule-00425792" target="_blank">deferred to the chamber’s parliamentarian</a> on those judgments.</p> 
<p>“A lot of the reforms my colleagues thought about earlier, the parliamentarian didn’t accept,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.), adding that he expected only “a pretty limited universe” of health care proposals to pass muster.</p> 
<p>Indeed, Senate Republicans tried to include one of Trump’s health care proposals in their megabill last year — funding a kind of insurance subsidy for out-of-pocket payments in a bid to lower premiums for some Obamacare plans. The parliamentarian ultimately ruled the measure was noncompliant.</p> 
<p>Trump’s call for insurers and providers to publish their prices is also unlikely to qualify for inclusion, considering that any fiscal impact of the transparency measures would be purely incidental to the policy.</p> 
<p>Two senior Republicans involved in the internal conversations granted anonymity to speak about them said GOP leaders will likely have to carve out a narrow slice of the Trump health plan to pursue via reconciliation, if that’s even possible. Other pieces, they said, would have to advance through bipartisan talks with Democrats, who have in the past endorsed proposals to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senators-facing-heat-on-affordability-turn-on-drug-industry-middlemen-00659685" target="_blank">crack down on pharmaceutical industry intermediaries</a> who help negotiate drug prices.</p> 
<p>A senior administration official said Thursday that “reconciliation would not be necessary” because the ideas sketched out under the health care framework could get bipartisan support. But at a White House event Friday, Trump acknowledged that was unlikely, saying “the problem we’ll have with this is, we’ll get no Democrat votes.”</p> 
<p>There’s another complication: A key plank of the Trump plan — codifying “most favored nation” drug pricing deals — is opposed by many senior Republicans. Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said last year he was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/johnson-not-a-big-fan-of-drug-policy-white-house-wants-for-trumps-megabill-00320974" target="_blank">"not a big fan" of the policy</a> as White House officials tried unsuccessfully to shoehorn it into the GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Still, many Republicans are making a public show of embracing the Trump framework — including Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.), who quickly reinforced the need for a party-line bill to implement the White House plan after it was released Thursday.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> (R-La.), who chairs a Senate committee dealing with health care, said he would take “action” on some of the president’s proposals, including codifying transparency rules. Meanwhile, House Ways and Means Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> (R-Mo.), who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/jason-smith-reconciliation-2026-00698324" target="_blank">previously expressed deep skepticism</a> about the GOP’s ability to pass another party-line bill, complimented the plan’s “bold vision” and said his panel would move to advance it.</p> 
<p>Any action will be in the hands of the top Republican leaders. Johnson and Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> discussed a second reconciliation bill during their regular weekly meeting last week. Thune said the two will “coordinate” but that the House will be “first movers” on any new partisan package.</p> 
<p>“They’ve got some ideas about what they want to do with it,” Thune said. “As I’ve said before, you’ve got to have a reason to do it.”</p> 
<p><i>Cheyenne Haslett contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘No longer in my hands’: How Hill Republicans stopped caring about DOJ releasing the Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/19/epstein-files-release-delay-00735612</link>
      <description>On the one-month anniversary of the Justice Department missing the deadline to release all the Epstein materials in its possession, Republicans in Congress are largely shrugging their shoulders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-d128-dcbd-afbb-d97b6b6a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/74/93/e617e95646369d8aaae1e86a60dd/epstein-victims-press-conference-us-capitol-23610.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), center, speaks during a press conference with Reps. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.) and victims of Jeffrey Epstein outside the U.S. Capitol in Washington, on Nov. 18, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/74/93/e617e95646369d8aaae1e86a60dd/epstein-victims-press-conference-us-capitol-23610.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One month after the congressionally mandated deadline to release all its files on convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, the Justice Department has made only a fraction of the files public — and it remains silent on its plans to fully comply with the law.</p> 
<p>Also keeping quiet about the DOJ delays are congressional Republicans, almost all of whom voted in November to release the records after spending months heeding President Donald Trump's opposition to the move.</p> 
<p>Some of them are openly admitting it's no longer a priority.</p> 
<p>“I don’t give a rip about Epstein,” Rep. Lauren Boebert (R-Colo.) said last week when she was asked to take stock of the month since the Dec. 19 deadline.</p> 
<p>“Like, there’s so many other things we need to be working on,” she added. “I’ve done what I had to do for Epstein. Talk to somebody else about that. It’s no longer in my hands.”</p> 
<p>Boebert was one of four House Republicans, alongside Thomas Massie of Kentucky, Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and Nancy Mace of South Carolina, who joined with Democrats to force a House floor vote on the Epstein legislation when leadership resisted moving it.</p> 
<p>The White House lobbied these lawmakers heavily to take their names off the discharge petition to compel the bill’s consideration, with administration officials at <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank"><u>one point summoning Boebert</u></a> to the Situation Room for a final plea.</p> 
<p>Now Washington’s attention has since shifted to other political firestorms, from Trump's military action in Venezuela to the shooting of a U.S. citizen by an ICE agent in Minnesota, and congressional Republicans are eager to move on — underscoring the extent to which the GOP remains wary of crossing swords with the president.</p> 
<p>The public falling out between Greene and Trump was largely over Greene’s support for releasing the Epstein files — Trump called her a “traitor” — and ultimately culminated in Greene’s resignation from the House earlier this month. Trump vetoed a bill that would have supported a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/house-will-vote-thursday-to-override-trump-veto-of-two-gop-backed-bills-00711322" target="_blank"><u>water infrastructure project in Boebert’s district</u></a>, and administration officials privately warned Mace that her defiance would likely to cost her the president's endorsement in the South Carolina governor’s race.</p> 
<p>Mace has vowed on social media to “<a href="https://x.com/RepNancyMace/status/2011163899194757197" target="_blank"><u>keep fighting</u></a>” for justice for Epstein's victims but has not otherwise continued the drumbeat against the Justice Department.</p> 
<p>Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), who has worked with Democrats on a House Oversight and Government Reform Committee investigation into the Epstein case, said in a recent interview she's now more more focused on holding Bill and Hillary Clinton in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/clintons-defy-subpoena-to-testify-in-epstein-investigation-risking-being-held-in-contempt-00724394" target="_blank">contempt of Congress</a>for not honoring the panel’s subpoena to testify about Epstein.</p> 
<p>Many of the photos released by the DOJ so far feature the former president consorting with Epstein, and the administration has sought to portray Bill Clinton as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/trump-world-takes-shots-at-favorite-boogeyman-bill-clinton-in-epstein-file-dump-00701780" target="_blank">the real pariah</a>, not Trump. Both men have denied wrongdoing, and neither has been implicated in Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>Pressed on the delays in releasing more records, Luna said the initial deadline was not “realistic” and that “I'm not going to rush the process on that — we're going to get them.”</p> 
<p>House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) is also defending the administration.</p> 
<p>“From my standpoint, the Department of Justice is cooperating,” he told reporters after Bill Clinton defied his subpoena to testify last week. “They are turning over documents. We would all like for them to turn documents over quicker, but at the end of the day, they are complying.”</p> 
<p>Not only has the administration failed to fully release Epstein records in its possession — as mandated in the bill passed overwhelmingly in the House and unanimously in the Senate in November — it has also failed to give its rationales for redactions in the files, as mandated by the statute.</p> 
<p>On Christmas Eve, the Justice Department said the U.S. attorney’s office in the Southern District of New York and the FBI have identified potentially more than a million documents related to Epstein that have yet to be made public, offering no updated timing beyond “<a href="https://x.com/TheJusticeDept/status/2003901580341334257" target="_blank"><u>a few more weeks</u></a>” to complete an internal audit. In a recent court filing, the department said more than 500 people were involved in its review.</p> 
<p>That leaves Massie, who has already <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/thomas-massie-trump-jeffrey-epstein-00654214" target="_blank">burned his bridges</a> with the president for championing the Epstein release effort among other perceived slights, as the lone House Republican now publicly agitating for DOJ compliance.</p> 
<p>“They're in clear violation of the law, and I don't think they've allocated the necessary resources to release these files,” Massie said in an interview. “But I'm most concerned about the over-redaction of the files. … There's a list of things they can redact and a list of things they can't redact in our bill, and they're violating that.”</p> 
<p>In an effort to establish some oversight of the Justice Department’s actions, Massie and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), who together championed the bill to release the Epstein files, have asked a judge in New York to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/massie-khanna-jeffrey-epstein-files-release-00717659" target="_blank">appoint an independent third party</a> to oversee the documents’ release. The judge has since asked the Trump administration to respond to their motion.</p> 
<p>Asked about the waning GOP appetite for accountability around the Epstein files release, Khanna signaled he wasn't concerning himself with that, saying in an interview it was now irrelevant what his Republican colleagues are or are not doing.</p> 
<p>“The law has passed,” he said. “Now it's for the courts. Now it's a legal matter.”</p> 
<p>A Justice Department spokesperson did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>The conversation is due to pick back up on Capitol Hill in early February: Attorney General Pam Bondi <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/bondi-set-to-testify-00729891" target="_blank">is scheduled to testify</a> before the House Judiciary Committee on Feb. 11, after a previous appearance was cancelled due to the prolonged government shutdown. She'll surely face questions about the delays from Democrats, as well as from Massie, who sits on the panel.</p> 
<p>“I'll probably focus my five minutes on the Epstein files and her noncompliance with the law,” Massie said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-20T22:09:38-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Louisiana’s Letlow prepares Senate bid after Trump endorsement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/18/louisianas-letlow-prepares-senate-bid-00735697</link>
      <description>Her entry would be the worst-case scenario for GOP Sen. Bill Cassidy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-d21f-dcbd-afbb-da7f9cdf0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 12:51:32 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/52/48/612e0f9841979aa2247366ac3fdb/trump-87232.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Brandon/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump stands at the podium with Rep. Julia Letlow (R-La.) as he speaks in the White House during the Congressional Ball on Dec. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/52/48/612e0f9841979aa2247366ac3fdb/trump-87232.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Julia Letlow is preparing to jump into the Louisiana Senate race against GOP Sen. Bill Cassidy after President Donald Trump publicly endorsed her, according to three people granted anonymity to disclose a yet-to-be-announced bid.</p> 
<p>Letlow is expected to announce her decision as soon as Monday, according to two of the people, though the date isn’t set in stone.</p> 
<p>The move comes after Trump upended Cassidy’s reelection bid on Saturday night, posting on Truth Social that Letlow, if she ran, would have his endorsement. Trump officials have privately encouraged her to run, but Letlow previously told Trump officials she would need the president’s public endorsement to get into the already crowded Republican primary field.</p> 
<p>Letlow didn’t explicitly declare her candidacy in the wake of Trump’s endorsement, but signaled in a post on X that she was likely to get into the race.</p> 
<p>“I’m honored to have President Trump’s endorsement and trust,” she wrote. “My mission is clear: to ensure the nation our children inherit is safer and stronger. This United States Senate seat belongs to the people of Louisiana, because we deserve conservative leadership that will not waver.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s decision to endorse Letlow ends months of speculation among Republicans about if he would get into the race against Cassidy.</p> 
<p>People close to Letlow last week were expecting a public endorsement from Trump in the coming days, according to two people.</p> 
<p>But as the filing deadline drew closer, some fellow GOP lawmakers believed she would ultimately not get in. Cassidy has been telling fellow Republicans for months that senior White House officials had pledged to him that the president would stay neutral in his race — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/04/bill-cassidy-trump-rfk-jr-louisiana-endorsement-00543192" target="_blank">a promise first reported by POLITICO last year</a>.</p> 
<p>Yet even some fellow GOP senators were skeptical of that given Trump’s mercurial moods. Trump had also privately temperature checked some GOP lawmakers on their views about Letlow, according to one person with knowledge of the outreach.</p> 
<p>Trump also called Majority Leader John Thune on Friday and told him that while he had not made a final decision, he was likely to endorse Letlow, according to two people with knowledge of the conversation. Thune encouraged Trump during the call to support Cassidy, the two people said, pointing to the president needing his vote this year and Cassidy’s role as HELP chair, which gives him a role in advancing Trump’s health care push. </p> 
<p>Senate GOP leaderships and the Senate GOP campaign arm are supporting Cassidy, with Thune campaigning with him in Louisiana late last week.</p> 
<p>Trump didn’t directly mention Cassidy in his Truth Social post, instead making it clear that Letlow would have his backing if she gets in.</p> 
<p>“Should she decide to enter this RACE,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115913724519885202" target="_blank">Trump wrote on Truth Social</a>, “Julia Letlow has my Complete and Total Endorsement. RUN, JULIA, RUN!!!”</p> 
<p>Cassidy is seeking his third term in the Senate. He has drawn criticism from Trump at times, particularly over <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/112198571294871461" target="_blank">his 2021 vote</a> to convict Trump of impeachment charges over the Jan. 6 Capitol riot. But Cassidy has touted his working relationship with Trump over the past year, including supporting Robert F. Kennedy Jr.’s nomination to lead HHS and vowing last week to help enact part of Trump’s health care framework.</p> 
<p>“I'm proudly running for re-election as a principled conservative who gets things done for the people of Louisiana. If Congresswoman Letlow decides to run I am confident I will win,” Cassidy <a href="https://x.com/BillCassidy/status/2012729538422153506?s=20" target="_blank">posted on X</a> after Trump endorsed Letlow.</p> 
<p>Republicans for months have already been privately looking at candidates to replace Letlow in the House, with state Sen. Rick Edmonds at the top of the list, according to three people.</p> 
<p><i>David Cohen contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this article referred imprecisely to Cassidy's 2021 vote against Donald Trump. It was a vote to convict the impeached president.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hochul’s sharper stance on ICE complicates life for vulnerable Democrats</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/17/hochul-ice-proposals-new-york-swing-seat-democrats-00733843</link>
      <description>Swing seat incumbents are already facing Republican attacks over the governor’s efforts to curb ICE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c813-dcbd-afbb-c87b0b970000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 14:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/b5/22/b0d1e60342c3bbdd4d8cfb61aa4f/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2254658829">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Octavio Jones/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Gov. Kathy Hochul's push to address federal immigration enforcement in New York is being sidestepped by Democrats in close House races.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b5/22/b0d1e60342c3bbdd4d8cfb61aa4f/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2254658829" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nick Reisman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nick Reisman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Gov. Kathy Hochul’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/hochuls-new-agenda-blends-trump-fighting-with-affordability-00723208" target="_blank"><u>proposals to rein in</u></a> President Donald Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement tactics are putting swing seat Democrats in a tight spot.</p> 
<p>Republicans are eager to capitalize on state-level efforts to undermine deportations as a cudgel against vulnerable House Democrats — especially those representing the bellwether New York suburbs. Left-leaning Democrats — responding to <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3944" target="_blank"><u>eroding support for</u></a> Trump’s immigration policies <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/woman-killed-by-ice-agent-in-minneapolis-was-a-mother-of-3-poet-and-new-to-the-city-00715809" target="_blank"><u>after the shooting of Renee Good</u></a> in Minneapolis — are increasingly willing to take a confrontational approach with federal law enforcement.</p> 
<p>The rapidly shifting events driving public opinion, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook-pm/2026/01/15/trump-ramps-up-threats-on-minnesota-00731068" target="_blank"><u>Trump’s escalating deployment</u></a> of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents and Democrats’ desire to protect undocumented communities has created treacherous political crosscurrents for swing seat lawmakers. And the Empire State — home to large immigrant populations and several contested House districts that may determine control of the chamber — is a case in point.</p> 
<p>“They’re going to have to be really careful how they talk about this,” Laura Curran, a Democrat and former Nassau County executive, said of her party’s swing seat candidates. “We don’t want to talk about defunding the police or all that stuff.”</p> 
<p>Proposals by Hochul and the Democratic-dominated state Legislature to put guardrails around Trump’s immigration tactics have not been enthusiastically received by vulnerable House Democrats.</p> 
<p>Reps. Tom Suozzi and Josh Riley would not comment on the governor’s policy pushback, which she outlined in her State of the State speech this week. And a third Democrat, Rep. Laura Gillen, provided a statement calling for federal immigration reform that avoided any mention of Hochul’s proposals.</p> 
<p>Efforts in Albany to check ICE’s actions are quickly becoming an issue in the three Democrats’ races as Trump moves to deport more undocumented immigrants and potentially use the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/trump-insurrection-act-minnesota-00730664?fbclid=IwY2xjawPXX49leHRuA2FlbQIxMQBzcnRjBmFwcF9pZAwzNTA2ODU1MzE3MjgAAR6Psykun980noX7UdPKJAolBn7eWuBd53Qhf6kUIBSYIvDXYXkrtorkKs_obA_aem_VEuUDjiccfQwTo648uq2eQ" target="_blank"><u>Insurrection Act to quell</u></a> adversarial protests. Republicans plan to mount competitive campaigns against Suozzi, Riley and Gillen this year with the goal of making in-roads among voters in purplish areas of New York state. Attacks over the governor’s immigration measures are already starting: A spokesperson for the House Republicans’ campaign arm accused Hochul and her fellow Democrats of trying to “reopen the illegal immigration floodgates.”</p> 
<p>“New Yorkers haven’t forgotten what Democrats’ reckless open borders did to their state, and they won’t stand for it again,” said National Republican Congressional Committee spokesperson Maureen O’Toole.</p> 
<p>The stakes for New York Democrats to get the immigration policy right couldn’t be higher. Races in at least four seats in this deep blue state are expected to determine control of the House — and the course of Trump’s final two years in office.</p> 
<p>Republicans in the past have pointed to state-level laws in Democratic-dominated Albany to blast Democrats running for federal office. GOP candidates hammered Democrats, regardless of what office they were running for, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/14/new-yorks-kathy-hochul-faces-a-crime-conundrum-ahead-of-reelection-00509076" target="_blank"><u>over a controversial law</u></a> that restricted cash bail.</p> 
<p>State-backed provisions that undermine federal law enforcement stand to serve as a replay of a fight that played out in several election cycles and led to electoral gains for Republicans.</p> 
<p>Gillen’s office sidestepped questions about the Hochul-backed measures and instead called for action on the federal level.</p> 
<p>“Our immigration system has been broken for decades and is in dire need of repair,” she said in a statement. “Comprehensive reform must be done at the federal level. Congress should pass my bipartisan Dignity Act to strengthen our border security, remove dangerous criminals, and provide a pathway for law-abiding immigrants to earn legal status.”</p> 
<p>Curran, who led bellwether Nassau County for four years, believes Democrats in swing seats will have to remain cautious with calls to scale back ICE. But she acknowledged some voters want action following Good’s death and Trump’s threat of invoking the Insurrection Act amid ICE’s clashes with protesters. The fraught emotions have created a tricky balancing act for Democrats in tough races.</p> 
<p>“The dramatic nature of all this ICE action is really starting to freak people out,” Curran said. “The popularity of Republicans is starting to go down if this escalates. This is going to become much more toxic, but I also understand why some of these Congressional Democrats are being vanilla. I understand these districts; they have to be.”</p> 
<p>The lack of support for Hochul’s ICE-curbing plans among the trio of vulnerable New York Democrats underscores how Trump’s increasingly controversial deportation efforts continue to be a third rail for the party. Democrats have struggled to articulate an alternative plan and voters punished their candidates in 2024 as the president returned to the White House promising swift action.</p> 
<p>But the expansive efforts to remove people from the country have changed how the party’s officials — especially at the state level — are approaching the issue.</p> 
<p>Democrats in Albany this year want new boundaries around federal immigration officers — provisions that would apply to a state with a civically engaged immigrant population. Hochul <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/new-york-gov-kathy-hochul-wants-recourse-when-ice-agents-act-improperly-00716720" target="_blank"><u>wants to make it easier</u></a> for New Yorkers to sue federal officials in state court and to require a judicial warrant before carrying out a civil deportation proceedings in locations like schools or houses of worship. Hochul will also implement restrictions on new state-funded public safety grants to require they not be used to support civil immigration enforcement by the federal government.</p> 
<p>The moderate Democrat in interviews has hammered ICE’s recent actions around the country, accusing the agency of abusing its power.</p> 
<p>“It hurts peoples’ confidence in all law enforcement,” <a href="https://www.fox5ny.com/news/ny-nyc-long-island-governor-kathy-hochul-interview-trump" target="_blank"><u>she told Fox 5</u></a>. “This undermines the NYPD, and our state police, who are just doing their jobs.”</p> 
<p>State lawmakers have proposed bills to prohibit federal agents <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2026/01/12/new-york-democrats-apply-ice-melt-00721687" target="_blank"><u>from wearing masks</u></a> while carrying out their official duties. They are calling for new monitoring requirements for ICE. And there are discussions to guarantee that every person facing civil deportation proceedings has access to an attorney.</p> 
<p>“There’s a massive shift — including my own shift,” said Democratic state Sen. Pat Fahy. “Public opinion has shifted dramatically.”</p> 
<p>The Albany-area Democrat has worked with state lawmakers across the country in recent weeks to develop new legislation. Spurred by efforts in California — like requiring ICE agents be unmasked — Fahy and her fellow legislators have been on group chats trading ideas for new ways of bottling up federal enforcement efforts. She acknowledged, though, that some moderate Democrats are yet to come around amid uncertainty over how the rapidly changing events will shape the public’s view of the deportation crackdown.</p> 
<p>“The marginal Democrats or the swing area Democrats are still nervous about it,” she said. “But now it’s more than an immigration issue. This is about who we are as Americans.”</p> 
<p>Even among Democrats eager to put the brakes to ICE’s enforcement there are disagreements.</p> 
<p>Hochul is typically cautious around controversial immigration issues — she is not embracing calls <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/proposal-new-york-sanctuary-state-00715220" target="_blank"><u>to expand sanctuary protections</u></a> and said <a href="https://www.fox5ny.com/news/ny-nyc-long-island-governor-kathy-hochul-interview-trump" target="_blank"><u>in a Fox 5 interview this week</u></a> she does not want the agency abolished. But the governor received standing ovations from the audience when she laid out her immigration measures in her State of the State address — a speech given days after Good’s shooting in Minneapolis and an indication she is delicately threading a needle with her proposals.</p> 
<p>“This doesn’t interfere with lawful enforcement or public safety,” Hochul said in the speech. “It simply affirms a core truth: Power does not justify abuse.”</p> 
<p>There are signs voters across the country are becoming unnerved by immigration agents’ expansive tactics and deployments. <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3944" target="_blank"><u>A Quinnipiac University poll this week</u></a> found 57 percent of voters disapproved of how ICE is enforcing immigration laws while 53 percent of those surveyed believe Good’s shooting was not justified.</p> 
<p>Hochul has said she was “sickened” by Good’s death and called for “recourse” when a federal official acts inappropriately.</p> 
<p>“Let’s start holding these people accountable,” she told MSNOW this month.</p> 
<p>Her likely Republican opponent, Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman, has taken a starkly different posture.</p> 
<p>Blakeman — who signed an executive order opposing sanctuary-related policies — told reporters this week he does not want to “put any shackles on ICE.” He said videos of Good appeared to show her turning her car toward an ICE agent and “trying to run down” the officer — <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2026/01/14/blakemans-ice-thaw-00729497" target="_blank">a claim Hochul's campaign rebuked</a>. The Republican added that there should be more support for victims of crimes by undocumented immigrants.</p> 
<p>“You want to talk about ICE? Let’s talk about the victims of crimes committed in New York state by the people who shouldn’t be here,” said Blakeman, who Republicans expect will have strong coattails in down-ballot Long Island races.</p> 
<p>The differing views among Democrats over how to address Trump’s immigration actions highlights Hochul’s imperative to win over statewide voters, while swing seat incumbents must take a more careful approach, said independent political analyst J.C. Polanco.</p> 
<p>“Hochul understands she’s never going to win a Blakeman voter,” he said. “Unfortunately for Gillen and Suozzi, they need Blakeman voters.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denmark presses Hill to avoid narrow Greenland vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/denmark-greenland-vote-congress-00735132</link>
      <description>Danish officials told lawmakers this week they worried an overly partisan vote could undercut their position.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c90a-dd3c-a5df-eb7a886c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:02:58 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/4d/89/c19e99d742e7bcb29733c9e89be0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2256606279">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Sean Gallup/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>The city center stands on Jan. 16, 2026, in Nuuk, Greenland.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4d/89/c19e99d742e7bcb29733c9e89be0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2256606279" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Joe Gould and Daniella Cheslow</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Joe Gould and Daniella Cheslow</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Danish officials told U.S. lawmakers this week to avoid a war powers vote on Greenland unless it could pass overwhelmingly, warning that a narrow or partisan outcome could do more harm than good.</p> 
<p>Danish representatives delivered their message to lawmakers from both parties in a closed-door meeting on Capitol Hill earlier this week, according to three people familiar with the discussions who were granted anonymity to discuss a sensitive matter.</p> 
<p>A weak showing that included little Republican support, the Danes believe, could undercut Copenhagen’s position and bolster President Donald Trump’s drive to acquire the Danish territory through any means possible.</p> 
<p>The message was relayed in a meeting Wednesday involving Danish Foreign Minister Lars Løkke Rasmussen and Greenland’s foreign minister, Vivian Motzfeldt, as well as Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189136" data-person-id="189136">Ruben Gallego</a> (D-Ariz.).</p> 
<p>Gallego is spearheading the yet-to-be-introduced Greenland war powers legislation, which is aimed at barring Trump from using military force against the Danish territory without congressional approval. The Wednesday meeting was aimed at reassuring Danish and Greenlandic officials — who have expressed repeated alarm over Trump’s rhetoric — that they have support in Congress.</p> 
<p>Following the meeting, Gallego signaled that a vote on the resolution was not imminent.</p> 
<p>“I'm going to keep it on the shelf as an option, should we ever need it,” Gallego said. “But I've offered that language, and we'll make sure to have it handy in case it rises to the moment.” The Danish Embassy declined to comment. Rasmussen and Motzfeldt were part of a delegation whose meeting, also on Wednesday, with Trump administration officials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/denmark-greenland-failed-trump-problems-00729246" target="_blank">failed to resolve the impasse</a>.</p> 
<p>But Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/senate-republicans-derail-effort-to-rebuke-trump-on-venezuela-00730314" target="_blank">are expected to roll out</a> several additional war powers resolutions, including on Greenland, as they force Republicans to go on the record over Trump’s foreign policy decisions, which have repeatedly left Capitol Hill flat-footed.</p> 
<p>“At a minimum, we're forcing a vote that may get the administration to change its course, we're chewing up Senate floor time and highlighting the fact that the president is engaged in external adventurism, rather than solving everyday problems that Americans wanted him to solve,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.) said about the forthcoming efforts.</p> 
<p>And while he acknowledged that it was unlikely they would get a veto-proof number of GOP senators to join most of those war powers resolutions, he added: “We might on Greenland.”</p> 
<p>But while Trump’s refusal to rule out military action has sparked <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/greenland-trump-republicans-congress-00732945" target="_blank">widespread heartburn among Republicans</a>, with even top allies warning he doesn’t have support on Capitol Hill for such a step, there has not been a rush of GOP support for a Greenland war powers resolution.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) predicted it would easily pass if an invasion was imminent, but he wouldn’t support one yet. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.), one of the five Republicans who initially supported a Venezuela war powers resolution, also said that at this point he wasn’t on board. Murkowski, who was in Copenhagen on Friday as part of a bicameral, bipartisan congressional delegation, has said she would support a war powers resolution.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Ethics Committee considering allegations against Nancy Mace</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/house-ethics-allegations-nancy-mace-00734467</link>
      <description>The panel did not disclose details about the ethics claims.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c886-dcbd-afbb-c8ffe0d40001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:11:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/45/6e/d8c9b72241bc84175e727b60ecd9/u-s-congress-13896.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Nancy Mace speaks with reporters outside the U.S. Capitol on Sept. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/45/6e/d8c9b72241bc84175e727b60ecd9/u-s-congress-13896.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The bipartisan House Ethics Committee is weighing allegations against South Carolina Republican Rep. Nancy Mace.</p> 
<p>The panel, in a statement Friday, did not explain the reason for its probe that the Office of Congressional Conduct, an independent ethics watchdog, transmitted a referral late last year. The committee must announce its plans for the investigation by March 2.</p> 
<p>In response to a request for comment on the committee’s plans, a spokesperson for Mace provided a letter to the House Ethics Committee from the lawmaker’s attorney in response to claims regarding her “lodging expenses and reimbursement practices.”</p> 
<p>William Sullivan Jr., a partner at Pillsbury Winthrop Shaw Pittman, asserted in the letter that the Office of Congressional Conduct — the quasi-independent agency that accepts and vets outside complaints against House members and staff — did not disclose if Mace’s ex-fiancé or his associates were involved in their probe. Information provided from her former partner would be suspect, Sullivan argued.</p> 
<p>“[T]he referral appears to rely heavily on unverified materials originating from individuals with personal or adversarial motives, while leaving unanswered whether those individuals contributed to the information underlying the OCC’s analysis,” Sullivan wrote.</p> 
<p>Mace’s spokesperson also pointed to a statement from November, in which Mace claimed the OCC probe was the result of retribution and denied charges of wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Mace previously championed the cause to censure Rep. Cory Mills regarding ongoing ethics allegations against the embattled Florida Republican. That effort failed on the House floor, after a dramatic standoff between Mills and Mace.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-16T09:55:39-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘Dumbest thing I’ve ever heard’: Republicans amp up their resistance to Trump’s Greenland push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/greenland-trump-republicans-congress-00732945</link>
      <description>GOP lawmakers are stepping up their warnings and engaging in diplomacy as the president's threats escalate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c470-dd3c-a5df-ee7aa7bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/81/b5/91b97d4644a2b1b5f2bd1eebdf12/u-s-congress-40836.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A key player in Arctic policy, Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) is involved in several efforts to restrain Trump's Greenland ambitions.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/81/b5/91b97d4644a2b1b5f2bd1eebdf12/u-s-congress-40836.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is talking about taking over Greenland by any means necessary. Republicans in Congress are trying to scare him back to reality.</p> 
<p>As Trump continually threatens to bring the Danish territory into the U.S. over the objections of key global allies and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-greenland-residents-independence-00726696" target="_blank">island’s elected representatives</a>, some GOP lawmakers are stepping up their warnings and engaging in diplomacy as Democrats prepare to put the other party on record opposing a military invasion.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) predicted members on both sides of the aisle would lock arms and require congressional signoff if it became clear Trump was preparing imminent military action.</p> 
<p>“If there was any sort of action that looked like the goal was actually landing in Greenland and doing an illegal taking … there’d be sufficient numbers here to pass a war powers resolution and withstand a veto,” Tillis said.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227109" data-person-id="227109">Don Bacon</a> (R-Neb.) went further, predicting that it <a href="https://omaha.com/news/local/government-politics/article_bdf0d63a-d6e8-43b5-bb3e-086928a8edfe.html" target="_blank">would lead to impeachment</a> and calling Trump’s Greenland obsession “the dumbest thing I’ve ever heard.”</p> 
<p>The blunt public messaging comes as lawmakers try to reassure U.S. allies, including Denmark, in private. A bipartisan group of House and Senate lawmakers are in Copenhagen Friday to try to drive home in person the message that military action does not have support on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>"Greenland needs to be viewed as our ally, not as an asset, and I think that's what you're hearing with this delegation," Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) said after meeting with Danish and Greenlandic leaders there.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> did not join the delegation but he largely endorsed the message the contingent is sending in comments to reporters Thursday, saying “there’s certainly not an appetite here for some of the options that have been talked about or considered” — an apparent reference to military action.</p> 
<p>The pushback amounts to one of the most profound breaches yet seen between GOP lawmakers and the president in Trump’s second term. So far the Republican uneasiness over Trump’s brash foreign policy moves have not resulted in any successful steps to restrain him.</p> 
<p>Following the operation to remove Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro earlier this month, five Republicans joined Democrats to advance a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_SJRES_98" target="_blank">measure</a> restraining Trump from future military incursions in the South American country. But on Wednesday, two of them reversed course and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/senate-republicans-derail-effort-to-rebuke-trump-on-venezuela-00730314" target="_blank">ended the threat</a> after the administration made some commitments regarding future action.</p> 
<p>Democrats believe Greenland — sovereign territory belonging to a NATO ally — could be different. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> of Virginia, who co-authored the Venezuela measure and signaled a raft of new war-powers legislation, acknowledged to reporters Wednesday that prospects were dim that a veto-proof number of GOP senators would join Democrats’ efforts.</p> 
<p>But “we might on Greenland," Kaine added.</p> 
<p>Thune’s predecessor as Republican leader, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51216" data-person-id="51216">Mitch McConnell</a> of Kentucky, spoke out in a floor speech where he said military action against Greenland would be “an unprecedented act of strategic self-harm” that risks “incinerating” NATO alliances.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/476519" data-person-id="476519">Jeff Hurd</a> (R-Colo.), meanwhile, said he was “deeply concerned” about the administration’s Greenland message.</p> 
<p>“I don't think it is productive, and I don't think this is the way to treat an ally,” he said, adding that he “would be opposed to military action in Greenland.”</p> 
<p>But even as more Republicans speak out about Trump’s Greenland ambitions, it’s not clear they could put preemptive guardrails on his actions in this Congress even if they wanted to. Instead, they appear to be hoping that Trump will read the writing on the wall and realize he doesn’t have support on the other end of Pennsylvania Avenue.</p> 
<p>Democrats are vowing to introduce a spate of war powers resolutions, including on Greenland, in the coming weeks and months. Yet even Tillis, who predicted overwhelming support for such a resolution in the case of “imminent” military action, said he would not currently support a measure to stop Trump from using force in the region because it would “legitimize” a threat he doesn’t think is now real.</p> 
<p>Instead, Tillis is using his megaphone as a retiring senator to launch broadsides against Trump’s top aides, whom he blames for some excesses of the administration. While a Greenland takeover might be supported by hard-line deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller, Tillis said, “it’s not the position of the U.S. government.”That, he said, is “another reason I’m going to Copenhagen.”</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.), who initially supported the Venezuela war powers resolution before backtracking, also said in an interview that he was not on board with a similar effort for Greenland.</p> 
<p>“Not prospectively,” Hawley said, adding that any such measure “needs to respond to really particular facts.”</p> 
<p>Any formal GOP pushback is certain to include Murkowski, a co-founder of the Senate Arctic Caucus, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/bipartisan-bill-targets-trumps-greenland-talk-00730427" target="_blank">introduced a nonbinding resolution</a> Thursday with Sen. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.), Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) and Bacon that would affirm the U.S. partnership with Greenland and Denmark. The resolution stresses the “mutual respect for sovereignty and territorial integrity” and that any military action would need congressional authorization.</p> 
<p>Murkowski, who also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/lawmakers-meet-danish-officials-rebuke-trump-greenland-00726166" target="_blank">met with Danish diplomats in Washington</a> this week before traveling to Copenhagen, said she would support a Greenland war powers resolution if it came to that. She also introduced a bill with Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) that would prohibit the administration from using funding to unilaterally blockade, occupy, annex or assert control over Greenland or any other territory belonging to a NATO country.</p> 
<p>“We are operating in times where we’re having conversations about things that we never thought even possible,” Murkowski said. “To use the name Greenland in the context of a war powers resolution is absolutely stunning.”</p> 
<p>While a war powers resolution can be fast-tracked to the floor, Greenland’s allies in the Senate can’t easily force a vote on the NATO measure or even the nonbinding resolution. And some Senate Republicans expressed skepticism that party leaders would let those latter measures go anywhere.</p> 
<p>“I’m sure Thune will jump on it like a bad rash,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Joe Gould contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump, Schumer hold rare White House meeting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/trump-and-schumer-meet-00732580</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c3c6-d6ec-a99b-cbef31a80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:32:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump met with Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer on Thursday — a rare one-on-one meeting between the two native New Yorkers.</p> 
<p>The two have shadow-boxed repeatedly over the past year, including on a failed nominations deal and a historic government shutdown, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/05/donald-trump-chuck-schumer-showdown-00493388" target="_blank">have had virtually no personal interaction</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump, according to a statement from Schumer’s office, called the meeting to talk about the Gateway tunnel project, which the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/01/trump-to-withhold-billions-of-dollars-from-gateway-tunnel-and-second-ave-subway-projects-00589772" target="_blank">administration said late last year</a> would not be funded because of the shutdown.</p> 
<p>But the Senate leader also used the sit-down to raise two unrelated issues — health care and the administration's decision to deploy ICE around the country to carry out mass deportations.</p> 
<p>“Schumer also told President Trump that their actions are dangerous and putting more people at risk and he must pull back ICE from U.S. cities,” the statement said.</p> 
<p>Schumer’s decision to raise recently expired Affordable Care Act subsidies comes as the bipartisan health care negotiations in the Senate struggle. The group is discussing a two-year extension of the enhanced subsidies with new restrictions paired with broader health care changes in the second year.</p> 
<p>But Schumer told Trump to “push Senate Republicans to support the 3-year extension of the ACA tax credit bill that has already passed the House.” Democrats forced a Senate vote on a three-year extension last year, but it failed to advance.</p> 
<p>The White House did not immediately respond to a request for comment on the meeting.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congress clears first funding bills since government shutdown ended</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/congress-funding-government-shutdown-00732209</link>
      <description>Lawmakers have their work cut out for them ahead of the next funding cliff, however.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c3a0-dd3c-a5df-ebfaf0ae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:48:39 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/12/0a/ceadcf744f0183565972c8b6687a/u-s-congress-60366.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks on a phone as he departs the Senate chamber at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 7, 2026. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/12/0a/ceadcf744f0183565972c8b6687a/u-s-congress-60366.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate cleared a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6938" target="_blank">three-bill spending package</a> Thursday for President Donald Trump’s signature, completing a fraction of government funding measures necessary to avert another shutdown ahead of the month-end deadline.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers voted 82-15 to approve legislation funding the departments of Justice, Interior, Commerce and Energy, as well as the EPA, water programs and federal science initiatives through the end of the current fiscal year.</p> 
<p><a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7006" target="_blank">Another spending package</a>, funding the departments of Treasury and State, will be waiting for senators when they return from their recess next week. The House passed that measure Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Together, they represent significant progress after last year’s record-breaking funding lapse. But the vast majority of government programs still need to be funded if Congress wants to avoid another stopgap to keep federal operations afloat beyond Jan. 30. That includes more than 75 percent of discretionary funding, including for the Pentagon and many of the largest non-defense programs.</p> 
<p>“We’ve got to continue to complete the job and make progress on the remainder of the appropriations bills,” said Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine) on the floor Thursday afternoon.</p> 
<p>“Our goal is to get all of these bills signed into law, no continuing resolutions that lock in previous priorities and don’t reflect today’s realities,” she added. “No more disastrous government shutdowns that are totally unnecessary and so harmful.”</p> 
<p>The next two weeks will be a gauntlet for both chambers as the thorniest bills are still in the throes of bipartisan, bicameral negotiations.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers are optimistic that the text of another spending package funding Defense, Transportation-HUD and Labor-HHS-Education could be released in the middle of the upcoming long weekend. The Homeland Security funding package, however, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552" target="_blank"><u>remains in limbo</u></a>,<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552" target="_blank"></a>complicated by ongoing tensions in Minnesota where ICE agents have in recent days shot at least two people — one fatally.</p> 
<p>“We know that they're working, and we're hoping they make some magic out of it,” Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.) said in an interview about appropriators who are in the throes of negotiating the DHS bill.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/house-gop-offer-to-dems-explicit-funding-for-ice-body-cameras-following-minneapolis-shooting-pro-00729265" target="_blank"><u>latest offer</u></a> House Republicans sent to the Senate on the DHS bill would order the department to fund body cameras for immigration enforcement agents. But Democrats are hold more restrictions on the agency.</p> 
<p>“There's no budget like DHS. The way that they move money, the way that they've moved personnel, has no precedent,” Connecticut Sen. Chris Murphy, the Democrat leading DHS funding negotiations in the Senate, said in a brief interview Thursday afternoon.</p> 
<p>“We need to have restraints that actually make a difference,” Murphy added.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune admitted Thursday that if any of the dozen annual funding bills would be “a candidate” for short-term funding, “it would be that one.”</p> 
<p>The protracted runway to finish this work is compounded by the fact that the Senate is planning to be in recess next week, with the House set to be gone the week after for a district work period.</p> 
<p>The House itself is also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/embarrassing-floor-meltdown-has-house-republicans-questioning-their-leaders-00730119" target="_blank"><u>struggling to function</u></a> under the razor-thin GOP majority, where Speaker Mike Johnson spent the past several days contending with dire attendance issues and intraparty revolts — including over earmarks.</p> 
<p>Fiscal hawks including Texas Republican Rep. Chip Roy call earmarks “the currency of corruption” and have taken aim at specific funding lawmakers have secured for projects in their districts.</p> 
<p>The “minibus” funding package the Senate passed Thursday, meanwhile, prevailed over hard-liner attempts to severely shrink spending. It largely rejects the dramatic cuts the White House requested and instead makes more restrained spending reductions to energy and environment programs.</p> 
<p>The National Park Service would face a moderate reduction from current funding levels — much less than the 37 percent cut the White House sought. The EPA would see a 4 percent reduction of $320 million, instead of the more than $4 billion President Donald Trump proposed to slash.</p> 
<p>One area set to get a boost is trade agencies, with an 18 percent increase for the U.S. Trade Representative’s Office and a 23 percent increase for the Commerce Department office responsible for designing and enforcing export controls used to target China and other countries.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-15T15:36:13-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Billy Long apologizes for joking about Iceland as '52nd state'</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/billy-long-apologizes-to-iceland-00732007</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c346-dd3c-a5df-eb7ed7780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:31:58 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Rep. Billy Long has reportedly apologized after privately joking to House lawmakers that Iceland would be the "52nd state" and he would be its governor. </p> 
<p>Long was recently nominated to be ambassador to the island nation by President Donald Trump, who has said he wanted to make Canada the 51st state and is now seeking to take over another Arctic realm, Greenland.</p> 
<p>“There was nothing serious about that, I was with some people, who I hadn’t met for three years, and they were kidding about Jeff Landry being governor of Greenland and they started joking about me and if anyone took offense to it, then I apologize,” Long told <a href="https://www.arctictoday.com/trumps-iceland-ambassador-pick-apologizes-for-52nd-state-comment/" target="_blank">Arctic Today</a>, an Alaska-based nonprofit news site. </p> 
<p>Long did not respond to multiple requests for comment from POLITICO. Trump recently named Landry, the elected governor of Louisiana, as a special envoy to Greenland. </p> 
<p>Long, who represented a southwest Missouri House district for six terms and served a brief stint as IRS commissioner last year, was visiting former colleagues on the House floor earlier this week. His private quip first <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/01/14/more-floor-meltdowns-threaten-funding-bills-00727023" target="_blank">reported in POLITICO</a> kicked off a minor diplomatic row, with Iceland's Ministry for Foreign Affairs <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/iceland-us-ambassador-billy-long-donald-trump-52nd-state/" target="_blank">demanding answers</a> from the U.S. Embassy in Reykjavík over Long's comments. </p> 
<p>Long's comment appears to have struck a nerve as NATO countries, including Iceland, cringe at Trump's repeated threats to commandeer Greenland, a Danish territory. Some Icelanders launched a petition drive urging their government to reject Long as ambassador.</p> 
<p>Asked about the "52nd state" remark, Senate Majority Leader John Thune said Long was "probably having some fun" and "I wouldn't read too much into that."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bill Cassidy raises $1.65 million for reelection fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/cassidy-raises-1-65m-00730420</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beee-d22e-a1db-bfff1a880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:02:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Bill Cassidy raised $1.65 million in the latest fundraising quarter and has $11 million in cash on hand, his team told POLITICO, as he seeks to ward off a right-wing primary challenge.</p> 
<p>The Louisiana Republican is facing several primary challengers on the right fueled by his past criticism of President Donald Trump. Cassidy voted to impeach Trump following the Jan. 6, 2021, attack against the Capitol, a stance that angered the GOP base in Louisiana.</p> 
<p>Cassidy has consistently posted slightly higher fundraising numbers than his opponents, John Fleming, the state treasurer and a former congressman, and state Sen. Blake Miguez, but has a significantly larger war chest. Cassidy has raised more than $17 million this cycle to date. Fleming and Miguez haven’t released their latest numbers; they had just over $2 million and $2.5 million in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/15/congress/bill-cassidy-fec-deadline-primary-challengers-00610818" target="_blank">the bank</a> respectively as of the end of September. Rep. Julia Letlow (R-La.) has also flirted with a bid, though <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">sources told POLITICO</a> she is not expected to run; she had $2.3 million in the bank as of the end of September.</p> 
<p>The senator will have some help. A pair of super PACs supporting Cassidy’s reelection will show they had $5 million in cash on hand at the end of 2025 and received an additional $2 million in the first two weeks of January, according to a person close to those efforts. The PACs expect to spend between $13 million and $15 million on his behalf.</p> 
<p>Cassidy is one of a trio of GOP senators facing tough reelection fights where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">Trump is declining to endorse a candidate</a>, along with Texas Sen. John Cornyn and Maine Sen. Susan Collins.</p> 
<p>Cassidy’s Senate GOP colleagues are backing his reelection. On Thursday, Majority Leader John Thune will host a fundraiser for Cassidy in Baton Rouge that’s expected to bring in $600,000.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: A crypto titan flexes in the Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/crypto-vote-canceled-tim-scott-coinbase-brian-armstrong-00730617</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bff7-dd3c-a5df-ffff9e9f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tim Scott is facing a crypto calamity.</p> 
<p>Landmark digital asset legislation that the Senate Banking chair hoped to advance out of committee Thursday is in extreme jeopardy after one of the industry’s most influential executives announced his opposition Wednesday, setting off a scramble in the Senate and the White House to rescue the bill.</p> 
<p>Scott <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/scott-delays-senate-banking-crypto-vote-00730162" target="_blank">has now postponed the markup</a>, and it’s unclear where he goes from here.</p> 
<p>The last-minute backlash is crypto’s biggest flex yet on Capitol Hill, after the industry’s largest players doled out more than $100 million on races across the country to ensure their allies controlled the 119th Congress.</p> 
<p>Scott is facing opposition from Coinbase CEO Brian Armstrong, founder of the largest U.S.-based crypto exchange. Coinbase has one of the most aggressive lobbying and legal operations in the realm of crypto policy, and it has pumped tens of millions of dollars into a pro-crypto super PAC network.</p> 
<p>The bill at issue is on its face the kind of thing crypto companies have been working toward for years — a sweeping rewrite of Wall Street regulations to accommodate the trading of crypto tokens. It’s also a top financial policy priority for the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>But the legislation isn’t accommodating enough for Coinbase, which had been generally supportive of Scott’s approach until he revealed a new version of the bill this week.</p> 
<p>“Evidently, the industry writes the bill and if anybody in Congress has the nerve to slightly amend it, the industry says that the whole thing is off and they have canceled the law,” Massachusetts Sen. Elizabeth Warren, the top Democrat on Senate Banking and an opponent of the bill, told POLITICO. “These are folks who think that when they’ve bought themselves a Congress, then they expect it to behave the way they say.”</p> 
<p>Armstrong is balking at what he calls the bill’s “erosion” of authority at the Commodity Futures Trading Commission — a regulator the industry has long preferred over the Securities and Exchange Commission. He’s also concerned about the potential for amendments that would crack down on “rewards” from stablecoins — a flashpoint between crypto firms and traditional banks, which see them as threats to old-school savings accounts.</p> 
<p>“We’d rather have no bill than a bad bill,” Armstrong <a href="https://x.com/brian_armstrong/status/2011545247105355865?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a> — a statement that was also at odds with other big players in the crypto world, who say the bill is flawed but still worth advancing.</p> 
<p>Before Armstrong’s surprise rebellion, Scott told POLITICO that he was fully committed to holding the markup, despite looming opposition from key crypto-friendly Democrats and further complications from Republican allies of the banking industry.</p> 
<p>“I am hopeful that it will be a bipartisan victory,” Scott said Wednesday around noon. “But at the end of the day, it’s time for us to come and say where we are on the underlying issues.”</p> 
<p>But for some Republicans, the outcome was obvious after Armstrong’s power play.</p> 
<p>“I think there’s a deal to be had,” Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said. “But [Armstrong’s] probably made the right assessment in terms of us being ready for the markup.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Approps progress: </b>Senators expect to pass the three-bill appropriations minibus Thursday, and some are confident that another funding package could be released this weekend covering Defense, Transportation-HUD and Labor-HHS-Education. Senate Majority Leader John Thune told POLITICO that senators are keeping their options open for how to process the six remaining funding bills once they return from next week’s recess.</p> 
<p><b>— What’s next on war powers: </b>Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.) says Democrats plan to force votes on military action in Greenland, Iran, Colombia, Mexico, Nicaragua and Cuba, after Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/senate-republicans-derail-effort-to-rebuke-trump-on-venezuela-00730314" target="_blank">derailed the Venezuela war powers measure</a> Wednesday. “You make them have to work their ass off to keep their people in the corral,” Kaine told reporters.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congressional Black Caucus endorses former rival Rep. Adriano Espaillat over Black primary challenger</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/congressional-black-caucus-espaillat-primary-00728543</link>
      <description>The CBC’s political wing is endorsing Espaillat after excluding him from the group almost a decade ago.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd90-d6ec-a99b-fff941a20001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/a9/e3/82770ad34aa7bfb1ff880a360db5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2195543097">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Kayla Bartkowski/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Adriano Espaillat received the endorsement of the Congressional Black Caucus's political wing in his primary race against a democratic socialist.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a9/e3/82770ad34aa7bfb1ff880a360db5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2195543097" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jason Beeferman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jason Beeferman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NEW YORK — The Congressional Black Caucus’ political arm is endorsing Rep. Adriano Espaillat over a democratic socialist, Afro-Latina primary challenger — about a decade after the group rejected Espaillat’s efforts to join its ranks.</p> 
<p>Espaillat, an Afro-Latino who represents Upper Manhattan and parts of the Bronx, is <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2025/11/20/justice-dems-vs-squadriano-00663337" target="_blank">facing a primary challenge from Darializa Avila Chevalier</a>, a 32-year-old pro-Palestine organizer who led Columbia University’s protest encampment in 2024. Her candidacy is part of a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/israel-divides-democrats-midterms-00716025" target="_blank">wave of left-leaning primary challenges</a> against pro-Israel incumbents in New York and beyond.</p> 
<p>“Congressman Adriano Espaillat reflects the kind of leadership that our caucus and its members have long championed,” said Rep. Gregory Meeks, chair of the CBC’s PAC, in a statement. “At a time when working families are being priced out of neighborhoods they’ve called home for generations, Adriano has been on the front lines of the fight to make New York City more affordable. That commitment is rooted in lived experience, moral clarity, and a deep commitment to economic justice and civil rights.”</p> 
<p>Espaillat’s rocky history with the Congressional Black Caucus predates his election to Congress. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2017/02/congressional-black-caucus-hispanic-adriano-espaillat-234575" target="_blank">rankled members of the group</a> in 2012 and 2014 when he waged unsuccessful efforts to unseat Rep. Charles Rangel, a founding member of the CBC.</p> 
<p>When Rangel retired, Espaillat ran for the seat a third time and again found himself at odds with the caucus, which endorsed then-state Assemblymember Keith Wright, Rangel’s handpicked successor. Wright, currently the leader of the Manhattan Democratic Party, lost to Espaillat, and the two now helm warring political factions in New York politics.</p> 
<p>Once in Congress, Espaillat attempted in 2017 to join the CBC while simultaneously serving in the Congressional Hispanic Caucus, a group he now leads as its chair. He has identified as a Latino of African descent on the campaign trail, but his request was denied.</p> 
<p>Former CBC Chair Karen Bass <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/07/22/bass-torres-black-hispanic-caucuses-379070" target="_blank">told POLITICO in 2020</a> “there was a specific situation that was more important than [Espaillat’s] ethnic background” that prevented him from joining the caucus. “It was a specific conflict, and I’m not going to talk about it.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.axios.com/2022/02/15/adriano-espaillat-black-caucus" target="_blank">Espaillat said he was still trying</a> to join the group in 2022. Now, the organization is backing him for the first time as he faces a challenge from Avila Chevalier, who holds endorsements from the city’s DSA chapter and the Justice Democrats.</p> 
<p>In its announcement — shared first with POLITICO — the CBC’s PAC said its decision to back Espaillat was rooted in his alignment with its core values and touted his work to fund affordable housing and advocate against President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement tactics.</p> 
<p>“I am deeply honored to receive the endorsement of the Congressional Black Caucus PAC,” Espaillat said in a statement. “The CBC has long stood at the forefront of the fight for economic opportunity and social justice for Black and other marginalized communities. As the first formerly undocumented person to serve in Congress, this endorsement carries special meaning for me.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-14T22:16:27-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Tim Scott postpones Senate Banking crypto vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/scott-delays-senate-banking-crypto-vote-00730162</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bf7b-dd3c-a5df-ff7b20020000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 21:29:52 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> is abandoning plans to hold a vote Thursday on <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_3633" target="_blank">landmark cryptocurrency legislation</a> amid surprise new opposition from a leading crypto firm and uncertainty about the whip counts on both sides of the aisle.</p> 
<p>The South Carolina Republican’s move to punt a scheduled markup comes after the largest U.S. crypto exchange, Coinbase, <a href="https://x.com/brian_armstrong/status/2011545247105355865?s=20" target="_blank">came out against the latest draft</a> of the bill Wednesday afternoon, thrusting the effort into chaos less than 24 hours ahead of a scheduled markup.</p> 
<p>“I’ve spoken with leaders across the crypto industry, the financial sector, and my Democratic and Republican colleagues, and everyone remains at the table working in good faith,” Scott said in a statement. “This bill reflects months of serious bipartisan negotiations and real input from innovators, investors, and law enforcement. The goal is to deliver clear rules of the road that protect consumers, strengthen our national security, and ensure the future of finance is built in the United States.”</p> 
<p>Scott has been working for months negotiate with a bloc of crypto-friendly Senate Democrats on Senate Banking, but they remained opposed to the bill as of late Wednesday, meaning it was unlikely to draw bipartisan support if he forged ahead with a markup. Some Republicans also had outstanding concerns with the bill.</p> 
<p>Coinbase CEO Brian Armstrong wrote on X Wednesday afternoon that the bill as written “would be materially worse than the current status quo.”</p> 
<p>“We’d rather have no bill than a bad bill,” he said. “Hopefully we can all get to a better draft.”</p> 
<p>Coinbase has led the crypto industry’s Washington influence efforts in recent years, but other digital asset firms pushed back on social media after Armstrong’s post on Wednesday, saying the bill remained workable and pushing for it to advance.</p> 
<p>Armstrong said the bill would erode the Commodity Futures Trading Commission’s authority, “stifling innovation and making it subservient to the” Securities and Exchange Commission.</p> 
<p>He also raised concerns about potential “amendments that would kill rewards on stablecoins, allowing banks to ban their competition.” Coinbase offers a rewards program that pays an annual percentage yield to premium subscribers who hold so-called stablecoins — an arrangement that banks are pushing to ban as part of the bill.</p> 
<p>The banking lobby’s position gained steam from lawmakers on both sides of the aisle in recent days, and it looked increasingly likely that provisions cracking down on stablecoin rewards programs would make it into the bill during a markup. Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/466203" data-person-id="466203">Angela Alsobrooks</a> (D-Md.) were preparing a slate of amendments aimed at addressing concerns raised by banks, which have said that allowing stablecoin holders to earn yield risks sparking deposit flight.</p> 
<p>It is unclear when Scott will try again to hold a markup.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66891" data-person-id="66891">Cynthia Lummis</a> (R-Wyo.), who chairs a Senate Banking subcommittee on crypto, said in a statement that lawmakers “have spent thousands of hours working in good faith to deliver a bill that offers the digital asset industry the clarity it needs to thrive on U.S. soil and solidify America's leadership in financial innovation for generations to come.”</p> 
<p>“Today's response from some in the industry proves they just are not ready, and while I am deeply disappointed, I am committed to taking this feedback and partnering with the industry to deliver a product that helps them thrive,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans point fingers at Democrats, Biden at first Jan. 6 committee hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/republicans-hold-first-jan-6-hearing-00730206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beb7-dcbd-afbb-feff17f90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:59:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans used the first hearing of the new committee to investigate the Capitol attacks on Jan 6, 2021, to explore the Biden-era investigation into the pipe bombs left at the Democratic and Republican National Committee headquarters the day before riots — and relitigate conspiracy theories and grievances.</p> 
<p>It illustrated how Republicans plan to use their new select subcommittee and how far apart the two parties remain five years later in their accounts of the day a violent mob stormed the Capitol to contest the results of the 2020 presidential election.</p> 
<p>Rep. Barry Loudermilk (R-Ga.), the chair of the new GOP-led panel, questioned why it took nearly half a decade for law enforcement to identify a suspect in the pipe bombs case, when the Trump Justice Department apprehended the alleged perpetrator, Brian Cole, late last year.</p> 
<p>“How is it that the Biden-Wray FBI was able to flawlessly execute a cellular dragnet to capture the information and eventually apprehend those trespassing at the Capitol, but failed to exercise the same investigative technique into the pipe bomber,” Loudermilk said, referring to President Joe Biden and his FBI chief, Christopher Wray.</p> 
<p>“How is it that the [Democratic]-controlled select committee to investigate January 6th managed to write a final report in which they cover more than 700 pages and 8 chapters without ever mentioning the pipe bombs until an appendix in the back of the report?,” Loudermilk added.</p> 
<p>Michael Romano, the former deputy chief of the Justice Department’s Capitol Siege Section called to testify by the Democrats, said the pipe bombs investigation was particularly difficult, given the “needle-in-a-haystack nature of the evidence.”</p> 
<p>At one point, Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Tex.) physically brandished a binder that appeared to be the report of the previous Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee in his hands, calling that panel’s work a “total sham.”</p> 
<p>And Rep. Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) noted that Stewart Rhodes, a leader of the Oath Keepers, was in attendance for the hearing. Rhodes had been convicted of seditious conspiracy before he was pardoned by President Donald Trump, along with other rioters who stormed the Capitol on Jan. 6.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee who also served on the Democratic-led Jan 6. panel, called Cole’s apprehension a “rare bright spot” in the last year of federal law under the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Still, Raskin maintained that Cole voted for Trump twice and believed the conspiracy championed by Trump and his allies that Biden unfairly won the 2020 election. He also questioned whether Trump’s sweeping pardons for the Capitol rioters<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2026/01/06/jan-6-pipe-bomber-trump-pardon-column-00712039" target="_blank"><u>included Cole</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“Nothing will ever whitewash the indelible facts of that day,” Raskin said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embarrassing floor meltdown has House Republicans questioning their leaders</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/embarrassing-floor-meltdown-has-house-republicans-questioning-their-leaders-00730119</link>
      <description>A group of pro-labor holdouts handed the GOP its latest setback and underscored the tough path for party-line legislation this year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beb8-dd3c-a5df-fefa9c260001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:57:51 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4c/98/fb19fba3415eaf593527ff6105fc/u-s-congress-16351.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mike Johnson (center) is the speaker, but members are questioning the leadership of Tom Emmer (left) and Steve Scalise (right) after Tuesday's implosion.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4c/98/fb19fba3415eaf593527ff6105fc/u-s-congress-16351.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Frustrations are growing among House Republicans as their majority dwindles and agenda sputters — and it’s not just Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> who is feeling the heat.</p> 
<p>Members were aghast after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-defections-labor-bill-overtime-rules-00725803" target="_blank">stunning Tuesday night meltdown</a> on the House floor, where opposition from a handful of GOP members led to the defeat of <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_2262" target="_blank">one labor bill</a> and the postponement of three others. Some questioned why the Republican floor and whip teams — under the direction of Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> and Majority Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227580" data-person-id="227580">Tom Emmer</a>, respectively — had allowed the votes to be scheduled.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) was among the members who voted no Tuesday. He said he told leaders about his opposition and questioned why they are “bringing bills to the floor they don't have the votes for, other than to think that they're going to strong-arm people.”</p> 
<p>“I think it's really a question for them as to where they're getting their math,” he added.</p> 
<p>The rising concerns about the GOP whip operation come as the party struggles to hang onto its razor-thin voting majority. Since the beginning of the year, Georgia Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene resigned, Rep. Doug LaMalfa of California <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">suddenly died</a> and a spate of medical-related absences and family emergencies have plagued the party.</p> 
<p>The GOP currently has a 218-213 majority if all members are present and voting — which day-to-day is a huge “if.”</p> 
<p>Leaving the floor after the failed vote Tuesday night, Johnson insisted, “We're totally in control of the House.”</p> 
<p>Asked in an interview if GOP leaders have a whipping problem, Scalise said, “We ultimately have a vote count problem with the limited number of members.”</p> 
<p>“You have absences, you have other things — I mean, we just had a member pass away,” he added. “It's going to be a tough road, but we're going to keep moving our agenda.”</p> 
<p>Still, the Tuesday episode led to a significant waste of precious floor time for House Republicans as they try to convince voters they’re working to address cost-of-living issues ahead of the midterms and Johnson continues to insist on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/johnson-pledges-to-push-ahead-on-another-party-line-megabill-00729264" target="_blank">pursuing a party-line policy bill</a> this year — a follow-up to last year’s tax-cuts-focused GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Top leaders did see some success last year eking out tough votes, calling the question and then cajoling and cutting deals with holdouts before bringing the gavel down. One procedural vote for the GOP megabill last year was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/02/congress/longest-vote-ever-00438166" target="_blank">held open for more than nine hours</a> while leaders and White House officials negotiated a deal securing the legislation’s passage.</p> 
<p>“I have a magic power of being able to whip everybody at the end, and it usually works,” Johnson told reporters Wednesday.</p> 
<p>But that didn’t happen Tuesday, when leaders had to give up on a bill that would rewrite wage rules so employers would not have to pay overtime rates for training in some cases. Pro-labor GOP Reps. Fitzpatrick, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478639" data-person-id="478639">Rob Bresnahan</a> (Pa.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/81211" data-person-id="81211">Nick LaLota</a> (N.Y.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew</a> (N.J.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51627" data-person-id="51627">Chris Smith</a> (N.J.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/26827" data-person-id="26827">Riley Moore</a> (W.Va.) all voted against the legislation.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51135" data-person-id="51135">Pete Sessions</a> (R-Texas), a former Rules Committee chair, largely reserved judgment about the floor chaos. But he did note that “in the past, we focused on an entirely different process than I believe is done today.”</p> 
<p>Other GOP members granted anonymity to speak candidly about the episode were less restrained.</p> 
<p>“They didn’t even whip the fucking bill,” one House Republican said. “It was unbelievably dumb and unbelievably reckless,” said another.</p> 
<p>Members of the whip team led by Emmer checked in with key Republicans during House votes the night before about how they planned to vote on the labor bill. They heard concerns from some members, but not many hard "nos," according to three people granted anonymity to describe the internal process. A spokesperson for Emmer did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>“I let them know,” Moore said. “We need to be standing up for the American worker, not making it more difficult.”</p> 
<p>Van Drew said he didn’t decide to vote against the bill until the day of the vote and did not inform leaders in advance, but he also said they never asked about his view on it.</p> 
<p>“Our majority is so tight — it's a problem,” he said. “They should have whipped it, No. 1. And then secondly, my bad. I should have let them know, even if it was only a half-hour before.”</p> 
<p>The heads-up likely wouldn’t have made a difference. Other Republicans directly warned Emmer and Scalise of the labor problem, according to four people granted anonymity to describe private conversations about the legislation.</p> 
<p>Scalise said in the interview that when a bill is unanimously approved by Republicans on a committee — as was the case for the overtime bill — “then we're going to make our best effort to get it passed.”</p> 
<p>“You don't want days like yesterday,” he said. “But … on the bills that are the top priorities of our agenda, which we make very clear well in advance, we're moving those bills. We have moved them, and we've got a lot more we're going to be bringing this year, and we will pass those bills.”</p> 
<p>In other words, Scalise gave no indication GOP leaders plan to abandon their get-close-and-roll-the-dice approach in 2026.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, Johnson’s leadership team knew there would be some GOP absences, and at least some idea of the intraparty opposition, according to four other people with direct knowledge of the matter, but they believed they could wrangle enough votes to pass the scheduled bills.</p> 
<p>Among the Republicans leaders tried to work over was Smith — one of the longest-serving members of the House and one who has long held pro-labor positions. Smith held his ground, saying he had made commitments to people in his district and he was not going to vote for the legislation, according to three people who heard the conversation.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters Wednesday Smith was among a group of members “that didn't let us know in advance, and it was nobody's mistake.”</p> 
<p>“He was with his wife in an oncology appointment all morning, so he wasn't here to inform us,” he said. “But not a big deal, just part of the process.”</p> 
<p>The episode underscored how GOP leaders are effectively unable to move pro-business and anti-union labor legislation, a key plank of the party agenda. The slim majority allowed the small band of pro-labor Republicans to corner Johnson late last year, signing a Democratic-led discharge petition forcing a vote on a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-passes-bill-federal-workers-bargaining-rights-00687594" target="_blank">bill protecting federal worker unions</a>.</p> 
<p>Democrats are eager to push other discharge petitions on labor matters in the wake of the recess successes, while the GOP is unlikely to bring the issue to the floor themselves.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think you’re going to see another labor bill on the floor this year,” another House Republican said.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Judiciary Committee schedules Bondi testimony for Feb. 11</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/bondi-set-to-testify-00729891</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-be8e-d6ec-a99b-ffef40780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:16:03 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi will appear before the House Judiciary Committee Feb. 11, Rep. Jim Jordan, who chairs the panel, said in an interview Wednesday night.</p> 
<p>Her appearance, which had been postponed due to the government shutdown, comes at a perilous time for the Justice Department. Bipartisan lawmakers have criticized her agency's handling of the release of files in the case against Jeffrey Epstein as mandated by Congress under law and now will have to answer for the legality of President Donald Trump's actions in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Decisions under Bondi's watch to prosecute the president’s political adversaries, including former FBI Director James Comey and New York Attorney General Letitia James, have also drawn scrutiny after Trump ordered Bondi to pursue them. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slotkin says she is under investigation for November military video</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/slotkin-investigation-trump-00728241</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd66-d6ec-a99b-ff6f8eaf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:16:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Elissa Slotkin on Wednesday confirmed she is under federal investigation for her participation in a November video urging military members not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/SenatorSlotkin/status/2011472739693912187?s=20" target="_blank">In a video response</a> to the investigation, the Michigan Democrat said President Donald Trump was weaponizing the federal government against those who disagree with him. Slotkin is the latest video participant to face investigation from the administration.</p> 
<p>“To be clear, this is the president's playbook,” Slotkin said. “Truth doesn't matter. Facts don't matter, and anyone who disagrees with him becomes an enemy, and he then weaponizes the federal government against them. It's legal intimidation and physical intimidation meant to get you to shut up.”</p> 
<p>Slotkin, who was recruited by the CIA as a Middle East analyst and served three tours in Iraq, was among five other Democratic military veterans <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2558895077819811" target="_blank">featured in the video</a>, including Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.) and Reps. Maggie Goodlander (N.H.), Jason Crow (Colo.), Chris Deluzio (Pa.) and Chrissy Houlahan (Pa.).</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">Trump at the time called the lawmakers' actions</a> “seditious” and said they should face trial.</p> 
<p>Crow said he had been contacted by the Trump administration as well about the video.</p> 
<p>"Donald Trump is using the Department of Justice as a weapon to harass and intimidate me in particular, as well as the other members who filmed that video," he told reporters. "We are not going to stop it from us doing our job." </p> 
<p>Kelly this week <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/mark-kelly-pete-hegseth-lawsuit-00722382" target="_blank">filed a lawsuit</a> against Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth and other senior military leaders after his own investigation was announced and the Defense Department <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/hegseth-kelly-punish-video-00710555" target="_blank">began to take steps</a> to downgrade his retirement rank.</p> 
<p>Slotkin <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/13/us/politics/slotkin-pirro-trump-justice-dept-video.html" target="_blank">first told The New York Times</a> she had learned about the investigation from the office of Jeanine Pirro, the U.S. attorney for the District of Columbia. Pirro’s office told POLITICO it does not confirm or deny the existence of federal investigations.</p> 
<p>Following Trump’s response to the November video, Slotkin on Wednesday said that threats against her and her family “went through the roof.”</p> 
<p>“We had over 1,000 threats come in. Over 100 were credible and are being investigated,” she said. “I went on 24/7 security from Capitol Police. I had a bomb threat at my house. My parents were swatted in the middle of the night, and my siblings had cop cars placed in their driveways, and now [Trump] is using his political appointees at the FBI and the Department of Justice to follow through with his threats.”</p> 
<p>Slotkin said that freedom of speech is “worth fighting for.”</p> 
<p>“Right now, speaking out against the abuse of power is the most patriotic thing we can do,” she said.</p> 
<p><i>Nick Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
