<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 23:52:02 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Filibuster fight comes full circle as GOP faces internal pressure on elections bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/senate-filibuster-gop-save-act-00775393</link>
      <description>Sen. Mike Lee and other hard-liners want to pursue the “talking filibuster.” Their colleagues are skeptical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4a38-d0f8-adde-fa7a441b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:30:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/54/c1/b62b6dd54b68830aea65790b522e/u-s-congress-31702.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mike Lee (R-Utah) has been at the front of the push for the SAVE America Act.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/54/c1/b62b6dd54b68830aea65790b522e/u-s-congress-31702.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans are facing a full-circle moment on the filibuster.</p> 
<p>Four years ago, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/01/19/democrats-senate-rules-change-527366" target="_blank">GOP stood united</a> against a failed attempt by Democrats to sidestep the chamber’s 60-vote supermajority requirement and pass a voting-rights bill demanded by their party base. Now — with their own trifecta and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499?can_id=71597c61003cabad9b09c8444aa14487&amp;email_referrer=email_3092311&amp;email_subject=bumping-this-sign-and-send-a-letter-to-your-members-of-congress-opposing-the-save-act-which-would-impose-significant-new-documentation-requirements-when-registering-to-vote&amp;link_id=1&amp;source=email-sign-and-send-a-letter-to-your-members-of-congress-opposing-the-save-act-which-would-impose-significant-new-documentation-requirements-when-registering-to-vote" target="_blank">their own elections bill</a> at issue — Republicans are under pressure to do much the same.</p> 
<p>The shoe-on-the-other-foot moment is being fueled by a cadre of hard-right senators arguing forcefully for tactics once embraced by Senate progressives. Many Democrats, meanwhile, are keeping silent and watching as the GOP undergoes similar internal turmoil to what they had experienced in the majority.</p> 
<p>Only a few, like Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska), have acknowledged the irony of the moment — noting in a statement Tuesday that the push for the <a href="https://x.com/lisamurkowski/status/2021245420303782254?s=20" target="_blank">GOP elections bill</a> looks a lot like what Democrats had previously attempted.</p> 
<p>“Once again, I do not support these efforts,” she said in a statement. “Ensuring public trust in our elections is at the core of our democracy, but federal overreach is not how we achieve this.”</p> 
<p>But the dial on the intraparty pressure cooker is set to ratchet up Wednesday, when House Republicans are expected to pass the SAVE America Act and send it to the Senate. Backed by an Elon Musk-driven public pressure campaign, the conservative hard-liners are working overtime to bend their GOP colleagues toward allowing a “talking filibuster” — a strategy they believe will ultimately allow the Senate to act on a simple-majority basis.</p> 
<p>Much as Democrats said their voting-rights legislation dealt with existential issues of democracy that necessitated an exception to the filibuster, GOP Sen. Mike Lee of Utah and his allies argue SAVE America is essential to securing elections — including the upcoming midterms — from a purported surge of noncitizen voting.</p> 
<p>The bill would mandate voters present proof of citizenship, such as a passport or birth certificate, to register and would require photo ID to vote in every state, among other changes, and has garnered strong backing from President Donald Trump. The push to make Democrats hold the floor indefinitely if they want to block it has picked up support from many of Trump’s GOP allies in the Senate.</p> 
<p>“I’m a fan of the talking filibuster … especially as Democrats have proven more and more obstructionist,” Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said.</p> 
<p>Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas) said forcing a talking filibuster is “exactly what we should do” and that he’s “making the case vigorously” for it.</p> 
<p>But many other Senate Republicans are wary of any step that further waters down the 60-vote margin after both parties have already diluted it over the past decade. Once a majority makes an exception for one bill, Republicans argue it will effectively mark the beginning of the end for the legislative filibuster — something many of them see as a bulwark against big-government Democratic policies, not an obstacle to GOP priorities.</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said he was not eager to rejoin a battle that has resulted in party-line confirmations of presidential nominees after a series of partisan escalations involving the so-called “nuclear option.”</p> 
<p>Tillis said he did not see a substantial difference between those sorts of rules changes and instead by trying to force Democrats into a talking filibuster, which GOP proponents suggest would not require going nuclear. Both, he said, have the “same fundamental message.”</p> 
<p>Lee has been urging his legion of X followers to reach out to his GOP colleagues, seeking to build public pressure on them to support the voting bill even if it means throwing them into a filibuster fight they don’t want.</p> 
<p>He also gave a presentation on his talking filibuster proposal during a closed-door GOP lunch Tuesday, and the topic is expected to come up again Wednesday when Senate Republicans hold a private retreat on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, a band of ultraconservatives in the House, led by Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), is trying to focus pressure on Senate Majority Leader John Thune. Luna told reporters last week that she had received “assurances” that the Senate would allow a talking filibuster for the voting bill — something Thune denied.</p> 
<p>The multifront push has sparked frustration among Senate Republicans, according to two people granted anonymity to speak candidly, who warned that trying to put words in Thune and other GOP senators' mouths was only undermining her cause.</p> 
<p>A GOP senator who granted anonymity to disclose private discussions said that while Lee gave a good presentation during Tuesday’s lunch, “a lot of people in the room are sick of Mike Lee fundraising off of it.”</p> 
<p>“It’s a political spectacle,” the senator added. “It’s never going to happen. It doesn’t work.”</p> 
<p>Republican senators have raised concerns that pursuing a talking filibuster strategy would require either eating up potentially weeks of floor time with no guarantee of success or pursuing strategies that would require procedural votes that would essentially require 50 GOP lawmakers to sidestep recent Senate precedent — a hurdle they wouldn’t be able to clear.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Lee did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Republicans have been privately circulating op-eds <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/bench-memos/the-talking-filibuster-quagmire/" target="_blank">detailing the procedural headaches</a> they could invite upon themselves if they backed Lee’s idea. And they’ve warned that opening up the floor to unlimited amendments could set the stage for Democrats to hijack any bill and turn it into a health care bill or tariff bill or any other proposal they could get a majority to support.</p> 
<p>Many GOP senators aside from Tillis, who is retiring, are starting to speak out against the idea — including Sen. John Curtis of Utah, <a href="https://x.com/SenJohnCurtis/status/2019088376066957731?s=20" target="_blank">who said that</a> “for those concerned in the House, I also oppose skirting around the filibuster.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Kevin Cramer of North Dakota predicted that it wouldn’t go anywhere and summed up his own position as “not interested.”</p> 
<p>One Democrat who has closely studied the issue, Sen. Jeff Merkley of Oregon, said he relished the idea of a “talking filibuster.” During the Biden-era debates over voting legislation, he put forward a <a href="https://www.merkley.senate.gov/jeff-merkley-circulates-talking-filibuster-reform-proposal/" target="_blank">proposal of his own</a> — albeit with rules changes that would ultimately allow debate to end.</p> 
<p>“If they’re operating within the existing rules and looking to have an extended debate where they maintain a quorum and go day and night … I say thumbs up,” Merkley said.</p> 
<p>Thune has vowed to put the SAVE America Act up for a Senate vote at some point after it comes over from the House, and he said he was open to discussions about getting it passed. But he reiterated Tuesday that changing the 60-vote filibuster through a party-line vote is an idea “that doesn’t have a future.”</p> 
<p>Asked later if he knew how a “talking filibuster” could work without a prolonged floor battle — something the South Dakota Republican warned could derail other GOP priorities — Thune started laughing.</p> 
<p>“No, I don’t,” Thune said. “It takes you back over 100 years. So, unlimited debate and unlimited amendments. … Nobody knows.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Leo Shane III contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-10T23:52:02-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Dan Osborn cancels fundraiser after co-host’s Epstein link surfaces</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/dan-osborn-dana-chasin-fundraiser-00775138</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-49c6-d3b5-addf-e9c666030000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:04:52 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Lippman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Lippman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nebraska Senate candidate Dan Osborn abruptly canceled a <a href="https://www.politico.com/osborn_invite" target="_blank">Tuesday fundraiser</a> that was set to be co-hosted by a Democratic operative who was mentioned in the recently released Jeffrey Epstein files as allegedly transporting young girls for the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>Dana Chasin — a Rockefeller heir who advised Hillary Clinton’s 2016 presidential campaign as well as former Sens. Tim Johnson (D-S.D.) and Jon Tester (D-Mont.) — was listed on an invitation for the Washington event benefiting Osborn, who is running against GOP Sen. Pete Ricketts as an independent.</p> 
<p>His name <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2012/EFTA02731721.pdf" target="_blank">appears in a March 2024 email</a> sent to a Justice Department attorney by Jeanne Christensen, a lawyer representing a young unnamed woman who alleged Chasin flew her on a private plane to Epstein’s Manhattan townhouse for sex with powerful men. The email, which details allegations of sexual abuse, also mentions a second flight with Chasin but does not make a direct accusation against him.</p> 
<p>Christensen did not respond to an email seeking comment. A spokesperson for her firm, Wigdor, declined to comment.</p> 
<p>POLITICO asked the Osborn campaign Tuesday afternoon whether it was aware of Chasin’s name surfacing in the files. “This event has been cancelled,” a spokesperson replied.</p> 
<p>“Anyone who hurt kids or engaged in other illegal activity needs to be arrested and prosecuted,” the statement continued. The spokesperson did not respond to a question about what vetting had been done of the co-hosts in advance of the event.</p> 
<p>Chasin — who has donated more than $2 million to Democrats since the 1990s, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/receipts/individual-contributions/?contributor_name=chasin+dana&amp;max_date=12%2F31%2F2026" target="_blank">according to federal records</a> — did not respond to requests for comment. An invitation to the fundraiser listed tickets from $250 to $3,500.</p> 
<p>Chasin donated $3,300 to Osborn’s 2024 failed Senate campaign, according to FEC records. the campaign told POLITICO in an email “a donation has already been made by the Osborn campaign to a nonprofit organization in Nebraska whose mission is to end child abuse and trafficking that is the equivalent to the amount donated by this individual.”</p> 
<p>In recent weeks, Osborn has made numerous posts on X calling for justice to be served for Epstein’s victims.</p> 
<p>“There is a small, powerful group of ELITES who think they can do anything they want on this earth,” he <a href="https://x.com/osbornforne/status/2020873083704230393?s=20" target="_blank">posted Monday</a>. “They think they are deserving. They think they are exceptional.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-10T16:19:25-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House Dem identifies ‘wealthy, powerful men’ DOJ redacted in Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/ro-khanna-names-names-00774551</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-491b-d647-addc-ebdf5eda0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 14:56:17 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Ro Khanna took to the House floor Tuesday and read aloud the names of six “wealthy, powerful men” whose names were originally redacted in the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>It comes after Khanna (D-Calif.) and Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) emerged from reviewing unredacted materials related to the late convicted sex offender and demanded that the Justice Department reveal these individuals’ identities to the public if their redactions did not fall under the terms established by Congress..</p> 
<p>The lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/reps-question-epstein-file-redactions-00772399" target="_blank">threatened to expose</a> the men if DOJ did not cooperate, taking advantage of the Constitution’s Speech or Debate Clause that under certain circumstances can shield members of Congress from litigation. DOJ ultimately complied with some of their requests, Massie announced in <a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/2021235321942217085" target="_blank">social media posts</a> Tuesday morning.</p> 
<p>Khanna, however, wasn’t satisfied to stop there.</p> 
<p>“Why did it take Thomas Massie and me going to the Justice Department to get these six men’s identities to become public?” he asked from the House floor. “And if we found six men that they were hiding in two hours, imagine how many men they are covering up for in those 3 million files.”</p> 
<p>Khanna accused the Trump administration of continuing to violate the law he and Massie helped shepherd through Congress in November that placed limits on DOJ redactions of the documents.</p> 
<p>It’s not immediately clear who some of the individuals are, but Khanna identified Leslie Wexner as the billionaire former owner of Victoria’s Secret and other retail companies, and Sultan Ahmed bin Sulayem as the chief executive officer of DP World. </p> 
<p>“The Assistant U.S. Attorney told Mr. Wexner’s legal counsel in 2019 that Mr. Wexner was being viewed as source of information about Epstein and was not a target in any respect," a legal representative for Wexner said in a statement. "Mr. Wexner cooperated fully by providing background information on Epstein and was never contacted again.”</p> 
<p>A representative for bin Sulayem did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Other names include Salvatore Nuara, Zurab Mikeladze, Leonic Leonov, and Nicola Caputo, who could not be reached for comment.</p> 
<p>Khanna did not provide evidence of wrongdoing against any of them. </p> 
<p>Massie<a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/2021327147403706470" target="_blank">in a social media</a>post Tuesday afternoon, also said that while "Appearing in the Epstein files does not prove guilt ... Leslie Wexner was designated as a coconspirator of Epstein for 'child sex trafficking' in a 2019 FBI document and the Sultan’s email address was used to send correspondence about the 'torture video.' Four other men and their pictures appear in a list with Epstein, Maxwell, two known victims, and several women."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rule vote postponed amid tariff backlash</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/rule-vote-postponed-amid-tariff-backlash-00773687</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-488f-d0f8-adde-fadf5d7e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 12:20:03 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House leaders are postponing their latest effort to block votes on President Donald Trump’s tariffs until 8:30 p.m. amid internal GOP backlash.</p> 
<p>House Republican leaders are attempting to use a procedural measure to block any resolutions related to Trump’s tariffs until the end of July, restarting a moratorium on such votes that expired on January 31. But they face <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/johnson-tariff-vote-ban-00773143" target="_blank">significant internal opposition</a> from a band of tariff-skeptical Republicans, led by Reps. Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Rep. Kevin Kiley of California.</p> 
<p>Several Republican lawmakers have expressed discomfort with a tariff regime that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/poll-affordability-cost-of-living-00678076" target="_blank">polling shows is broadly unpopular</a>, even with parts of the GOP base, as Americans continue to grapple with high costs for everyday goods.</p> 
<p>House leaders have side-stepped the controversy since last March, when they first used a procedural measure to block efforts to force a vote on the national emergency Trump used to implement the tariffs. The move has guarded members from a controversial vote ahead of a crucial midterm election and has protected the president from clear vote of Congressional disapproval as his administration attempts to strike agreements with major trading partners.</p> 
<p>If Republicans fail to pass the new procedural block, Democrats are aiming to force a vote on Trump’s 25 percent tariff on Canadian goods as early as Wednesday, with votes on the president’s global tariffs and tariffs on Brazil and Mexico to follow.</p> 
<p>The Senate has already disapproved of the tariffs four times.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jeffries slams Republican DHS offer as 'woefully inadequate'</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/jeffries-slams-republican-dhs-offer-as-woefully-inadequate-00773372</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4845-d3b5-addf-e8c52eb10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 10:58:11 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> said Tuesday a GOP counterproposal on Department of Homeland Security funding is “woefully inadequate” and shows the White House “is clearly not open to” several key Democratic demands.</p> 
<p>Speaking four days ahead of a DHS shutdown deadline, Jeffries said the Republican offer did not satisfactorily address a need for judicial warrants, detention center standards, independent investigations and excessive-force standards. Asked about whether the Trump administration would support a prohibition on masks for federal agents, Jeffries said, “That’s an open question.”</p> 
<p>“They don't appear to be open to ... ensuring that ICE agents are identifiable in a manner consistent with every other law enforcement agency in the country,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>Also speaking Tuesday morning, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said he believed there was still room for compromise, with support from at least seven Senate Democrats needed for any shutdown-averting stopgap measure.</p> 
<p>"There are things I think on probably both sides that are non-negotiables," he said. "But I do think there are a number of things in the range of common ground."</p> 
<p>Speaking on the Senate floor, Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> struck a more cautious tone than Jeffries, saying Democrats "need to see more from Republicans very soon."</p> 
<p>"What Democrats propose is the definition of common sense," he said. "We simply want ICE to follow the same standards that most law enforcement agencies across America already follow."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson says it's full steam ahead on tariff vote ban</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/johnson-tariff-vote-ban-00773143</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-482d-d3b5-addf-e8edcc6c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 10:33:07 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said in an interview Tuesday he will push ahead an afternoon vote to ban challenges to President Donald Trump’s global tariffs over committed internal GOP opposition.</p> 
<p>Language tucked into a procedural measure would forestall votes on privileged resolutions of disapproval through July 31, reviving a ban that expired Jan. 31 as Democrats plan to push fresh tariff votes as soon as Wednesday. But Johnson is facing growing GOP backlash to the move from a band of tariff-skeptical House Republicans. </p> 
<p>Two of them, Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260571" data-person-id="260571">Kevin Kiley</a> of California and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> of Kentucky, told POLITICO they will oppose the rule — enough to tank the procedural vote if all Democrats vote against it as expected. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/276525" data-person-id="276525">Victoria Spartz</a> (R-Ind.) also said she is a "no" on the procedural vote, though she is known to change her mind on the floor.</p> 
<p>Inside a closed-door conference meeting Tuesday morning, Johnson told House Republicans he was going ahead with the vote, arguing to members that they needed to wait until the Supreme Court rules on Trump's tariff powers, according to three people in the room granted anonymity to describe the private meeting. That ruling could comes as late as the end of June.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> declined to say if GOP leaders would have the vote to adopt the blockade language, telling a POLITICO reporter to "ask the whip questions about vote coalitions."</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maxine Waters is the newest target in Democrats’ intergenerational war</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/maxine-waters-newest-target-democrats-intergenerational-00772858</link>
      <description>Waters has been in Congress for 35 years, but Myla Rahman says the district needs fresh representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4564-d0f8-adde-ff7e39da0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ba/9a1a456b49338dd68b87fe59d88d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2198970159">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Anna Moneymaker/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Financial Services ranking member Maxine Waters has opposed GOP-led crypto legislation, in part over concerns about the Trump family's digital assets business ventures.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c5/ba/9a1a456b49338dd68b87fe59d88d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2198970159" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Melanie Mason</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Melanie Mason</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>LOS ANGELES — Rep. Maxine Waters, an institution of Los Angeles Democratic politics, is facing an upstart challenger from her party seeking to capitalize on the national wave of generational change-seekers.</p> 
<p>Myla Rahman, a nonprofit executive, hopes to turn Waters’ 35 years in Congress — and 50 years overall as an elected official — against her, arguing the 87-year-old incumbent has lost touch with her district.</p> 
<p>“The community has said that they’d like new energy, a new perspective,” said Rahman in an interview. “And the reality is, the average age is 36 years old in the district. The average person is a renter in the district. So we've got a lot of issues that are relatable to my life experience.”</p> 
<p>Waters is the rare member of Congress to be both a local icon and a national meme. She gained near-celebrity status in President Donald Trump’s first term as “Auntie Maxine” who regularly lobbed acerbic barbs at the president and his administration. She has maintained an electoral lock on her South Los Angeles district, normally winning with more than 70 or 80 percent of the vote.</p> 
<p>That commanding presence has deterred any serious challenge against Waters in decades. But Rahman is aiming to tap into Democrats’ party-wide discontent over their graying representation, spurred on by President Joe Biden’s initial decision to run for reelection in 2024 despite concerns about his advanced age and mental acuity.</p> 
<p>In California, long-serving Democratic incumbents like Reps. Brad Sherman and Mike Thompson are facing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/16/democrats-generational-challenges-california-00565027" target="_blank"><u>insurgent campaigns</u></a> from younger opponents. The generational rift is also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/congressional-black-caucus-2026-midterms-00741618" target="_blank"><u>roiling the Congressional Black Caucus</u></a>, whose members are facing challenges from younger Black politicians who argue the old guard is not fighting hard enough for the current political moment.</p> 
<p>Rahman, who is 53, pointedly noted Waters has been her representative since she moved into the district at age 6. She said her differences from the congressmember are stylistic, not ideological, and that she considers herself “more energetic, younger, more relatable in terms of the experiences that people face in the district.”</p> 
<p>Rahman said she is especially focused on affordable health care after surviving two occurrences of breast cancer. She received her diagnosis the second time just as she was elected city clerk in Carson and stepped down from the role one day after winning because of her health. She is now cancer-free.</p> 
<p>Waters’ seniority in Congress has made her a powerful force on the Hill; she is currently the top-ranking Democrat on the House Financial Services committee and is in position to become its chair if the Democrats win control in the midterm elections.</p> 
<p>But Waters is not particularly flush in campaign cash, perhaps because she has so rarely faced a serious challenge. She raised roughly $430,000 in 2025 and started the year with less than $150,000 cash on hand.</p> 
<p>Rahman initially sought a state legislative seat in 2026 and raised less than $35,000 for her Assembly campaign, most of which she donated herself. But she said she’s “very confident” she’d be competitive fundraising for a congressional seat. She’s hired veteran Democratic consultant Mike Trujillo to work on the campaign.</p> 
<p>After working as a high-level staffer for Los Angeles-area legislators, Rahman said she’s well aware her decision to go up against a pillar of the city’s political scene will stir some outrage.</p> 
<p>“I'm sure I'll get a lot of calls. I’m waiting for ‘how dare you? The audacity of you, who do you think you are,’” she said. “And what I can say is that there's a choice, and this is a democracy. That's why we have elections, and the voters can decide.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Democrats demand more from GOP on DHS</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/democrats-white-house-dhs-proposal-shutdown-00772903</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-45eb-d0f8-adde-fffba9370000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Do we have a negotiation or a stalemate?</p> 
<p>The answer to that question will determine whether the Department of Homeland Security shuts down in just four days, and Tuesday morning, it’s not entirely clear which way things are headed.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders Chuck Schumer and Hakeem Jeffries panned a White House counterproposal sent to them Monday evening as too light on details for how to rein in President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p><b>— Dems vs. White House:</b> “The initial GOP response is both incomplete and insufficient in terms of addressing the concerns Americans have about ICE’s lawless conduct,” the leaders said in a statement. “Democrats await additional detail and text.”</p> 
<p>That’s far from a “hell no,” but expect to hear more later Tuesday morning on where Democrats stand after Jeffries and Schumer meet with their respective caucuses.</p> 
<p>Neither side is saying exactly what the GOP counter to the 10-point Democratic offer entails, but White House allies made clear Monday that one key Democratic demand — requiring federal law enforcement officials to obtain judicial warrants before entering private property — is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/09/a-complete-non-starter-white-house-draws-red-lines-in-dhs-funding-talks-as-shutdown-looms-00772302" target="_blank">dead on arrival</a>. </p> 
<p>Other Democratic asks — including a mask prohibition, ID display requirements and limits on places where agents can operate — would need major concessions from Democrats to make them palatable for the administration, several people close to the White House said.</p> 
<p>But the trading of offers is giving GOP leaders optimism that a deal is possible. Senate Majority Leader John Thune said he’ll probably get the ball rolling on a continuing resolution Tuesday to give negotiators more time to strike a deal.</p> 
<p>—<b> About that CR:</b> Whether a stopgap can pass depends almost entirely on the tenor of DHS talks come Thursday, when senators are hoping to leave town.</p> 
<p>Republicans need at least seven votes from Senate Democrats to prevent a DHS shutdown, and some Senate Democrats continue to signal they could be convinced — if there’s a bona fide negotiation.</p> 
<p>“It depends on whether we’re making progress or not,” Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) told reporters Monday. “We’ve got some time. Hopefully people will be working to try and get something done.”</p> 
<p>Also undecided is how long a short-term DHS funding punt might run. GOP appropriators want at least two weeks, but the exact length “will have to be negotiated,” Thune said.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— A high-stakes rule vote: </b>House GOP leaders will attempt to adopt a rule Tuesday that includes language to block votes on President Donald Trump’s global tariffs through July after Democrats threatened to move as soon as Wednesday to overturn the president’s levies on Canada.</p> 
<p>It could get hairy: Under the current member math, as few as two GOP defections could block adoption of the rule. Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) is a no. Keep an eye on Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.), Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.) and Tom McClintock (R-Calif.).</p> 
<p><b>— SAVE America Act inches forward: </b>The House will consider the SAVE America Act in Rules on Tuesday despite the uncertain future in the Senate for the GOP elections overhaul. It’s on track to hit the House floor Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The four Democrats who supported a version of the bill in April — Reps. Henry Cuellar of Texas, Ed Case of Hawaii, Marie Gluesenkamp Perez of Washington and Jared Golden of Maine — have so far been mum on whether they will support the updated measure. Jeffries said House Democrats will discuss the measure Tuesday morning.</p> 
<p><b>— DHS officials take the stand: </b>House Homeland Security Committee members will question DHS officials Tuesday morning for the first time since last month’s fatal shootings of Renée Good and Alex Pretti sparked bipartisan backlash against the Trump administration. </p> 
<p>Acting director for ICE Todd Lyons, Customs and Border Protection Commissioner Rodney Scott and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services Director Joseph Edlow will testify.</p> 
<p>While Democrats are expected to give the officials a fierce grilling, some Republicans will also likely push them for more clarity on ICE operations.</p> 
<p><i>Myah Ward, Alex Gangitano, Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson moves to again block House from voting on Trump tariffs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/johnson-moves-to-again-block-house-from-voting-on-trump-tariffs-00772559</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-44fa-de8a-a1fc-fdfa2b9b0005</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:37:47 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said Monday he is moving forward with a plan to revive a prohibition on House votes to overturn President Donald Trump's global tariffs.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters he believes he will have the votes to include the block in a procedural measure set for House consideration Tuesday. The House Rules Committee <a href="https://rules.house.gov/sites/evo-subsites/rules.house.gov/files/documents/rule_hr2189hr261hr3617.pdf" target="_blank">approved legislation Monday</a> that would prevent any further tariff votes through July 31.</p> 
<p>The move comes after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/16/congress/house-again-votes-to-surrender-tariff-powers-to-trump-00566975" target="_blank">previous blockade imposed by GOP leaders</a> expired — and House Democrats threatened to force a vote as soon as Wednesday that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/house-vote-canada-tariffs-00772224" target="_blank">effectively cancel Trump's tariffs on Canada</a>.</p> 
<p>But it is far from clear that Johnson will actually have the necessary votes. A band of House Republicans are already pushing back on the plans, with a group of at least six tariff-skeptical GOP members discussing the matter on the floor Monday night. With united Democratic opposition expected, nays from as few as two Republicans could derail the effort.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House approves housing bill, setting stage for tough Senate negotiations</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/house-approves-housing-bill-setting-stage-for-tough-senate-negotiations-00772552</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-44eb-d3b5-addf-e4ef08510005</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 19:20:30 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Cassandra Dumay</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cassandra Dumay</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House on Monday night passed its bipartisan <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/house-financial-services-introduces-bipartisan-housing-package-00688305" target="_blank">housing package</a> aimed at increasing home supply and affordability, setting up an uncertain effort to merge the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6644" target="_blank">measure</a> with a Senate housing bill.</p> 
<p>House lawmakers approved by a vote of 390-9 the <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/02/house-republicans-eye-next-week-for-housing-bill-vote-00761249#:~:text=Housing%20in%20the%2021st%20Century%20Act" target="_blank">Housing in the 21st Century Act</a> under suspension of the rules, a fast-track procedure for non-controversial legislation. The bill includes provisions to modernize local development and rural housing programs, expand manufactured and affordable housing, protect borrowers and those utilizing federal housing programs and enhance oversight of housing providers. The package also contained a recently added section aimed at increasing community bank lending.</p> 
<p>Congress must now work to get a unified bill to the president’s desk. The Senate passed its own bipartisan housing affordability package in October, which was supported by the White House. Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) — who spearheaded the House bill with ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51664" data-person-id="51664">Maxine Waters</a> (D-Calif.) — told reporters Monday he plans to negotiate with the administration as well as his counterparts on the Senate Banking Committee to get a final version which both chambers and the White House can support.</p> 
<p>“We wanted to get [the housing bill and other committee priorities] through the House so that we could work with the Senate to find packages that the President could sign into law, long before the very active summer campaign season,” Hill said. “So I would hope that we could work over the spring and find a way to have a bicameral, bipartisan set of bills.”</p> 
<p>Hill has previously said the Senate bill, the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2651" target="_blank">ROAD to Housing Act</a>, contained a number of provisions that House Republicans would likely not support. Although the House and Senate bills share many similarities, the Senate measure includes a number of grant programs that would expand federal spending.</p> 
<p>But Senate Banking ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> (D-Mass.) said that she still wants the House to take up the Senate bill, setting the stage for a potential clash. Support from Senate Democrats will likely be necessary to get housing legislation through the upper chamber.</p> 
<p>“ROAD to Housing is a Jenga tower. Adding or taking things away risks losing the unanimous coalition that we have built in the Senate,” Warren said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Warren also signaled that she disapproved of the new section added to the House legislation, which would ease regulation on community banks — reflecting Hill’s <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/hill-barr-introduce-community-banking-package-00715479?site=pro&amp;prod=alert&amp;prodname=alertmail&amp;linktype=headline&amp;source=email" target="_blank">“Make Community Banking Great Again” agenda</a>.</p> 
<p>“House Republicans should not hold housing relief hostage to push forward several bank deregulatory bills that will make our community banks more fragile,” Warren said in a statement before Monday’s House vote.</p> 
<p><i>Katherine Hapgood contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers don't rule out exposing redacted names of powerful men in Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/reps-question-epstein-file-redactions-00772399</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-44bb-d0f8-adde-fefb06f50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 18:41:27 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Reps. Ro Khanna and Thomas Massie are challenging the Justice Department for redacting the names of six men in the publicly released materials related to the convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein — and they could take matters into their own hands to reveal their identities.</p> 
<p>These omissions, the two lawmakers argued Monday evening outside the Justice Department, could go beyond the scope of redactions that are permitted under the legislation they championed — and which President Donald Trump signed into law in November — to compel the full release of Epstein files within DOJ’s possession.</p> 
<p>And while they declined to share the names with reporters Monday, Massie, a Kentucky Republican, didn’t rule out taking steps to do so in the coming days. He told reporters he should “probably” broadcast the identity of the shielded individuals “from the floor or in a committee hearing,” where his remarks would be protected from lawsuits through the Speech and Debate Clause.</p> 
<p>“What we’re after is the men who Jeffrey Epstein trafficked women to,” said Massie, adding he would give DOJ officials the opportunity to “correct their mistakes” and reverse the redactions on their own before reading the names of the six men on the chamber floor or from a committee dais.</p> 
<p>Massie said at least one of the men was a U.S. citizen, another was a foreigner and the nationalities of others were unclear. He suggested authorities were investigating at least one of them.</p> 
<p>“There are six men, some of them with their photographs, that have been redacted, and there's no explanation why those people were redacted,” Khanna, a California Democrat, told reporters. “That’s really concerning.”</p> 
<p>Khanna and Massie were at a DOJ office building Monday to peruse the unredacted Epstein files, a privilege being afforded to members of Congress following the files' public release. The lawmakers scrutinized the unscrubbed materials on closely held computers — though Massie complained he was unable to view some documents that have since been taken down from the Justice Department website after being posted publicly.</p> 
<p>Khanna suggested that some materials may have been redacted before the Justice Department review — potentially by the FBI — complicating the process for complete transparency.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, also viewed the unredacted materials earlier in the day Monday. He said there were about four computers for lawmakers’ use and viewers can only take written notes on what they see.</p> 
<p>“We didn't want to see any redactions of the names of co-conspirators, accomplices, enablers, abusers, rapists, simply to spare them potential embarrassment, political sensitivity or disgrace of some kind,” Raskin told reporters. “And yet nonetheless, the Epstein … documents that were released are filled with redactions of names and information about people who clearly are not victims and may fall into that other category.”</p> 
<p>He pointed to the redaction of Les Wexner’s identity as an example. Wexner, the former CEO of Victoria’s Secret, was an Epstein client and has a deposition scheduled before the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee later this month.</p> 
<p>Raskin also said he saw one redacted document, a message from Epstein’s legal team regarding Trump. He recalled the note mentioned that Trump had identified Epstein as a guest, but not a member, of Mar-a-Lago.</p> 
<p>“That was redacted for some indeterminate, inscrutable reason,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House vote on Canada tariffs coming as soon as Wednesday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/house-vote-canada-tariffs-00772224</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4482-d3b5-addf-e4c62af80006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 17:28:02 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Desrochers and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Desrochers and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Democrats are aiming to force a vote on President Donald Trump’s Canada tariffs as early as Wednesday.</p> 
<p>House Democrats still need to meet and decide when to offer the resolution, but it is likely to come Wednesday, according to two staffers granted anonymity to discuss private plans.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/51521" target="_blank">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.) <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HJRES_72?q=H.J.Res.72" target="_blank">introduced the resolution</a> last March, but House Republican leaders <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/03/11/congress/house-republicans-move-to-block-vote-on-trumps-tariffs-00223947" target="_blank">blocked a vote on the measure and any others</a> disapproving of Trump’s emergency powers to impose tariffs. That block <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/16/congress/house-again-votes-to-surrender-tariff-powers-to-trump-00566975" target="_blank">expired in January</a>, after a group of Republicans pushed leadership to allow tariff votes.</p> 
<p>One of those lawmakers, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/6d3990d9-4e46-4bc9-a299-af8b3dad90fd" target="_blank">Don Bacon</a> (R-Neb.), said he is inclined to vote to end the tariffs on Canada.</p> 
<p>“We have a trade agreement with them, and I don’t like how the White House has treated our neighbor and ally,” Bacon said Monday in an interview.</p> 
<p>If it is offered, it would force a difficult vote for Republican lawmakers, who have faced sustained pressure from businesses in their districts over the costs and disruptions the tariffs have produced.</p> 
<p>The Senate has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/29/congress/senate-votes-to-block-trumps-tariffs-on-canada-for-a-second-time-00629068" target="_blank">voted twice</a> to block Trump from imposing tariffs on Canada, first in April and then again in October. Four Republican Senators voted with the Democrats each time: <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/aa48154b-408e-4868-a88a-e4c2151d6492" target="_blank">Mitch McConnell</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/4b1312cc-ee28-4ef7-aeac-bd4f852ca121" target="_blank">Rand Paul</a> of Kentucky, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/6c1b2696-bcf8-42e0-8d5f-b4d513a17758" target="_blank">Susan Collins</a> of Maine, and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/a5094dbc-f9c4-455a-875d-d56a1b3f0abd" target="_blank">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska.</p> 
<p>The votes are largely symbolic — even if Congress disapproves of Trump’s national emergency, the president is likely to veto it, and it would require a two-thirds vote from both chambers to overturn his veto.</p> 
<p>Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/01/trump-tariffs-canada-mexico-00201953" target="_blank">used his emergency powers</a> to impose a 25 percent tariff on goods from Canada, Mexico and China in February, accusing the three countries of failing to prevent undocumented migrants and fentanyl from flowing into the U.S.</p> 
<p>The administration exempted the majority of Canadian goods from those tariffs, however, if they comply with the existing U.S.-Mexico-Canada free trade agreement.</p> 
<p><i>Doug Palmer contributed to this article.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-09T15:29:36-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Howard Lutnick faces bipartisan calls to resign over latest Epstein revelations</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/howard-lutnick-epstein-resignation-00771261</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-432e-d3b5-addf-e3ee29e90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:15:16 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick is facing bipartisan calls to resign after he appeared in a recent batch of files linked to convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51608" data-person-id="51608">Adam Schiff</a> (D-Calif.) accused Lutnick in a statement Monday of having “lied” about the extent of his connection to Epstein. Lutnick has sought to downplay their relationship, saying in a podcast appearance last year he vowed in 2005 to never again be in the same room as Epstein.</p> 
<p>But files recently released by the Justice Department <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/epstein-europe-america-fallout-00769506" target="_blank">suggest he continued his interactions with Epstein</a>, including planning a visit several years later to Epstein’s Caribbean island.</p> 
<p>“Lutnick’s lies about his business dealings with a convicted child sex offender, raise serious concerns about his judgement and ethics,” Schiff said. “Lutnick has no business being our Commerce Secretary, and he should resign immediately.”</p> 
<p>Asked about the scrunity, White House spokesperson Kush Desai did not respond directly but said President Donald Trump "has assembled the best and most transformative cabinet in modern history." </p> 
<p>"The entire Trump administration, including Secretary Lutnick and the Department of Commerce, remains focused on delivering for the American people,” he said.</p> 
<p>House Oversight Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260072" data-person-id="260072">James Comer</a> (R-Ky.), who is leading an investigation into Epstein and has already subpoenaed multiple associates, did not rule out issuing one for Lutnick. But he said the panel's outstanding subpoenas take priority for now.</p> 
<p>"We're interested in talking to anyone that might have any information that would help us get justice for the survivorship," he told reporters Monday.</p> 
<p>Schiff is joining a bipartisan chorus of House members who have called in recent days for Lutnick to either resign or be fired — neither of which appears to be on the precipice of happening.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.) <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/02/08/politics/massie-howard-lutnick-epstein-files" target="_blank">told CNN</a> during an interview that aired over the weekend that Lutnick should “make life easier on the president, frankly, and just resign.” House Democrats, including top Oversight Committee member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/420280" data-person-id="420280">Robert Garcia</a>, have also called on Lutnick to go.</p> 
<p>“It’s now clear that Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick has been lying about his relationship with Epstein,” the Californian posted on X. “Lutnick must resign or be fired. And he must answer our questions.”</p> 
<p><i>Hailey Fuchs and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ghislaine Maxwell pleads the Fifth in House Oversight Epstein investigation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/maxwell-pleads-the-fifth-00771258</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-431e-d3b5-addf-e3def70a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 11:12:25 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The congressional investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein hit its latest snag Monday morning when Epstein’s longtime associate, Ghislaine Maxwell, declined to answer questions in a sworn deposition.</p> 
<p>Maxwell, now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in Epstein’s sex trafficking scheme, invoked her Fifth Amendment right over video from a prison camp in Texas, months after she had been subpoenaed by the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee.</p> 
<p>In a copy of Maxwell's lawyer’s opening statement obtained by POLITICO, David Oscar Markus reiterated that grant of clemency would facilitate her testimony — a power only President Donald Trump can bestow. He has not ruled out issuing a pardon.</p> 
<p>“Only she can provide the complete account. Some may not like what they hear, but the truth matters,” according to Markus’ prepared remarks. “For example, both President Trump and President Clinton are innocent of any wrongdoing. Ms. Maxwell alone can explain why, and the public is entitled to that explanation.”</p> 
<p>He also noted some of Maxwell’s legal proceedings were still ongoing.</p> 
<p>Democrats accused Maxwell of using the deposition as part of a campaign for clemency from Trump, while House Oversight Chair James Comer told reporters he did not believe Maxwell should be granted clemency.</p> 
<p>“Unfortunately, she had an opportunity today to answer questions that every American has — questions that would be very important in this investigation — and she chose to invoke her Fifth Amendment right,” the Kentucky Republican said. </p> 
<p>Rank-and-file members of the panel who shuffled into the deposition room Monday morning for Maxwell's questioning included Reps. Andy Biggs (R-Ariz.), who is running for governor, and Raja Krishnamoorthi (D-Il.), who is running for Senate.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) said he intended to view the unredacted Epstein files from the Justice Department on Monday afternoon. He also noted he would be joined by Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), with whom Khanna led the effort to force a floor vote on the release of the files.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Republicans prepare DHS punt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/09/congress/dhs-shutdown-funding-bill-continuing-resolution-00771028</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-40a4-d0f8-adde-fafe543b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With fewer than five days to go before a DHS shutdown, Senate Democrats have put bill text for full-year funding on the table. But another punt is probably still the best-case scenario, and it’s by no means guaranteed.</p> 
<p><b>— What Democrats are pitching: </b>The draft legislation Democrats sent Republicans on Sunday would codify the immigration enforcement guardrails outlined by Democratic leaders last week, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss the plans. They include new judicial warrant requirements and limits on masking by federal agents.</p> 
<p><b>— Republicans review and prepare for CR: </b>While getting bill text is generally a good thing for the process, after Republicans complained publicly into the weekend about the lack of specifics from Democrats, it hasn’t changed the endgame for this week. Republicans and the White House view some of the ideas as possible areas for negotiation, but it’s just highly unlikely all sides agree to a full-year DHS revamp by Friday at midnight.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans expect to begin taking procedural steps Monday to set up consideration of a DHS funding patch. Senate aides still hope there’s a way to prevent a DHS shutdown, and progress on negotiations could dictate how easy it is to get bipartisan buy-in for another CR. Most Democrats will be reluctant to punt.</p> 
<p><b>— Shutdown still looks likely: </b>Unless the Senate does the unexpected and clears a new CR for DHS by Wednesday, there probably won’t be enough time for the House to follow suit before the shutdown deadline. House GOP leaders have no plans to cancel next week’s recess absent clearer proof of progress in the Senate, meaning a DHS shutdown could take even longer to resolve.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Ghislaine</b> <b>Maxwell deposition: </b>The House Oversight Committee<b>&nbsp;</b>will depose Jeffrey Epstein co-conspirator Ghislaine Maxwell virtually at 10 a.m. Monday. Maxwell is expected to invoke the Fifth Amendment and be uncooperative with questioning. House Judiciary ranking member Jamie Raskin (D-Md.) will be reviewing unredacted Epstein files, according to a spokesperson. Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) will review the files as well. </p> 
<p><b>— House moves on housing package: </b>The House is expected to swiftly pass a sweeping, bipartisan housing supply bill from the Financial Services Committee on Monday afternoon. After that, it’s unclear how the House and Senate will come together on one of the country’s most urgent cost-of-living problems.</p> 
<p>— <b>D.C. tax bill advances:</b> Senate Republicans are expected to act early this week to pass a measure that would force the District of Columbia to implement GOP tax cuts. The bill, which the House <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/house-passes-measure-to-force-d-c-s-hand-on-tax-cuts-00766206" target="_blank">passed along party lines</a> last week, would block a November D.C. budget law that tossed aside tax provisions from last year’s “Big, Beautiful Bill.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Hailey Fuchs and Cassandra Dumay contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-09T17:52:16-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>How cigars, whiskey and an old-school Oklahoman got the government funded</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/09/tom-cole-house-appropriations-profile-00770360</link>
      <description>From his clubby Capitol office, the 76-year-old Appropriations chair managed demanding colleagues and political headwinds — and pulled off a seemingly impressive feat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-3dc5-d3b5-addf-fdc5a500000b</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e1/3c/93c180a44d4386400b263070b18e/2026-0205-cole-francis-1-13-edit.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Appropriations Committee Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) smokes a cigar in his office at the U.S. Capitol, on Feb. 5, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e1/3c/93c180a44d4386400b263070b18e/2026-0205-cole-francis-1-13-edit.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The crucial votes to fund the government last week were brokered in Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>'s ceremonial office just off the House floor. But the groundwork to get the $1.6 trillion spending package through the chamber was laid in a literal smoke-filled room just steps away.</p> 
<p>That would be the domain of Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51327" data-person-id="51327">Tom Cole</a>, the 76-year-old cigar-and-whiskey-loving chair of the House Appropriations Committee. Inside that haunt, the Oklahoman took an unabashedly old-school approach over the course of months to getting the congressional funding process unstuck after a record-long, 43-day shutdown last year.</p> 
<p>“That’s not actually an office — it’s a smoke room,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51132" data-person-id="51132">Darrell Issa</a> (R-Calif.), a regular in what some members cheekily call the “Cigar SCIF,” a play on the “sensitive compartmented information facilities” where government officials review state secrets.</p> 
<p>Inside, Cole “doesn't dazzle you with numbers, he works on people-to-people skills,” Issa said, “and it's the reason we've gotten something done.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/b1/96/c7135a594e80bc9e9230d6ae96e2/2026-0205-cole-francis-1-8-edit.jpg" alt="A cigar cutter and an ashtray are among the objects in Cole's office. “That’s not actually an office — it’s a smoke room,” said Rep. Darrell Issa (R-Calif.)." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="A cigar cutter and an ashtray are among the objects in Cole's office. “That’s not actually an office — it’s a smoke room,” said Rep. Darrell Issa (R-Calif.)."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/97/b7/7374335d4d0084bf9f47762cb3c6/2026-0205-cole-francis-1-7-edit.jpg" alt="A wide variety of members are often seen slipping in and out inside Cole’s tobacco-scented inner sanctum." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="A wide variety of members are often seen slipping in and out inside Cole’s tobacco-scented inner sanctum."/><p>That’s something of a miracle considering who Cole is and what his colleagues have demanded.</p> 
<p>When Cole took the Appropriations gavel in the spring of 2024, conservative demands for spending reductions were mounting. Hard-liners citing unfulfilled promises of funding cuts had ousted Kevin McCarthy, a close Cole ally, from the speakership just six months earlier. Months later, Donald Trump was elected to a second term as president and immediately began freezing billions of dollars top appropriators had already fastidiously allocated.</p> 
<p>“We often joke: Boy, did we get here at a bad time,” Cole said in an interview, describing the situation he and Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) confronted.</p> 
<p>While the politics of government spending grew stormy as 2025 wore on, Cole and his allies were biding their time and working — puff by puff and sip by sip — to build support for the government funding bills he was quietly negotiating with his counterparts across the aisle and across the Capitol.</p> 
<p>Matters came to a head in the weeks after the longest shutdown in U.S. history concluded in November. Fiscal conservatives in the House were threatening to block passage of the bills Cole had helped craft — demanding changes to legislation that had already been settled with Democrats.</p> 
<p>In early January, with tensions high and the chances for another lengthy shutdown rising, House Majority Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227580" data-person-id="227580">Tom Emmer</a> (R-Minn.) entered Cole’s office off the House floor. He emerged more than an hour later and gave Cole his public blessing to proceed with what appropriators had negotiated, a key vote of confidence from the GOP leadership.</p> 
<p>“The bills are being built by the Appropriations Committee in the House and the Senate,” Emmer said. “Tom Cole and his colleagues on the Appropriations Committee are doing excellent work.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/3c/7a/116811954df7a794f2ac496361e0/ap25281549696252-edit.jpg" alt="Cole speaks as members of the House GOP leadership look on during a press conference on the 8th day of the government shutdown at the U.S. Capitol, on Oct. 8, 2025." data-portal-copyright="John McDonnell/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25281549696252" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Cole speaks as members of the House GOP leadership look on during a press conference on the 8th day of the government shutdown at the U.S. Capitol, on Oct. 8, 2025."/><p>House hard-liners, who were eyeing massive cuts to member-requested earmarks, didn’t secure any further changes to the funding bills. Now eleven of the 12 annual measures have been signed into law, guaranteeing cash through September for every federal agency except the embattled Department of Homeland Security.</p> 
<p>Along the way Cole has won grudging respect from those same hard-liners, who give him credit for negotiating relatively flat overall funding levels and for trying to return the House to its traditional process of debating the 12 bills individually instead of as a catchall omnibus package.</p> 
<p>“Heavy is the head that wears the crown,” Republican Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/194221" data-person-id="194221">Scott Perry</a> said of Cole in an interview. "Of course he listens. He listens because he has to listen — we have votes.”</p> 
<p>Cole is “a big reason,” the Pennsylvania conservative continued, that the House is “crawling out of this hole of just ‘go along to get along’ in Washington, D.C.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium is-centered">‘Space is a great gift’</h5> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium is-centered"></h5> 
<p>While Freedom Caucus types like Perry tend not to be denizens of Cole’s tobacco-scented inner sanctum, a wide variety of members are often seen slipping in and out.</p> 
<p>Alongside top Republican appropriators like California Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51306" data-person-id="51306">Ken Calvert</a> are some GOP lawmakers who don’t sit on the spending panel, among them Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/385782" data-person-id="385782">Derrick Van Orden</a> of Wisconsin, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/240947" data-person-id="240947">Andrew Garbarino</a> of New York and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227109" data-person-id="227109">Don Bacon</a> of Nebraska. Some Democrats, including California Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259997" data-person-id="259997">Jimmy Panetta</a>, are known to drop in.</p> 
<p>“I've learned more in that room than anywhere else in Congress about how things operate,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/416993" data-person-id="416993">Mark Alford</a>, a second-term GOP congressman from Missouri who coined the “Cigar SCIF” moniker. “But it's just good to have a place to have honest conversations and develop friendships.”</p> 
<p>A grand photo of Cole’s great aunt, a famous Chickasaw storyteller known as Te Ata, is mounted beside a window overlooking the west front of the Capitol and the National Mall. Most days in winter, a fire burns in a black marble fireplace.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/c2/e0/0769d78947afbf2f202ef55d6691/2026-0205-cole-francis-1-1-edit.jpg" alt="A photo of Cole’s great aunt, a famous Chickasaw storyteller known as Te Ata, hangs in his office." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="A photo of Cole’s great aunt, a famous Chickasaw storyteller known as Te Ata, hangs in his office."/><p>“I think space is a great gift, and I think it's misused quite often,” Cole said. “These are grand settings. They're lovely rooms. They're obviously immediately adjacent to the floor. You can't have much better real estate than that.”</p> 
<p>Engraved on one chair is the name of Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51589" data-person-id="51589">Hal Rogers</a>, the longest-serving House member and a former Appropriations chair. The 88-year-old Kentucky Republican is often by Cole’s side during House votes and spends hours each week in the room off the floor, which Rogers said wasn’t used as “an open forum” until Cole got the gavel.</p> 
<p>When Nebraska GOP Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196030" data-person-id="196030">Mike Flood</a> — more than 25 years Cole’s junior — came to Capitol Hill in 2022, he sought Cole’s guidance on how to get on the Financial Services Committee. He got an invitation to another one of Cole’s smoke-filled offices — this one upstairs, next to the Rules Committee hearing room where Cole was then serving as chair — and received an education on Congress from Cole and “four other guys north of 75.”</p> 
<p>“The people who don't avail themselves of that have a much different experience in Congress,” Flood said in an interview, “because they're not learning the Congress as an institution, as a functioning way to make laws and govern Americans.”</p> 
<p>Cole likes to be regarded as an institutionalist and a “practical politician.” He holds a masters degree from Yale and a doctorate from the University of Oklahoma — both in British history — and is an avid reader of nonfiction accounts of war and politics. He was a member of the Oklahoma Senate in the 1980s, ran the National Republican Congressional Committee in the 1990s, served as Oklahoma secretary of state and then came to Congress in 2003.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/af/2f/075e66204444adb023d7c2e29a1c/ap23290603422057-edit.jpg" alt="Cole and Rep. Hal Rogers (R-Ky.) on the House floor in 2023. The 88-year-old Kentucky Republican is often by Cole’s side during House votes and spends hours each week in the room off the floor." data-portal-copyright="J. Scott Applewhite/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="23290603422057" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Cole and Rep. Hal Rogers (R-Ky.) on the House floor in 2023. The 88-year-old Kentucky Republican is often by Cole’s side during House votes and spends hours each week in the room off the floor."/><p>“Experience, knowledge, temperament and persistence — he has it all in spades,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51356" data-person-id="51356">Mario Diaz-Balart</a> (R-Fla.), a senior appropriator and one of Cole’s closest friends. “The cigar does not hurt.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium is-centered">Beyond the House</h5> 
<p>Last March, Cole joined with House GOP leaders to halt bipartisan negotiations with Democrats and instead advanced a six-month funding patch — an audacious move that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/14/schumer-democrats-anger-shutdown-fight-00231908" target="_blank">spurred Democratic fury</a> and fueled the government shutdown this past fall.</p> 
<p>“The Democrats just didn't think we could do it,” Cole said. “I think that’s what made the 12 bills possible this year. They know we can do it. They know we will.”</p> 
<p>Even as Trump directly undermines Congress’ power to steer funding, Cole frequently praises the president in the first lines of any speech or statement celebrating a spending deal. He also was among the Republicans who voted Jan. 6, 2021, against certifying Joe Biden as the winner of the 2020 election, saying in a statement at the time that he did so “on behalf of my constituents."</p> 
<p>“I look on the administration as allies, not as enemies. But I also recognize that they can't just do what they want to do,” Cole said this year. “Anybody that thinks that Congress has somehow lost its power of the purse — it has not.”</p> 
<p>As Congress stares down another partial government shutdown over DHS funding, Cole is deferring to the White House in negotiations with Democrats who are demanding changes to the administration’s immigration enforcement tactics.</p> 
<p>“Clearly the decision is going to be made by the president on this,” he said.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/1e/cc/dc47ec364663997821eaa178085c/2026-0205-cole-francis-1-6-edit.jpg" alt="One of the windows in Cole's office overlooks the National Mall." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="One of the windows in Cole's office overlooks the National Mall."/><p>Cole also doesn’t meddle in the negotiations of his “cardinals,” the dozen lawmakers who chair his panel’s subcommittees, empowering each of them to resolve differences with Democrats on their own.</p> 
<p>“His word is gold,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151805" data-person-id="151805">Chuck Fleischmann</a> (R-Tenn.), one of those chairs. “He's infinitely fair, infinitely reasonable. He is so well attuned to working with people.”</p> 
<p>Cole instead focuses on negotiating overall totals and tricky policy disputes with Congress’ other three top appropriators: Collins, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a> (D-Conn.) and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51219" data-person-id="51219">Patty Murray</a> (D-Wash.).</p> 
<p>None of those women smoke cigars, and they prefer to meet in Collins’ less-odorous office on the Senate side. But they all have a close relationship with Cole.</p> 
<p>Murray and Cole go back years: They faced off in negotiations over health, education and labor funding as subcommittee chairs during Paul Ryan’s speakership. Cole described the Washington Democrat as “a candid politician” who is “steely in her resolve” but “wants to get to a deal.”</p> 
<p>Cole said Collins reminds him of his mother, who was the first Native American woman to serve in the Oklahoma Senate. “Her political skills are formidable,” he said, and “she's a hard person not to like.”</p> 
<p>As for his Democratic counterpart in the House, Cole calls DeLauro one of his “favorite people in Congress” and describes her as “an Italian grandmother.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/0f/fa/4e0f1d404716ac3d93823418f413/ap26021711285961-edit.jpg" alt="Cole and Rep. Rosa DeLauro (D-Conn.) greet each other as they prepare to testify before the House Appropriations Committee at the U.S. Capitol, on Jan. 21, 2026." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26021711285961" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Cole and Rep. Rosa DeLauro (D-Conn.) greet each other as they prepare to testify before the House Appropriations Committee at the U.S. Capitol, on Jan. 21, 2026."/><p>The respect is mutual. “You make a lot of acquaintances in this business, but you have few friends,” DeLauro said in an interview. “Tom Cole is my friend.”</p> 
<p>That relationship was built not only through years of hard-nosed negotiations but also gentler moments like a 2024 Middle East trip the pair took as part of a bipartisan delegation of appropriators.</p> 
<p>“I’m going to drink all the bourbon with you that I can,” she recalled telling him. “On the other hand, I’m not smoking any cigars.”</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misstated the year of a congressional delegation trip to the Middle East. It was in 2024.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-06T14:49:07-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Nevada Republican Mark Amodei to retire</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/nevada-republican-mark-amodei-retiring-00769192</link>
      <description>Amodei’s decision comes just three months after President Donald Trump blessed him with a “Complete and Total endorsement for Re-election."</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-3454-d0f8-adde-fe5eb4dc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 14:02:40 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/34/f0/68f7e8184435ae8168e5f8377954/congress-budget-81404.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">J. Scott Applewhite/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Mark Amodei (R-Nev.) on Capitol Hill in Washington on Oct. 2, 2023.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/34/f0/68f7e8184435ae8168e5f8377954/congress-budget-81404.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/177013" data-person-id="177013">Mark Amodei</a> (R-Nev.), the top Republican on the DHS appropriations subcommittee, will not seek reelection to the House this year, he announced Friday.</p> 
<p>The eight-term lawmaker is just the latest high-profile Republican to announce plans to retire from Congress in an increasingly murky midterm environment for the GOP.</p> 
<p>“I came to Congress to solve problems and to make sure our State and Nation have strong voice in the federal policy and oversight processes,” <a href="https://amodei.house.gov/news-releases/amodei-announces-retirement" target="_blank">he said in a statement</a>. “I look forward to finishing my term.”</p> 
<p>Amodei’s 2nd District is Republican-leaning and would likely remain in GOP hands even in a tough year for the party overall. He’s the only Republican in the state’s congressional delegation.</p> 
<p>Amodei’s decision comes just three months after President Donald Trump blessed him with a “Complete and Total Endorsement for Re-election” in November. At the time, it appeared he would run again.</p> 
<p>“Thank you Mr. President @realDonaldTrump!” <a href="https://x.com/AmodeiForNevada/status/1985448520665489444" target="_blank">Amodei wrote in response</a>.</p> 
<p>Just over a week ago, Amodei became the rare Republican to publicly push back against elements of the president’s agenda, when he called for a “pivot” in <a href="https://amodei.house.gov/news-releases/amodeis-statement-homeland-security-developments-minnesota" target="_blank">ICE’s core mission in Minnesota</a>. He also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/house-gop-offer-to-dems-explicit-funding-for-ice-body-cameras-following-minneapolis-shooting-pro-00729265" target="_blank">led a DHS funding bill with explicit funding</a> for body cameras to be worn by ICE officials and additional deescalation training for DHS officers.</p> 
<p>Amodei has also worked to curtail DHS’ ability to move congressionally appropriated money in this year’s funding bill for the agency, a move he in January <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/dhs-reprogramming-crackdown-00713569" target="_blank">conceded could be unpopular with White House officials</a>, including Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem.</p> 
<p>But <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-funding-deal-shutdown-00763718" target="_blank">momentum toward a federal funding deal for DHS has stalled</a> due to the chaos in Minnesota, and Congress has just days to avert a shutdown affecting the agency.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elections overhaul takes center stage in House as hard-right pressure mounts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499</link>
      <description>The SAVE America Act, up for a vote next week in the House, has been a rare rallying point for a divided GOP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-30a0-d647-addc-bbe70c5a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ca/bd/b609b3fe48c098d30e0ba721bb05/u-s-congress-97978.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>GOP hard-liners like Reps. Chip Roy of Texas (left) and Andy Harris of Maryland (center) have pressured Speaker Mike Johnson for a fresh vote on an election overhaul.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ca/bd/b609b3fe48c098d30e0ba721bb05/u-s-congress-97978.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House is set to vote next week on a once-obscure elections bill that has now become a household name among hard-right activists and a major rallying point for an otherwise divided GOP.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7296" target="_blank">SAVE America Act</a>, aimed at tightening voter registration standards, has a difficult path to enactment despite a no-holds-barred pressure campaign from the likes of President Donald Trump and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/elon-musk-gop-comeback-00751572" target="_blank">tech mogul Elon Musk</a>. Democrats are certain to filibuster the bill in the Senate, and it’s unlikely the GOP is ready to take extraordinary steps to overcome that hurdle.</p> 
<p>But amid growing fears that their party is not doing enough to address Americans’ key concerns — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/republicans-affordability-congress-00679545" target="_blank">rising prices chief among them</a> — House GOP leaders and key senators have chosen to put the election security push at the center of their agenda.</p> 
<p>The issue almost tanked a massive government funding package this week and threatened to extend a four-day partial government shutdown — until Trump intervened and ordered House Republicans to pass the bill without attaching the elections legislation.</p> 
<p>But the issue is not going away. Besides the House action next week — the chamber’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2025/04/14/the-house-passed-the-save-act-what-comes-next-00288458" target="_blank">second vote on a version of the legislation</a> in less than a year — there is a mounting campaign on GOP senators to find ways around Democratic opposition and get the bill to Trump’s desk.</p> 
<p>Trump is personally involved in the effort. Majority Leader Steve Scalise spoke with the president about the bill at a Jan. 29 White House meeting, and GOP Sens. Mike Lee of Utah, Rick Scott of Florida and Ron Johnson of Wisconsin <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/gop-senators-meet-with-trump-on-save-act-00767525" target="_blank">met with Trump to discuss it</a> Thursday afternoon.</p> 
<p>Scalise said in an interview that Trump “wants to find the best place to get it passed so it can get signed into law” and Republican leaders are “in the process of working with the president to get the best path forward.”</p> 
<p>The legislation would <a href="https://roy.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-roy-senator-lee-launch-save-america-act-renewed-push-election-integrity" target="_blank">trigger major changes</a> to how Americans vote, including requiring would-be voters to present proof of citizenship to register, eliminating mail-only registrations, and requiring photo ID in every state for the first time. It would also require states to take new steps to remove noncitizens from existing voter rolls.</p> 
<p>The push for the bill has taken flight among GOP hard-liners, who won a private promise from Speaker Mike Johnson to schedule the upcoming vote, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the conversations, in lieu of attaching the election bill to the larger spending package and threatening its ability to clear the Senate.</p> 
<p>White House deputy chief of staff James Blair this week also wrangled House GOP holdouts upset over the lack of action on the elections bill. The top Trump political aide worked to salvage the funding package in a series of phone calls in the final minutes <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/congress-ends-shutdown-00762482" target="_blank">before it was ultimately passed</a>, according to three people with direct knowledge of the conversations.</p> 
<p>Democrats and voting-access advocates have attacked the legislation as likely to disenfranchise huge swaths of legitimate voters in a misguided effort to address an alleged epidemic of noncitizen voting that they say does not exist.</p> 
<p>“If you’re one of the tens of millions of U.S. citizens who does not have access to your birth certificate, or if you’re one of the 50 percent of Americans who don’t have a passport, the SAVE Act could make it impossible for you to participate in elections,” Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said this week.</p> 
<p>But the bill is in keeping with Trump’s longstanding belief, unsupported by evidence, that elections in many states are “rigged” in favor of Democrats and that strong federal action is needed to rectify it. He said in an interview this week that Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/trump-nationalize-elections-2026-midterms-00760015" target="_blank">should seek to “nationalize” elections</a>.</p> 
<p>Addressing House Republicans at a policy retreat last month, Trump told them they “ought to pass” the SAVE America Act, formerly known as the Safeguard American Voter Eligibility Act.</p> 
<p>“Our elections are crooked as hell, and you can win — not only win elections over that and not only win future elections, but you'll win every debate because the public is really angry about it,” he said.</p> 
<p>He reiterated the message in a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116020521328279296" target="_blank">Truth Social post</a> Thursday, published after his meeting with the three senators: “We are either going to fix [America’s elections], or we won’t have a Country any longer.”</p> 
<p>The House is expected to vote on a procedural measure Tuesday paving the final floor action later in the week. What happens in the Senate after that is less clear.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune has pledged to call the bill up for a vote at some point in the coming months, but under normal circumstances Democrats could block it from proceeding.</p> 
<p>Yet rank-and-file House Republicans and some GOP senators are pushing for a breakthrough, urging Thune to require a “talking filibuster” or “standing filibuster” that would eventually, they believe, force Democrats to relent. The change would force senators to be present and speaking on the Senate floor to block legislation, as opposed to the current practice of requiring 60 votes to end debate and move to the final passage of most bills.</p> 
<p>But Thune has treaded carefully around any suggestion that the 60-vote rule should be diluted. Many Republican senators want to see the supermajority threshold start in place, and Thune <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/thune-filibuster-deal-luna-00761867" target="_blank">dismissed claims from some House Republicans</a> this week that he had agreed to pursue the talking filibuster route. He said he would only agree to discuss the matter with his conference.</p> 
<p>With the Senate still working through how to pass long-term Department of Homeland Security funding, that internal conversation has yet to take place. Some senators are privately and publicly warning the push could tie up the Senate floor for weeks or months, blocking other GOP priorities.</p> 
<p>Some hard-line Republicans are floating a trial run, using the talking filibuster to try to pass a DHS funding stopgap, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the private discussions.</p> 
<p>“I would just remind people that the coin of the realm in the Senate is floor time, and we have a lot of things we have to do,” Thune told reporters. “Triggering a talking filibuster has implications and ramifications that I think everybody needs to be aware of. So we will have those discussions.”</p> 
<p>In a sign that Republicans are looking at this as more than a political messaging exercise, the bill’s proponents say they are addressing some of the criticisms of the bill — including that it could effectively bar members of the U.S. military stationed abroad from voting.</p> 
<p>Co-author Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) said there are exceptions in the bill that would address the military and other concerns but allow only “true absentee ballots.” He said he was otherwise focused on pushing the other chamber to sidestep Democrats and send the bill to Trump.</p> 
<p>“They get on the Senate floor, they can call the question, if there are people willing to speak … there'll be drama, and then we'll see what happens,” Roy said. “We'll see who wins, but that's what we're supposed to do.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-05T20:35:05-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>DHS watchdog details extensive probes into Trump's immigration crackdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/dhs-watchdog-probe-trump-immigration-00768311</link>
      <description>The investigations include reviews of hiring, interior immigration enforcement and expedited removal of individuals by ICE and CBP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-3063-d0f8-adde-fa7bd78a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 20:04:14 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/80/9f/05cb035e417f89e90d48e57aec41/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-63575.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ryan Murphy/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>The spate of investigations comes as the Trump administration faces an uproar from Democrats and a growing number of Republicans over its immigration enforcement operations in several states</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/80/9f/05cb035e417f89e90d48e57aec41/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-63575.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Department of Homeland Security’s independent watchdog disclosed numerous investigations into the department on Thursday as the White House faces heightened scrutiny over its nationwide immigration crackdown.</p> 
<p>The probes, some of which have previously been disclosed, span ICE’s hiring surge, expedited removal of individuals, use of force and compliance with detention standards. An additional review pertains to “DHS’ processes for determining U.S. citizenship for individuals detained or arrested during immigration enforcement operations.”</p> 
<p>The inspector general’s office is also conducting a probe into Customs and Border Patrol. The investigation — which is reviewing whether CBP conducts interior immigration enforcement in accordance with department policies and federal requirements — was opened in early January, according to a spokesperson for the DHS OIG.</p> 
<p>The spate of investigations comes as the Trump administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/noems-problems-go-beyond-the-ice-shootings-in-minneapolis-00767750" target="_blank">faces an uproar</a> from Democrats and a growing number of Republicans over its immigration enforcement operations in several states, which have at times turned violent. Senate Democrats are currently <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/dhs-negotiations-thune-shutdown-00767076" target="_blank">holding up DHS funding</a> over a list of demands for reforms to ICE and CBP, including requirements that federal officers wear body cameras and IDs. The administration has also refused to budge on a demand that immigration enforcement agents do not wear masks.</p> 
<p>DHS spokesperson Tricia McLaughlin dismissed the probes, writing in a statement that "the supposed number of ongoing matters doesn’t say anything about their disposition or the facts."</p> 
<p>“DHS’s job is to secure the homeland, and we do so in line with federal law and the Constitution," she said. "The Trump administration is committed to transparency, and we have no problem with honest and impartial oversight.”</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/01/25/donald-trump-inspectors-general-firing-00200611" target="_blank">purged independent watchdogs</a> for several government agencies during the first month of his second term, but Joseph Cuffari — the inspector general for DHS nominated by Trump during his first term — remains in place.</p> 
<p>Dozens of congressional Democrats wrote last week to Cuffari <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-investigation-use-of-force-ice-00761953" target="_blank">urging him to expedite his probe</a> into “whether ICE investigates allegations of use of excessive force,” which his office opened in June.</p> 
<p>In a Thursday statement, Cuffari’s office said the timeline for conducting an oversight review “is affected by several variables.” The office has an internal goal of completing audits within 397 days but routinely misses the benchmark, <a href="https://www.gao.gov/assets/gao-26-107341.pdf" target="_blank">according to a report</a> released by the Government Accountability Office last month.</p> 
<p>“If, however, during our work we find matters that warrant immediate attention and action (such as those posing serious risk or imminent threat to safety, health, property, or continuity of operations), DHS OIG has mechanisms to promptly inform the Department and Congress, rather than waiting for a final report,” the office said.</p> 
<p>Dozens of Democratic lawmakers have also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865" target="_blank">called for the removal</a> of DHS Secretary Kristi Noem in recent weeks, although <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/democratic-house-leaders-kristi-noem-impeachment-00749643" target="_blank">an impeachment resolution</a> is unlikely to garner sufficient bipartisan support in the House.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tim Scott clashes with Chuck Grassley, Dick Durbin over Nazi-linked bank probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/tim-scott-chides-judiciary-committee-in-turf-battle-00767522</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2f93-d647-addc-afd7b4cb0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 15:54:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The leaders of two Republican-led committees are quietly locked in a behind-the-scenes turf battle.</p> 
<p>Sen. Tim Scott (R-S.C.), who helms the Senate Banking Committee, <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-2f52-d647-addc-afd747a70000" target="_blank"><u>sent a letter</u></a> this week to Sens. Chuck Grassley (R-Iowa) and Dick Durbin (D-Ill.), the chair and ranking member of the Senate Judiciary panel, saying he was “surprised” to learn that Judiciary had convened a hearing on the history of Credit Suisse’s servicing of Nazi-linked bank accounts.</p> 
<p>“While this subject matter is of historic importance, its connection to the Judiciary Committee's jurisdiction is less clear,” Scott wrote in the letter, a copy of which was obtained by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>In his opening statement at the Judiciary hearing earlier this week, Grassley said the proceedings were designed to provide an “interim investigative update” on the probe he launched in the previous Congress with Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse (D-R.I.) when the two men served as the ranking member and chair of the Budget Committee.</p> 
<p>But Scott, in his letter, said that Senate rules gave the Banking Committee jurisdiction over banks, banking and financial institutions — and “the rules do not provide an exception to this exclusive jurisdiction for morally grave topics.” </p> 
<p>“The subject matter of this hearing should therefore fall under the Banking Committee's oversight because the Banking Committee has the expertise, jurisdiction, and institutional responsibility to investigate these kinds of banking matters,” he added.</p> 
<p>It’s not the first time the two committees have clashed, according to the letter: Scott recalled receiving a note from the Judiciary Committee last month when the Banking Committee took up legislation on which Judiciary believed it should have been consulted.</p> 
<p>Now, Scott contended, the Judiciary Committee is revisiting previous work by the Banking Committee that “could provide benefits to banking regulation and bring additional accountability to banks” — but it had to be done in consultation with Banking.</p> 
<p>Scott is asking Grassley and Durbin to hand over a swath of information, including records related to U.S. banks and details on any future hearings on the subject, by Feb. 25.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Grassley declined to comment on the letter. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-05T15:15:45-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>DHS standoff threatens bipartisan Munich delegation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/dhs-standoff-threatens-bipartisan-munich-delegation-00767475</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2f5d-d3b5-addf-efdd2bad0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 14:53:43 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Joe Gould and Connor O'Brien</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Joe Gould and Connor O'Brien</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans are weighing whether to bow out of a major international gathering next week as GOP leaders press them to stay in Washington and hammer out a Homeland Security Department funding deal.</p> 
<p>This year’s Munich Security Conference — a marquee transatlantic gathering that begins Feb. 13 — has taken on new urgency in the wake of President Donald Trump’s threats to invade Greenland, a Danish territory, and tariff core NATO allies over the dispute. Trump backed down, but dozens of lawmakers planned to go in order to shore up ties and reaffirm America’s commitment to NATO.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), a Munich mainstay and Trump ally, said Thursday he won’t attend unless a DHS deal is reached. The department is on a short-term stopgap funding measure while Democrats are demanding new limits and oversight on Immigration and Customs Enforcement practices, which Republicans say would undercut security.</p> 
<p>“The reason we go to these places is to have an American voice, and if we can't get our act together here, a lot of people are wondering what we're going to do about Russia,” he said. “People say if you want to be safe at home you have to engage the world, and I agree.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), another regular at the conference, told reporters his decision to go would hinge on the status of cross-party negotiations.</p> 
<p>“Game day decision,” said Tillis, the top Republican on the Senate’s NATO Observer Group. “It's gonna be based on how well we're working and if the Democrats are being reasonable. That’s one thing, and if they’re not, it’s another thing.”</p> 
<p>Not all Republicans are on the fence. Senate Armed Services Chair Roger Wicker (R-Miss.) said he is going to the Munich Security Conference again this year and doesn't anticipate the threat of a DHS shutdown derailing his trip, which includes Italy’s defense ministry and the Organization for Security Cooperation in Europe’s parliamentary assembly in Vienna.</p> 
<p>A spending deal that became law this week gives lawmakers until next Friday to negotiate a Homeland Security funding package. But funding will lapse if Republicans and Democrats can’t forge a deal by next weekend or don’t pass another stopgap.</p> 
<p>Earlier in the day, Senate Majority Leader John Thune told reporters that it's a “serious question” whether senators should suspend their travel — including to Munich — until the impasse ends. </p> 
<p>“If we get to the end of next week and we're in a shutdown posture, I think that the idea of people going on trips, no matter how justified or well-intended they are, it seems like that ought to be a non-starter,” he said.</p> 
<p>Sen. Chris Coons of Delaware, the top Democrat on the panel that controls defense funding, argued lawmakers from both parties should attend the international conference despite the funding standoff to shore up the transatlantic alliance. Trump’s Greenland pressure campaign “profoundly undermined” European confidence in the U.S., he said.</p> 
<p>"We have a genuine problem in our transatlantic relationship," Coons told reporters. "And to cancel sending a large delegation to Munich simply so that we can figure out how to actually do policing in a democracy sends exactly the wrong message."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lindsey Graham says Johnson is open to expanding Smith probe payouts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/graham-pitches-johnson-on-payouts-00767375</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2f1a-d0f8-adde-ff5a62e10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:42:53 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>South Carolina Sen. Lindsey Graham is pitching fellow Republicans on expanding who can sue over the now-defunct Jack Smith investigation — and Graham claims he has a key supporter in Speaker Mike Johnson.</p> 
<p>Graham said in a statement to POLITICO that he had spoken with Johnson about his push to allow lawsuits from people he claims were improperly targeted by the former special counsel during his probe of the 2020 election. Johnson, he said, is amenable to expanding who can sue beyond just the handful of GOP senators who had their phone records seized.</p> 
<p>“I had a very good conversation with Speaker Johnson who does, in my view, want to open the courthouse doors to people wronged and hold Jack Smith accountable,” Graham said. “He wants to expand the ability to sue to more people, not less, consistent with congressional ethics rules. I share that view.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Johnson did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>The interchamber communication is the latest turn in a monthslong saga over <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/john-thune-government-funding-phone-records-seizure-00646094" target="_blank">letting Graham and other senators sue the Justice Department</a> for potentially millions of dollars over Smith’s decision to subpoena their phone records.</p> 
<p>The provision was tucked into a spending bill enacted in November, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/senate-republicans-phones-sue-jack-smith-00651463" target="_blank">prompting an uproar from Democrats and House Republicans</a> who saw it as a case of secret self-dealing. The House in turn moved last month to insert its own provision in a separate spending bill undoing the effort — prompting the South Carolina Republican to lash out at the speaker during a floor speech last week.</p> 
<p>Graham briefly held up the spending bill but won a commitment from Senate Majority Leader John Thune for a separate vote on an expanded provision that would allow not only senators to sue, but also other members of Congress, groups and individuals.</p> 
<p>“We’re going to give everyone in the South Carolina delegation the chance to open the courthouse doors to conservatives who were targeted by Jack Smith and the Biden DOJ,” Graham said Thursday.</p> 
<p>At the same time, Graham has sought to emphasize that his legislation is not aimed at self-enrichment, claiming to reporters last week that the Senate Ethics Committee confirmed he could not personally profit.</p> 
<p>The Ethics Committee guidance, which was reviewed by POLITICO, holds that senators are not entitled to receive monetary compensation under the original provision enacted in November but can seek a declaratory judgment and/or injunctive relief. Graham’s forthcoming legislation, his office said, will follow the committee guidelines.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bessent refuses to say the administration will not sue the next Fed chair</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/bessent-fed-chair-lawsuit-00767130</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2eef-de8a-a1fc-ffef21930002</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 12:53:36 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Aiden Reiter</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aiden Reiter</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent on Thursday left open the possibility the administration could sue President Donald Trump’s pick for Federal Reserve chair, Kevin Warsh, if he doesn’t deliver on the president’s desired interest rate cuts.</p> 
<p>Trump said Saturday he would consider suing Warsh if he did not cut interest rates. The Fed is an independent agency.</p> 
<p>When asked by Sen. Elizabeth Warren (D-Mass.) during a Senate Banking Committee hearing about the possibility of a lawsuit, Bessent refused to answer.</p> 
<p>“That is up to the president,” he said, before adding: “Warsh is highly qualified.”</p> 
<p>The Trump administration, including Bessent, has been sharply critical of the Fed and its current Chair Jerome Powell for its interest rate policy and its handling of a building renovation. The <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/scott-powell-doj-probe-00764230" target="_blank">Department of Justice is investigating</a> Powell in relation to the renovation, moves Powell has called “pretexts.”</p> 
<p>Bessent furthered that criticism Thursday, saying Treasury cannot print “magic money” to solve some of the nation’s economic issues — referring to the Fed’s ability to expand the amount of money in circulation, a power both Bessent and Warsh say has been overused.</p> 
<p>The comments echo remarks Bessent made in a fiery <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/02/bessent-outlines-deregulation-priorities-to-lawmakers-00764130" target="_blank">House hearing</a> Wednesday. “The Fed has lost accountability,” he said. “It lost the trust of the American people when it allowed the greatest inflation in 49 years.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), who has said he will <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/powell-pardon-tillis-blockade-00763054" target="_blank">not vote</a> for Warsh until the Powell probe is resolved, said senators had already heard from Powell about the cost overruns.</p> 
<p>“[Powell] was testifying and we didn’t see a crime,” he said.</p> 
<p>There were multiple moments of tension between the Treasury secretary and Democratic senators Thursday, similar to Wednesday’s at-times rocky House meeting.</p> 
<p>Bessent took shots at Warren, with whom he has feuded publicly in the past. When she asked why he had previously written that tariffs would be inflationary — an economic effect he and the administration argue is not at play today — he answered that he is not always right.</p> 
<p>“A year before [writing that letter to investors], I also wrote that I thought Senator Warren would be the Democratic presidential nominee. So my predictions have been bad,” he said.</p> 
<p>In one line of questioning from multiple senators, Bessent was asked how he, as acting director of the Internal Revenue Service, would handle the president’s $10 billion dollar lawsuit against the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/trump-sues-irs-leaked-tax-returns-00756718" target="_blank">tax agency</a>, filed last week.</p> 
<p>“It’s a Justice department matter,” he said. “I will follow the law.” He acknowledged that if the president were to be successful, the funds would come out of the Treasury General Account, the checking account of the government that he oversees.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DHS negotiations have yet to get underway, Thune says, as shutdown clock ticks</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/dhs-negotiations-thune-shutdown-00767076</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2edc-d647-addc-afdf76bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 12:33:24 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With eight days to avert a Department of Homeland Security shutdown, serious negotiations have yet to begin, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said Thursday.</p> 
<p>The South Dakota Republican said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a> (R-Ala.), who is leading the talks for Republicans, has reached out to Democrats for a sitdown but has gotten “crickets” so far in response.</p> 
<p>Britt <a href="https://x.com/SenKatieBritt/status/2019269903488823471" target="_blank">publicly slammed</a> a Democratic offer released Wednesday night as a “a ridiculous Christmas list of demands for the press,” while Thune also pooh-poohed <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-2c02-d647-addc-afc7b33a0000" target="_blank">the proposal</a> from Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> and House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>.</p> 
<p>“There are a few things that there’s probably some room to negotiate on,” Thune said about the 10-item list. “But a lot of that stuff obviously just wasn’t serious.”</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a> of Connecticut, who is the top Democrat on the Appropriations subpanel overseeing DHS that Britt chairs, said Thursday, “I don't think that's accurate” when asked about claims that Democrats were not willing to sit down. Britt was also spotted talking Thursday afternoon with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/201768" data-person-id="201768">Brian Schatz</a> (D-Hawaii), a frequent leadership go-between. </p> 
<p>Thune is waiting to see if the talks shake loose by Thursday afternoon, when senators will leave Washington for the week. He warned he is ready to start moving Monday to pass another DHS stopgap bill ahead of the Feb. 13 deadline.</p> 
<p>“If they refuse to sit down and actually come to the table and negotiate, pretty clearly we’ll need one,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>Republicans haven’t decided how long that stopgap should be. Thune has floated a two- or three-week patch if negotiations are ongoing but is also warning Congress could shift to long-term continuing resolution, keeping current funding levels in place through September, if talks don’t progress.</p> 
<p>He said Thursday that the length of the stopgap would depend on what Democrats would accept since their votes will be needed to advance another patch through the Senate. Many House and Senate Democrats have vowed not to support another CR, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/02/05/the-dems-not-opposed-to-another-dhs-punt-00766667" target="_blank">though a crucial swath</a> of senators have left the door open.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: The Democrats not opposed to another DHS punt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/05/congress/dhs-funding-democrats-deal-stopgap-continuing-resolution-00766669</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2c8e-d0f8-adde-fedecaff0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A sizable number of Senate Democrats haven’t ruled out another short-term funding punt for the Department of Homeland Security.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders Hakeem Jeffries and Chuck Schumer sent a <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-2c02-d647-addc-afc7b33a0000" target="_blank">formal wishlist of DHS policy changes</a> Wednesday to GOP leaders Mike Johnson and John Thune. But Republicans <a href="https://x.com/SenKatieBritt/status/2019269903488823471?s=20" target="_blank">have little interest</a> in their ideas, with leaders hinting at the need for another continuing resolution to buy more time for talks.</p> 
<p><b>— Dodging the question: </b>“We need to keep as many options on the table as possible,” Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) told reporters when asked whether she would rule out a CR.</p> 
<p>Shaheen was one of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/09/senate-democrats-shutdown-vote-00644146" target="_blank">eight Senate Democrats</a> who voted to help Republicans end the record government shutdown last fall. Some other senators in that group also didn’t give direct answers Wednesday on whether they’d support a second DHS stopgap — a stark contrast to many fellow Democrats, who immediately rejected the idea.</p> 
<p>Most of the eight Democrats instead noted there’s more than a week before the funding cliff arrives.</p> 
<p>“As soon as you say [another CR], you can bet it’ll take another two, three weeks to reach a conclusion,” Sen. Dick Durbin, the No. 2 Democrat, told Calen. “We can fix this problem. We’ve got enough time to do it by the 13th of this month.”</p> 
<p>“We’re going to give [Republicans] a proposal and they should say yes to it,” Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.) told POLITICO. Asked if he’d help move another funding patch if Republicans object to their pitches, Kaine said, “I won’t say past that.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto (D-Nev.) also did not respond directly to questions about whether she’d support another DHS CR.</p> 
<p><b>— The brewing CR length fight:</b> Another stopgap to buy time for more talks is one thing; a full-year CR like what Thune is floating is another.</p> 
<p>Democrats want to force the White House and Republicans into a deal in the next few days. They are opposed to a yearlong measure that would keep the status quo at DHS and allow the administration more leeway in how it uses money for ICE and Customs and Border Protection.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats who plan to attend Thursday morning’s National Prayer Breakfast are hoping to talk directly with President Donald Trump about his immigration agenda and the recent killings of two U.S. citizens in Minnesota at the hands of federal agents.</p> 
<p>Thune is open to another two-week measure, but said “it may be the best way to deal with this particular appropriations bill is do a yearlong CR, if that’s what it takes.” Keep an eye on whether the majority leader starts laying the procedural groundwork for a CR before the Senate adjourns Thursday.</p> 
<p>While Johnson is “optimistic” there will be a DHS deal, he told POLITICO he was “neither ruling it in or out” when it comes to a short-term CR.</p> 
<p>“I don’t make any projections on that,” Johnson added about the possibility of a full-year CR for DHS.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— The likely next member of the House: </b>New Jersey voters Thursday will pick Gov. Mikie Sherrill’s likely successor in Congress in the first congressional Democratic primary election of the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>Eleven Democrats are vying in a special election primary to fill the reliably-blue 11th District seat. Among the front-runners is former Rep. Tom Malinowski, who represented the 7th District for two terms before he lost the 2022 race to Republican Rep. Tom Kean.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy, Meredith Lee Hill and Timothy Cama contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hill Republican who could get a deal on AI — if his leadership lets him</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/obernolte-ai-framework-congress-00764601</link>
      <description>Rep. Jay Obernolte’s compromise approach to AI regulation is seen by many in the tech industry as their best hope to block state AI laws. But do GOP leaders want what he’s selling?</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-29cf-d647-addc-abcf16820000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f9/76/73c16cec434fb1a4e8eeb68ec685/u-s-congress-68781.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Jay Obernolte speaks with reporters on Capitol Hill on May 7, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f9/76/73c16cec434fb1a4e8eeb68ec685/u-s-congress-68781.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brendan Bordelon and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brendan Bordelon and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tech companies desperately want Congress to pass a federal law this year blocking state rules on artificial intelligence, and many think their best shot lies with California Republican Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/76dc3dbe-83e3-41e1-875c-58c75270e9b0" target="_blank">Jay Obernolte</a>, a former computer engineer now serving his third term in the House.</p> 
<p>There’s just one problem: House GOP leaders don’t appear to be listening to him.</p> 
<p>AI industry lobbyists have been pushing Capitol Hill for months to pass a bill that would preempt the ability of states to enact AI laws, arguing it would stop a patchwork of conflicting state rules from impeding innovation.</p> 
<p>Many see Obernolte, who co-chaired a bipartisan AI task force last Congress and has deep relationships across the aisle, as their greatest hope for action before the end of the year. They say his technical acumen and consensus-building approach on AI will be key to clinching an agreement with Democrats, necessary in a politically polarized Washington.</p> 
<p>“If there is anyone in the House who can run point and cobble together the pieces on what meaningful federal AI standards and an AI package could look like, it's Jay Obernolte,” said Tony Samp, principal AI adviser at lobbying firm DLA Piper, in an interview.</p> 
<p>Obernolte is currently <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/09/obernolte-prepping-his-own-ai-legislation-as-cruz-moves-00561579" target="_blank">working on an AI bill</a> that could pair preemption of state AI laws with a framework to regulate the technology, including new research infrastructure and safety checks on advanced AI models — a compromise that senior AI lobbyists now support after Hill Republicans failed twice last year to unilaterally block state AI regulations.</p> 
<p>“You need to codify the federal regulatory framework for AI and, if you don’t do that … essentially you’re saying that there’s no regulation,” said Obernolte in a recent interview. “And I don’t blame people for being uncomfortable with that.”</p> 
<p>But four senior tech industry representatives who want a deal, granted anonymity to discuss sensitive legislative talks, said Obernolte’s influence has so far been stifled by GOP leadership, and that he’s been largely absent from high-level Hill negotiations over the future of AI policy.</p> 
<p>It’s a sign, they said, that Republican leaders may not be serious about reaching an AI compromise, despite President Donald Trump’s recent call for Congress to come up with a solution to thwart states from freelancing. Both the tech industry representatives and some Democrats instead worry that GOP leaders are refusing to budge on their stance that there should be minimal regulation of the technology — a position shared by some <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/20/big-tech-gets-worried-about-trumps-ai-czar-00701112" target="_blank">venture capitalists and White House officials</a>.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders publicly insist they’re on the same page with Obernolte and share his goal of drafting consensus legislation that would preempt state AI laws, even as they have so far failed to embrace his ideas and, in fact, appear determined to pursue other tracks.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/9254ce9b-038e-47a5-aab0-17cd3173dc0a" target="_blank">Steve Scalise</a> said that while the Louisiana Republican supports a relatively hands-off approach to AI regulation, “preempting a patchwork of countless varying state laws does not mean no guardrails.”</p> 
<p>Nonetheless, Scalise recently expressed skepticism towards any regulations on the sector — a stance that could make a political compromise on AI harder to achieve.</p> 
<p>“A lot of these people that want to limit and regulate any industry, a lot of times, what they’re really trying to do is make it hard to do those things in America,” Scalise told reporters in early January. “We should maintain that edge, and we do it by innovating — not by regulating.”</p> 
<p>The four tech representatives said they’ve so far seen little to suggest that leadership is interested in Obernolte’s plan for an AI accord. They said he should have been brought into the preemption effort last year, after Senate Commerce Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/9c10f49c-c99d-46b3-854b-28db18856420" target="_blank">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Texas) <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/02/ai-regulation-trump-allies-state-powers-00428337" target="_blank">fell short in his efforts</a> to insert a ban on state AI rules into the GOP’s tax and spending megabill.</p> 
<p>They also said Obernolte’s absence from last fall’s unsuccessful push by House leadership to insert a similar provision into the year-end defense bill was unfortunate, largely because it made a compromise tougher to achieve.</p> 
<p>“It was a little surprising that one of their best players wasn't even in the game during the latest push for federal AI standards,” said Samp.</p> 
<p>Connor Chapinski, Obernolte’s communications director, downplayed the characterization that Obernolte is being kept away from the GOP’s high-level AI strategy. In a statement, he said Obernolte remains fully engaged with his leadership and the Trump administration around crafting “thoughtful legislation.”</p> 
<p>Athina Lawson, a spokesperson for Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/575304ca-80a9-49bb-817e-4215621a1682" target="_blank">Mike Johnson</a>, in a statement credited Obernolte’s chairmanship of the task force with giving members “a clearer understanding of how to responsibly leverage the opportunities of artificial intelligence.” She said GOP leadership is coordinating with the Trump administration on AI and plans to “work through committees of jurisdiction to build consensus” among Republicans.</p> 
<p>The task force’s <a href="https://obernolte.house.gov/AITFReport" target="_blank">255-page report</a> — released by Obernolte and fellow California Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/aac1bf52-a187-494e-afd6-d86f9cd0be6c" target="_blank">Ted Lieu</a>, a Democrat, in December 2024 — laid out a slew of findings and policy recommendations related to AI. Yet despite some interest from the tech industry, the panel was not renewed by GOP leadership and its recommendations have gone virtually unheeded.</p> 
<p>One senior GOP aide who works on AI policy, granted anonymity to discuss internal GOP strategy, said the report was produced under former President Joe Biden and was “somewhat outdated now that we have a new administration, a new dynamic in Congress.”</p> 
<p>A senior Democratic aide who was closely involved with the task force, also granted anonymity to speak candidly, said it has become clear over a period of time that “Mr. Obernolte, for better or worse, had been sort of sidelined … He was like their lead guy on AI, put in a corner.”</p> 
<p>Some Democrats are now looking to exploit what they perceive as a leadership gap on AI policy on the other side of the aisle. Lieu now co-chairs a new House Democratic Commission on AI, convened by House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/196306" target="_blank">Hakeem Jeffries</a> (N.Y.) and co-chaired by Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/1e33558b-6bee-4149-b50c-db990e1c6305" target="_blank">Josh Gottheimer</a> (N.J.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/5479cb8d-0608-4a9b-967c-538cd92946f4" target="_blank">Valerie Foushee</a> (N.C.). In the absence of bipartisan action, they plan to formulate their own plan for regulating the fast-moving technology.</p> 
<p>“The White House has led the industry astray, down a bad path,” Lieu said in an interview. “Steve Scalise is very opposed to any kind of legislation at the federal level. … And that’s now resulted in three things the tech industry wanted to avoid, which is, backlash from the public, backlash from bipartisan members of Congress and multiple states regulating their industry.”</p> 
<p>Gottheimer, in a recent interview, said, “I think Republicans have certainly ceded the turf.”</p> 
<p>There are signs that GOP leaders are starting to feel pressure to legislate on AI. Ohio Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/191ff88b-badc-4f7e-b8c8-e47d200f0aab" target="_blank">Jim Jordan</a> — chair of the Judiciary Committee, which has jurisdiction over AI issues like privacy, surveillance and intellectual property — suggested in a Monday interview that “I don’t know about moving anything, but we’re definitely talking about AI.”</p> 
<p>Jordan added that one of his staffers had just informed him that his panel should ramp up those discussions.</p> 
<p><i>Gabby Miller contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republican Barry Loudermilk won’t seek reelection</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/barry-loudermilk-georgia-retires-00766319</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2ad9-d3b5-addf-eadd82200000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 17:51:45 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Georgia Republican Rep. Barry Loudermilk announced he will not run for reelection this year, the latest Republican to retire amid what’s shaping up to be a tough midterm for Republicans.</p> 
<p>Loudermilk, who was first elected to Congress in 2014, said in a statement he’s retiring to “spend more dedicated time with my family.”</p> 
<p>“Although I continue to have strong support from the people of the Eleventh Congressional District, I believe it is time to contribute to my community, state, and nation in other ways,” he said in the statement.</p> 
<p>Loudermilk’s retirement comes as his select subcommittee reinvestigating the Jan. 6, 2021, attack at the Capitol ramps up its probe. </p> 
<p>The panel — which was launched as a response to the probe helmed by Rep. Bennie Thompson (D-Miss.) and now-former Rep. Liz Cheney (R-Wyo.) in the year after the attack — held its first hearings last month, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/jan-6-committee-subpoenas-t-mobile-for-records-relating-to-alleged-pipe-bomb-perpetrator-00764604" target="_blank">subpoenaed for phone records</a> in connection to the suspect accused of placing pipe bombs outside Republican and Democratic headquarters prior to the riot.</p> 
<p>Republicans will expect to retain Loudermilk’s seat in suburban Atlanta in November, which he won by 34 points in 2024. </p> 
<p>But the announcement marks the latest member of the House Republican caucus to leave Congress this cycle. Since the beginning of 2025, <a href="https://pressgallery.house.gov/member-data/casualty-list" target="_blank">33 other House Republicans</a> have resigned, announced their retirements or launched campaigns seeking other elected office.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top Oversight Republican mulls Bill Gates subpoena in Epstein probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/house-oversight-mulls-bill-gates-subpoena-00766254</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2ac0-d647-addc-abc7213d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 17:27:28 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Oversight and Government Reform Chair James Comer is considering calling Bill Gates to testify in his ongoing Jeffrey Epstein investigation, saying in an interview Wednesday a bipartisan group of lawmakers on the panel are pressing for a chance to question the billionaire Microsoft founder.</p> 
<p>“We're certainly looking at that, so we'll have more to come on that,” said the Kentucky Republican, adding that he’s been “approached by multiple Republicans and Democrats on the committee that would like to ask Bill Gates questions, so odds are.”</p> 
<p>Comer said he also wants to review an interview from Gates’ ex-wife, Melinda Gates, which will air on NPR Thursday, to see if she divulges any more information about her former husband and the extent of his possible involvement with Epstein, the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>Bill Gates was depicted in the release of Epstein-related materials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/bill-gates-appears-in-newly-released-photos-from-epstein-estate-00688695" target="_blank">in December</a> but has come under renewed security over his ties to the disgraced financier in the latest set of documents to be made public.</p> 
<p>The newest tranche of files includes allegations that Gates contracted a sexually transmitted disease from women in Epstein’s orbit. A spokesperson for Gates has called the allegations absurd.</p> 
<p>Gates has said he had <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/bill-gates-appears-in-newly-released-photos-from-epstein-estate-00688695" target="_blank">several dinners</a> with Epstein based on an understanding that Epstein would use his wealthy connections to fundraise for global health causes. When that didn’t happen, Gates told PBS NewsHour in 2021, he cut off the dinners, calling the meetings “a mistake.”</p> 
<p>Comer has already issued subpoenas for other individuals known to have had some ties to Epstein, or mentioned in the Epstein files, including Bill and Hillary Clinton. Negotiations with the former president and secretary of State over the terms of their testimonies dragged on for months, culminating in their final caving to the Oversight committee under threat of being held in contempt of Congress. They will now sit for closed-door depositions at the end of the month.</p> 
<p>It’s not immediately clear if Gates would be willing to share information with the committee.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats plan DHS funding offer as Thune floats long-term punt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/democrats-dhs-funding-offer-00764643</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-29ea-d647-addc-abefb3bd0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 13:30:29 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic and Republican leaders showed no sign of narrowing their <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-funding-deal-shutdown-00763718" target="_blank">differences on Department of Homeland Security funding</a> Wednesday as a Feb. 13 deadline draws nearer.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> and Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> reiterated demands for new restrictions on immigration enforcement agencies at a joint news conference. Flanked by other Democratic leaders, the leaders said they plan to submit draft legislation to Republicans by Thursday.</p> 
<p>“We're going to have tough, strong legislation,” Schumer said. “We want our Republican colleagues to finally get serious about this, because this is turning America inside out.”</p> 
<p>Earlier Wednesday, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> not only warned that a deal would be next to impossible to consummate before next week’s deadline but threatened a possible long-term stopgap that would effectively exclude changes to immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>Without quick progress in the talks, he said, “it may be the best way to deal with this particular appropriations bill is, do a year-long CR if that's what it takes,” Thune said, referring to a continuing resolution that would continue existing DHS funding levels through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>While the two Democratic leaders reiterated in a news conference that they are “on the same page,” Jeffries and Schumer declined to draw the same red lines on a full-year DHS punt.</p> 
<p>Jeffries said after the news conference he is “a hard no” on a full-year CR, while Schumer stopped short of a hard commitment.</p> 
<p>“Republicans shouldn't expect our votes if they're not willing to enact strong, tough reform,” he said when asked if Senate Democrats would oppose another punt.</p> 
<p>The list of demands Jeffries and Schumer laid out Wednesday largely tracks with an earlier list of DHS proposals Senate Democrats put forward after the Jan. 24 killing of a Minneapolis man by federal agents there. They include prohibiting masks for federal agents in most circumstances and requiring a judge to sign off on warrants for DHS immigration apprehensions — proposals that some top Republicans have already rejected.</p> 
<p>In addition to the policy sparring Wednesday, there was some personal squabbling, too — including over who should be involved in notching any agreement.</p> 
<p>Thune suggested any deal needed to be cut primarily between Democrats and the Trump administration. He also warned that he does not view Jeffries as a reliable negotiating partner.</p> 
<p>“He's just not, and I think he and, for that matter, Leader Schumer are afraid of their shadows and they are getting a lot of blowback and pressure from their left,” he said. “I don't think he wants a deal at all. I think he wants the issue.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries, in response to the comments, said it was Thune who is “afraid of his own shadow” in the form of President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>“We are negotiating in good faith because we want to try to achieve an outcome, but the changes that are enacted with respect to the way in which the Department of Homeland Security is conducting itself need to be bold, meaningful and transformative,” he told reporters.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tim Scott on DOJ probe into Powell: ‘I do not believe that he committed a crime’ in Fed HQ testimony</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/scott-powell-doj-probe-00764230</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2962-d0f8-adde-fb7a8d290000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:02:03 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Victoria Guida</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Victoria Guida</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> on Wednesday said he did not believe Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell committed a crime during his congressional testimony last year about the central bank’s headquarter renovations.</p> 
<p>“I was the one asking the questions,” he said on Fox Business. “Jay Powell was responding to me. Obviously, he and I have very, very strong disagreements on many issues, everyone.”</p> 
<p>He said it was time for a new head of the central bank and called Powell “inept” but added: “ineptness or being incompetent is not a criminal act.”</p> 
<p>“I believe what he did was made a gross error in judgment,” Scott said. “He was not prepared for that hearing. I do not believe that he committed a crime during the hearing.”</p> 
<p>The Justice Department issued subpoenas last month to the Fed, probing his statements to Congress, a fact revealed by Powell himself in an unprecedented video message where he accused the administration of using the investigation to pressure him to lower interest rates. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.), saying he fears for the Fed’s independence, has said he will not vote to advance any Fed nominees until the administration has finished its probe.</p> 
<p>Scott said the issue would be “resolved,” adding: “Thom Tillis will be voting for Kevin Warsh as the next chairman of the Federal Reserve.”</p> 
<p>Tillis has spoken positively of Warsh but said his stance regarding the DOJ investigation has not changed.</p> 
<p>Scott’s comments mark the first time that the powerful banking head has substantively weighed in on the administration’s move.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
