<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 20:08:37 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Here’s how to watch Trump’s State of the Union address</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/trump-state-of-the-union-address-2026/how-to-watch-what-time-00794726</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-918b-d0f8-adde-fbdb65900000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 20:08:37 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is set to descend on Capitol Hill for his annual State of the Union address on Tuesday, as his administration faces growing outcry over its nationwide immigration crackdown and declining support for several of his key policies.</p> 
<p>Trump’s high-stakes speech <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/21/a-high-stakes-state-of-the-union-just-got-even-harder-for-trump-00791753" target="_blank">comes just days</a> after the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trump-tariffs-supreme-court-ruling-00790687" target="_blank">dealt a crushing blow</a> to the centerpiece of his economic and foreign policy agenda, ruling his sweeping tariffs illegal. The president is also staring down brewing conflict abroad, with an immense military <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trumps-iran-buildup-risks-drowning-out-affordability-message-00788875" target="_blank">buildup in the Middle East</a> amid threats toward Iran, and an ongoing partial government shutdown impacting the Department of Homeland Security.</p> 
<p>Amid a stark backdrop — and just months before kicking off festivities for America’s 250th anniversary — Trump will be tasked with highlighting his administration’s biggest wins in his first year back in office and shoring up support with key voter blocs ahead of November’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>Here’s what you need to know before Trump delivers his highly anticipated address to Congress — and the nation:</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>How can I watch the speech?</b></span><br>Trump’s State of the Union speech is scheduled to begin at 9 p.m. Eastern on Tuesday. The address will be broadcast on major television networks and available to stream online, including on POLITICO’s website. You can follow our live coverage of the address here.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>What will Trump talk about?</b></span><br>Trump said Monday that his address is “going to be a long speech because we have so much to talk about,” hinting that his remarks will likely touch on the state of the economy. The White House has attempted to keep Trump on message about affordability ahead of this fall’s midterm elections, with the president <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-sotu-georgia-rally-00790155" target="_blank">offering a preview</a> of his possible remarks during a Thursday rally in Georgia.</p> 
<p>“They would say affordability, everybody would say, ‘Oh, Trump caused–,’ no, they cause– they caused the affordability problem,” Trump said at the rally. “And we’ve solved it. And we’re going still lower, but we’ve solved it.”</p> 
<p>Several Republicans told POLITICO they hope Trump will focus on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/trump-sotu-speech-tariffs-fallout-dhs-shutdown-00792608" target="_blank">highlighting economic issues</a>, <a href="https://www.eenews.net/articles/state-of-the-union-republicans-eager-for-trump-to-talk-energy/" target="_blank">American energy dominance</a> and the tax cuts passed in last year’s GOP megabill during his address.</p> 
<p>The president’s job approval has slid in recent months, with numerous polls <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/trump-state-of-the-union-polling-00793017" target="_blank">revealing widespread disapproval</a> of his handling of immigration and the economy — two issues that helped propel Trump back to a second term in the White House.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>Who is attending?</b></span><br>Lawmakers from both chambers of Congress, members of Trump’s family and several administration officials, including Cabinet secretaries and Vice President JD Vance, are expected to attend. Several personal guests of the president will also be at the Capitol, including Turning Point CEO Erika Kirk, widow of the late conservative influencer Charlie Kirk.</p> 
<p>Supreme Court justices are also invited to the State of the Union, although Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/donald-trump-tariff-supreme-court-reaction-00791245" target="_blank">sniped at several of the justices</a> who voted to strike down his tariffs last week, telling reporters Friday: “I couldn't care less if they come.”</p> 
<p>Members of Congress are each permitted to invite a guest to the address, and lawmakers frequently use the invite to draw attention to high-profile issues. Some Democrats — including House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries and Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer — have announced that they’ll bring survivors of convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein as their guests. Many Republicans are bringing guests who benefited from Trump’s One Big Beautiful Bill Act passed last year.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/squeeze-in-the-hockey-players-00794705" target="_blank">confirmed Tuesday</a> the U.S. men’s hockey team will attend Trump’s address, although the women’s team said it would not participate due to scheduling issues.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>Who won’t be there?</b></span><br>More than a dozen Democratic lawmakers have announced that they won’t attend Trump’s State of the Union, with several choosing to attend <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/democrats-trump-state-of-the-union-boycott-00786370" target="_blank">a counterprogramming rally</a> on the National Mall instead.</p> 
<p>The event, dubbed the “People’s State of the Union,” will feature lawmakers who also skipped Trump’s inaugurations, including Sens. Ed Markey (D-Mass.) and Chris Murphy (D-Conn.) and Reps. Greg Casar (D-Texas) and Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.).</p> 
<p>Jeffries advised Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/trump-state-of-the-union-shutdown-00781266" target="_blank">during a private leadership meeting</a> earlier this month that members of his caucus should either attend alternative programming or sit in “silent defiance” of Trump’s speech, hoping to avoid the image of Democratic hecklers during last year’s address.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers from both parties are also facing weather-related delays in traveling back to Washington after a winter storm led the House to cancel Monday votes.</p> 
<p><span class="story-text__heading-medium"><b>Who is giving the Democratic response?</b></span><br>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger is set to deliver the official Democratic rebuttal to Trump’s address Tuesday night.</p> 
<p>Spanberger, a former CIA officer who served in the House from 2019-2025, defeated GOP nominee Winsome Earle-Sears to flip the Virginia governor’s mansion blue in November. Democrats widely <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/affordability-affordability-affordability-democrats-new-winning-formula-00637023" target="_blank">lauded her campaign</a> for its focus on affordability.</p> 
<p>Spanberger <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/spanberger-state-of-the-union-dems-00789425" target="_blank">hinted last week</a> that her response will likely center on those issues, writing in a statement that “Virginians and Americans across the country are contending with rising costs, chaos in their communities, and a real fear of what each day might bring.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Alex Padilla (D-Calif.) — California’s first Latino senator and the son of Mexican immigrants — will deliver the Democratic response in Spanish.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shutdown talks make little progress as DHS bill stalls in Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/shutdown-talks-make-little-progress-as-dhs-bill-stalls-in-senate-00796857</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91f2-d0f8-adde-fbfa4f010000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 18:19:40 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats blocked a Department of Homeland Security funding for a second time Tuesday, underscoring a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/shutdown-stalemate-deepens-as-white-house-dems-dig-in-on-dhs-funding-00789614" target="_blank">shutdown stalemate</a> now in its second week.</p> 
<p>Senators voted 50-45 to advance a House-passed DHS bill in their first action on funding for the department since a partial government shutdown started Feb. 14. The bill needed 60 votes to move forward.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump will use part of his State of the Union speech Tuesday evening to encourage Democrats to reopen the Department of Homeland Security, White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Tuesday. But with lawmakers just returning to Washington from a weeklong recess, the talks appear to have almost entirely stalled.</p> 
<p>“We've heard crickets from them, nothing,” Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> told reporters Tuesday. “They're not negotiating. They're just trying to pass paper back and forth with no real changes.”</p> 
<p>There’s currently no meeting scheduled between congressional leaders and Trump to talk about the funding fight, which disproportionately impacts nonimmigration agencies such as TSA and the Coast Guard. With talks going slowly, there’s no expectation that a deal to end the partial shutdown is reached this week, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the private negotiations.</p> 
<p>Democrats have vowed to oppose DHS funding until they get changes to Trump’s immigration enforcement tactics after federal agents killed two U.S. citizens in Minneapolis. Democrats have outlined more than a dozen changes that they want, including banning masks for federal agents, requiring them to obtain judicial warrants to search private property and requiring independent investigations of agent misconduct.</p> 
<p>Despite the partial shutdown, Trump’s immigration agencies have funding under the party-line megabill Republicans passed last year. But Democrats believe they have public opinion on their side due to the political backlash over Trump’s immigration tactics, which have also sparked unease among some Republican lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Democrats gave their latest counteroffer to the White House last week. Asked about a possible White House response, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said in an interview Tuesday that the talks are now more “informal,” with the parties “just kind of going back and forth and trying to hit the landing spot.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-24T19:03:45-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Ahead of SOTU, Dems demand Trump make Iran plans public</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/ahead-sotu-dems-demand-trump-iran-plans-public-00796594</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91be-d3b5-addf-f1fe43930000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:33:44 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Joe Gould</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Joe Gould</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As President Donald Trump prepared to deliver his State of the Union Address Tuesday night, top Democratic lawmakers emerged from a classified briefing on Iran and urged him to explain how he will resolve the standoff over Tehran’s nuclear program. </p> 
<p>The briefing, which Secretary of State Marco Rubio delivered to House and Senate leadership, as well as the top members of the House and Senate Intelligence Committees, comes as the administration weighs potential military action against Iran.</p> 
<p>Though Trump hasn’t indicated he has made a final decision, he has ordered a huge expansion of U.S. military forces in the Middle East and warned of “really bad things” if a deal isn’t reached with Tehran on its nuclear enrichment program.</p> 
<p>“Look, this is serious, and the administration has to make its case to the American people,” Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said after the briefing. </p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> afterward questioned the need for military action, pointing to Trump’s past claims that he had destroyed Tehran’s nuclear program during Operation Midnight Hammer this past summer.</p> 
<p>“Part of the concern that I’ve articulated, and will continue to do so, is that the president made the representation that Iran’s nuclear program was completely and totally obliterated last year as a result of actions that the administration has taken,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>“And so if that, in fact, was true, what is the urgency as of this moment? That’s an open question, and the American people need a real explanation,” he added.</p> 
<p>Senate Intelligence Vice Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66837" data-person-id="66837">Mark Warner</a> (D-Va.) called it was “a serious moment” for the Middle East and America. He noted that some of the sailors in the administration’s military buildup are from his state.</p> 
<p>“I think it is incumbent upon the president to make the case of what our country's goals are, what our country's interests are, and how we're going to protect American interests in the region,” he said. “Maybe we'll hear that tonight, but if we don't hear it tonight, we need to hear it very, very soon.”</p> 
<p>On the other side of the aisle, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said “consultation” with Congress “needs to happen” on Iran.</p> 
<p>But he said it was unclear what decisions the administration has made on military action.</p> 
<p>“There are multiple issues with regard to Iran, one of which is the nuclear program; The other is the ballistic missile program,” Thune said. “It is a dangerous country, and very volatile, as you know, right now.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No. 2 House Democrat won’t attend State of the Union</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/katherine-clark-skip-sotu-00796596</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91b8-de8a-a1fc-f9f8e53e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:19:27 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Minority Whip Katherine Clark said she will be skipping President Donald Trump’s State of the Union speech Tuesday, becoming the most senior Democrat to boycott the annual address.</p> 
<p>“I will be hearing from the people of my district about their personal experiences with skyrocketing costs, new barriers to health care, dismantled Social Security services, and brutal cuts to medical research,” the No. 2 House Democrat said in a statement.</p> 
<p>The Massachusetts lawmaker pointed to the fatal shootings of U.S. citizens in Minnesota last month as a stalemate over Homeland Security funding heads into a second week. She also said Trump is “standing in the way of truth” in citing the DOJ’s handling of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries and Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer have said they plan to attend Trump’s address. Jeffries has encouraged members to either sit in silent defiance or attend alternative programming as dozens of rank-and-file members have announced plans to skip the speech.</p> 
<p>“Donald Trump’s presidency has been one broken promise after another, and the people of this country and the Commonwealth deserve so much better,” Clark said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalise, committee chairs huddle with White House officials on GOP agenda</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/scalise-committee-chairs-huddle-with-white-house-officials-on-gop-agenda-00796589</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-91b4-d3b5-addf-f1f416ee0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 17:11:13 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Majority Leader Steve Scalise held a dinner Monday night with Republican committee chairs and senior White House officials to discuss the GOP legislative agenda ahead of the midterms, according to five people granted anonymity to share details of the private event.</p> 
<p>White House deputy chief of staff for legislative affairs James Blair was in attendance at the dinner, held at a Capitol Hill restaurant, alongside the administration’s legislative affairs director James Braid and top House liaison, Jeff Freeland, according to the people.</p> 
<p>Blair and White House officials discussed key affordability policy areas they feel are especially salient in a midterm election year, including housing. They also raised health care and economic issues — topics Trump plans to hit on in his State of the Union address Tuesday night.</p> 
<p>But notably, the people with knowledge of the meeting said the group did not discuss pursuing these priorities through another party-line budget reconciliation package.</p> 
<p>Scalise said in an interview Tuesday afternoon he organized the dinner to coordinate with the White House and invited the chairs to share details of the legislation they plan to work on for the rest of the year.</p> 
<p>White House officials also gave a rough overview of what to expect from Trump’s State of the Union speech, Scalise continued.</p> 
<p>Blair and other White House representatives said the president will laud American greatness ahead of the country’s upcoming 250th birthday, according to Scalise. Trump will also talk about “the mess he inherited from Biden,” including high inflation and rampant illegal border crossings.</p> 
<p>Trump will give examples of how he’s working with his Republican majority in Congress to fix a lot of those problems, but “also make clear that the work’s not done,” Scalise said. </p> 
<p>He added that Trump's speech also will preview “what we need to do in the next few months” ahead of the midterms.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-24T18:10:34-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democrats to probe DOJ’s alleged withholding of Epstein files on Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/24/democrats-doj-epstein-files-trump-00795347</link>
      <description>Republicans are accusing their colleagues across the aisle of launching a “witch hunt.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-90c1-d0f8-adde-fadbb3330000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 15:35:11 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/cf/8e/e31d11f64453856343b8855d0f7b/epstein-congress-clintons-05916.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Ranking member Rep. Robert Garcia, D-Calif., speaks during a House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform markup business meeting about finding former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Rodham Clinton in contempt of Congress, Wednesday Jan. 21, 2026, on Capitol Hill in Washington. (AP Photo/Jacquelyn Martin)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/cf/8e/e31d11f64453856343b8855d0f7b/epstein-congress-clintons-05916.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats on the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee are investigating whether the Justice Department purposefully withheld materials in its release of the Jeffrey Epstein files that included sexual assault allegations against President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia (D-Calif.), the ranking member of the panel, said in a statement Tuesday that such an act by DOJ would violate the law Congress passed in November, which required the administration to publicly release all files in its possession related to the federal case against Epstein, a convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>Garcia also said it also would run afoul of the subpoenas the Oversight Committee separately transmitted to DOJ last summer as part of<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/02/house-releases-first-trove-of-epstein-files-00540467" target="_blank"><u> its own Epstein investigation</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“For the last few weeks, Oversight Democrats have been investigating the FBI’s handling of allegations from 2019 of sexual assault on a minor made against President Donald Trump by a survivor,” Garcia said <a href="https://x.com/OversightDems/status/2026326604335522245" target="_blank"><u>in the statement</u></a>. “Oversight Democrats can confirm that the DOJ appears to have illegally withheld FBI interviews with this survivor who accused President Trump of heinous crimes.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the White House did not immediately provide comment to POLITICO regarding whether the administration is withholding incriminating materials.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department, <a href="https://x.com/dojrr47/status/2026366459375497413?s=46" target="_blank">on social media</a>, called on Oversight Democrats to "stop misleading the public while manufacturing outrage from their radical anti-Trump base," asserting that "NOTHING has been deleted."</p> 
<p>"If files are temporarily pulled for victim redactions or to redact Personally Identifiable Information, then those documents are promptly restored online and are publicly available," the DOJ X post continued. "ALL responsive documents have been produced unless a document falls within one of the following categories: duplicates, privileged, or part of an ongoing federal investigation."</p> 
<p>Trump has denied wrongdoing in relation to the Epstein allegations, and no evidence has suggested that Trump took part in Epstein’s trafficking operation. Many of the materials released by the Justice Department also lack substantiation or context.</p> 
<p>Congressional investigators identified missing materials after matching public files with case files listed in the evidence manifest provided to the legal team of Ghislaine Maxwell, Epstein’s co-conspirator who is currently serving a 20-year prison sentence, said Sara Guerrero, a spokesperson for Oversight Democrats.</p> 
<p>One of those files include an allegation from a redacted individual that Trump sexually assaulted a minor. The accusation appears in <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2010/EFTA01660622.pdf" target="_blank"><u>a slide deck presentation</u></a> featuring a list of powerful men who had been at one point connected to Epstein, including Trump.</p> 
<p>In that slide deck, a person, whose name has been redacted but was estimated to be between 13 and 15 years old at the time of the alleged incident sometime in the 1980s, accuses Trump of forcing her head down to his penis, then reacting violently when she resisted.</p> 
<p>An investigative <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/24/nx-s1-5723968/epstein-files-trump-accusation-maxwell" target="_blank"><u>report by NPR</u></a>, published Tuesday, found that DOJ withheld “what appears to be more than 50 pages of FBI interviews, and notes from conversations with a woman who accused Trump of sexual abuse decades ago when she was a minor.” The report also notes that DOJ “removed some documents from the public database where accusations against Jeffrey Epstein also mention Trump.”</p> 
<p>POLITICO did not independently verify the NPR findings.</p> 
<p>Garcia said he viewed unredacted files on a DOJ computer Monday, per privileges afforded to members of Congress.</p> 
<p>“Covering up direct evidence of a potential assault by the President of the United States is the most serious possible crime in this White House cover up,” he added.</p> 
<p>The Democrats’ probe, which will lack subpoena power given the party’s minority status, comes as party operatives see political advantage in drawing attention to DOJ’s handling of the Epstein files, alleging the administration is working to hide information that could be damaging to the president and not making enough efforts to bring justice to Epstein's accusers, a charge that the DOJ denies.</p> 
<p>Separately, two House Democrats are asking deputy attorney general Todd Blanche to appoint a special counsel to investigate whether the nation’s top prosecutor, Pam Bondi, lied to Congress during her recent testimony before the House Judiciary Committee regarding Trump’s involvement with Epstein.</p> 
<p>At that hearing earlier this month, Bondi said there is “no evidence” in the Epstein documents made public by her department that shows Trump committed a crime. In a letter to Blanche, Reps. Dan Goldman of New York and Ted Lieu of California pointed to the unsubstantiated claim in the Epstein documents that Trump allegedly forced himself on the young girl.</p> 
<p>Lieu accused Bondi of lying to Congress during the hearing about whether Trump was accused of committing crimes in the Epstein files, without specifying details. Bondi responded, “don’t you ever accuse me of a crime.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for House Oversight Republicans, in a statement, accused Democrats of “playing politics instead of seeking justice for survivors.”</p> 
<p>“In the course of their witch hunt, they’ve cherry-picked and doctored documents to mislead the public and released images with no context to create a false narrative,” she continued<b>.&nbsp;</b></p> 
<p>She also noted Democrats have “refused to condemn their own colleague,” Del. Stacey Plaskett (D-V.I.), who was found to have been<a href="https://www.notus.org/congress/stacey-plaskett-virgin-islands-epstein-emails-document-release" target="_blank"><u> a close associate of Epstein,</u></a> texting and speaking on the phone with him and trying to set up a visit to his private island.</p> 
<p>All Democrats voted against a Republican-led resolution in November that would have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-epstein-defense-00657798" target="_blank"><u>formally reprimanded Plaskett</u></a> and kicked her off the House Intelligence Committee.</p> 
<p>“Democrats have no credibility on this issue,” the spokesperson said.</p> 
<p>Plaskett has not been found guilty of wrongdoing and <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-98dd-df0f-abfa-f9ff4bbc0000" target="_blank"><u>has described Epstein</u></a> as her former “constituent.” </p> 
<p>“The partisan attack on the congresswoman is a pathetic and deliberate distortion of the facts," a Plaskett spokesperson said in a statement. "The Congresswoman has never visited Jeffrey Epstein’s island and has been clear in condemning his abhorrent behavior and has a long history of fighting against the sexual exploitation of women. It is imperative that we do not allow politically motivated distractions to pull the focus away from the actual bad actors who perpetrated and enabled these crimes.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-24T17:28:11-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Judges plead with Congress for control of crumbling courthouses</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/congress-pressed-on-courthouses-00795767</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-9143-d3b5-addf-f1c7b1e00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 15:09:39 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Josh Gerstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Josh Gerstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The infrastructure of the nation’s federal courthouses is crumbling, plagued by collapsing ceilings, malfunctioning elevators and contaminated water supplies, a top representative for the federal judiciary declared in <a href="https://www.uscourts.gov/sites/default/files/document/judiciary-real-property-authority-legislative-package.pdf" target="_blank">an unusual plea</a> to Congress on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>“Federal courthouses are in crisis. Without immediate action, the problems will continue to worsen,” Judge Robert J. Conrad Jr., director of the Administrative Office of the U.S. Courts, said in a letter to lawmakers. “Action is needed now to reverse a downward spiral of critical-system failures, long-term underfunding of repairs, security risks, and climbing costs.”</p> 
<p>Conrad urged lawmakers to address the problem by giving the courts the power to build and operate their courthouses — tasks now handled by the General Services Administration.</p> 
<p>While judges have groused for decades about neglect by their government landlord, complaints about GSA reached a fever pitch last year after haphazard moves by President Donald Trump’s Department of Government Efficiency initiative radically downsized the agency and targeted some courthouses for sale without any input from the judges who work there.</p> 
<p>The urgent missive the judiciary sent to Congress on Tuesday doesn’t make direct mention of DOGE, but it notes that GSA eliminated almost half its staff in recent months, creating security and safety risks by leaving no one on site at many courthouses to address hazards and urgent repairs. Legislation the judges are backing would gradually transition existing courthouses from GSA to a new Judiciary Buildings Service.</p> 
<p>GSA spokesperson Marianne Copenhaver said in a statement that the agency disputes the suggestion that courthouses are in "crisis." </p> 
<p>“While aging federal buildings present well-known challenges, [the judiciary’s] narrative omits critical context regarding our lack of access to GSA's Federal Building Fund to address delinquent maintenance," she added. "The American taxpayer is best served by the Judiciary focusing on the rule of law while GSA continues to focus on the federal real estate portfolio."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tony Gonzales says he will not resign</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/tony-gonzales-not-resigning-00795580</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-90fe-d0f8-adde-fafe61250000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 14:05:08 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>GOP Rep. Tony Gonzales told reporters Tuesday he will not step down from his seat amid <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/tony-gonzales-affair-allegations-00793653" target="_blank">allegations he had an affair with a staffer</a> who later died by suicide.</p> 
<p>“I am not going to resign,” the Texas lawmaker said.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said earlier Tuesday he planned to meet with Gonzales. Asked several times in a Capitol hallway if Gonzales should run for reelection under the circumstance, he replied, “I haven't met with him yet.”</p> 
<p>Gonzales faces a competitive GOP primary race on March 3. Five fellow House Republicans have called on him to resign, most recently Reps. Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Tim Burchett of Tennessee, with others saying he should end his reelection campaign.</p> 
<p>Gonzales has previously denied having an affair with the late staffer, Regina Santos-Aviles, but has not addressed the newly released text messages, which appear to show Gonzales asking for intimate photos and discussing sex acts.</p> 
<p>“I work every day for the people of Texas,” he said Tuesday. “And there will be an opportunity for all the details and facts that come out. What you've seen is not all the facts.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Abigail Spanberger to address House Democrats at policy retreat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/abigail-spanberger-house-democratic-retreat-00794859</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-907f-d3b5-addf-f0ffd3020000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 11:37:58 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger will headline House Democrats’ annual policy retreat Wednesday, addressing her former colleagues just a day after delivering her party’s televised response to President Donald Trump’s State of the Union address.</p> 
<p>Spanberger is expected to discuss her successful statewide campaign and what lessons House Democrats can take into the midterms from the party’s triumphs in Virginia last year, according to a <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-907e-d0f8-adde-fa7e7dac0000" target="_blank">Dear Colleague letter</a> from Democratic Caucus Chair Pete Aguilar.</p> 
<p>Democratic members will also hear from historians Ron Chernow and Heather Cox Richardson in a Thursday night session reflecting on America’s 250th birthday, moderated by House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries.</p> 
<p>The retreat will center on affordability in housing, utilities, groceries and other areas, according to a schedule shared with POLITICO. Labor leaders are set to speak at a number of sessions, including Brent Booker of the Laborers' International Union of North America, Lee Saunders of the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees and Leslie Frane of the Service Employees International Union.</p> 
<p>Aguilar said in the letter that members “will spend the coming days discussing how we are ‘Fighting for an Affordable America’ and building our affirmative affordability agenda, which will guide our caucus as we work to take back the majority.”</p> 
<p>Punchbowl News first reported on the event’s agenda.</p> 
<p>Other speakers include members of former President Joe Biden’s administration, including former OMB Director Shalanda Young, former CFPB Director Rohit Chopra and former deputy secretary of Agriculture Xochitl Torres Small.</p> 
<p>DCCC Chair Suzan DelBene (D-Wash.) will address Democrats Thursday night on taking back the House, with remarks from Lakshya Jain, co-founder and CEO of Split Ticket, and Stephanie Valencia, president and co-founder of Equis Research. Alexis McGill Johnson, the president and CEO of Planned Parenthood Action Fund, will speak at a Friday morning session focused on fixing health care.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump faces a midterms reality check</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/24/congress/trump-sotu-speech-tariffs-dhs-midterms-democrats-00794547</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8dd3-d647-addc-afd729e90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is heading into one of his most high-profile moments of the midterm year as he grapples with plunging public opinion and growing congressional dissent.</p> 
<p>“It’s going to be a long one because we have so much to talk about,” Trump told reporters Monday.</p> 
<p>Keep in mind: He already set the record last year with an hour-and-thirty-nine-minute SOTU address, so buckle in.</p> 
<p>Here’s some of what to expect throughout the night:</p> 
<p><b>— Tariff talk:</b> Trump is likely to have words for the Supreme Court justices sitting right in front of him who last week ruled to overturn his sweeping tariff regime. The ruling represented a rare setback for Trump from the conservative high court.</p> 
<p>It was especially significant as it becomes increasingly clear that Congress won’t be there to back up Trump, who could press for legislative action on tariffs Tuesday night. Speaker Mike Johnson said Monday <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/mike-johnson-congress-unlikely-to-find-consensus-to-codify-trumps-tariffs-00793462" target="_blank">it’s unlikely</a> Congress will act to codify the president’s tariff agenda to comply with the ruling.</p> 
<p><b>— DHS prognosis:&nbsp;</b>The president could offer a hint at how long the partial government shutdown affecting Homeland Security agencies, now on Day 11, will last.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders, after a series of back-and-forth proposals with the White House, claim the administration isn’t serious about adopting stricter guardrails on federal immigration agents. The White House, meanwhile, signaled it was willing to play hardball by scaling back airport security operations in ways that could cause pain for travelers.</p> 
<p>Watch to see if Trump provides more clarity on his negotiating position or simply takes aim at Democrats for challenging his immigration agenda.</p> 
<p><b>— A midterm signal:&nbsp;</b>Trump is facing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/trump-state-of-the-union-polling-00793017" target="_blank">abysmal approval ratings</a> as he heads into midterm season, as voters increasingly disapprove of his handling of immigration, inflation and tariffs. But while the president walks into the House chamber Tuesday evening in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/24/a-defensive-posture-trump-speaks-to-congress-on-shakier-ground-than-last-year-00793455" target="_blank">far weaker position than last year</a>, he also has a huge opportunity to define his party’s campaign message.</p> 
<p>Listen for Trump to define the direction of his final two years in the White House with an eye toward November. You can expect the embattled GOP lawmakers in the audience to be listening closely themselves as they grow more concerned about the public’s deteriorating view of his presidency.</p> 
<p>“He is currently at his lowest point in the second term,” said Whit Ayres, a Republican pollster in Washington. “The single most important variable in midterm elections is the president’s job approval.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Dems split on SOTU attendance: </b>Democratic leaders Chuck Schumer and Hakeem Jeffries will be in their seats for Trump’s SOTU address, but dozens of their members will be absent, with some attending <a href="https://www.mobilize.us/moveon/event/903012/" target="_blank">alternative programming</a>.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats are instead sending Trump a pointed message with their guests of choice. Schumer, Jeffries and other Democrats have invited victims of Jeffrey Epstein to the building.</p> 
<p>Others are bringing small business owners and Americans <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/02/democrats-and-trump-prep-for-health-clash-at-state-of-the-union-00794231" target="_blank">grappling with costly health care premiums</a> since Congress failed to extend enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies last year.</p> 
<p><b>— House takes up aviation safety: </b>A House and Senate fight over how to address the deadly January 2025 DCA crash is coming to a head Tuesday as Johnson attempts to muscle through the House floor a Senate-passed bill that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/congress-air-safety-fight-comes-to-a-head-00791864" target="_blank">some of his key committee chairs oppose</a>.</p> 
<p><b>— New housing bills incoming: </b>Sen. Elizabeth Warren (D-Mass.) is unveiling legislation Tuesday morning that would limit the ability of large Wall Street investors to buy up homes — a policy goal that Trump is also pushing to include in Warren’s bipartisan housing bill with Senate Banking Chair Tim Scott (R-S.C.).</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Reps. Vicente Gonzalez (D-Texas) and Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) are introducing legislation Tuesday that would allow federally-insured credit unions to access additional mortgage lending capacity through the Federal Home Loan Bank System.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Eli Stokols, Hailey Fuchs, Robert King, Mia McCarthy, Sam Ogozalek, Oriana Pawlyk, Chris Marquette and Victoria Guida contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neal Dunn says he'll serve out term, quashing resignation rumors</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/neal-dunn-serve-out-term-00793804</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8ca1-d0f8-adde-fefb02120000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 17:43:16 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Neal Dunn plans to serve out the rest of his term, a spokesperson said Monday, addressing rumors that the Florida Republican would resign early and potentially put the GOP House majority at risk.</p> 
<p>The announcement comes after Speaker Mike Johnson said earlier this month <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/neal-dunn-resignation-johnson-00776216" target="_blank">he'd urged Dunn to stay in Congress</a>. Senior House Republicans believed at the time that Dunn, who is facing health issues and announced his retirement in January, could step down in the coming months and further narrow the GOP's majority.</p> 
<p>"As a dedicated public servant, he will remain in Congress to represent his constituents through the end of this term," spokesperson Eleanor Allison said in response to inquiries first made on Feb. 11.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-23T17:30:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Tony Gonzales faces mounting pressure from GOP women over affair allegations</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/23/tony-gonzales-affair-allegations-00793653</link>
      <description>Speaker Mike Johnson is also pressing the Texas Republican to address his relationship with a staffer who later died by suicide.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8c4e-d647-addc-afcf4d250000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 16:07:09 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e7/a5/38c591aa4a3ba85eb516bbc8bcb8/house-of-representatives-49850.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Tony Gonzales (R-Texas) arrives for a House Republican Conference meeting at the U.S. Capitol, on Oct. 3, 2023.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e7/a5/38c591aa4a3ba85eb516bbc8bcb8/house-of-representatives-49850.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Three prominent House Republican women called on GOP Rep. Tony Gonzales to step down Monday, applying major new pressure on the Texas lawmaker to address accusations that he had an affair with his staffer who later died by suicide.</p> 
<p>Rep. Lauren Boebert of Colorado became the first Republican lawmaker to call for Gonzales' resignation, followed by Reps. Anna Paulina Luna of Florida and Nancy Mace of South Carolina, who were both prompted to speak out by the release of new alleged text messages between the lawmaker and his subordinate.</p> 
<p>Separately Monday, in his first comments on the matter, Speaker Mike Johnson called the allegations “very serious” but declined to call for further action as investigations into Gonzales play out. Rep. Brandon Gill, a fellow Texas Republican, also called for Gonzales to end his reelection bid.</p> 
<p>Gonzales, who is in his third term representing a potentially competitive south Texas district, has <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/02/20/politics/tony-gonzales-denies-affair-allegations" target="_blank">previously denied</a> having an improper relationship with the staffer, Regina Santos-Aviles, who <a href="https://people.com/regina-santos-aviles-cause-of-death-determined-after-catching-fire-alone-in-her-backyard-11816190" target="_blank">died after lighting herself on fire</a> in September.</p> 
<p>The sordid allegations have come under intense public scrutiny in recent weeks as Gonzales faces a heated primary election, fueling widespread speculation about his future in politics as he faces a potential ethics investigation.</p> 
<p>Gonzales’ office did not respond to messages seeking comment Monday on the recent comments from his colleagues.</p> 
<p>Boebert told POLITICO that <a href="https://www.expressnews.com/news/article/tony-gonzales-texts-regina-santos-aviles-pictures-21362068.php" target="_blank">newly released text messages</a> published in media outlets underscore the need for Gonzales to resign, saying they “seemingly show a perverted boss drunkenly coercing a vulnerable staffer into explicit conversations, pressing her for ‘sexy pics,’ asking about her favorite sexual positions.”</p> 
<p>POLITICO has not independently reviewed the messages.</p> 
<p>“This kind of abuse of power has no place anywhere, let alone in Congress, and Tony Gonzales should be ashamed and RESIGN IMMEDIATELY!” Boebert said.</p> 
<p>Luna <a href="https://x.com/RepLuna/status/2026010250382610570" target="_blank">said on X</a> that “every single other Member of Congress … should be condemning a sitting Member of Congress asking for explicit photos of their staff.”</p> 
<p>“As a woman, this is really disgusting to see. Not to mention, it brings dishonor on the House of Representatives. I am so sick of people not calling this crap out,” Luna added.</p> 
<p>Mace called the texts "disgusting and inexcusable" and said Congress should "have ZERO tolerance for those who abuse their power over others."</p> 
<p>In comments to reporters Monday, Johnson said Gonzales must “address” the allegations with his constituents. But the speaker, who is struggling to maintain a razor-thin GOP majority, did not pull his endorsement of the Texas Republican with the primary just eight days away — in keeping with handling of other personal controversies faced by his members.</p> 
<p>“I endorsed Tony before all these allegations came out — they're obviously very serious,” Johnson told reporters at the Capitol. “And I've spoken with him and told him he's got to address that in the appropriate way with his constituents, and all of that.”</p> 
<p>Luna and Boebert were among a group of House Republican women who have criticized how top House GOP leaders, mostly men, have approached allegations of sexual misconduct — including, for Boebert and Mace, the effort to keep the Justice Department’s Jeffrey Epstein files under wraps.</p> 
<p>Both were outraged at how Johnson and other GOP leaders handled an unsuccessful Democratic effort recently to censure Rep. Cory Mills (R-Fla.) over <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/06/cory-millis-threats-allegations-gop-00496518" target="_blank">now-retracted allegations of domestic assault</a> and improper dealings with his arms company. Mills has denied the allegations, which remain <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/ethics-investigates-mills-00660582" target="_blank">under Ethics Committee review</a>.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters Monday he is handling the Gonzales matter in line with other allegations of misconduct, including those surrounding then Rep. George Santos (R-N.Y.), who was expelled from the House over Johnson’s objections in 2023 ahead of a formal ethics trial.</p> 
<p>“You have to let the system play out,” he said. “If the accusation of something is going to be the litmus test for someone being able to continue to serve in the House, we'll have a lot of people who would have to resign or be removed or expelled from Congress.”</p> 
<p>More House Republican women are reading the purported text messages between Gonzales and Santos-Aviles, and two women lawmakers granted anonymity to comment on the sensitive situation said it’s likely Johnson will come under more internal pressure to take action against Gonzales.</p> 
<p>Johnson said he understood that the Office of Congressional Conduct is investigating Gonzales as well as Texas state authorities. Mills also remains <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/ethics-investigates-mills-00660582" target="_blank">subject to a House ethics investigation</a>.</p> 
<p>More recently, he has accused Santos-Aviles’ widower, Adrian Aviles, of engaging in a blackmail effort as he has given interviews criticizing Gonzales and released text messages between the lawmaker, who is a 45-year-old married father of six, and Santos-Aviles, who was 35.</p> 
<p>An attorney for Aviles, Bobby Barrera, did not immediately return a call for comment. Barrera has <a href="https://apnews.com/article/tony-gonzales-blackmail-allegation-ce31ebb350599731f2e833db1e9bf0d3" target="_blank">publicly denied</a> the blackmail accusation, explaining that he was attempting to recover damages through a potential lawsuit on behalf of Aviles.</p> 
<p>One key player who has not weighed in on Gonzales is President Donald Trump, who endorsed him in December as Republicans face pressure to hold on to his must-win seat. Trump this weekend withdrew his endorsement for one House Republican — Rep. Jeff Hurd of Colorado, who voted down Trump’s Canada tariffs last week — but has stayed silent as the Gonzales scandal swirls.</p> 
<p>Another issue facing Gonzales: GOP hardliners in Congress have been trying to replace him with a more hard-right Republican on immigration for years now. And Monday, the Freedom Caucus’ campaign arm officially endorsed his GOP primary challenger, Brandon Herrera, for a second time.</p> 
<p>Herrera only lost to Gonzales by several hundred votes in 2022. He is now calling on Gonzales to step down and for congressional Republicans to rescind their support for the incumbent. Gonzales has countered that his opponent is fueling what he says are false allegations.</p> 
<p>Trump, meanwhile, is facing intraparty pressure to distance himself from Gonzales, with far-right influencer Laura Loomer recently <a href="https://x.com/LauraLoomer/status/2024299165518369252" target="_blank">calling on social media</a> for Trump to rescind his endorsement of Gonzales.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this article misreported Rep. Brandon Gill's position. He called on Gonzales to end his reelection bid.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House scrambling to host hockey teams at State of the Union, Johnson says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/usa-hockey-teams-sotu-00793130</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8bac-d3b5-addf-ebec79480000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 13:19:41 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said Monday House officials are scrambling to find a way to accommodate the gold-medal-winning U.S. men and women's hockey teams at Tuesday's State of the Union address.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters Monday he's working to "figure out logistics" now for a potential visit from the teams, which were each invited by the White House and have dozens of players and coaches on their rosters.</p> 
<p>"There's no way to have special guests on the floor because it's a literal session of Congress," he said. "But we're going to work and do what we can to accommodate." </p> 
<p>The speaker added that House officials are "trying to work out logistics to see if there's some way to perhaps get them into the gallery and the doors, wave and receive the applause that they're due."</p> 
<p>Neither team has announced plans to attend the speech, though Trump <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/sports/trump-invites-us-mens-hockey-team-state-union-speech-after-olympic-triumph" target="_blank">personally invited the men's team</a> in the immediate aftermath of their overtime win Sunday, offering to send a military jet to bring them to Washington.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the women's team <a href="https://x.com/albamonica/status/2025989449197158504?s=46&amp;t=ncdqfRV74gcQrRg3XkYQbA" target="_blank">told NBC News</a> that while its members are "sincerely grateful" for the invitation, they cannot attend the speech "due to the timing and previously scheduled academic and professional commitments."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump’s SOTU clouded by chaos</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/23/congress/trump-sotu-speech-tariffs-fallout-dhs-shutdown-00792608</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-8846-d3b5-addf-e8c6c78c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is heading into Tuesday’s State of the Union facing a messy Capitol Hill backdrop: a Supreme Court smackdown of his global tariffs, fresh GOP anxiety over the political fallout and a DHS funding standoff that’s revealing chaos within his own administration.</p> 
<p>Add in a snowstorm scrambling the House and Senate schedule — postponing House votes on aviation safety legislation and delaying a key farm bill markup — and lawmakers are facing a compressed, high-stakes week.</p> 
<p>Here’s what we’re watching:</p> 
<p><b>— Trump's address:&nbsp;</b>Attendance could be thin as lawmakers try to get back to Washington after a major snow storm on the East Coast. Many Democrats had already planned to boycott.</p> 
<p>Several Republicans told POLITICO they hope Trump will focus on affordability and economic issues and highlight the megabill tax cuts.</p> 
<p>Trump critics on both sides of the aisle plan to make statements with their SOTU guests. Several Democrats are bringing individuals impacted by rising health care costs and the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown. Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) is bringing his wife, Carolyn Moffa, who has been a target of attacks from Trump.</p> 
<p>“Trump thought it was appropriate to include her in two of his broadsides,” Massie said. “So I thought it would be appropriate to invite her to his speech.”</p> 
<p><b>— Tariff fallout:&nbsp;</b>After the Supreme Court struck down Trump’s sweeping global tariffs Friday — a move <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/anti-tariff-republicans-cheer-supreme-court-decision-checking-trump-00790772" target="_blank">cheered by a number of GOP lawmakers</a> — Hill Republicans are now in a tough position as Democrats hope to put them on the record voting for or against the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/21/trump-tariff-supreme-court-00792288" target="_blank">new 15 percent global tariffs</a> the president announced in response.</p> 
<p>The new tariffs expire after 150 days and Congress will have to vote to extend them — something Republicans privately say they won’t have the support to do.</p> 
<p>Among the Republicans who have tough decisions to make are farm state lawmakers who had been pressing the administration for carveouts in Trump’s tariffs but voted in support of his Canada tariffs. They got a taste of what could happen if they cross Trump, who over the weekend rescinded his endorsement of Rep. Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) and endorsed his GOP challenger.</p> 
<p>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.), one of the six Republicans who voted to rebuke Trump’s Canada tariffs two weeks ago, said the levies are “terrible politics for Republicans” and that Trump’s latest move “will also fail in the courts.”</p> 
<p>“President Trump is putting a ball and chain” on the GOP in the midterms, Bacon told POLITICO. “I hate seeing it.”</p> 
<p><b>— DHS stalemate:&nbsp;</b>The DHS shutdown appeared to get real over the weekend when the department said it would suspend TSA PreCheck and other airport security services, but then quickly reversed course “based off of conversations the secretary had with the White House and TSA,” <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/nation/2026/02/21/tsa-precheck-global-entry-shutdown/" target="_blank">according to the Washington Post</a>. Officials still plan to pause airport courtesy escorts for members of Congress as well as Global Entry.</p> 
<p>The White House and Democrats are entering the week without substantial public evidence of progress on an agreement to fund DHS and establish immigration enforcement guardrails. Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said Sunday that the administration is “choosing to inflict pain on the public instead of adopting common sense ICE reforms.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p>House Rules will take up two bills to roll back Biden-era efficiency standards at 4 p.m.<b><i>&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-20T18:05:03-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘I feel vindicated’: Anti-tariff Republicans cheer as Supreme Court checks Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/anti-tariff-republicans-cheer-supreme-court-decision-checking-trump-00790772</link>
      <description>Speaker Mike Johnson and other key GOP leaders did not immediately weigh in on the ruling Friday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7bd7-d647-addc-fbd7d3260000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 11:19:07 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9a/57/7cc888c2402fbcf7c7712168f153/u-s-congress-87783.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) arrives to speak with reporters outside the U.S. Capitol on Nov. 21, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9a/57/7cc888c2402fbcf7c7712168f153/u-s-congress-87783.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican tariff skeptics on Capitol Hill celebrated Friday after the<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trump-tariffs-supreme-court-ruling-00790687" target="_blank">Supreme Court struck down</a> the core authority behind President Donald Trump’s sweeping global tariffs — dealing a blow to a major plank of the president’s agenda but offering a welcome off-ramp to GOP lawmakers who viewed the levies as a political loser.</p> 
<p>Retiring Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) broke with Trump and GOP leaders a week ago to help<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/house-rebukes-trumps-canada-tariffs-00776898" target="_blank">overturn Trump’s Canada tariffs</a>. On Friday, he hailed the “common sense ruling” by the high court that essentially invalidates those and many other tariffs.</p> 
<p>“The checks and balances our Constitution puts in place works,” Bacon said in an interview Friday morning shortly after the decision, adding, “I feel vindicated.”</p> 
<p>Another Republican who backed the effort to overturn the Canada tariffs, Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky, also praised the ruling.</p> 
<p>“On its face, this case was obvious, because the Constitution vests the power to tax with the legislative branch, not the Executive branch,” Massie said in a text message. “No contrived emergency can undo that.”</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson sidestepped any praise or criticism of the ruling, saying that Trump’s tariffs had “brought in billions of dollars and created immense leverage for America’s trade strategy.”</p> 
<p>“Congress and the Administration will determine the best path forward in the coming weeks,” he <a href="https://x.com/speakerjohnson/status/2024892242930884617?s=46" target="_blank">said in a statement</a>.</p> 
<p>Johnson later Friday postponed a trade briefing for a group of House Republicans, including tariff skeptics, that he had scheduled for Monday evening, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the private plans.</p> 
<p>The lawmakers were set to meet in the speaker's office with U.S. Trade Representative Jamieson Greer, who has played a lead role in assuaging wary Republicans about Trump's sweeping tariff regime as Democrats push to bring the matter to the House floor. A staffer in the speaker’s office said a new date and time for the discussion would be set “soon.”</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) in a statement said his members would "continue working with the administration and our colleagues in the House to advance our shared goal to strengthen rural America, including South Dakota’s farm and ranch communities, and the broader U.S. economy."</p> 
<p>But Trump, during a news conference Friday afternoon, made clear he had no interest in engaging Congress further on the matter. In announcing his plans to slap a new "10% global tariff" on goods coming into the U.S., Trump said he would not ask lawmakers to take additional action: "I don't need to. It's already been approved. I mean — I would ask Congress and probably get it."</p> 
<p>He added, "I have the right to do tariffs. And I've always had the right to do tariffs." </p> 
<p>In the immediate aftermath of the Supreme Court's ruling, Trump appeared visibly upset at the decision, according to two people in the room granted anonymity to describe the private event, cutting short remarks he was delivering to governors upon hearing the news at a White House breakfast Friday morning.</p> 
<p>“He was not happy. He got the info in real time,” one of the people said.</p> 
<p>The ruling comes just four days before Trump is set to deliver his State of the Union address to a joint session of Congress and an audience that will include the Supreme Court justices who rebuffed the cornerstone of his economic and foreign policy agendas. Trump said during his Friday news conference that the six justices who ruled against his tariffs were "barely" invited to the address and "I couldn't care less if they come."</p> 
<p>A few GOP backers of the tariffs quickly spoke out, with Sen. Bernie Moreno of Ohio decrying the ruling as “outrageous” and saying it “handcuffs our fight against unfair trade that has devastated American workers for decades.”</p> 
<p>“These tariffs protected jobs, revived manufacturing, and forced cheaters like China to pay up. Now globalists win,” Moreno added in a social media post Friday.</p> 
<p>The ruling also prompted tough questions for both parties about what comes next. Bacon indicated the decision could put an end to a flood of additional tariff disapproval votes headed to the House floor in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see if it’s necessary,” he said.</p> 
<p>But House Democrats could keep hammering Republicans on the topic in the weeks ahead. Rep. Gregory Meeks of New York, the top Foreign Affairs Committee Democrat who has orchestrated the tariff disapproval votes, said he would “continue to review the SCOTUS ruling to assess future legislative steps,” though there are no plans at the moment to force additional disapproval votes next week, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats, according to a person granted anonymity to discuss private strategy, are waiting to see how Trump responds to the decision before determining whether to force more votes disapproving of individual emergency declarations.</p> 
<p>Democrats in the Senate had hoped to put up the House-passed Canada resolution for a vote in the coming weeks, but there are ongoing internal conversations over whether it qualifies for special fast-track procedures allowing for a quick simple-majority vote, according to a second person granted anonymity to describe the matter.</p> 
<p>Other Democrats said further action was needed to forestall the Trump administration from sidestepping the ruling, possibly by invoking separate national security powers. Rep. Suzan DelBene of Washington, who chairs the House Democratic campaign arm and sits on the chamber’s main trade panel, noted that the White House “has promised to use other avenues to maintain these illegal tariffs.”</p> 
<p>“Congress must step up to put an end to this chaos and protect our economy,” she added.</p> 
<p>Asked about the prospect of Trump trying to implement his tariffs through other avenues, Bacon said, “I think they’ll try, but it would not be advisable.” Friday’s ruling authored by Chief Justice John Roberts broadly defended Congress’ sole power under the Constitution to levy taxes.</p> 
<p>Congress might also end up having to wrangle with the question of whether refunds are due to businesses or consumers who paid levies now found to be illegal.</p> 
<p>“The Court has struck down these destructive tariffs, but there is no legal mechanism for consumers and many small businesses to recoup the money they have already paid,” Sen. Elizabeth Warren (D-Mass.) noted in a statement. “Instead, giant corporations with their armies of lawyers and lobbyists can sue for tariff refunds, then just pocket the money for themselves.”</p> 
<p>Some Republicans are also urging congressional action in response to the ruling, with Rep. John Moolenaar of Michigan, who chairs the Select Committee on China, pressing for a revocation of Beijing’s permanent normal trade relations status.</p> 
<p>But to the handful of GOP lawmakers who stuck to their free-trade guns as Trump unleashed his global tariff campaign, the overwhelming sentiment has been relief and praise for the high court.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.), who joined Bacon and Massie in opposing the Canada tariffs last week, said in an interview that the ruling was “an example of our institution working” and called on Congress to set trade policy in concert with Trump.</p> 
<p>“We need to make sure that when it comes to trade policy that we have stability and predictability,” he said. “And the way that we get that predictability and stability is through congressional action.”</p> 
<p>Kentucky Sen. Mitch McConnell, who orchestrated the confirmations of several justices who participated in the ruling in his former role as Republican leader, said the justices “reaffirmed authority that has rested with Congress for centuries.”</p> 
<p>“If the executive would like to enact trade policies that impact American producers and consumers, its path forward is crystal clear,” he said in a statement. “Convince their representatives under Article 1” of the Constitution.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Daniel Desrochers and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans are ignoring Trump and holding out hope for a second megabill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/20/trump-megabill-reconciliation-gop-00789794</link>
      <description>The president said Republicans have “gotten everything passed that we need,” but lawmakers aren’t so sure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-780e-d3b5-addf-f8ce03dd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/51/f5/676a7ce747f9a2d70b9d40d010b7/house-gop-leadership-elections-59917.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Angelina Katsanis/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“There's always a chance until there's not,” Rep. Kevin Hern (R-Okla.) said of the prospects for more party-line legislation.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/51/f5/676a7ce747f9a2d70b9d40d010b7/house-gop-leadership-elections-59917.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump sent a clear message to congressional Republicans this month that there’s no need to pass another party-line megabill this year. Many, however, aren’t ready to give up yet.</p> 
<p>Trump’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/trump-reconciliation-package-00774834" target="_blank">comments in a Fox Business Network interview</a> earlier this month appeared to finally settle a long-running GOP debate over whether to pursue a follow-up to the “big, beautiful bill” enacted in July, saying “we’ve gotten everything passed that we need.”</p> 
<p>But some lawmakers are insisting that the filibuster-skirting budget reconciliation process <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698" target="_blank">offers an unmissable opportunity</a> for Republicans to enact major conservative policy changes ahead of the midterm elections — and that there is still a window to get it done.</p> 
<p>Those Republicans are largely brushing off Trump’s comments, refusing to take them as a death knell for their efforts.</p> 
<p>“One day he’s okay with it, and the next day he’s not,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.), who is one of the loudest evangelists for passing another party-line bill before the midterms, arguing Republicans “haven’t done a damn thing” since last year’s effort.</p> 
<p>Those attitudes threaten to extend the will-they-or-won’t-they discussion for potentially several more months as some factions keep pressure on GOP leaders to keep hope alive.</p> 
<p>The influential Republican Study Committee, which includes scores of House conservatives, has been holding listening sessions since last August for what could go into "Reconciliation 2.0.” It <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/rsc-reconciliation-framework-megabill-00724594" target="_blank">put out a framework in January</a> outlining how such a bill could fulfill an ambitious housing, health care and energy agenda. The group is not yet abandoning the effort.</p> 
<p>“There's always a chance until there's not,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/306850" data-person-id="306850">Kevin Hern</a> (R-Okla.), a former RSC chair and member of House GOP leadership.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> (R-Texas), the RSC's current chair, said in a statement that a second reconciliation bill would be “the perfect vehicle” to unite Republicans behind “Trump’s America First agenda in 2026.”</p> 
<p>“This is our moment, and we intend to make the most of it,” he said.</p> 
<p>But to many senior Republicans that amounts to false hope — and a distraction from other matters on the congressional agenda in the coming months. Hopes abound for progress on bipartisan housing, permitting and transportation bills.</p> 
<p>It was a particularly grueling process to get the first megabill through both chambers last year — and leaders had $5 trillion worth of tax cuts to dangle in front of recalcitrant members to help push it along.</p> 
<p>House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/house-passes-gop-megabill-00438206" target="_blank">barely passed the bill</a> on party lines in July, and their margin has only decreased since: They can currently afford no more than one defection.</p> 
<p>“I would love a second reconciliation bill, but I can count votes,” Ways and Means Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> (R-Mo.) said in an interview. “And we do not have the votes for a second reconciliation.”</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and other House GOP leaders insist they haven’t ruled out doing a second reconciliation bill and say it's still an active discussion, even as some senior House Republicans and GOP leadership aides privately doubt they will ever have the votes to move forward.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> also hasn’t dismissed another bill — but privately there’s a hefty dose of skepticism among senators and aides that there’s much of an appetite for another big party-line heave.</p> 
<p>Asked about Trump’s latest comments, Thune acknowledged in an interview that there’s interest among some members. But he added that Republicans have to be “realistic” about the prospects of assembling a proposal that can garner 51 GOP votes and withstand a free-for-all of politically tricky changes from Democrats.</p> 
<p>“We have to have a reason to do it,” Thune added.</p> 
<p>To get another bill across the finish line during a midterm year, Republicans would likely need Trump to articulate what precisely he wants in a bill and then for the president to spend weeks, and potentially months, trying to help round up the votes.</p> 
<p>But Trump has expressed skepticism about reconciliation, further raising the likelihood that the prospects of another bill are DOA. In addition to his recent comments, he kvetched about how little can actually get done in a reconciliation bill during a meeting with Senate Republicans last fall, instead urging Republicans to break the filibuster — a nonstarter for a significant swath of the conference.</p> 
<p>Trump rekindled that push Thursday, telling senators in a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116099119307195442" target="_blank">Truth Social post</a> to pass a GOP elections bill by insisting on a “talking filibuster” that would theoretically force Democrats to hold the floor indefinitely. The Senate is expected to vote on the bill, but many Republicans aren’t interested in skirting the chamber’s 60-vote supermajority requirement for most legislation.</p> 
<p>The intraparty division is expected to come to a head next month at the House Republican retreat in south Florida, where a second reconciliation bill will be a topic of conversation. A <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698" target="_blank">previous closed-door meeting</a> of GOP lawmakers in December grew heated, with vulnerable Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) saying it would “never” happen.</p> 
<p>Reconciliation got a brief mention during a Senate GOP retreat earlier this month, but most of the focus was on a slate of bipartisan bills that could come up this year, as well as the need to promote last year’s megabill, according to attendees who were granted anonymity to describe the closed-door event.</p> 
<p>But some Republicans on the Senate Budget Committee — including Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) — are pushing for more. Graham has told his members that he plans to move forward with a budget resolution that would tee up a second reconciliation bill aimed at beefing up military and border spending, addressing health care costs and targeting fraud in social services.</p> 
<p>But according to his committee members, Graham hasn’t given a strict timeline for when he’ll start moving, and there’s skepticism that it will amount to much without GOP leaders’ involvement.</p> 
<p>“I don’t know how you move forward without the majority leader’s okay,” Kennedy said in an interview. “Senator Thune wants us to only work on bipartisan bills. I love Senator Thune like a taco, but he needs to back off the crank if he believes that. There aren’t going to be any bipartisan bills — we’re right in the middle of the midterm election. Our one shot to get something is reconciliation.”</p> 
<p>One of the other challenges is litigating what exactly would go into a second reconciliation bill.</p> 
<p>Senate conservatives have floated taking another crack at healthcare, but that would risk exposing deep GOP divisions just months before the midterms. Many of the party’s most unifying health care proposals were omitted from last year’s megabill because of the Senate’s strict rules governing reconciliation.</p> 
<p>Some senior House Republicans have discussed attempting to codify Trump’s tariffs in another party-line bill. But that long-shot effort is now effectively dead after six Republicans voted this month to reject Trump’s levies on Canadian imports — with more such tariff votes to come.</p> 
<p>Asked about the possibility of codifying tariffs in a party-line package, Smith reiterated in an interview, “There's not going to be a second reconciliation bill.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger tapped for State of the Union rebuttal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/spanberger-state-of-the-union-dems-00789425</link>
      <description>California Sen. Alex Padilla will deliver the Democratic response in Spanish.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7790-de8a-a1fc-ffd0fdab0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 15:22:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/11/4e/bf4733954b2e8b297c01d663dafe/spanberger-state-of-commonwealth-83883.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Steve Helber/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger delivers her State of the Commonwealth address before a joint session of the Virginia General Assembly at the Capitol on Jan. 19, 2026, in Richmond, Virginia.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/11/4e/bf4733954b2e8b297c01d663dafe/spanberger-state-of-commonwealth-83883.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger will deliver the Democratic rebuttal to President Donald Trump’s State of the Union address next week, Democratic Minority Leaders <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> announced Thursday.</p> 
<p>Sen. Schumer said Spanberger “has always put service over politics,” and Rep. Jeffries praised Spanberger for her decisive victory in November’s election.</p> 
<p>“She stands in stark contrast to Donald Trump, who will lie, deflect and blame everyone but himself for his failed presidency on Tuesday evening,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>In a statement, Spanberger said Americans expect and deserve “leaders who are working hard to deliver for them.”</p> 
<p>“We are at a defining moment in our nation’s history,” she said. “Virginians and Americans across the country are contending with rising costs, chaos in their communities, and a real fear of what each day might bring.”</p> 
<p>Spanberger <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/spanberger-wins-virginia-governors-race-00633606" target="_blank">flipped Virginia’s governor’s mansion blue</a> last year, becoming the state’s first female governor. She previously represented the commonwealth’s 7th District in the House. Before her time in politics, Spanberger served in the CIA.</p> 
<p>The two minority leaders also announced Thursday that Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189610" data-person-id="189610">Alex Padilla</a> (D-Calif.) will deliver the Democratic response in Spanish on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Padilla, the son of Mexican immigrants and California's first Latino senator, garnered nationwide attention last summer after he was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/12/california-sen-alex-padilla-handcuffed-at-noem-presser-00403253" target="_blank">forcibly detained</a> by officers during a press conference with Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem.</p> 
<p>“As Donald Trump, Kristi Noem and MAGA extremists have tried to silence the voices of our Latino brothers and sisters, Senator Alex Padilla has consistently fought back and proven Democrats will not bend the knee to this out-of-control administration,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>Schumer added that Padilla’s message will be a “sharp contrast to President Trump’s chaos and self-dealing.”</p> 
<p>Padilla said he plans to discuss lowering costs, safeguarding democracy and reining in “rogue federal agencies" in his speech.</p> 
<p>“Americans don’t need another speech from Donald Trump pretending everything is fine when their bills are too high, paychecks are too low and masked and militarized federal agents are roaming our communities violating Constitutional rights on a daily basis,” Padilla said.</p> 
<p>Trump will address the nation from the Capitol on Tuesday, though a swath of Democrats have announced <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/democrats-trump-state-of-the-union-boycott-00786370" target="_blank">they plan to boycott the address</a>. Jeffries, however, told reporters Wednesday that he plans to attend Trump’s speech.</p> 
<p>“We’re not going to Donald Trump’s house, he’s coming to our house,” Jeffries said. “It’s my view that you don’t let anyone ever run you off of your block.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP senator backs Democratic wife’s bid for office</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/ricketts-endorses-democratic-wifes-bid-00789053</link>
      <description>Trump ally Sen. Pete Ricketts is supporting his wife, Susanne Shore, in her run as a Democrat for the University of Nebraska Board of Regents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-76f1-d3b5-addf-f6f581c40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 13:02:25 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b5/20/aeb9b29d4f1598974fc07ddea837/u-s-congress-28252.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I usually vote straight Republican, but Susanne will be my one Democrat exception in 2026!” Sen. Pete Ricketts said.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b5/20/aeb9b29d4f1598974fc07ddea837/u-s-congress-28252.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Finya Swai</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Finya Swai</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In a rare move, Sen. Pete Ricketts (R-Neb.) is reaching across party lines to endorse his wife, Susanne Shore, who announced Thursday that she is running as a Democrat for a seat on the University of Nebraska Board of Regents.</p> 
<p>Ricketts said in a statement that his wife would be an “outstanding voice” for the university, noting her love for Nebraska and their shared goals of making higher education more affordable and accessible.</p> 
<p>“I usually vote straight Republican, but Susanne will be my one Democrat exception in 2026!” he said.</p> 
<p>The former Nebraskan first lady is seeking an Omaha seat representing Douglas County after former Regent Elizabeth O’Connor resigned in January following a charge of felony DUI. Shore described herself as a “Regent-ready” candidate, pointing to her background in university administration, health care and public service.</p> 
<p>“Our university must be an engine, not a museum,” she said in a statement. “By focusing on results over rhetoric, we can keep our university affordable, competitive and ready for the challenges of the future.”</p> 
<p>The political split between the former two-term governor and his wife has been apparent for more than a decade. The two donate to opposing parties and have even backed candidates running against one another. Shore acknowledged the dynamic, saying differences at home are routine but respectful. In an <a href="https://nebraskaexaminer.com/2026/02/19/former-nebraska-first-lady-susanne-shore-runs-for-nu-regent-in-omaha/" target="_blank">interview with the Nebraska Examiner</a>, Shore said Ricketts has been “nothing but supportive” of her political aspirations.</p> 
<p>“He’s told me what it’s like to run for office, and I’ve seen it firsthand,” she said. “It does feel different to be on this side, but so far it’s been amazing.”</p> 
<p>Shore said her husband has his own campaign to worry about. He’s facing off against Dan Osborn, an independent and former Omaha labor leader, in a competitive Nebraska Senate race.</p> 
<p>Ricketts has been a loyal supporter of President Donald Trump and the Republican Party, backing the administration on many of its key issues. He was, however, one of the few Republicans to criticize Trump after he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/donald-trump-obamas-monkey-video-00768745" target="_blank">posted a racist video to social media</a> depicting former President and first lady Barack and Michelle Obama as monkeys earlier this month.</p> 
<p>“Even if this was a Lion King meme, a reasonable person sees the racist context to this,” <a href="https://x.com/SenatorRicketts/status/2019814293366272277?s=20" target="_blank">he wrote on X</a>. “The White House should do what anyone does when they make a mistake: remove this and apologize.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House wants a reprieve in spy-powers fight that is splitting the GOP</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/trump-section-702-clean-extension-00787007</link>
      <description>The Trump administration is pushing for a clean extension of Section 702 surveillance authority ahead of an April deadline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-72df-d3b5-addf-f2dfb299000a</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/48/dd/375d3faa421480ace751f6473ebd/u-s-congress-14598.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Intelligence Committee Chair Rick Crawford said he's "still shopping" a clean Section 702 extension.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/48/dd/375d3faa421480ace751f6473ebd/u-s-congress-14598.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, John Sakellariadis and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, John Sakellariadis and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some of Donald Trump's biggest loyalists in Congress are itching to rein in federal surveillance powers. So far his administration isn't biting.</p> 
<p>Instead, the White House is quietly pushing for a key spy authority to be extended as is into 2027, according to five people granted anonymity to discuss the private talks. The length of that “clean” extension is still under discussion, but the administration wants at least 18 months, according to three of the people.</p> 
<p>Stephen Miller, the influential senior White House domestic policy adviser, is a leading advocate within the administration for extending the program that lets the government collect the data of noncitizens abroad without a warrant, according to two of the five people. One of the people said that Miller sees the spying statute under Section 702 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act, or FISA, as critical to a variety of homeland security missions.</p> 
<p>The behind-the-scenes push comes as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/section-702-donald-trump-surveillance-00708042" target="_blank">Congress barrels toward an April 20 deadline</a> to reauthorize Section 702, which is itself a perennial source of intraparty tension for the GOP. Even as some Hill Republicans believe that Trump supports a clean extension, others cautioned there are still two months to go and things will remain in flux until the president weighs in publicly — underscoring the fraught nature of the discussion.</p> 
<p>But if Trump embraces the view held by Miller and other administration officials, it would be a major win for the intelligence community and its allies in Congress, who have fretted for months that Trump’s stated hatred of the broader FISA law could tank hopes of getting any reauthorization of the warrantless spy provision over the finish line.</p> 
<p>On the other hand, it’s likely to be a major problem for Speaker Mike Johnson, a former Judiciary Committee member who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/04/29/trump-conservatives-spy-power-00154619" target="_blank">frustrated conservative hard-liners in 2024</a> when he sided with the Intelligence Committee and cast the deciding vote to reject a new policy requiring law enforcement to obtain a warrant before searching for Americans under Section 702 surveillance.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders are involved in conversations with House Republicans about how to reauthorize the program, but there is not yet a consensus on how to move forward ahead of the April deadline.</p> 
<p>Ultimately, there’s no easy path to pass a clean extension in the House. One of the people with knowledge of the discussions said GOP leaders are “going to have a problem” trying to unite Republicans behind a special “rule” allowing for an up-or-down floor vote on a clean extension, which are typically party-line affairs.</p> 
<p>But Republicans also believe that with Trump in office, a number of Democrats who previously supported leaving Section 702 intact will now support putting more fetters on intelligence agencies — making the alternative route, a two-thirds-majority bipartisan vote under suspension of the rules, all but impossible.</p> 
<p>Asked about trying to pass a clean 702 extension, House Intelligence Committee Chair Rick Crawford (R-Ark.) said in an interview that “we’re still shopping that.”</p> 
<p>“I have a responsibility to … run the play that the coach calls, so we'll see,” he said, acknowledging that while he’s “not a mathematician” that it’s unlikely any bill will be able to clear the two-thirds hurdle for speedy passage.</p> 
<p>Across the Capitol, Senate Intelligence Committee Chair Tom Cotton (R-Ark.) has been pitching a clean 18-month extension, with some members of his panel interested in going even longer. But lawmakers have also grown frustrated after administration officials were evasive about their position in recent Capitol Hill meetings, with one person saying Wednesday they still had not been informed of the White House’s official posture.</p> 
<p>Intelligence officials have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/04/28/biden-surveillance-program-republicans-bush-00094435" target="_blank">argued in public</a> that the 702 program is critical to stopping a wide range of national security threats, from narcotics trafficking and weapons proliferation to cyberattacks and terrorism. U.S. spy agencies are also <a href="https://www.intel.gov/assets/documents/702-documents/FISA_Section_702_Vignettes-20240214_Final.pdf" target="_blank">authorized to use the authority</a> to vet foreigners trying to enter the country or seeking certain benefits under federal immigration law.</p> 
<p>Miller <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/2025/11/22/drug-boats-strikes-cia-legal-concerns/" target="_blank">was one of the architects</a> of the Trump administration's policy of bombing suspected drug trafficking boats in the Caribbean and the Pacific under the controversial legal theory that their crews were “combatants” in an armed conflict against the U.S.</p> 
<p>The White House did not provide a comment about its position on extending the program. The Office of the Director of National Intelligence did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Beyond the surveillance policy itself, any 702 extension will face other problems getting through the House: Trying to pass a bill under a rule would give an opportunity to Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) and her allies to make good on their threat to attach a partisan voting bill, the SAVE America Act. If that effort were successful, it would kill the ability for Republicans to get the Democratic votes they will inevitably need to pass the legislation in the House.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers at the heart of the debate know they are quickly running out of time to figure out a strategy. The House is planning to be out of session for three of the coming eight weeks before Section 702 expires.</p> 
<p>“April 20 is the deadline, so we've got to work fast,” Crawford said, adding that “obviously the White House has vested interest in retaining 702, authority. It's a national security issue. So, you know, it's very important to them.”</p> 
<p>Crawford and Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) are in talks over a potential compromise effort that could put new guardrails on Section 702 surveillance. They’ve participated in a joint meeting at the White House and held staff dinners to try and feel out a compromise — which would be a huge relief for Johnson if it could come together.</p> 
<p>But the two panels have historically diverged, particularly on the warrant issue. There’s already skepticism that Jordan or his panel’s members will drop their demands to require warrants in relation to Americans caught in the surveillance data just because the White House is pushing for a clean extension.</p> 
<p>Jordan <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/section-702-donald-trump-surveillance-00708042" target="_blank">indicated to POLITICO late last year</a> that he was hoping to get a warrant requirement written into law, along with a separate proposal banning data brokers from selling information to law enforcement without a warrant.</p> 
<p>But he was more general in comments last week, where he noted there are ongoing conversations about possible additional changes Congress could make while also offering a more measured assessment of the overall program.</p> 
<p>“We know 702 is important,” Jordan said. “We know it needs to get reauthorized. We're committed to getting that done. We just want to do it in the best way possible so that you can get the bad guys, know what the bad guys are doing overseas, but also protect Americans, and I'm confident we'll get there.”</p> 
<p>But some hard-liners in both chambers are as insistent as ever on the need for a warrant requirement.</p> 
<p>Rep. Andy Biggs (R-Ariz.) asked Attorney General Pam Bondi about it during her appearance last week before the House Judiciary Committee. And Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah) said Congress "has no business" reauthorizing Section 702 without adding a warrant requirement for searches involving U.S. persons — a provision that supporters of the program believe would be unworkable.</p> 
<p>Lee and Sen. Dick Durbin of Illinois, the top Democrat on the Senate Judiciary Committee, are planning to revive a bill that would extend Section 702 with changes, including a warrant requirement for searching the content of communications involving Americans, according to a person granted anonymity to disclose the unannounced effort.</p> 
<p>“I think a lot of members still want to be able to have some semblance of a warrant requirement when it comes to FISA 702 uses,” Rep. Byron Donalds (R-Fla.) said. “I don't really see that changing anytime soon.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-18T17:17:15-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Former Victoria Secret CEO denies connection to Jeffrey Epstein's crimes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/les-wexner-jeffrey-epstein-files-00786674</link>
      <description>Les Wexner sat in a closed-door deposition Wednesday with members of the House Oversight panel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-723c-de8a-a1fc-fb7c4b380000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 14:48:34 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ec/0b/094b16854cd6a74c4fe07d9bcdd7/epstein-wexner-congress-07256.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Joshua A. Bickel/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>2026-02-18 Robert Garcia - AP</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ec/0b/094b16854cd6a74c4fe07d9bcdd7/epstein-wexner-congress-07256.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Les Wexner, a billionaire businessman and former client of Jeffrey Epstein, said in a statement shared Wednesday with members of the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee he had no contact with Epstein after the sex offender’s first conviction — nor did he have any knowledge of Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>“I completely and irrevocably cut ties with Epstein nearly twenty years ago when I learned that he was an abuser, a crook, and a liar,” Wexner, the Ohio-based founder of L Brands, said in the statement obtained by POLITICO. “And, let me be crystal clear: I never witnessed nor had any knowledge of Epstein’s criminal activity.”</p> 
<p>Wexner, in compliance with a congressional subpoena, testified behind closed doors in New Albany, Ohio, as part of the Oversight panel’s investigation into Epstein and the Justice Department’s handling of the case.</p> 
<p>A longtime Republican donor, Wexner has become a central figure in the fallout over the so-called Epstein files after he was listed in DOJ materials as a potential secondary co-conspirator — though <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%209/EFTA00175080.pdf" target="_blank">the memo also said</a> there was “limited evidence regarding his involvement,” and he has not been charged in the case.</p> 
<p>House Democrats, speaking during the deposition, sought to portray Wexner as a key enabler of Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>Rep. Robert Garcia of California, the top Democrat on the Oversight panel, said Epstein’s victims had expressed concern about the “enormous amount of money” Wexner transferred to Epstein — potentially over a billion dollars, Garcia claimed.</p> 
<p>“There is no single person that was more involved in providing Jeffrey Epstein with the financial support to commit his crimes than Les Wexner,” Garcia told reporters in Ohio. “Mr. Epstein would not be the wealthy man he was without the support of Les Wexner.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Stephen Lynch (D-Mass.) said that throughout the deposition, Wexner claimed to know less and less about his relationship with Epstein.</p> 
<p>“There was a deep trust between these two men,” he said. “There was a deep friendship there.”</p> 
<p>No Republican lawmakers were present for the deposition, with Committee Chair James Comer unable to attend due to previously scheduled oral surgery, according to a spokesperson.</p> 
<p>According to the statement provided to the House panel, Wexner said his formal relationship with Epstein began after Epstein offered to provide financial advice as a personal favor — a gesture Wexner said he has come to believe was a move to gain his trust. Wexner later hired Epstein in an official capacity to oversee his personal finances and gave him power of attorney.</p> 
<p>“Over the course of many years, [Epstein] carefully used his acquaintance with important individuals to curate an aura of legitimacy that he then used to expand his network of acquaintances, and apparent credibility, even farther,” said Wexner’s written statement.</p> 
<p>As the case against Epstein in the 2000’s ballooned and it became clear that Epstein had been stealing from Wexner’s family, the two men severed ties entirely, Wexner said. Epstein transferred some money back to Wexner’s family but never admitted to wrongdoing, Wexner added.</p> 
<p>Wexner also maintained he had never been unfaithful to his wife over more than three decades together.</p> 
<p>A Oversight Committee spokesperson said in a statement that Wexner answered every question during the deposition, and the panel would soon release a video and transcript of the interview.</p> 
<p>“Mr. Wexner honestly answered every question put to him today by the Committee,” a Wexner spokesperson also said in a statement after the deposition had concluded. “Mr. Wexner reiterated that he has no knowledge of, and did not participate in, Epstein’s illegal conduct. He stands by that fervently.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Democrats plan boycott of Trump’s State of the Union</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/democrats-trump-state-of-the-union-boycott-00786370</link>
      <description>Democrats are skipping Trump’s address and holding a rally on the National Mall instead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-71bf-d0f8-adde-fbffca9a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 12:16:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/fd/5c/50db3b7347408f47d485aa20aa48/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/1198673262">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Leah Millis-Pool/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump arrives to deliver the State of the Union address in the House chamber Feb. 4, 2020, in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fd/5c/50db3b7347408f47d485aa20aa48/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/1198673262" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Finya Swai</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Finya Swai</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A slate of Democrats plan to skip President Donald Trump’s State of the Union address to Congress next week and instead will attend a counterprogramming event on the National Mall that same evening.</p> 
<p>The rally, dubbed the “People’s State of the Union,” will include lawmakers who skipped Trump’s first and second inaugurations, underscoring a small but consistent block of Democrats who continue to opt out of the president’s most high-profile events.</p> 
<p>Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51500" data-person-id="51500">Ed Markey</a> (D-Mass.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66836" data-person-id="66836">Jeff Merkley</a> (D-Ore.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a> (D-Conn.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/282320" data-person-id="282320">Tina Smith</a> (D-Minn.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51658" data-person-id="51658">Chris Van Hollen</a> (D-Md.) and Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478829" data-person-id="478829">Yassamin Ansari</a> (D-Ariz.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/239019" data-person-id="239019">Becca Balint</a> (D-Vt.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/418214" data-person-id="418214">Greg Casar</a> (D-Texas), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/304660" data-person-id="304660">Veronica Escobar</a> (D-Texas), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/239242" data-person-id="239242">Pramila Jayapal</a> (D-Wash.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/312750" data-person-id="312750">Delia Ramirez</a> (D-Ill.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196528" data-person-id="196528">Bonnie Watson Coleman</a> (D-N.J.) are expected to join the rally, organizers said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>“These aren’t normal times and showing up for this speech puts a veneer of legitimacy on the corruption and lawlessness that has defined his second term,” Murphy said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Ansari, who walked out of Trump’s address to Congress last year, said the rally continues her earlier protest. </p> 
<p>“Americans deserve an honest account of the state of our union,” she said. </p> 
<p>She said she plans to bring in a guest who was targeted by the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown.</p> 
<p>The liberal group MoveOn is hosting the rally alongside other organizations, including the popular Democratic-aligned podcasting and media network MeidasTouch.</p> 
<p>The White House dismissed the boycott, saying Democrats have routinely worked to thwart the administration's policy goals.</p> 
<p>“It’s not a surprise that they refuse to celebrate and honor the Americans who have benefited from the commonsense policies Republicans have governed with,” said White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson.</p> 
<p>Democrats have boycotted a series of Trump’s biggest moments throughout both of his terms. Of the dozens of House Democrats who skipped Trump’s first inauguration, 31 were still in Congress and <a href="https://www.politico.com/interactives/2025/democrats-trump-inauguration-boycott-plans/" target="_blank">seven chose to attend</a> his second one, signaling a faded resistance from the first Trump era.</p> 
<p>Trump is set to deliver his address Tuesday night, even as a partial government shutdown continues, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/trump-state-of-the-union-shutdown-00781266" target="_blank">prompting concerns from some senior Hill Republicans and White House officials</a> about the optics. </p> 
<p>But Republicans also see the address as an opportunity to shift the focus away from mounting negative headlines — including fatal shootings by federal immigration agents in Minnesota and scrutiny over the release of the Epstein files — and instead bolster its economic messaging ahead of the midterms.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans are eyeing major election changes. Trump’s mail voting crackdown isn’t one of them.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/trump-mail-voting-congress-00785635</link>
      <description>GOP lawmakers prefer a more targeted approach as the president rails against mail-in ballots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-6e64-d0f8-adde-fe7e8b8e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/19/b2/0db0381041c78fcaf1a633e27b88/u-s-congress-00597.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>An elections bill written by House Administration Committee Chair Bryan Steil would not restrict mail voting as aggressively as Trump has demanded.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/19/b2/0db0381041c78fcaf1a633e27b88/u-s-congress-00597.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is pushing Congress to end mail voting as Americans have come to know it. So far, Republican lawmakers aren’t heeding his calls.</p> 
<p>Trump has long railed against the expansion of vote-by-mail, arguing despite scant evidence that it is rife with fraud and suggesting it was responsible in part for his 2020 election loss. Since retaking office, he has repeatedly called for action — most recently Monday night to reporters on Air Force One.</p> 
<p>“Why would you want mail-in ballots if you know it's corrupt?” Trump said. “It's a corrupt system.”</p> 
<p>But other Republicans don’t see it that way — many of their own voters have voted by mail consistently for decades. So far, the type of blanket ban on mail voting Trump wants has not gained traction on Capitol Hill as GOP lawmakers counsel for a more targeted approach.</p> 
<p>“I support the use of mail-in voting,” said Rep. Mike Lawler, a New York Republican facing a tight reelection contest. “The idea that some states just mail out ballots without any requests is absurd, but the use of mail-in balloting, I do not have an objection.”</p> 
<p>A sweeping elections bill the House passed last week, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/save-america-act-passes-house-00777405" target="_blank">the SAVE America Act</a>, included strict <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499" target="_blank">proof-of-citizenship requirements</a> for voter registration and new photo-ID rules for casting ballots.</p> 
<p>But it did not address voting by mail — even though Trump publicly called for a crackdown in a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116035773358024034" target="_blank">Truth Social post</a> just three days before the vote: “NO MAIL-IN BALLOTS (EXCEPT FOR ILLNESS, DISABILITY, MILITARY, OR TRAVEL!)”</p> 
<p>Behind the scenes, the White House pushed to include language in the bill that would prohibit mail-in voting, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the issue. But that risked losing support from some Republicans and endangering the bill’s ability to pass the narrowly divided House, and it was ultimately left out.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/saveamerica/" target="_blank">White House website</a> touting the bill still lists “No Mail-in Ballots” as one of its features.</p> 
<p>Asked about the discrepancy, White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson said in a statement that Trump “has repeatedly urged Congress to pass the SAVE Act and other legislative proposals that would establish a uniform standard of photo ID for voting, prohibit no-excuse mail-in voting, and end the practice of ballot harvesting to ensure the safety and security of our elections.”</p> 
<p>Several House Republicans said in interviews over the past week they sympathized with Trump’s push to crack down on mailed ballots, but many couched their words carefully. A number hail from states like Florida that have a long history of expansive mail voting and little evidence that the practice has been abused.</p> 
<p>Even as the president pushed to curtail mailed ballots, the RNC and state Republican parties worked to take advantage of the practice during the 2024 campaign to increase voter turnout — and they are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/republicans-midterms-mail-in-voting-00693867" target="_blank">planning to do much the same in 2026</a>.</p> 
<p>Instead, many congressional Republicans insist that Trump is really targeting states like California, Oregon and Utah that conduct their elections almost entirely by mail. Others emphasize the need for exceptions, as Trump has acknowledged, for cases of illness, military service and other reasons they view as legitimate, as well as the other election changes Trump is backing.</p> 
<p>“We have to be very cautious about mail-in-ballot voting,” Rep. Cory Mills (R-Fla.) said in an interview. “But I think that if we get the registration process correct, then that'll fix a lot of this.”</p> 
<p>GOP Rep. Byron Donalds, who is running for governor in Florida, said his state's laws should serve as a model for the country. Florida voters have to request a mail-in ballot and include identification. But there is no limitation on who can request a mail ballot along the lines of what Trump is proposing.</p> 
<p>“In Florida, we treat ballots like they're evidence in a trial,” Donalds said. “Other states need to follow that. … I think that's what the White House is referencing. You just can't have ballots out there in the ether.”</p> 
<p>Another elections bill moving through the House, the <a href="https://cha.house.gov/2026/1/chairman-steil-unveils-the-make-elections-great-again-act" target="_blank">Make Elections Great Again Act</a>, does include provisions dealing with mail voting — including language aimed at preventing “ballot harvesting” where third parties collect ballots on voters’ behalf. It would also ban “universal” vote-by-mail where ballots are sent to all registered voters — but would not narrow who could request a mailed ballot.</p> 
<p>That policy appears to be more in keeping with what most GOP lawmakers envision for an elections overhaul — and they insist that is what Trump in fact supports.</p> 
<p>“If you're sick and you can't get to the polling [place], he wants you to have a ballot. If you're a military member, he wants you to have a ballot,” Rep. Derrick Van Orden (R-Wis.) said of the president. “Who he doesn't want to have a ballot is the illegal alien that registered or even a lawful alien who got a driver's license to be registered to vote and get a mail-in ballot.”</p> 
<p>The MEGA Act is sponsored by House Administration Committee Chair Bryan Steil (R-Wis.) and was the subject of a recent hearing. But it has not yet moved through the panel or been scheduled for the House floor.</p> 
<p>The SAVE America Act also appears likely to stall in the Senate, despite a conservative effort to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/senate-filibuster-gop-save-act-00775393" target="_blank">utilize a so-called talking filibuster</a> to skirt Democratic opposition there.</p> 
<p>Trump appears to be recognizing the obstacles to his elections agenda on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116065471857020644" target="_blank">Friday Truth Social post</a>, he suggested he would take executive action to implement “Voter I.D. for the Midterm Elections, whether approved by Congress or not,” while also mentioning “No Mail-In Ballots, with exceptions for Military, Disability, Illness, or Travel.”</p> 
<p>But to Republicans like Lawler, who voted for the SAVE America Act and is facing a tough reelection fight this year, the GOP’s efforts going forward would be best spent making sure “people get out and vote.”</p> 
<p>“If they vote by mail, if they vote early, if they vote on Election Day, the objective is to get them out and vote,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans worry shutdown will overshadow Trump’s State of the Union</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/trump-state-of-the-union-shutdown-00781266</link>
      <description>President Donald Trump’s Feb. 24 address to Congress is set to collide with a DHS funding lapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5946-d0f8-adde-fb5e982f000b</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 18:13:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/91/4c/78543cc64c42afcfd170ffe3bb99/trump-speech-98364.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP/Ben Curtis</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump arrives to address a joint session of Congress at the U.S. Capitol  on March 4, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/91/4c/78543cc64c42afcfd170ffe3bb99/trump-speech-98364.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Mia McCarthy and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Mia McCarthy and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is barreling ahead with the first State of the Union address of his second term, despite concerns among Republicans that it’s set to hit during a partial government shutdown.</p> 
<p>The speech, set for 11 days from now, is poised to land in the middle of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/congress-shutdown-dhs-ice-00779881" target="_blank">a funding lapse at the Department of Homeland Security</a> – the product of a standoff with Democrats over immigration enforcement that the White House had hoped to avoid. Behind the scenes, some administration officials and senior Capitol Hill Republicans are quietly fretting about the optics, according to six people granted anonymity to describe private conversations.</p> 
<p>The concerned Republicans believe it would be less than ideal for Trump to stand in the well of the House and declare that the state of the union is strong when a critical part of the federal government remains shuttered.</p> 
<p>“It doesn't exactly scream ‘a functioning GOP trifecta,’” said one House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly.</p> 
<p>Asked whether postponing the address was under discussion, a senior White House official said Friday, “Not as of yet.” Senior Hill Republicans believe the president is full steam ahead as well. In 2019, <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2019/01/17/trump-pelosi-letter-1108470" target="_blank">Trump publicly battled</a> with then-Speaker Nancy Pelosi for more than a week over whether to delay his State of the Union address during an earlier government shutdown. He eventually relented.</p> 
<p>Republicans expect Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, who is responsible for extending the formal invitation to the president to address a joint session of Congress, not to delay the speech unless the White House specifically asks.</p> 
<p>The latest shutdown, which will begin when DHS funding lapses overnight, is expected to drag on until at least the week of Trump’s Feb. 24 State of the Union speech because the White House and Senate Democrats appear to be far apart on how far to rein in Trump’s immigration enforcement activities as part of a funding agreement.</p> 
<p>Both sides are continuing to negotiate, but lawmakers left Washington Thursday for a week-long recess with little expectation they would be called back early. The address is scheduled for one day after lawmakers return to Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>White House officials and senior Hill Republicans have been eager for Trump to use the prime time address to tamp down a swirl of negative headlines over the past few weeks, from the fatal shootings by federal immigration agents in Minnesota to the release of the files of the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein. They instead want to focus on the GOP’s economic messaging heading into the midterms.</p> 
<p>Some Republicans also see it as an opportunity to blame Democrats for the DHS funding lapse, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499" target="_blank">which impacts TSA baggage screeners</a>, who will work without pay, FEMA and the Coast Guard.</p> 
<p>“President Trump has been, and always will be, on the side of the American people,” White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said in a Fox News interview Friday. “He wants our government to remain open, and unfortunately, it appears that Democrats are barreling our government towards another shutdown for political and partisan reasons.”</p> 
<p>Among the considerations for Republicans is how difficult Democrats plan to make things for Trump during the speech itself. Senate Democrats are having discussions about whether to boycott the event and talked it over during a closed-door lunch this week, according to two people granted anonymity to share details of the private conversations. Some members of the caucus are currently expected to attend, though a swath is undecided.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> on Friday declined to say whether he believed the speech should go forward during a DHS shutdown.</p> 
<p>“That's an open question,” he told reporters. “We'll have more to say about that next week.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries advised Democrats during a private leadership meeting earlier this week that his members should either sit in “silent defiance” or attend alternative programming, according to two people granted anonymity to describe his comments.</p> 
<p>Heckling has become increasingly common from a president’s political opponents during State of the Union speeches.</p> 
<p>Johnson pleaded with his own members to maintain decorum during former President Joe Biden’s 2024 State of the Union appearance, only for several House GOP hard-liners <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/03/07/bidens-gop-hecklers-vent-their-fury-over-the-border-and-more-00145938" target="_blank"><u>to openly taunt him</u></a>. During Trump’s address to Congress last year, Democrats showed up with signage and jeers, with multiple members walking out either on their own accord or at the insistence of Capitol Police.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51410" data-person-id="51410">Al Green</a> (D-Texas), who stood up to yell at the president at the very beginning of Trump’s speech last year, was later censured by the House for his actions.</p> 
<p>Asked Thursday whether he would attend this year’s State of the Union address, Green said, “I’m not making an announcement right now.”</p> 
<p><i>Eli Stokols and Diana Nerozzi contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meet the YOLO Republicans: Lawmakers with nothing to lose are threatening Trump’s grip on Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/republican-trump-congress-defections-00780479</link>
      <description>A small group of politically insulated members is causing headaches for party leaders and anxiety among their GOP colleagues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-57d8-d647-addc-ffdff49e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 11:44:42 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a7/6e/d04a07984d02b4c3b8b125a26dad/u-s-congress-51147.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) reacts to being photographed as he walks to a vote on Capitol Hill May 14, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a7/6e/d04a07984d02b4c3b8b125a26dad/u-s-congress-51147.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump spent the past year using fear and intimidation to keep Hill Republicans in line, with considerable success. Now those tactics are starting to lose their bite — thanks to a small group of Republicans with nothing to lose.</p> 
<p>The reasons why this handful of GOP lawmakers feel empowered to spurn their president and their party vary. But they are launching mini-rebellions with increasing frequency. It’s causing headaches for party leaders who want to keep tight control of the legislative agenda in an election year and anxiety among rank-and-file Republicans who are facing intense pressure to stick with Trump.</p> 
<p>“Some people live in fear,” said Rep. Don Bacon, a retiring Nebraska Republican who was at the center of a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/house-tariff-votes-republicans-affordability-00777567" target="_blank">crucial episode this past week</a>, where he and two colleagues joined with Democrats to force House votes on Trump’s controversial tariffs.</p> 
<p>When a vote to overturn his Canada levies came to the floor Wednesday, “I was in the cloakroom, and I heard people say, 'I hate tariffs,' and then voted” to leave them in place, Bacon recalled. Were it not for threats of retaliation from Trump and a heavy White House lobbying campaign, he estimated “30 or 40” Republicans would have broken ranks.</p> 
<p>In the end, only six did. But thanks to the thin margins in both chambers — especially the House — a few steel-spined lawmakers can have an outsized impact. That’s a change from the dynamics in Trump’s first term, when many House Republicans weren’t fully on board with the president’s MAGA agenda, but the GOP had a much larger majority to work with.</p> 
<p>Just ask Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky, who has gone from an occasional annoyance to Republican leaders to a persistent problem in the 119th Congress.</p> 
<p>“The margin is razor-thin, so on any given day, I would just need one or two of my own co-conspirators to get something done,” Massie said in an interview before predicting the situation will only get worse for Trump.</p> 
<p>“The retirement caucus is growing,” he said, referring to the dozens of members <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/nevada-republican-mark-amodei-retiring-00769192" target="_blank">not seeking reelection to the House</a>. “Once we get past March, April, and May, which contain a large portion of their Republican primaries, I think you're going to see more defections.”</p> 
<p>Those who have not defected are losing patience with their colleagues, with many arguing it is only hurting the GOP’s chances in the upcoming midterms.</p> 
<p>“Certainly, I respect their right to be independent,” said Republican Rep. Buddy Carter, who is running for Senate in Georgia. “But you know, this is a team game. We got to remember that.”</p> 
<p>One House Republican who was granted anonymity to speak candidly complained about a faction that “just wants to go rogue” while putting colleagues in a politically difficult spot — such as with the tariff vote this week.</p> 
<p>“Those guys might lose now,” the lawmaker said of the House GOP’s most vulnerable members.</p> 
<p>As voting was underway on the tariff measure this week, Trump publicly threatened to support primary challengers and enact other “consequences” against the members who didn't fall in line. To some degree it worked — predictions of a mass GOP jailbreak didn’t materialize.</p> 
<p>But enough members with some political insulation defected, allowing the measure to advance through the House and onto the Senate, which is likely to approve it and set up a Trump veto. Bacon and Rep. Dan Newhouse of Washington are retiring, freeing them from concerns about primary threats.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Reps. Brian Fitzpatrick of Pennsylvania and Jeff Hurd of Colorado are in competitive districts that Republicans can’t afford to lose, putting pressure on the duo to show independence from their party. Rep. Kevin Kiley’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/kevin-kiley-shutdown-gop-critic-00608517" target="_blank">California district got blown up</a> as part of Trump’s redistricting war. And Massie has long been accustomed to being at odds with party leaders, with his campaign to pry open the Jeffrey Epstein files sparking open warfare with the White House.</p> 
<p>Some have doubts that a larger group of Republicans will ever break dramatically with Trump, given his durable popularity with the party base and the need for GOP candidates even in purple districts to appeal to the president’s loyalists.</p> 
<p>One test will come later this year when Trump hits the midterm campaign trail, said Sam Geduldig, a lobbyist at CGCN Group and former House leadership aide.</p> 
<p>“I would be surprised if a candidate didn’t want him at a rally, and that speaks to Trump’s strength,” he said. “If he can do that, it says a lot. In 2006, no one wanted [former President] George W. Bush in their district — not in conservative districts, not in moderate ones. If you’re measuring him against modern Republican presidents, he looks strong by comparison.”</p> 
<p>Over in the Senate, Trump already has a fraught relationship with some GOP senators, like Maine’s Susan Collins and Alaska’s Lisa Murkowski, and there is generally a stronger culture of lawmaker independence. But Trump’s decision to essentially send Sen. Thom Tillis of North Carolina into retirement has introduced a new wild card in the chamber’s dynamics.</p> 
<p>Tillis announced he would not seek reelection after voting to oppose Trump’s signature “big, beautiful bill” and warning the Medicaid cuts in the party-line policy package would be a political death knell for the GOP. Now Tillis is frequently speaking out against Trump and is single-handedly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/kevin-warsh-thom-tillis-federal-reserve-confirmation-00756958" target="_blank">blocking his Federal Reserve nominees</a> until a Justice Department investigation into Fed Chair Jerome Powell is resolved.</p> 
<p>Some members are also eyeing GOP Sen. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana as a freer agent after Trump went ahead and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/letlow-senate-cassidy-trump-00736200" target="_blank">endorsed an opponent</a> in the May 16 primary. Asked about Trump’s threats to lawmakers, Tillis suggested they could easily backfire.</p> 
<p>“I still maintain a good relationship with him ... but I think we need to check our passions at the door," he said this week.</p> 
<p>Hurd, the Colorado moderate who voted to cancel the Canada tariffs and is facing a more conservative primary challenger, said he would “let the president’s statement speak for itself.”</p> 
<p>But Hurd prevailed in 2024 without Trump’s endorsement and is in a competitive enough district that Trump can’t afford to meddle too much. The district was decided by 546 votes in 2022, when GOP Rep. Lauren Boebert narrowly held onto the seat.</p> 
<p>“If they want to come to a district where Trump is underwater and push for tariffs in an agriculture- and manufacturing-heavy area, fine — that’s not going to work,” said a person granted anonymity to candidly discuss party strategy. “If they want to lose the majority and play in these primaries, then go ahead.”</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson, meanwhile, has his hands full just keeping his majority intact. He currently can afford to lose only a single GOP member on party-line votes, and while upcoming special elections could boost that margin slightly, things are likely to remain super tight.</p> 
<p>Johnson this week said he had urged one <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/neal-dunn-resignation-johnson-00776216" target="_blank">Republican battling health issues</a>, Rep. Neal Dunn of Florida, to stick it out and finish his term amid concerns he might resign early.</p> 
<p>Dunn declined to comment on his plans, but a close friend of his, Rep. Joe Wilson (R-S.C.), said he had jokingly told Dunn he would like to be helpful amid all the floor unrest.</p> 
<p>"I did offer to carry him into the chamber,” Wilson said.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Mia McCarthy and Alex Gangitano contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers resign themselves to lengthy DHS shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/congress-shutdown-dhs-ice-00779881</link>
      <description>Negotiations will keep going but Democrats and the White House are far apart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-54ad-d0f8-adde-feffb3a80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 20:46:52 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7c/47/e91ee91d43858abdfb9c45234517/2026-0129-congress-francis-12-1-83379.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.) speaks during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 30, 2026. He is standing near a sign listing demands relating to U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE). (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7c/47/e91ee91d43858abdfb9c45234517/2026-0129-congress-francis-12-1-83379.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawmakers left Washington for a week-long recess Thursday, showing no urgency to avert a shutdown at the Department of Homeland Security that will take effect Saturday morning.</p> 
<p>The overwhelming sense of resignation reflected the reality that neither Republicans nor Democrats saw an obvious path forward to resolving their differences over President Donald Trump’s immigration crackdown and whether to rein it in as part of <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">legislation to fund DHS.</a></p> 
<p>Though negotiations between the White House and Senate Democrats continue, the trajectory of talks suggest DHS funding will be lapsed for at least 10 days — meaning the soonest any resolution would be reached is in the political hothouse around Trump’s State of the Union address on Feb. 24. The lack of progress has even raised the prospect that Trump’s speech to Congress might be postponed, and some Democrats are mulling a boycott.</p> 
<p><b>“</b>This ‘nyah nyah’ is going to go on for a while,” Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) said Thursday.</p> 
<p>Even if a deal were struck, Kennedy added, “I’m not entirely convinced that anybody would vote for it. I can’t see the Dems voting for anything because they’re not going to get pounded for funding ICE. And the Republicans on my side are not going to get pounded for hurting ICE.”</p> 
<p>Negotiations between Democrats and White House officials were ongoing as of Thursday evening. Democrats, who have floated a series of guardrails on immigration enforcement agencies in exchange for funding DHS, were expected to formally respond to the latest White House offer over the weekend after Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries bashed it Thursday without disclosing specifics on what was contained within.</p> 
<p>The absence of leaked bill text in the exchanges between Democrats and the White House was one subtle sign of encouragement for those watching the negotiations that both sides were taking the talks seriously.</p> 
<p>As they prepared to leave Washington, Republicans continued to knock key demands from Democrats, including a proposal that immigration enforcement agents seek judicial warrants before entering private property.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said that Republicans and Democrats were “not close.” A senior White House official granted anonymity during a call with reporters warned that the administration wouldn’t “accept concessions that meaningfully affect its ability to carry out its immigration enforcement agenda.”</p> 
<p>Even if a compromise emerges, some Democrats worry that Republicans will insist on so many qualifications that any of their proposed guardrails would be rendered toothless.</p> 
<p>“We can't pass reform that has exceptions and caveats — ‘you can't wear masks, except for seven different situations where you can. You can't bust into people's homes, except 20 different situations where you can,’” said Sen. Chris Murphy of Connecticut, the top Democrat on the subcommittee overseeing DHS appropriations. “The offers we've gotten are just not serious.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) said it was paramount that both sides “sit down with each other face to face and talk about what you’re doing.” But there were no plans for an in-person meeting<b>.</b></p> 
<p>It will likely take weeks for the public to start feeling pain from a lapse in DHS funding, meaning each side will feel limited political pressure to give in right away. TSA screeners are not set to miss paychecks until March, and FEMA coffers are likely full enough to respond to natural disasters for the near future.</p> 
<p>After the Senate failed to pass DHS funding legislation Thursday, lawmakers in both chambers left Washington with guidance to be ready to come back in a matter of days if Democrats and the White House were able to strike a deal – something that members didn’t see as a realistic possibility before the end of next week.</p> 
<p>“Both sides could dig in and just let this thing drag on,” Thune said. “I don’t think that’s in anybody’s best interest.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes, Mia McCarthy, Myah Ward contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartisan congressional delegation saves US-Mexico joint military exercise</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/bipartisan-congressional-delegation-us-mexico-military-exercise-00779598</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5418-d3b5-addf-f4dc3f0b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 18:13:20 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bipartisan congressional pressure helped push Mexico’s legislature to approve a joint military exercise between the U.S. and Mexican militaries, according to two people familiar with a U.S. delegation to the country.</p> 
<p>The U.S. and Mexico had been considering a joint exercise for which 19 U.S. Marines would train with the Mexican Navy in the city of Campeche along the Gulf of Mexico (the U.S. calls it the “Gulf of America”). But Mexican lawmakers balked at approving the exercise after the U.S. conducted a Jan. 3 operation to capture former Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>The plan got back on track following a visit from a congressional delegation led by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51507" data-person-id="51507">Michael McCaul</a> (R-Texas), according to two people familiar with the visit who were granted anonymity to discuss sensitive conversations. U.S. lawmakers raised the issue with their counterparts in the Mexican Senate, urging them to approve the exercise and telling Mexican lawmakers they would closely track the matter, the people said.</p> 
<p>Mexican President Claudia Sheinbaum <a href="https://www.infobae.com/mexico/2026/02/11/sheinbaum-solicita-al-senado-el-ingreso-de-19-navy-seals-estadounidenses-para-adiestramiento-en-mexico/" target="_blank">officially requested the Marines’ entry earlier this week</a> for the exercises, which will run from Feb. 15 to April 16. The nudge from Congress apparently helped, and Mexico’s Senate unanimously approved the Marines’ entry on Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The involvement of the congressional delegation in securing the approval of the exercise has not been previously reported.</p> 
<p>McCaul, who chairs the Mexico-United States Interparliamentary Group, and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a> of Texas, the top Democrat for the group, said in a joint statement that they “welcome the approval” and said it was a “key objective of our bipartisan delegation to Mexico this past weekend.”</p> 
<p>“We are grateful for the Mexican Senate’s commitment to shared security, which will enable our countries to enhance intelligence-sharing and naval capabilities, intercept dangerous shipments before they reach our shores, and better protect communities on both sides of the border,” McCaul and Cuellar said.</p> 
<p>U.S. Ambassador to Mexico Ronald Johnson said in his own statement that the delegation “in its meetings with Mexican authorities and Senate counterparts, reflects the profound depth of our bilateral cooperation.” He added it was also part of the embassy’s round-the-clock efforts “to work alongside the Government of Mexico and deliver greater security and prosperity for the American and Mexican peoples.”</p> 
<p>At least in this case, the episode underscores that lawmakers still have some ability to sway foreign policy.</p> 
<p>And the approval of the exercise comes at a critical juncture for the bilateral security relationship between Mexico City and Washington. President Donald Trump has previously warned he might consider using military force against Mexico’s drug cartels in the name of combating fentanyl trafficking.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, drug cartels, which control an increasing amount of territory in Mexico, have continued to expand their technological capabilities. On Wednesday, the U.S. abruptly closed the airspace around El Paso International Airport, saying that a Mexican cartel’s drone had breached U.S. airspace and counter-drone operations around the airport could have endangered commercial flights.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-12T15:05:55-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>DHS shutdown all but certain after failed Senate vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/dhs-shutdown-all-but-certain-00778721</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5339-d0f8-adde-fb7bcf6e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 14:01:38 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawmakers are heading for the exits following a failed Senate vote Thursday, all but guaranteeing the Department of Homeland Security shuts down early Saturday morning.</p> 
<p>The funding lapse, which will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499" target="_blank">hit parts of DHS harder than others</a>, comes as the White House and congressional Democrats have failed to move closer to a deal after trading proposals to rein in immigration enforcement practices in the wake of two high-profile shootings in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>Democrats called the latest offer from the White House insufficient Thursday and are expected to send a counteroffer.</p> 
<p>“Democrats have been very clear: We will not support an extension of the status quo,” Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said on the Senate floor ahead of the vote.</p> 
<p>Democrats went on to block progress on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">DHS funding bill</a> the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402" target="_blank">House passed last month</a>, which would have been the vehicle for a short-term funding punt or a larger immigration agreement. The procedural vote was 52-47, well short of the needed 60 votes.</p> 
<p>Prior to the vote, Trump’s border czar, Tom Homan, announced that ICE would be ending its enhanced immigration enforcement, a step Democrats have called for. But Schumer said Thursday that “ICE’s abuses cannot be solved merely through executive fiat alone — we first and foremost need legislation.”</p> 
<p>Republicans attempted to pass a two-week-long stopgap for DHS Thursday afternoon. But every senator needed to agree to quick passage, and Democrats blocked it on the Senate floor, saying a durable agreement to rein in the department was necessary.</p> 
<p>While the negotiations have centered on ICE and Customs and Border Protection, a shutdown will affect a wider variety of agencies including TSA, FEMA and the Coast Guard.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> told reporters he thought the White House offer went “a long ways” toward an agreement, adding: “There are a couple of issues obviously that they’re going to have to work through and work out [with Democrats], and lines that neither side is probably going to be able to cross.”</p> 
<p>Thune added that Democrats are “posturing right now” but that “progress has been real.”</p> 
<p>With no deal close at hand, the Senate is on track to adjourn Thursday for a previously scheduled one-week recess. The House also adjourned Thursday for its previously scheduled recess, though members are on call to return within 48 hours if an agreement is reached. Thune said Thursday if a deal is struck, senators will need to get back to the Capitol within 24 hours.</p> 
<p>Some GOP senators publicly pushed to stay in session in the event of a DHS shutdown, but many others pleaded with their colleagues during a closed-door lunch earlier this week to let them go back home and campaign.</p> 
<p>Others are scheduled to leave Thursday to go on international trips, including a bipartisan group heading to the Munich Security Conference. House Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> has barred members from traveling to Munich or going on other government-funded trips over the break.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-12T14:45:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Mike Johnson chides DOJ for tracking lawmakers’ perusal of unredacted Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/member-backlash-to-doj-tracking-00778751</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5325-d647-addc-fbe7135b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 13:44:14 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said Thursday he disapproves of the Justice Department surveilling lawmakers who come to agency headquarters to review the unredacted Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>“I don't think it's appropriate for anybody to be tracking that,” Johnson told reporters. “So I will echo that to anybody involved with DOJ, and I'm sure it was an oversight. That's my guess.”</p> 
<p>This week, members of Congress have been invited to a DOJ office building to read materials related to the federal case against Epstein that have not been scrubbed for public consumption.</p> 
<p>“Members should obviously have the right to peruse those at their own speed and with their own discretion,” Johnson said.</p> 
<p>But revelations came to light Wednesday, when Attorney General Pam Bondi was testifying before the House Judiciary Committee, that the department might be keeping tabs on which documents lawmakers are viewing on official computers. During Bondi’s appearance on Capitol Hill, a <a href="https://www.gettyimages.com/detail/news-photo/attorney-general-pam-bondi-takes-her-seat-before-testifying-news-photo/2260529263?adppopup=true" target="_blank"><u>photo was taken of her research binder</u></a> that revealed a print-out page of the “Search History” for Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.).</p> 
<p>“It is an outrage that DOJ is tracking Members’ investigative steps undertaken to ensure that DOJ is complying with the Epstein File Transparency Act and using this information for the Attorney General’s embarrassing polemical purposes,” said Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the Judiciary Committee, in a statement.</p> 
<p>Jayapal said <a href="https://x.com/NPRinskeep/status/2021934199020601409" target="_blank"><u>in an interview</u></a> with NPR that she had also raised her concerns with Johnson.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, at his weekly news conference Thursday, said he would follow up to ensure Johnson is pressing the matter with the DOJ directly and “make clear to him that his job is to defend this institution.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries continued, “it does violate the principles of separate and co-equal branches of government. And of course, my Republican colleagues should be denouncing it, but they will not, because they simply are reckless rubber stamps for Donald Trump's extreme behavior.”</p> 
<p>It's not clear what will come from the complaints. A Justice Department spokesperson, in a statement, said the agency "has extended Congress the opportunity to review unredacted documents in the Epstein files. As a part of that review, DOJ logs all searches made on its systems to protect against the release of victim information."</p> 
<p>Asked whether Democrats would seek reprisal for the DOJ tracking, Jeffries said “accountability can either happen right now” or “in the aftermath of the November midterm elections,” when the New Yorker is bullish that his party will retake control of the House.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utah Sen. John Curtis is sinking Jeremy Carl's nomination for a State Department post</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/carl-hearing-00778566</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5316-d0f8-adde-fb5ef17a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 13:31:43 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Utah Sen. John Curtis will vote against Jeremy Carl's nomination for a top post at the State Department — dealing a crippling blow to the Trump nominee's chances of ascending to the job of assistant secretary of state for International Organizations.</p> 
<p>"After reviewing his record and participating in today’s hearing, I do not believe that Jeremy Carl is the right person to represent our nation’s best interests in international forums, and I find his anti-Israel views and insensitive remarks about the Jewish people unbecoming of the position for which he has been nominated,” Curtis said in a statement Thursday.</p> 
<p>The first-term senator's announcement came after Carl told the Senate Foreign Relations Committee at a confirmation hearing on Thursday he would not stop making posts and statements as he waits for congressional confirmation.</p> 
<p>Members from both parties on the committee grilled Carl over a string of comments Democrats call antisemitic and racist that have surfaced in recent months.</p> 
<p>“I greatly understand the importance of restraint and conduct,” said Carl, a senior fellow at the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/how-the-claremont-institute-became-a-power-center-in-trumps-washington-00700147" target="_blank">Claremont Institute</a>, a conservative think tank with members dispersed throughout Washington. “I unfortunately have to balance that with my current job, which involves advocacy and I can’t, as I’ve explained, just totally put away my day job. I’m not being offered a job here yet.“</p> 
<p>Assuming all Democrats in the Foreign Relations Committee join Curtis in voting to reject his nomination, Carl will not have enough votes to advance to the Senate floor. Carl previously served as Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Interior during Trump's first term.</p> 
<p>In the past, Carl has appeared to endorse the “great replacement theory,” slammed the Juneteenth holiday and called for the execution of American Federation of Teachers President Randi Weingarten, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/09/25/politics/kfile-jeremy-carl-state-department-deleted-tweets" target="_blank">according to CNN</a>. He deleted nearly 5,000 social media posts since before his nomination, the outlet reported in September.</p> 
<p>“We are essentially moving,” he told conservative media commentator Tucker Carlson in April 2024, “to what is effectively, a post-White America.”</p> 
<p>Democrats also hit out at Carl, who grew up Jewish before converting to Christianity, for what they say are derisive comments he’s made about Jewish Americans, including statements that diminish the effects of the Holocaust.</p> 
<p>“No person who thinks Jews should get over the Holocaust and spreads pernicious Jewish stereotypes can claim to have the character or judgment necessary to serve as a diplomat for this country,” Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, who is Jewish, <a href="https://www.democrats.senate.gov/newsroom/press-releases/leader-schumer-floor-remarks-opposing-the-nomination-of-jeremy-carl-following-his-record-of-racist-and-antisemitic-rhetoric" target="_blank">said in a statement this week</a>.</p> 
<p>Democrats on the foreign relations committee, including ranking member Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) and Jacky Rosen (D-Nev.), a former synagogue president, panned Carl for his past statements.</p> 
<p>A vote for Carl "tells Americans you're willing to use your sacred vote, not just to ignore but to endorse the hateful statements,” Rosen implored her colleagues.</p> 
<p>“It tells Jewish Americans they simply don't matter," she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Billy Long calls Iceland ‘52nd state’ joke ‘totally inappropriate’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/billy-long-on-greenland-00778409</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-52e9-de8a-a1fc-fbe9aa2c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 13:00:32 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Finya Swai</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Finya Swai</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Rep. Billy Long apologized to lawmakers for a private joke he made to former House colleagues saying Iceland would be the “52nd state” with him as its governor.</p> 
<p>Appearing Thursday before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, President Donald Trump’s pick to serve as ambassador to the Arctic nation moved to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/billy-long-apologizes-to-iceland-00732007" target="_blank">clean up a diplomatic mess</a> of his own making.</p> 
<p>“It was totally inappropriate,” Long told senators, describing the remark as an attempt at humor that did not land well. “I just hope that the people in Iceland will give me a second chance to make a first impression.”</p> 
<p>Long’s private joke on the House floor, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/01/14/more-floor-meltdowns-threaten-funding-bills-00727023" target="_blank">first reported by POLITICO</a>, prompted minor diplomatic issues amid tense relations between the U.S. and Iceland as Trump seeks to take control of nearby Greenland, a Danish territory. Icelanders also <a href="https://island.is/undirskriftalistar/915fdb39-dad8-4b98-86a1-da6db479775c" target="_blank">launched a petition</a> to their foreign minister, Katrín Gunnarsdóttir, to reject Long as ambassador.</p> 
<p>“We want [Gunnarsdóttir] to reject Billy Long as ambassador to Iceland and call for the United States to nominate another man, who will show Iceland and Icelanders more respect,” the petition read, garnering thousands of signatures.</p> 
<p>Long later apologized for the remark, telling Alaska-based news site <a href="https://www.arctictoday.com/trumps-iceland-ambassador-pick-apologizes-for-52nd-state-comment/" target="_blank">Arctic Today</a> that he was aware of the reaction in Iceland.</p> 
<p>“There was nothing serious about that, I was with some people, who I hadn’t met for three years, and they were kidding about Jeff Landry being governor of Greenland and they started joking about me and if anyone took offense to it, then I apologize,” Long said.</p> 
<p>The president has also mused about making Canada the 51st state.</p> 
<p>Trump nominated Long to replace former Ambassador Carrin Patman. Long represented Missouri’s 7th Congressional District for six terms and briefly served as IRS commissioner last year.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
