<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:09:38 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Trump’s Greenland tariffs could squeeze Hill Republicans</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-greenland-tariffs-congress-00738472</link>
      <description>Democrats plan to force House and Senate votes within weeks that stand to put GOP lawmakers on the spot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-de6e-dd3c-a5df-fe7eabca0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:44:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/6a/ff/62d854104c0fb56a443744648156/u-s-congress-81395.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) walks to a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 15, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/6a/ff/62d854104c0fb56a443744648156/u-s-congress-81395.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump’s threat to weaponize steep new tariffs as part of his bid to acquire Greenland could soon put queasy Republicans on the spot.</p> 
<p>House and Senate Democrats plan to force votes as soon as next month to block the European tariffs Trump announced over the weekend, according to two aides granted anonymity to disclose private scheduling. That, for now, is likely to be the main avenue of congressional accountability as the president amps up his campaign targeting the icy Danish territory.</p> 
<p>Democrats are waiting for Trump to file his executive order, but once he does, a resolution would ripen about 20 days later, according to one Senate aide granted anonymity to describe internal planning.</p> 
<p>While some lawmakers have floated using the spending legislation now moving through Congress ahead of next week’s government funding deadline as a way to block Trump, leaders of both parties are wary of taking any steps that could lead to a government shutdown. And, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/denmark-greenland-vote-congress-00735132" target="_blank">as POLITICO first reported</a>, Danish officials have privately urged against forcing a vote on a separate war powers authorization unless it has overwhelming bipartisan support.</p> 
<p>But the 10 percent tariffs threatened against Denmark, France, Germany, the U.K. and four other countries that recently sent a small contingent of troops to Greenland offer a clear opportunity for congressional pushback from Republicans uneasy about the geopolitics of Trump’s audacious demands, their own free-trade views or a combination of both.</p> 
<p>The Greenland reckoning comes as the House prepares to come off the sidelines on the gamut of Trump’s second-term tariffs. Speaker Mike Johnson has so far been able to shield Trump — and his own GOP members — from a direct confrontation over the president's aggressive levies, which have sparked private heartburn among some Republicans.</p> 
<p>But that appears to be coming to an end. A procedural maneuver that blocked efforts to cancel prior Trump tariffs expires next week, and Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/01/16/funding-crunch-threatens-house-recess-00733035" target="_blank">no firm plan to extend</a> the protections for the president. Already one House Republican — Rep. Don Bacon of Nebraska — says he is likely to oppose any effort by Johnson to block a cancellation of the Greenland-related tariffs from coming to the floor.</p> 
<p>“It's crazy — they're an ally, and we’ve alienated our good friends,” Bacon said Tuesday about Trump’s move targeting the Danes and other NATO countries that have backed them.</p> 
<p>With Republicans holding a threadbare House majority, and Democrats outnumbering them on some days, even one or two GOP defectors might be able to quash any effort to prevent a tariff vote.</p> 
<p>Three Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/16/congress/house-again-votes-to-surrender-tariff-powers-to-trump-00566975" target="_blank">voted in September against Johnson’s last effort</a>to block tariff votes: Reps. Kevin Kiley of California, Thomas Massie of Kentucky and Victoria Spartz of Indiana, who could be likely allies of Bacon.</p> 
<p>Rep. Tom McClintock (R-Calif.) also said he would oppose any effort to prevent tariff votes and doesn't support the president's plan to impose new trade levies on European countries over Greenland.</p> 
<p>“I think that the Trump economic policies overall are having a tremendous positive effect on the economy. I think the tariffs are hurting. And when you're trying to accelerate, it doesn't make much sense to tap on the brakes,” McClintock said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) said Trump’s plan to slap financial penalties on European allies over Greenland is a “bad idea” and that he wants to know the rationale for preventing a vote on blocking them. Fitzpatrick didn’t say how he would vote if he had the chance.</p> 
<p>“My sense is that he’s trying to gain leverage, but I still don’t support the rhetoric,” Fitzpatrick said. “Denmark has given us full access to the country, they’re a NATO ally. There’s no reason for any of this.”</p> 
<p>Republicans are already on edge as they await a ruling from the Supreme Court about Trump’s ability to use emergency powers to implement tariffs at will. The justices skipped an opportunity to issue a decision Tuesday, and it could be a month or more before they rule.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) said the legality of Trump’s latest tariff threat over Greenland is “a question that I have not seen answered yet.” He said he was wary of allowing a president to deploy tariffs as a way to secure new territory.</p> 
<p>“I think if it’s to address trade imbalances or trade abuses … then that’s the sort of thing where tariffs are certainly appropriate," Hurd said. “Outside of that context, I think it gets more problematic.”</p> 
<p>Johnson largely sidestepped a question Tuesday night on Trump’s threat to use tariffs as the latest salvo in his bid to acquire Greenland. He downplayed the odds of a conflict, saying that the U.S. has “great allies” and “everybody there wants to work towards a solution together.”</p> 
<p>The Senate is likely to pass a resolution to block the Greenland-related tariffs when it comes up for a vote. Already three Republicans — Sens. Rand Paul of Kentucky, Lisa Murkowski of Alaska and Thom Tillis of North Carolina — have publicly bashed Trump’s tariffs and urged Congress to take back its institutional prerogatives. Democrats would only need to pick up four GOP votes, and Sens. Susan Collins (R-Maine) and Mitch McConnell (R-Ky.) have both been publicly critical of Trump’s Greenland threats and previously supported resolutions targeting Trump’s other tariffs.</p> 
<p>“The way we are going about projecting power in the Arctic is costly, divisive and unnecessary,” Tillis said during a POLITICO panel Tuesday at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.</p> 
<p>The House and Senate both voting to block Trump’s tariffs would be a significant moment — marking the first time both chambers have moved to check Trump's most controversial trade tactic. But the president would surely veto such an effort, and there are no signs he is yet facing the type of GOP jailbreak that would allow Congress to override him.</p> 
<p>But forcing a vote stands to make things uncomfortable for those in the GOP who have tried to telegraph their discomfort with the Greenland push without fully breaking with Trump.</p> 
<p>Sen. John Barrasso (R-Wyo.), for instance, sidestepped weighing in directly on Trump’s latest tariff threat Tuesday, instead saying that the president has “been a strong supporter of tariffs.”</p> 
<p>“We've had a great relationship with them in the past, and there's a significant military presence,” Barrasso added on Greenland. “We need to build on that.”</p> 
<p>House Democrats, meanwhile, are seizing on the momentum to try to squeeze their GOP counterparts.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.), the top Democrat on the Rules Committee, recited Tillis’ and Murkowski’s remarks during a meeting of the panel Tuesday. He pressed Rep. Adrian Smith of Nebraska, a tariff-skeptical Republican who was testifying on an unrelated bill, whether he would support an effort by Johnson to block a vote on the Greenland-related tariffs.</p> 
<p>Smith said he would “prefer to vote on tariffs, certainly,” while adding he would need to look over any new language before making a commitment.</p> 
<p>“I wasn’t expecting to have this discussion,” Smith said, later adding: “I’ve been on the record for saying I’m not a fan of tariffs.”</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congress clinches bipartisan health deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/20/congress/congress-clinches-health-deal-to-crack-down-on-drug-intermediaries-00736680</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-dc32-d22e-a1db-df3721690000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:17:39 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congressional leaders reached a bipartisan, bicameral health care deal early Tuesday morning they hope lawmakers will pass later this week as part of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_DRAFT29" target="_blank">four-bill government spending package</a>. </p> 
<p>Alongside funding for the departments of Defense, Transportation, Labor, Health and Human Services and Homeland Security through Sept. 30, senior appropriators are proposing a crackdown on drug intermediates known as pharmacy benefit managers, or PBMs. </p> 
<p>Lawmakers in both parties and chambers have been working toward reaching a compromise in this policy area for months after a PBM overhaul fell out of the December 2024 government funding bill amid criticism from then-President-elect Donald Trump and billionaire ally Elon Musk.</p> 
<p>The health care agreement would extend several public health programs, including major telehealth flexibilities, through the end of 2027. It also would fund, through the end of the fiscal year in 2030, a program run through the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services that reimburses facilities for offering hospital-level care in the home.</p> 
<p>In a major win for Democrats, the deal would boost funding for community health centers to $4.6 billion for fiscal year 2026. Another provision in the package would allow Medicare coverage for multi-cancer early detection screening tests.</p> 
<p>It's not clear whether conservatives in the House will allow the health care deal to go through. Fiscal hawks are due to balk at the spending increases for various programs, and the framework is silent on many of the policies called for last week by President Donald Trump's “Great Healthcare Plan" — including expansions to tax-advantaged health savings accounts and certain policies mandating lower drug prices.</p> 
<p>In a continued blow for members on both sides of the aisle, the agreement also would not revive enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies that lapsed at the end of last year and are causing premiums to spike for individuals on Obamacare insurance plans.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Movement on a health plan, but not Trump’s</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/20/congress/health-care-policy-plan-congress-trump-appropriations-00736100</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-d9dd-d6ec-a99b-dbfd3c320000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawmakers are eyeing a health care deal this week, but it’s far from the “Great Healthcare Plan” that President Donald Trump outlined last Thursday.</p> 
<p>Here’s a rundown of the latest developments and why Trump’s grander ambitions are looking DOA on Capitol Hill:</p> 
<p><b>— The deal Republicans could get:</b> After weeks of committee-level negotiations, congressional leadership and top appropriators on both sides of the aisle have clinched a deal on a smaller and far less contentious health care proposal that could hitch a ride on the next government funding package. Most ideas in the plan had a shot at becoming law in December 2024, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/12/18/congress/musk-opposes-funding-bill-00195021" target="_blank">were torpedoed</a> by Elon Musk and Trump.</p> 
<p>The deal released early Tuesday morning as part of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/congress-clinches-funding-deal-for-dhs-pentagon-domestic-agencies-00735698" target="_blank">$1.2 trillion funding package</a> includes a crackdown on drug intermediaries known as pharmacy benefit managers, renewals of several public health programs and $4.6 billion in funding this fiscal year for community health centers.</p> 
<p>The inclusion of the health agreement has swelled the bill to over 1,000 pages, so keep an eye on House conservatives who have balked in the past over being asked to vote within days on such jam-packed legislation.</p> 
<p><b>— The deal they probably can't clinch: </b>Trump’s broader health care affordability pitch from last week appears to be <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-health-plan-congress-00734445" target="_blank">largely doomed on the Hill</a>, underscoring the extreme difficulty around uniting Republicans on any health plan.</p> 
<p>Among the reasons: Democrats are in no mood to help after a series of health care fights with Republicans this past year, and key parts of Trump’s proposal likely wouldn’t meet the strict Senate rules for party-line legislation that could skirt a Democratic filibuster. Republicans also face major divisions over whether to even pursue more health initiatives using the budget reconciliation process in the first place.</p> 
<p>One House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly about conference dynamics described the appetite among GOP moderates for another major party-line bill — especially a health-focused one — as “not good.”</p> 
<p>“You’re going to need 218 votes, which means you’re going to need to build consensus across the conference on what it is we’re pursuing,” said Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.).</p> 
<p>Another big complication: Many senior Republicans oppose a key part of Trump’s plan — codifying “most favored nation” deals to link some U.S. drug payments to the lower prices paid abroad. Speaker Mike Johnson said last year he was “<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/johnson-not-a-big-fan-of-drug-policy-white-house-wants-for-trumps-megabill-00320974" target="_blank">not a big fan</a>” of the policy when White House officials attempted to squeeze it into the first GOP megabill.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Funding bill finalized: </b>POLITICO reporters will continue to scrub the freshly released <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-db15-dd3c-a5df-fb7f1c4a0000" target="_blank">bipartisan, bicameral text</a> for the Defense, Transportation-HUD, Labor-HHS-Education and Homeland Security bills through the day. The House aims to pass the shutdown-averting bill by Friday, with the Senate acting next week — just ahead of the Jan. 30 deadline.</p> 
<p><b>— Voter registration action:</b> House Majority Leader Steve Scalise is eyeing a vote on revamped legislation that would require proof of citizenship when registering to vote, potentially putting pressure on Senate Majority Leader John Thune to follow suit.</p> 
<p>The House passed the so-called SAVE Act in April with the help of a few Democrats, but it died in the Senate. Scalise in a Fox News Sunday interview this weekend talked up a new version of the bill, which would add a photo ID requirement.</p> 
<p><b>— Expanding the CRA’s reach: </b>Republicans are attempting to use the Congressional Review Act this week to overturn mining protections on public lands for the first time. The House Rules Committee will consider a resolution related to Minnesota’s Boundary Waters wilderness at 3 p.m. Tuesday.</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim, Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Calen Razor and James Bikales contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans will be hard-pressed to pass Trump’s ‘Great Healthcare Plan’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-health-plan-congress-00734445</link>
      <description>A lack of Democratic cooperation and strict Senate rules threaten the legislative viability of the White House framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c886-dd3c-a5df-eafeeecd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/56/39/c94961af4efaa7191bf9c538f540/u-s-congress-46690.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Mike Lawler of New York is among the Republicans questioning a party-line health care push this year.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/56/39/c94961af4efaa7191bf9c538f540/u-s-congress-46690.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Benjamin Guggenheim and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Benjamin Guggenheim and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump announced his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/trump-health-outline-00730933" target="_blank">“Great Healthcare Plan”</a> to little fanfare on Capitol Hill last week.</p> 
<p>The question now is how willing and able congressional Republicans will be to actually pass any of it into law after stumbling for years over politically toxic plans to undo Obamacare. The prognosis is not encouraging for the White House.</p> 
<p>Key parts of the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/The-Great-Healthcare-Plan.pdf" target="_blank">light-on-details proposal</a> likely won’t meet the strict Senate rules for party-line legislation that could skirt a Democratic filibuster. Similar cost-reduction proposals from Republicans ran into problems on that count in last year's tax-cuts-focused megabill.</p> 
<p>White House officials argue the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/trump-health-plan-insurance-pharma-obamacare-00732557" target="_blank">new health care plan features initiatives</a> that should garner bipartisan support, but Democrats are already balking. They’re in no mood to help Republicans out after Trump's megabill slashed Medicaid funding, and they’re still fighting to revive the expired Obamacare subsidies that the Trump plan rejects.</p> 
<p>“Time and again, Donald Trump has made empty promises to the American people about lowering their health care costs, and today’s announcement is no different,” Senate Finance ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51247" data-person-id="51247">Ron Wyden</a> (D-Ore.) said in a statement following the release of the White House framework.</p> 
<p>Even without the procedural hurdles, uniting Republicans behind a health care plan has repeatedly proven next to impossible. The fate of the enhanced Obamacare subsidies roiled the party for months before they lapsed Jan. 1, and now <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698" target="_blank">there are major divisions</a> over whether to pursue more health initiatives using the partisan budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>One key House faction, the conservative Republican Study Committee, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/rsc-reconciliation-framework-megabill-00724594" target="_blank">released a blueprint last week</a> for a party-line bill that included health care provisions, and its leaders now argue Trump’s plan mirrors key parts of it. They are among a significant GOP bloc that sees reconciliation as the only way the party can pass health legislation — or any other substantive policy — ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>“Our framework for a second reconciliation bill includes many of these historic reforms, because that's how we're going to secure real wins for the people who sent us here,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> (R-Texas), who leads the group of nearly 200 House Republicans, said in a statement to POLITICO.</p> 
<p>But vulnerable incumbents have much less of a stomach for taking up a new health care package before Election Day — especially <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/06/republican-medicaid-cuts-midterms-big-beautiful-bill-00440023" target="_blank">after the bruising Medicaid</a> and Obamacare subsidy fights.</p> 
<p>One House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly about conference dynamics described the appetite among GOP moderates for another major party-line bill — especially a health-focused one — as “not good.”</p> 
<p>"You're going to need 218 votes, which means you're going to need to build consensus across the conference on what it is we're pursuing,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.), a centrist in a tough reelection fight who said the RSC’s plans are “not reflective of the entirety of the conference.”</p> 
<p>There’s also major skepticism among Senate Republicans, including some top Trump allies, who understand that many of their ideas don’t qualify under reconciliation rules, which generally allow only for initiatives that are primarily fiscal in nature. Senators have long <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/26/congress/john-thune-senate-parliamentarian-overrule-00425792" target="_blank">deferred to the chamber’s parliamentarian</a> on those judgments.</p> 
<p>“A lot of the reforms my colleagues thought about earlier, the parliamentarian didn’t accept,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.), adding that he expected only “a pretty limited universe” of health care proposals to pass muster.</p> 
<p>Indeed, Senate Republicans tried to include one of Trump’s health care proposals in their megabill last year — funding a kind of insurance subsidy for out-of-pocket payments in a bid to lower premiums for some Obamacare plans. The parliamentarian ultimately ruled the measure was noncompliant.</p> 
<p>Trump’s call for insurers and providers to publish their prices is also unlikely to qualify for inclusion, considering that any fiscal impact of the transparency measures would be purely incidental to the policy.</p> 
<p>Two senior Republicans involved in the internal conversations granted anonymity to speak about them said GOP leaders will likely have to carve out a narrow slice of the Trump health plan to pursue via reconciliation, if that’s even possible. Other pieces, they said, would have to advance through bipartisan talks with Democrats, who have in the past endorsed proposals to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senators-facing-heat-on-affordability-turn-on-drug-industry-middlemen-00659685" target="_blank">crack down on pharmaceutical industry intermediaries</a> who help negotiate drug prices.</p> 
<p>A senior administration official said Thursday that “reconciliation would not be necessary” because the ideas sketched out under the health care framework could get bipartisan support. But at a White House event Friday, Trump acknowledged that was unlikely, saying “the problem we’ll have with this is, we’ll get no Democrat votes.”</p> 
<p>There’s another complication: A key plank of the Trump plan — codifying “most favored nation” drug pricing deals — is opposed by many senior Republicans. Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said last year he was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/05/01/congress/johnson-not-a-big-fan-of-drug-policy-white-house-wants-for-trumps-megabill-00320974" target="_blank">"not a big fan" of the policy</a> as White House officials tried unsuccessfully to shoehorn it into the GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Still, many Republicans are making a public show of embracing the Trump framework — including Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.), who quickly reinforced the need for a party-line bill to implement the White House plan after it was released Thursday.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> (R-La.), who chairs a Senate committee dealing with health care, said he would take “action” on some of the president’s proposals, including codifying transparency rules. Meanwhile, House Ways and Means Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> (R-Mo.), who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/jason-smith-reconciliation-2026-00698324" target="_blank">previously expressed deep skepticism</a> about the GOP’s ability to pass another party-line bill, complimented the plan’s “bold vision” and said his panel would move to advance it.</p> 
<p>Any action will be in the hands of the top Republican leaders. Johnson and Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> discussed a second reconciliation bill during their regular weekly meeting last week. Thune said the two will “coordinate” but that the House will be “first movers” on any new partisan package.</p> 
<p>“They’ve got some ideas about what they want to do with it,” Thune said. “As I’ve said before, you’ve got to have a reason to do it.”</p> 
<p><i>Cheyenne Haslett contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘No longer in my hands’: How Hill Republicans stopped caring about DOJ releasing the Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/19/epstein-files-release-delay-00735612</link>
      <description>On the one-month anniversary of the Justice Department missing the deadline to release all the Epstein materials in its possession, Republicans in Congress are largely shrugging their shoulders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-d128-dcbd-afbb-d97b6b6a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/74/93/e617e95646369d8aaae1e86a60dd/epstein-victims-press-conference-us-capitol-23610.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), center, speaks during a press conference with Reps. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.) and victims of Jeffrey Epstein outside the U.S. Capitol in Washington, on Nov. 18, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/74/93/e617e95646369d8aaae1e86a60dd/epstein-victims-press-conference-us-capitol-23610.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One month after the congressionally mandated deadline to release all its files on convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, the Justice Department has made only a fraction of the files public — and it remains silent on its plans to fully comply with the law.</p> 
<p>Also keeping quiet about the DOJ delays are congressional Republicans, almost all of whom voted in November to release the records after spending months heeding President Donald Trump's opposition to the move.</p> 
<p>Some of them are openly admitting it's no longer a priority.</p> 
<p>“I don’t give a rip about Epstein,” Rep. Lauren Boebert (R-Colo.) said last week when she was asked to take stock of the month since the Dec. 19 deadline.</p> 
<p>“Like, there’s so many other things we need to be working on,” she added. “I’ve done what I had to do for Epstein. Talk to somebody else about that. It’s no longer in my hands.”</p> 
<p>Boebert was one of four House Republicans, alongside Thomas Massie of Kentucky, Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and Nancy Mace of South Carolina, who joined with Democrats to force a House floor vote on the Epstein legislation when leadership resisted moving it.</p> 
<p>The White House lobbied these lawmakers heavily to take their names off the discharge petition to compel the bill’s consideration, with administration officials at <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank"><u>one point summoning Boebert</u></a> to the Situation Room for a final plea.</p> 
<p>Now Washington’s attention has since shifted to other political firestorms, from Trump's military action in Venezuela to the shooting of a U.S. citizen by an ICE agent in Minnesota, and congressional Republicans are eager to move on — underscoring the extent to which the GOP remains wary of crossing swords with the president.</p> 
<p>The public falling out between Greene and Trump was largely over Greene’s support for releasing the Epstein files — Trump called her a “traitor” — and ultimately culminated in Greene’s resignation from the House earlier this month. Trump vetoed a bill that would have supported a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/house-will-vote-thursday-to-override-trump-veto-of-two-gop-backed-bills-00711322" target="_blank"><u>water infrastructure project in Boebert’s district</u></a>, and administration officials privately warned Mace that her defiance would likely to cost her the president's endorsement in the South Carolina governor’s race.</p> 
<p>Mace has vowed on social media to “<a href="https://x.com/RepNancyMace/status/2011163899194757197" target="_blank"><u>keep fighting</u></a>” for justice for Epstein's victims but has not otherwise continued the drumbeat against the Justice Department.</p> 
<p>Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), who has worked with Democrats on a House Oversight and Government Reform Committee investigation into the Epstein case, said in a recent interview she's now more more focused on holding Bill and Hillary Clinton in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/clintons-defy-subpoena-to-testify-in-epstein-investigation-risking-being-held-in-contempt-00724394" target="_blank">contempt of Congress</a>for not honoring the panel’s subpoena to testify about Epstein.</p> 
<p>Many of the photos released by the DOJ so far feature the former president consorting with Epstein, and the administration has sought to portray Bill Clinton as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/trump-world-takes-shots-at-favorite-boogeyman-bill-clinton-in-epstein-file-dump-00701780" target="_blank">the real pariah</a>, not Trump. Both men have denied wrongdoing, and neither has been implicated in Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>Pressed on the delays in releasing more records, Luna said the initial deadline was not “realistic” and that “I'm not going to rush the process on that — we're going to get them.”</p> 
<p>House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) is also defending the administration.</p> 
<p>“From my standpoint, the Department of Justice is cooperating,” he told reporters after Bill Clinton defied his subpoena to testify last week. “They are turning over documents. We would all like for them to turn documents over quicker, but at the end of the day, they are complying.”</p> 
<p>Not only has the administration failed to fully release Epstein records in its possession — as mandated in the bill passed overwhelmingly in the House and unanimously in the Senate in November — it has also failed to give its rationales for redactions in the files, as mandated by the statute.</p> 
<p>On Christmas Eve, the Justice Department said the U.S. attorney’s office in the Southern District of New York and the FBI have identified potentially more than a million documents related to Epstein that have yet to be made public, offering no updated timing beyond “<a href="https://x.com/TheJusticeDept/status/2003901580341334257" target="_blank"><u>a few more weeks</u></a>” to complete an internal audit. In a recent court filing, the department said more than 500 people were involved in its review.</p> 
<p>That leaves Massie, who has already <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/thomas-massie-trump-jeffrey-epstein-00654214" target="_blank">burned his bridges</a> with the president for championing the Epstein release effort among other perceived slights, as the lone House Republican now publicly agitating for DOJ compliance.</p> 
<p>“They're in clear violation of the law, and I don't think they've allocated the necessary resources to release these files,” Massie said in an interview. “But I'm most concerned about the over-redaction of the files. … There's a list of things they can redact and a list of things they can't redact in our bill, and they're violating that.”</p> 
<p>In an effort to establish some oversight of the Justice Department’s actions, Massie and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), who together championed the bill to release the Epstein files, have asked a judge in New York to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/massie-khanna-jeffrey-epstein-files-release-00717659" target="_blank">appoint an independent third party</a> to oversee the documents’ release. The judge has since asked the Trump administration to respond to their motion.</p> 
<p>Asked about the waning GOP appetite for accountability around the Epstein files release, Khanna signaled he wasn't concerning himself with that, saying in an interview it was now irrelevant what his Republican colleagues are or are not doing.</p> 
<p>“The law has passed,” he said. “Now it's for the courts. Now it's a legal matter.”</p> 
<p>A Justice Department spokesperson did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>The conversation is due to pick back up on Capitol Hill in early February: Attorney General Pam Bondi <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/bondi-set-to-testify-00729891" target="_blank">is scheduled to testify</a> before the House Judiciary Committee on Feb. 11, after a previous appearance was cancelled due to the prolonged government shutdown. She'll surely face questions about the delays from Democrats, as well as from Massie, who sits on the panel.</p> 
<p>“I'll probably focus my five minutes on the Epstein files and her noncompliance with the law,” Massie said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-20T22:09:38-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Louisiana’s Letlow prepares Senate bid after Trump endorsement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/18/louisianas-letlow-prepares-senate-bid-00735697</link>
      <description>Her entry would be the worst-case scenario for GOP Sen. Bill Cassidy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-d21f-dcbd-afbb-da7f9cdf0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 12:51:32 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/52/48/612e0f9841979aa2247366ac3fdb/trump-87232.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Brandon/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump stands at the podium with Rep. Julia Letlow (R-La.) as he speaks in the White House during the Congressional Ball on Dec. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/52/48/612e0f9841979aa2247366ac3fdb/trump-87232.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Julia Letlow is preparing to jump into the Louisiana Senate race against GOP Sen. Bill Cassidy after President Donald Trump publicly endorsed her, according to three people granted anonymity to disclose a yet-to-be-announced bid.</p> 
<p>Letlow is expected to announce her decision as soon as Monday, according to two of the people, though the date isn’t set in stone.</p> 
<p>The move comes after Trump upended Cassidy’s reelection bid on Saturday night, posting on Truth Social that Letlow, if she ran, would have his endorsement. Trump officials have privately encouraged her to run, but Letlow previously told Trump officials she would need the president’s public endorsement to get into the already crowded Republican primary field.</p> 
<p>Letlow didn’t explicitly declare her candidacy in the wake of Trump’s endorsement, but signaled in a post on X that she was likely to get into the race.</p> 
<p>“I’m honored to have President Trump’s endorsement and trust,” she wrote. “My mission is clear: to ensure the nation our children inherit is safer and stronger. This United States Senate seat belongs to the people of Louisiana, because we deserve conservative leadership that will not waver.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s decision to endorse Letlow ends months of speculation among Republicans about if he would get into the race against Cassidy.</p> 
<p>People close to Letlow last week were expecting a public endorsement from Trump in the coming days, according to two people.</p> 
<p>But as the filing deadline drew closer, some fellow GOP lawmakers believed she would ultimately not get in. Cassidy has been telling fellow Republicans for months that senior White House officials had pledged to him that the president would stay neutral in his race — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/04/bill-cassidy-trump-rfk-jr-louisiana-endorsement-00543192" target="_blank">a promise first reported by POLITICO last year</a>.</p> 
<p>Yet even some fellow GOP senators were skeptical of that given Trump’s mercurial moods. Trump had also privately temperature checked some GOP lawmakers on their views about Letlow, according to one person with knowledge of the outreach.</p> 
<p>Trump also called Majority Leader John Thune on Friday and told him that while he had not made a final decision, he was likely to endorse Letlow, according to two people with knowledge of the conversation. Thune encouraged Trump during the call to support Cassidy, the two people said, pointing to the president needing his vote this year and Cassidy’s role as HELP chair, which gives him a role in advancing Trump’s health care push. </p> 
<p>Senate GOP leaderships and the Senate GOP campaign arm are supporting Cassidy, with Thune campaigning with him in Louisiana late last week.</p> 
<p>Trump didn’t directly mention Cassidy in his Truth Social post, instead making it clear that Letlow would have his backing if she gets in.</p> 
<p>“Should she decide to enter this RACE,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115913724519885202" target="_blank">Trump wrote on Truth Social</a>, “Julia Letlow has my Complete and Total Endorsement. RUN, JULIA, RUN!!!”</p> 
<p>Cassidy is seeking his third term in the Senate. He has drawn criticism from Trump at times, particularly over <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/112198571294871461" target="_blank">his 2021 vote</a> to convict Trump of impeachment charges over the Jan. 6 Capitol riot. But Cassidy has touted his working relationship with Trump over the past year, including supporting Robert F. Kennedy Jr.’s nomination to lead HHS and vowing last week to help enact part of Trump’s health care framework.</p> 
<p>“I'm proudly running for re-election as a principled conservative who gets things done for the people of Louisiana. If Congresswoman Letlow decides to run I am confident I will win,” Cassidy <a href="https://x.com/BillCassidy/status/2012729538422153506?s=20" target="_blank">posted on X</a> after Trump endorsed Letlow.</p> 
<p>Republicans for months have already been privately looking at candidates to replace Letlow in the House, with state Sen. Rick Edmonds at the top of the list, according to three people.</p> 
<p><i>David Cohen contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this article referred imprecisely to Cassidy's 2021 vote against Donald Trump. It was a vote to convict the impeached president.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hochul’s sharper stance on ICE complicates life for vulnerable Democrats</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/17/hochul-ice-proposals-new-york-swing-seat-democrats-00733843</link>
      <description>Swing seat incumbents are already facing Republican attacks over the governor’s efforts to curb ICE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c813-dcbd-afbb-c87b0b970000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 14:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/b5/22/b0d1e60342c3bbdd4d8cfb61aa4f/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2254658829">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Octavio Jones/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Gov. Kathy Hochul's push to address federal immigration enforcement in New York is being sidestepped by Democrats in close House races.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b5/22/b0d1e60342c3bbdd4d8cfb61aa4f/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2254658829" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nick Reisman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nick Reisman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Gov. Kathy Hochul’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/hochuls-new-agenda-blends-trump-fighting-with-affordability-00723208" target="_blank"><u>proposals to rein in</u></a> President Donald Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement tactics are putting swing seat Democrats in a tight spot.</p> 
<p>Republicans are eager to capitalize on state-level efforts to undermine deportations as a cudgel against vulnerable House Democrats — especially those representing the bellwether New York suburbs. Left-leaning Democrats — responding to <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3944" target="_blank"><u>eroding support for</u></a> Trump’s immigration policies <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/woman-killed-by-ice-agent-in-minneapolis-was-a-mother-of-3-poet-and-new-to-the-city-00715809" target="_blank"><u>after the shooting of Renee Good</u></a> in Minneapolis — are increasingly willing to take a confrontational approach with federal law enforcement.</p> 
<p>The rapidly shifting events driving public opinion, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook-pm/2026/01/15/trump-ramps-up-threats-on-minnesota-00731068" target="_blank"><u>Trump’s escalating deployment</u></a> of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents and Democrats’ desire to protect undocumented communities has created treacherous political crosscurrents for swing seat lawmakers. And the Empire State — home to large immigrant populations and several contested House districts that may determine control of the chamber — is a case in point.</p> 
<p>“They’re going to have to be really careful how they talk about this,” Laura Curran, a Democrat and former Nassau County executive, said of her party’s swing seat candidates. “We don’t want to talk about defunding the police or all that stuff.”</p> 
<p>Proposals by Hochul and the Democratic-dominated state Legislature to put guardrails around Trump’s immigration tactics have not been enthusiastically received by vulnerable House Democrats.</p> 
<p>Reps. Tom Suozzi and Josh Riley would not comment on the governor’s policy pushback, which she outlined in her State of the State speech this week. And a third Democrat, Rep. Laura Gillen, provided a statement calling for federal immigration reform that avoided any mention of Hochul’s proposals.</p> 
<p>Efforts in Albany to check ICE’s actions are quickly becoming an issue in the three Democrats’ races as Trump moves to deport more undocumented immigrants and potentially use the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/trump-insurrection-act-minnesota-00730664?fbclid=IwY2xjawPXX49leHRuA2FlbQIxMQBzcnRjBmFwcF9pZAwzNTA2ODU1MzE3MjgAAR6Psykun980noX7UdPKJAolBn7eWuBd53Qhf6kUIBSYIvDXYXkrtorkKs_obA_aem_VEuUDjiccfQwTo648uq2eQ" target="_blank"><u>Insurrection Act to quell</u></a> adversarial protests. Republicans plan to mount competitive campaigns against Suozzi, Riley and Gillen this year with the goal of making in-roads among voters in purplish areas of New York state. Attacks over the governor’s immigration measures are already starting: A spokesperson for the House Republicans’ campaign arm accused Hochul and her fellow Democrats of trying to “reopen the illegal immigration floodgates.”</p> 
<p>“New Yorkers haven’t forgotten what Democrats’ reckless open borders did to their state, and they won’t stand for it again,” said National Republican Congressional Committee spokesperson Maureen O’Toole.</p> 
<p>The stakes for New York Democrats to get the immigration policy right couldn’t be higher. Races in at least four seats in this deep blue state are expected to determine control of the House — and the course of Trump’s final two years in office.</p> 
<p>Republicans in the past have pointed to state-level laws in Democratic-dominated Albany to blast Democrats running for federal office. GOP candidates hammered Democrats, regardless of what office they were running for, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/14/new-yorks-kathy-hochul-faces-a-crime-conundrum-ahead-of-reelection-00509076" target="_blank"><u>over a controversial law</u></a> that restricted cash bail.</p> 
<p>State-backed provisions that undermine federal law enforcement stand to serve as a replay of a fight that played out in several election cycles and led to electoral gains for Republicans.</p> 
<p>Gillen’s office sidestepped questions about the Hochul-backed measures and instead called for action on the federal level.</p> 
<p>“Our immigration system has been broken for decades and is in dire need of repair,” she said in a statement. “Comprehensive reform must be done at the federal level. Congress should pass my bipartisan Dignity Act to strengthen our border security, remove dangerous criminals, and provide a pathway for law-abiding immigrants to earn legal status.”</p> 
<p>Curran, who led bellwether Nassau County for four years, believes Democrats in swing seats will have to remain cautious with calls to scale back ICE. But she acknowledged some voters want action following Good’s death and Trump’s threat of invoking the Insurrection Act amid ICE’s clashes with protesters. The fraught emotions have created a tricky balancing act for Democrats in tough races.</p> 
<p>“The dramatic nature of all this ICE action is really starting to freak people out,” Curran said. “The popularity of Republicans is starting to go down if this escalates. This is going to become much more toxic, but I also understand why some of these Congressional Democrats are being vanilla. I understand these districts; they have to be.”</p> 
<p>The lack of support for Hochul’s ICE-curbing plans among the trio of vulnerable New York Democrats underscores how Trump’s increasingly controversial deportation efforts continue to be a third rail for the party. Democrats have struggled to articulate an alternative plan and voters punished their candidates in 2024 as the president returned to the White House promising swift action.</p> 
<p>But the expansive efforts to remove people from the country have changed how the party’s officials — especially at the state level — are approaching the issue.</p> 
<p>Democrats in Albany this year want new boundaries around federal immigration officers — provisions that would apply to a state with a civically engaged immigrant population. Hochul <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/new-york-gov-kathy-hochul-wants-recourse-when-ice-agents-act-improperly-00716720" target="_blank"><u>wants to make it easier</u></a> for New Yorkers to sue federal officials in state court and to require a judicial warrant before carrying out a civil deportation proceedings in locations like schools or houses of worship. Hochul will also implement restrictions on new state-funded public safety grants to require they not be used to support civil immigration enforcement by the federal government.</p> 
<p>The moderate Democrat in interviews has hammered ICE’s recent actions around the country, accusing the agency of abusing its power.</p> 
<p>“It hurts peoples’ confidence in all law enforcement,” <a href="https://www.fox5ny.com/news/ny-nyc-long-island-governor-kathy-hochul-interview-trump" target="_blank"><u>she told Fox 5</u></a>. “This undermines the NYPD, and our state police, who are just doing their jobs.”</p> 
<p>State lawmakers have proposed bills to prohibit federal agents <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2026/01/12/new-york-democrats-apply-ice-melt-00721687" target="_blank"><u>from wearing masks</u></a> while carrying out their official duties. They are calling for new monitoring requirements for ICE. And there are discussions to guarantee that every person facing civil deportation proceedings has access to an attorney.</p> 
<p>“There’s a massive shift — including my own shift,” said Democratic state Sen. Pat Fahy. “Public opinion has shifted dramatically.”</p> 
<p>The Albany-area Democrat has worked with state lawmakers across the country in recent weeks to develop new legislation. Spurred by efforts in California — like requiring ICE agents be unmasked — Fahy and her fellow legislators have been on group chats trading ideas for new ways of bottling up federal enforcement efforts. She acknowledged, though, that some moderate Democrats are yet to come around amid uncertainty over how the rapidly changing events will shape the public’s view of the deportation crackdown.</p> 
<p>“The marginal Democrats or the swing area Democrats are still nervous about it,” she said. “But now it’s more than an immigration issue. This is about who we are as Americans.”</p> 
<p>Even among Democrats eager to put the brakes to ICE’s enforcement there are disagreements.</p> 
<p>Hochul is typically cautious around controversial immigration issues — she is not embracing calls <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/proposal-new-york-sanctuary-state-00715220" target="_blank"><u>to expand sanctuary protections</u></a> and said <a href="https://www.fox5ny.com/news/ny-nyc-long-island-governor-kathy-hochul-interview-trump" target="_blank"><u>in a Fox 5 interview this week</u></a> she does not want the agency abolished. But the governor received standing ovations from the audience when she laid out her immigration measures in her State of the State address — a speech given days after Good’s shooting in Minneapolis and an indication she is delicately threading a needle with her proposals.</p> 
<p>“This doesn’t interfere with lawful enforcement or public safety,” Hochul said in the speech. “It simply affirms a core truth: Power does not justify abuse.”</p> 
<p>There are signs voters across the country are becoming unnerved by immigration agents’ expansive tactics and deployments. <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3944" target="_blank"><u>A Quinnipiac University poll this week</u></a> found 57 percent of voters disapproved of how ICE is enforcing immigration laws while 53 percent of those surveyed believe Good’s shooting was not justified.</p> 
<p>Hochul has said she was “sickened” by Good’s death and called for “recourse” when a federal official acts inappropriately.</p> 
<p>“Let’s start holding these people accountable,” she told MSNOW this month.</p> 
<p>Her likely Republican opponent, Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman, has taken a starkly different posture.</p> 
<p>Blakeman — who signed an executive order opposing sanctuary-related policies — told reporters this week he does not want to “put any shackles on ICE.” He said videos of Good appeared to show her turning her car toward an ICE agent and “trying to run down” the officer — <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2026/01/14/blakemans-ice-thaw-00729497" target="_blank">a claim Hochul's campaign rebuked</a>. The Republican added that there should be more support for victims of crimes by undocumented immigrants.</p> 
<p>“You want to talk about ICE? Let’s talk about the victims of crimes committed in New York state by the people who shouldn’t be here,” said Blakeman, who Republicans expect will have strong coattails in down-ballot Long Island races.</p> 
<p>The differing views among Democrats over how to address Trump’s immigration actions highlights Hochul’s imperative to win over statewide voters, while swing seat incumbents must take a more careful approach, said independent political analyst J.C. Polanco.</p> 
<p>“Hochul understands she’s never going to win a Blakeman voter,” he said. “Unfortunately for Gillen and Suozzi, they need Blakeman voters.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denmark presses Hill to avoid narrow Greenland vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/denmark-greenland-vote-congress-00735132</link>
      <description>Danish officials told lawmakers this week they worried an overly partisan vote could undercut their position.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c90a-dd3c-a5df-eb7a886c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:02:58 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/4d/89/c19e99d742e7bcb29733c9e89be0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2256606279">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Sean Gallup/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>The city center stands on Jan. 16, 2026, in Nuuk, Greenland.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4d/89/c19e99d742e7bcb29733c9e89be0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2256606279" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Joe Gould and Daniella Cheslow</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Joe Gould and Daniella Cheslow</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Danish officials told U.S. lawmakers this week to avoid a war powers vote on Greenland unless it could pass overwhelmingly, warning that a narrow or partisan outcome could do more harm than good.</p> 
<p>Danish representatives delivered their message to lawmakers from both parties in a closed-door meeting on Capitol Hill earlier this week, according to three people familiar with the discussions who were granted anonymity to discuss a sensitive matter.</p> 
<p>A weak showing that included little Republican support, the Danes believe, could undercut Copenhagen’s position and bolster President Donald Trump’s drive to acquire the Danish territory through any means possible.</p> 
<p>The message was relayed in a meeting Wednesday involving Danish Foreign Minister Lars Løkke Rasmussen and Greenland’s foreign minister, Vivian Motzfeldt, as well as Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189136" data-person-id="189136">Ruben Gallego</a> (D-Ariz.).</p> 
<p>Gallego is spearheading the yet-to-be-introduced Greenland war powers legislation, which is aimed at barring Trump from using military force against the Danish territory without congressional approval. The Wednesday meeting was aimed at reassuring Danish and Greenlandic officials — who have expressed repeated alarm over Trump’s rhetoric — that they have support in Congress.</p> 
<p>Following the meeting, Gallego signaled that a vote on the resolution was not imminent.</p> 
<p>“I'm going to keep it on the shelf as an option, should we ever need it,” Gallego said. “But I've offered that language, and we'll make sure to have it handy in case it rises to the moment.” The Danish Embassy declined to comment. Rasmussen and Motzfeldt were part of a delegation whose meeting, also on Wednesday, with Trump administration officials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/denmark-greenland-failed-trump-problems-00729246" target="_blank">failed to resolve the impasse</a>.</p> 
<p>But Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/senate-republicans-derail-effort-to-rebuke-trump-on-venezuela-00730314" target="_blank">are expected to roll out</a> several additional war powers resolutions, including on Greenland, as they force Republicans to go on the record over Trump’s foreign policy decisions, which have repeatedly left Capitol Hill flat-footed.</p> 
<p>“At a minimum, we're forcing a vote that may get the administration to change its course, we're chewing up Senate floor time and highlighting the fact that the president is engaged in external adventurism, rather than solving everyday problems that Americans wanted him to solve,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.) said about the forthcoming efforts.</p> 
<p>And while he acknowledged that it was unlikely they would get a veto-proof number of GOP senators to join most of those war powers resolutions, he added: “We might on Greenland.”</p> 
<p>But while Trump’s refusal to rule out military action has sparked <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/greenland-trump-republicans-congress-00732945" target="_blank">widespread heartburn among Republicans</a>, with even top allies warning he doesn’t have support on Capitol Hill for such a step, there has not been a rush of GOP support for a Greenland war powers resolution.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) predicted it would easily pass if an invasion was imminent, but he wouldn’t support one yet. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.), one of the five Republicans who initially supported a Venezuela war powers resolution, also said that at this point he wasn’t on board. Murkowski, who was in Copenhagen on Friday as part of a bicameral, bipartisan congressional delegation, has said she would support a war powers resolution.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Ethics Committee considering allegations against Nancy Mace</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/house-ethics-allegations-nancy-mace-00734467</link>
      <description>The panel did not disclose details about the ethics claims.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c886-dcbd-afbb-c8ffe0d40001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:11:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/45/6e/d8c9b72241bc84175e727b60ecd9/u-s-congress-13896.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Nancy Mace speaks with reporters outside the U.S. Capitol on Sept. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/45/6e/d8c9b72241bc84175e727b60ecd9/u-s-congress-13896.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The bipartisan House Ethics Committee is weighing allegations against South Carolina Republican Rep. Nancy Mace.</p> 
<p>The panel, in a statement Friday, did not explain the reason for its probe that the Office of Congressional Conduct, an independent ethics watchdog, transmitted a referral late last year. The committee must announce its plans for the investigation by March 2.</p> 
<p>In response to a request for comment on the committee’s plans, a spokesperson for Mace provided a letter to the House Ethics Committee from the lawmaker’s attorney in response to claims regarding her “lodging expenses and reimbursement practices.”</p> 
<p>William Sullivan Jr., a partner at Pillsbury Winthrop Shaw Pittman, asserted in the letter that the Office of Congressional Conduct — the quasi-independent agency that accepts and vets outside complaints against House members and staff — did not disclose if Mace’s ex-fiancé or his associates were involved in their probe. Information provided from her former partner would be suspect, Sullivan argued.</p> 
<p>“[T]he referral appears to rely heavily on unverified materials originating from individuals with personal or adversarial motives, while leaving unanswered whether those individuals contributed to the information underlying the OCC’s analysis,” Sullivan wrote.</p> 
<p>Mace’s spokesperson also pointed to a statement from November, in which Mace claimed the OCC probe was the result of retribution and denied charges of wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Mace previously championed the cause to censure Rep. Cory Mills regarding ongoing ethics allegations against the embattled Florida Republican. That effort failed on the House floor, after a dramatic standoff between Mills and Mace.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-16T09:55:39-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘Dumbest thing I’ve ever heard’: Republicans amp up their resistance to Trump’s Greenland push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/greenland-trump-republicans-congress-00732945</link>
      <description>GOP lawmakers are stepping up their warnings and engaging in diplomacy as the president's threats escalate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c470-dd3c-a5df-ee7aa7bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/81/b5/91b97d4644a2b1b5f2bd1eebdf12/u-s-congress-40836.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A key player in Arctic policy, Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) is involved in several efforts to restrain Trump's Greenland ambitions.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/81/b5/91b97d4644a2b1b5f2bd1eebdf12/u-s-congress-40836.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is talking about taking over Greenland by any means necessary. Republicans in Congress are trying to scare him back to reality.</p> 
<p>As Trump continually threatens to bring the Danish territory into the U.S. over the objections of key global allies and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-greenland-residents-independence-00726696" target="_blank">island’s elected representatives</a>, some GOP lawmakers are stepping up their warnings and engaging in diplomacy as Democrats prepare to put the other party on record opposing a military invasion.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) predicted members on both sides of the aisle would lock arms and require congressional signoff if it became clear Trump was preparing imminent military action.</p> 
<p>“If there was any sort of action that looked like the goal was actually landing in Greenland and doing an illegal taking … there’d be sufficient numbers here to pass a war powers resolution and withstand a veto,” Tillis said.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227109" data-person-id="227109">Don Bacon</a> (R-Neb.) went further, predicting that it <a href="https://omaha.com/news/local/government-politics/article_bdf0d63a-d6e8-43b5-bb3e-086928a8edfe.html" target="_blank">would lead to impeachment</a> and calling Trump’s Greenland obsession “the dumbest thing I’ve ever heard.”</p> 
<p>The blunt public messaging comes as lawmakers try to reassure U.S. allies, including Denmark, in private. A bipartisan group of House and Senate lawmakers are in Copenhagen Friday to try to drive home in person the message that military action does not have support on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>"Greenland needs to be viewed as our ally, not as an asset, and I think that's what you're hearing with this delegation," Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) said after meeting with Danish and Greenlandic leaders there.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> did not join the delegation but he largely endorsed the message the contingent is sending in comments to reporters Thursday, saying “there’s certainly not an appetite here for some of the options that have been talked about or considered” — an apparent reference to military action.</p> 
<p>The pushback amounts to one of the most profound breaches yet seen between GOP lawmakers and the president in Trump’s second term. So far the Republican uneasiness over Trump’s brash foreign policy moves have not resulted in any successful steps to restrain him.</p> 
<p>Following the operation to remove Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro earlier this month, five Republicans joined Democrats to advance a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_SJRES_98" target="_blank">measure</a> restraining Trump from future military incursions in the South American country. But on Wednesday, two of them reversed course and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/senate-republicans-derail-effort-to-rebuke-trump-on-venezuela-00730314" target="_blank">ended the threat</a> after the administration made some commitments regarding future action.</p> 
<p>Democrats believe Greenland — sovereign territory belonging to a NATO ally — could be different. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> of Virginia, who co-authored the Venezuela measure and signaled a raft of new war-powers legislation, acknowledged to reporters Wednesday that prospects were dim that a veto-proof number of GOP senators would join Democrats’ efforts.</p> 
<p>But “we might on Greenland," Kaine added.</p> 
<p>Thune’s predecessor as Republican leader, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51216" data-person-id="51216">Mitch McConnell</a> of Kentucky, spoke out in a floor speech where he said military action against Greenland would be “an unprecedented act of strategic self-harm” that risks “incinerating” NATO alliances.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/476519" data-person-id="476519">Jeff Hurd</a> (R-Colo.), meanwhile, said he was “deeply concerned” about the administration’s Greenland message.</p> 
<p>“I don't think it is productive, and I don't think this is the way to treat an ally,” he said, adding that he “would be opposed to military action in Greenland.”</p> 
<p>But even as more Republicans speak out about Trump’s Greenland ambitions, it’s not clear they could put preemptive guardrails on his actions in this Congress even if they wanted to. Instead, they appear to be hoping that Trump will read the writing on the wall and realize he doesn’t have support on the other end of Pennsylvania Avenue.</p> 
<p>Democrats are vowing to introduce a spate of war powers resolutions, including on Greenland, in the coming weeks and months. Yet even Tillis, who predicted overwhelming support for such a resolution in the case of “imminent” military action, said he would not currently support a measure to stop Trump from using force in the region because it would “legitimize” a threat he doesn’t think is now real.</p> 
<p>Instead, Tillis is using his megaphone as a retiring senator to launch broadsides against Trump’s top aides, whom he blames for some excesses of the administration. While a Greenland takeover might be supported by hard-line deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller, Tillis said, “it’s not the position of the U.S. government.”That, he said, is “another reason I’m going to Copenhagen.”</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.), who initially supported the Venezuela war powers resolution before backtracking, also said in an interview that he was not on board with a similar effort for Greenland.</p> 
<p>“Not prospectively,” Hawley said, adding that any such measure “needs to respond to really particular facts.”</p> 
<p>Any formal GOP pushback is certain to include Murkowski, a co-founder of the Senate Arctic Caucus, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/bipartisan-bill-targets-trumps-greenland-talk-00730427" target="_blank">introduced a nonbinding resolution</a> Thursday with Sen. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.), Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) and Bacon that would affirm the U.S. partnership with Greenland and Denmark. The resolution stresses the “mutual respect for sovereignty and territorial integrity” and that any military action would need congressional authorization.</p> 
<p>Murkowski, who also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/lawmakers-meet-danish-officials-rebuke-trump-greenland-00726166" target="_blank">met with Danish diplomats in Washington</a> this week before traveling to Copenhagen, said she would support a Greenland war powers resolution if it came to that. She also introduced a bill with Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) that would prohibit the administration from using funding to unilaterally blockade, occupy, annex or assert control over Greenland or any other territory belonging to a NATO country.</p> 
<p>“We are operating in times where we’re having conversations about things that we never thought even possible,” Murkowski said. “To use the name Greenland in the context of a war powers resolution is absolutely stunning.”</p> 
<p>While a war powers resolution can be fast-tracked to the floor, Greenland’s allies in the Senate can’t easily force a vote on the NATO measure or even the nonbinding resolution. And some Senate Republicans expressed skepticism that party leaders would let those latter measures go anywhere.</p> 
<p>“I’m sure Thune will jump on it like a bad rash,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Joe Gould contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump, Schumer hold rare White House meeting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/trump-and-schumer-meet-00732580</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c3c6-d6ec-a99b-cbef31a80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:32:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump met with Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer on Thursday — a rare one-on-one meeting between the two native New Yorkers.</p> 
<p>The two have shadow-boxed repeatedly over the past year, including on a failed nominations deal and a historic government shutdown, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/05/donald-trump-chuck-schumer-showdown-00493388" target="_blank">have had virtually no personal interaction</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump, according to a statement from Schumer’s office, called the meeting to talk about the Gateway tunnel project, which the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/01/trump-to-withhold-billions-of-dollars-from-gateway-tunnel-and-second-ave-subway-projects-00589772" target="_blank">administration said late last year</a> would not be funded because of the shutdown.</p> 
<p>But the Senate leader also used the sit-down to raise two unrelated issues — health care and the administration's decision to deploy ICE around the country to carry out mass deportations.</p> 
<p>“Schumer also told President Trump that their actions are dangerous and putting more people at risk and he must pull back ICE from U.S. cities,” the statement said.</p> 
<p>Schumer’s decision to raise recently expired Affordable Care Act subsidies comes as the bipartisan health care negotiations in the Senate struggle. The group is discussing a two-year extension of the enhanced subsidies with new restrictions paired with broader health care changes in the second year.</p> 
<p>But Schumer told Trump to “push Senate Republicans to support the 3-year extension of the ACA tax credit bill that has already passed the House.” Democrats forced a Senate vote on a three-year extension last year, but it failed to advance.</p> 
<p>The White House did not immediately respond to a request for comment on the meeting.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congress clears first funding bills since government shutdown ended</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/congress-funding-government-shutdown-00732209</link>
      <description>Lawmakers have their work cut out for them ahead of the next funding cliff, however.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c3a0-dd3c-a5df-ebfaf0ae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:48:39 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/12/0a/ceadcf744f0183565972c8b6687a/u-s-congress-60366.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks on a phone as he departs the Senate chamber at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 7, 2026. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/12/0a/ceadcf744f0183565972c8b6687a/u-s-congress-60366.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate cleared a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6938" target="_blank">three-bill spending package</a> Thursday for President Donald Trump’s signature, completing a fraction of government funding measures necessary to avert another shutdown ahead of the month-end deadline.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers voted 82-15 to approve legislation funding the departments of Justice, Interior, Commerce and Energy, as well as the EPA, water programs and federal science initiatives through the end of the current fiscal year.</p> 
<p><a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7006" target="_blank">Another spending package</a>, funding the departments of Treasury and State, will be waiting for senators when they return from their recess next week. The House passed that measure Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Together, they represent significant progress after last year’s record-breaking funding lapse. But the vast majority of government programs still need to be funded if Congress wants to avoid another stopgap to keep federal operations afloat beyond Jan. 30. That includes more than 75 percent of discretionary funding, including for the Pentagon and many of the largest non-defense programs.</p> 
<p>“We’ve got to continue to complete the job and make progress on the remainder of the appropriations bills,” said Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine) on the floor Thursday afternoon.</p> 
<p>“Our goal is to get all of these bills signed into law, no continuing resolutions that lock in previous priorities and don’t reflect today’s realities,” she added. “No more disastrous government shutdowns that are totally unnecessary and so harmful.”</p> 
<p>The next two weeks will be a gauntlet for both chambers as the thorniest bills are still in the throes of bipartisan, bicameral negotiations.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers are optimistic that the text of another spending package funding Defense, Transportation-HUD and Labor-HHS-Education could be released in the middle of the upcoming long weekend. The Homeland Security funding package, however, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552" target="_blank"><u>remains in limbo</u></a>,<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552" target="_blank"></a>complicated by ongoing tensions in Minnesota where ICE agents have in recent days shot at least two people — one fatally.</p> 
<p>“We know that they're working, and we're hoping they make some magic out of it,” Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.) said in an interview about appropriators who are in the throes of negotiating the DHS bill.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/house-gop-offer-to-dems-explicit-funding-for-ice-body-cameras-following-minneapolis-shooting-pro-00729265" target="_blank"><u>latest offer</u></a> House Republicans sent to the Senate on the DHS bill would order the department to fund body cameras for immigration enforcement agents. But Democrats are hold more restrictions on the agency.</p> 
<p>“There's no budget like DHS. The way that they move money, the way that they've moved personnel, has no precedent,” Connecticut Sen. Chris Murphy, the Democrat leading DHS funding negotiations in the Senate, said in a brief interview Thursday afternoon.</p> 
<p>“We need to have restraints that actually make a difference,” Murphy added.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune admitted Thursday that if any of the dozen annual funding bills would be “a candidate” for short-term funding, “it would be that one.”</p> 
<p>The protracted runway to finish this work is compounded by the fact that the Senate is planning to be in recess next week, with the House set to be gone the week after for a district work period.</p> 
<p>The House itself is also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/embarrassing-floor-meltdown-has-house-republicans-questioning-their-leaders-00730119" target="_blank"><u>struggling to function</u></a> under the razor-thin GOP majority, where Speaker Mike Johnson spent the past several days contending with dire attendance issues and intraparty revolts — including over earmarks.</p> 
<p>Fiscal hawks including Texas Republican Rep. Chip Roy call earmarks “the currency of corruption” and have taken aim at specific funding lawmakers have secured for projects in their districts.</p> 
<p>The “minibus” funding package the Senate passed Thursday, meanwhile, prevailed over hard-liner attempts to severely shrink spending. It largely rejects the dramatic cuts the White House requested and instead makes more restrained spending reductions to energy and environment programs.</p> 
<p>The National Park Service would face a moderate reduction from current funding levels — much less than the 37 percent cut the White House sought. The EPA would see a 4 percent reduction of $320 million, instead of the more than $4 billion President Donald Trump proposed to slash.</p> 
<p>One area set to get a boost is trade agencies, with an 18 percent increase for the U.S. Trade Representative’s Office and a 23 percent increase for the Commerce Department office responsible for designing and enforcing export controls used to target China and other countries.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-15T15:36:13-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Billy Long apologizes for joking about Iceland as '52nd state'</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/billy-long-apologizes-to-iceland-00732007</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c346-dd3c-a5df-eb7ed7780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:31:58 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Rep. Billy Long has reportedly apologized after privately joking to House lawmakers that Iceland would be the "52nd state" and he would be its governor. </p> 
<p>Long was recently nominated to be ambassador to the island nation by President Donald Trump, who has said he wanted to make Canada the 51st state and is now seeking to take over another Arctic realm, Greenland.</p> 
<p>“There was nothing serious about that, I was with some people, who I hadn’t met for three years, and they were kidding about Jeff Landry being governor of Greenland and they started joking about me and if anyone took offense to it, then I apologize,” Long told <a href="https://www.arctictoday.com/trumps-iceland-ambassador-pick-apologizes-for-52nd-state-comment/" target="_blank">Arctic Today</a>, an Alaska-based nonprofit news site. </p> 
<p>Long did not respond to multiple requests for comment from POLITICO. Trump recently named Landry, the elected governor of Louisiana, as a special envoy to Greenland. </p> 
<p>Long, who represented a southwest Missouri House district for six terms and served a brief stint as IRS commissioner last year, was visiting former colleagues on the House floor earlier this week. His private quip first <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/01/14/more-floor-meltdowns-threaten-funding-bills-00727023" target="_blank">reported in POLITICO</a> kicked off a minor diplomatic row, with Iceland's Ministry for Foreign Affairs <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/iceland-us-ambassador-billy-long-donald-trump-52nd-state/" target="_blank">demanding answers</a> from the U.S. Embassy in Reykjavík over Long's comments. </p> 
<p>Long's comment appears to have struck a nerve as NATO countries, including Iceland, cringe at Trump's repeated threats to commandeer Greenland, a Danish territory. Some Icelanders launched a petition drive urging their government to reject Long as ambassador.</p> 
<p>Asked about the "52nd state" remark, Senate Majority Leader John Thune said Long was "probably having some fun" and "I wouldn't read too much into that."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bill Cassidy raises $1.65 million for reelection fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/cassidy-raises-1-65m-00730420</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beee-d22e-a1db-bfff1a880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:02:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Bill Cassidy raised $1.65 million in the latest fundraising quarter and has $11 million in cash on hand, his team told POLITICO, as he seeks to ward off a right-wing primary challenge.</p> 
<p>The Louisiana Republican is facing several primary challengers on the right fueled by his past criticism of President Donald Trump. Cassidy voted to impeach Trump following the Jan. 6, 2021, attack against the Capitol, a stance that angered the GOP base in Louisiana.</p> 
<p>Cassidy has consistently posted slightly higher fundraising numbers than his opponents, John Fleming, the state treasurer and a former congressman, and state Sen. Blake Miguez, but has a significantly larger war chest. Cassidy has raised more than $17 million this cycle to date. Fleming and Miguez haven’t released their latest numbers; they had just over $2 million and $2.5 million in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/15/congress/bill-cassidy-fec-deadline-primary-challengers-00610818" target="_blank">the bank</a> respectively as of the end of September. Rep. Julia Letlow (R-La.) has also flirted with a bid, though <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">sources told POLITICO</a> she is not expected to run; she had $2.3 million in the bank as of the end of September.</p> 
<p>The senator will have some help. A pair of super PACs supporting Cassidy’s reelection will show they had $5 million in cash on hand at the end of 2025 and received an additional $2 million in the first two weeks of January, according to a person close to those efforts. The PACs expect to spend between $13 million and $15 million on his behalf.</p> 
<p>Cassidy is one of a trio of GOP senators facing tough reelection fights where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">Trump is declining to endorse a candidate</a>, along with Texas Sen. John Cornyn and Maine Sen. Susan Collins.</p> 
<p>Cassidy’s Senate GOP colleagues are backing his reelection. On Thursday, Majority Leader John Thune will host a fundraiser for Cassidy in Baton Rouge that’s expected to bring in $600,000.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: A crypto titan flexes in the Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/crypto-vote-canceled-tim-scott-coinbase-brian-armstrong-00730617</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bff7-dd3c-a5df-ffff9e9f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tim Scott is facing a crypto calamity.</p> 
<p>Landmark digital asset legislation that the Senate Banking chair hoped to advance out of committee Thursday is in extreme jeopardy after one of the industry’s most influential executives announced his opposition Wednesday, setting off a scramble in the Senate and the White House to rescue the bill.</p> 
<p>Scott <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/scott-delays-senate-banking-crypto-vote-00730162" target="_blank">has now postponed the markup</a>, and it’s unclear where he goes from here.</p> 
<p>The last-minute backlash is crypto’s biggest flex yet on Capitol Hill, after the industry’s largest players doled out more than $100 million on races across the country to ensure their allies controlled the 119th Congress.</p> 
<p>Scott is facing opposition from Coinbase CEO Brian Armstrong, founder of the largest U.S.-based crypto exchange. Coinbase has one of the most aggressive lobbying and legal operations in the realm of crypto policy, and it has pumped tens of millions of dollars into a pro-crypto super PAC network.</p> 
<p>The bill at issue is on its face the kind of thing crypto companies have been working toward for years — a sweeping rewrite of Wall Street regulations to accommodate the trading of crypto tokens. It’s also a top financial policy priority for the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>But the legislation isn’t accommodating enough for Coinbase, which had been generally supportive of Scott’s approach until he revealed a new version of the bill this week.</p> 
<p>“Evidently, the industry writes the bill and if anybody in Congress has the nerve to slightly amend it, the industry says that the whole thing is off and they have canceled the law,” Massachusetts Sen. Elizabeth Warren, the top Democrat on Senate Banking and an opponent of the bill, told POLITICO. “These are folks who think that when they’ve bought themselves a Congress, then they expect it to behave the way they say.”</p> 
<p>Armstrong is balking at what he calls the bill’s “erosion” of authority at the Commodity Futures Trading Commission — a regulator the industry has long preferred over the Securities and Exchange Commission. He’s also concerned about the potential for amendments that would crack down on “rewards” from stablecoins — a flashpoint between crypto firms and traditional banks, which see them as threats to old-school savings accounts.</p> 
<p>“We’d rather have no bill than a bad bill,” Armstrong <a href="https://x.com/brian_armstrong/status/2011545247105355865?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a> — a statement that was also at odds with other big players in the crypto world, who say the bill is flawed but still worth advancing.</p> 
<p>Before Armstrong’s surprise rebellion, Scott told POLITICO that he was fully committed to holding the markup, despite looming opposition from key crypto-friendly Democrats and further complications from Republican allies of the banking industry.</p> 
<p>“I am hopeful that it will be a bipartisan victory,” Scott said Wednesday around noon. “But at the end of the day, it’s time for us to come and say where we are on the underlying issues.”</p> 
<p>But for some Republicans, the outcome was obvious after Armstrong’s power play.</p> 
<p>“I think there’s a deal to be had,” Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said. “But [Armstrong’s] probably made the right assessment in terms of us being ready for the markup.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Approps progress: </b>Senators expect to pass the three-bill appropriations minibus Thursday, and some are confident that another funding package could be released this weekend covering Defense, Transportation-HUD and Labor-HHS-Education. Senate Majority Leader John Thune told POLITICO that senators are keeping their options open for how to process the six remaining funding bills once they return from next week’s recess.</p> 
<p><b>— What’s next on war powers: </b>Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.) says Democrats plan to force votes on military action in Greenland, Iran, Colombia, Mexico, Nicaragua and Cuba, after Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/senate-republicans-derail-effort-to-rebuke-trump-on-venezuela-00730314" target="_blank">derailed the Venezuela war powers measure</a> Wednesday. “You make them have to work their ass off to keep their people in the corral,” Kaine told reporters.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congressional Black Caucus endorses former rival Rep. Adriano Espaillat over Black primary challenger</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/congressional-black-caucus-espaillat-primary-00728543</link>
      <description>The CBC’s political wing is endorsing Espaillat after excluding him from the group almost a decade ago.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd90-d6ec-a99b-fff941a20001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/a9/e3/82770ad34aa7bfb1ff880a360db5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2195543097">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Kayla Bartkowski/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Adriano Espaillat received the endorsement of the Congressional Black Caucus's political wing in his primary race against a democratic socialist.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a9/e3/82770ad34aa7bfb1ff880a360db5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2195543097" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jason Beeferman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jason Beeferman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NEW YORK — The Congressional Black Caucus’ political arm is endorsing Rep. Adriano Espaillat over a democratic socialist, Afro-Latina primary challenger — about a decade after the group rejected Espaillat’s efforts to join its ranks.</p> 
<p>Espaillat, an Afro-Latino who represents Upper Manhattan and parts of the Bronx, is <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2025/11/20/justice-dems-vs-squadriano-00663337" target="_blank">facing a primary challenge from Darializa Avila Chevalier</a>, a 32-year-old pro-Palestine organizer who led Columbia University’s protest encampment in 2024. Her candidacy is part of a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/israel-divides-democrats-midterms-00716025" target="_blank">wave of left-leaning primary challenges</a> against pro-Israel incumbents in New York and beyond.</p> 
<p>“Congressman Adriano Espaillat reflects the kind of leadership that our caucus and its members have long championed,” said Rep. Gregory Meeks, chair of the CBC’s PAC, in a statement. “At a time when working families are being priced out of neighborhoods they’ve called home for generations, Adriano has been on the front lines of the fight to make New York City more affordable. That commitment is rooted in lived experience, moral clarity, and a deep commitment to economic justice and civil rights.”</p> 
<p>Espaillat’s rocky history with the Congressional Black Caucus predates his election to Congress. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2017/02/congressional-black-caucus-hispanic-adriano-espaillat-234575" target="_blank">rankled members of the group</a> in 2012 and 2014 when he waged unsuccessful efforts to unseat Rep. Charles Rangel, a founding member of the CBC.</p> 
<p>When Rangel retired, Espaillat ran for the seat a third time and again found himself at odds with the caucus, which endorsed then-state Assemblymember Keith Wright, Rangel’s handpicked successor. Wright, currently the leader of the Manhattan Democratic Party, lost to Espaillat, and the two now helm warring political factions in New York politics.</p> 
<p>Once in Congress, Espaillat attempted in 2017 to join the CBC while simultaneously serving in the Congressional Hispanic Caucus, a group he now leads as its chair. He has identified as a Latino of African descent on the campaign trail, but his request was denied.</p> 
<p>Former CBC Chair Karen Bass <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/07/22/bass-torres-black-hispanic-caucuses-379070" target="_blank">told POLITICO in 2020</a> “there was a specific situation that was more important than [Espaillat’s] ethnic background” that prevented him from joining the caucus. “It was a specific conflict, and I’m not going to talk about it.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.axios.com/2022/02/15/adriano-espaillat-black-caucus" target="_blank">Espaillat said he was still trying</a> to join the group in 2022. Now, the organization is backing him for the first time as he faces a challenge from Avila Chevalier, who holds endorsements from the city’s DSA chapter and the Justice Democrats.</p> 
<p>In its announcement — shared first with POLITICO — the CBC’s PAC said its decision to back Espaillat was rooted in his alignment with its core values and touted his work to fund affordable housing and advocate against President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement tactics.</p> 
<p>“I am deeply honored to receive the endorsement of the Congressional Black Caucus PAC,” Espaillat said in a statement. “The CBC has long stood at the forefront of the fight for economic opportunity and social justice for Black and other marginalized communities. As the first formerly undocumented person to serve in Congress, this endorsement carries special meaning for me.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-14T22:16:27-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Tim Scott postpones Senate Banking crypto vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/scott-delays-senate-banking-crypto-vote-00730162</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bf7b-dd3c-a5df-ff7b20020000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 21:29:52 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> is abandoning plans to hold a vote Thursday on <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_3633" target="_blank">landmark cryptocurrency legislation</a> amid surprise new opposition from a leading crypto firm and uncertainty about the whip counts on both sides of the aisle.</p> 
<p>The South Carolina Republican’s move to punt a scheduled markup comes after the largest U.S. crypto exchange, Coinbase, <a href="https://x.com/brian_armstrong/status/2011545247105355865?s=20" target="_blank">came out against the latest draft</a> of the bill Wednesday afternoon, thrusting the effort into chaos less than 24 hours ahead of a scheduled markup.</p> 
<p>“I’ve spoken with leaders across the crypto industry, the financial sector, and my Democratic and Republican colleagues, and everyone remains at the table working in good faith,” Scott said in a statement. “This bill reflects months of serious bipartisan negotiations and real input from innovators, investors, and law enforcement. The goal is to deliver clear rules of the road that protect consumers, strengthen our national security, and ensure the future of finance is built in the United States.”</p> 
<p>Scott has been working for months negotiate with a bloc of crypto-friendly Senate Democrats on Senate Banking, but they remained opposed to the bill as of late Wednesday, meaning it was unlikely to draw bipartisan support if he forged ahead with a markup. Some Republicans also had outstanding concerns with the bill.</p> 
<p>Coinbase CEO Brian Armstrong wrote on X Wednesday afternoon that the bill as written “would be materially worse than the current status quo.”</p> 
<p>“We’d rather have no bill than a bad bill,” he said. “Hopefully we can all get to a better draft.”</p> 
<p>Coinbase has led the crypto industry’s Washington influence efforts in recent years, but other digital asset firms pushed back on social media after Armstrong’s post on Wednesday, saying the bill remained workable and pushing for it to advance.</p> 
<p>Armstrong said the bill would erode the Commodity Futures Trading Commission’s authority, “stifling innovation and making it subservient to the” Securities and Exchange Commission.</p> 
<p>He also raised concerns about potential “amendments that would kill rewards on stablecoins, allowing banks to ban their competition.” Coinbase offers a rewards program that pays an annual percentage yield to premium subscribers who hold so-called stablecoins — an arrangement that banks are pushing to ban as part of the bill.</p> 
<p>The banking lobby’s position gained steam from lawmakers on both sides of the aisle in recent days, and it looked increasingly likely that provisions cracking down on stablecoin rewards programs would make it into the bill during a markup. Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/466203" data-person-id="466203">Angela Alsobrooks</a> (D-Md.) were preparing a slate of amendments aimed at addressing concerns raised by banks, which have said that allowing stablecoin holders to earn yield risks sparking deposit flight.</p> 
<p>It is unclear when Scott will try again to hold a markup.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66891" data-person-id="66891">Cynthia Lummis</a> (R-Wyo.), who chairs a Senate Banking subcommittee on crypto, said in a statement that lawmakers “have spent thousands of hours working in good faith to deliver a bill that offers the digital asset industry the clarity it needs to thrive on U.S. soil and solidify America's leadership in financial innovation for generations to come.”</p> 
<p>“Today's response from some in the industry proves they just are not ready, and while I am deeply disappointed, I am committed to taking this feedback and partnering with the industry to deliver a product that helps them thrive,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans point fingers at Democrats, Biden at first Jan. 6 committee hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/republicans-hold-first-jan-6-hearing-00730206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beb7-dcbd-afbb-feff17f90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:59:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans used the first hearing of the new committee to investigate the Capitol attacks on Jan 6, 2021, to explore the Biden-era investigation into the pipe bombs left at the Democratic and Republican National Committee headquarters the day before riots — and relitigate conspiracy theories and grievances.</p> 
<p>It illustrated how Republicans plan to use their new select subcommittee and how far apart the two parties remain five years later in their accounts of the day a violent mob stormed the Capitol to contest the results of the 2020 presidential election.</p> 
<p>Rep. Barry Loudermilk (R-Ga.), the chair of the new GOP-led panel, questioned why it took nearly half a decade for law enforcement to identify a suspect in the pipe bombs case, when the Trump Justice Department apprehended the alleged perpetrator, Brian Cole, late last year.</p> 
<p>“How is it that the Biden-Wray FBI was able to flawlessly execute a cellular dragnet to capture the information and eventually apprehend those trespassing at the Capitol, but failed to exercise the same investigative technique into the pipe bomber,” Loudermilk said, referring to President Joe Biden and his FBI chief, Christopher Wray.</p> 
<p>“How is it that the [Democratic]-controlled select committee to investigate January 6th managed to write a final report in which they cover more than 700 pages and 8 chapters without ever mentioning the pipe bombs until an appendix in the back of the report?,” Loudermilk added.</p> 
<p>Michael Romano, the former deputy chief of the Justice Department’s Capitol Siege Section called to testify by the Democrats, said the pipe bombs investigation was particularly difficult, given the “needle-in-a-haystack nature of the evidence.”</p> 
<p>At one point, Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Tex.) physically brandished a binder that appeared to be the report of the previous Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee in his hands, calling that panel’s work a “total sham.”</p> 
<p>And Rep. Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) noted that Stewart Rhodes, a leader of the Oath Keepers, was in attendance for the hearing. Rhodes had been convicted of seditious conspiracy before he was pardoned by President Donald Trump, along with other rioters who stormed the Capitol on Jan. 6.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee who also served on the Democratic-led Jan 6. panel, called Cole’s apprehension a “rare bright spot” in the last year of federal law under the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Still, Raskin maintained that Cole voted for Trump twice and believed the conspiracy championed by Trump and his allies that Biden unfairly won the 2020 election. He also questioned whether Trump’s sweeping pardons for the Capitol rioters<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2026/01/06/jan-6-pipe-bomber-trump-pardon-column-00712039" target="_blank"><u>included Cole</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“Nothing will ever whitewash the indelible facts of that day,” Raskin said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embarrassing floor meltdown has House Republicans questioning their leaders</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/embarrassing-floor-meltdown-has-house-republicans-questioning-their-leaders-00730119</link>
      <description>A group of pro-labor holdouts handed the GOP its latest setback and underscored the tough path for party-line legislation this year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beb8-dd3c-a5df-fefa9c260001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:57:51 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4c/98/fb19fba3415eaf593527ff6105fc/u-s-congress-16351.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mike Johnson (center) is the speaker, but members are questioning the leadership of Tom Emmer (left) and Steve Scalise (right) after Tuesday's implosion.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4c/98/fb19fba3415eaf593527ff6105fc/u-s-congress-16351.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Frustrations are growing among House Republicans as their majority dwindles and agenda sputters — and it’s not just Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> who is feeling the heat.</p> 
<p>Members were aghast after a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-defections-labor-bill-overtime-rules-00725803" target="_blank">stunning Tuesday night meltdown</a> on the House floor, where opposition from a handful of GOP members led to the defeat of <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_2262" target="_blank">one labor bill</a> and the postponement of three others. Some questioned why the Republican floor and whip teams — under the direction of Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> and Majority Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227580" data-person-id="227580">Tom Emmer</a>, respectively — had allowed the votes to be scheduled.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) was among the members who voted no Tuesday. He said he told leaders about his opposition and questioned why they are “bringing bills to the floor they don't have the votes for, other than to think that they're going to strong-arm people.”</p> 
<p>“I think it's really a question for them as to where they're getting their math,” he added.</p> 
<p>The rising concerns about the GOP whip operation come as the party struggles to hang onto its razor-thin voting majority. Since the beginning of the year, Georgia Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene resigned, Rep. Doug LaMalfa of California <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">suddenly died</a> and a spate of medical-related absences and family emergencies have plagued the party.</p> 
<p>The GOP currently has a 218-213 majority if all members are present and voting — which day-to-day is a huge “if.”</p> 
<p>Leaving the floor after the failed vote Tuesday night, Johnson insisted, “We're totally in control of the House.”</p> 
<p>Asked in an interview if GOP leaders have a whipping problem, Scalise said, “We ultimately have a vote count problem with the limited number of members.”</p> 
<p>“You have absences, you have other things — I mean, we just had a member pass away,” he added. “It's going to be a tough road, but we're going to keep moving our agenda.”</p> 
<p>Still, the Tuesday episode led to a significant waste of precious floor time for House Republicans as they try to convince voters they’re working to address cost-of-living issues ahead of the midterms and Johnson continues to insist on <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/johnson-pledges-to-push-ahead-on-another-party-line-megabill-00729264" target="_blank">pursuing a party-line policy bill</a> this year — a follow-up to last year’s tax-cuts-focused GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>Top leaders did see some success last year eking out tough votes, calling the question and then cajoling and cutting deals with holdouts before bringing the gavel down. One procedural vote for the GOP megabill last year was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/07/02/congress/longest-vote-ever-00438166" target="_blank">held open for more than nine hours</a> while leaders and White House officials negotiated a deal securing the legislation’s passage.</p> 
<p>“I have a magic power of being able to whip everybody at the end, and it usually works,” Johnson told reporters Wednesday.</p> 
<p>But that didn’t happen Tuesday, when leaders had to give up on a bill that would rewrite wage rules so employers would not have to pay overtime rates for training in some cases. Pro-labor GOP Reps. Fitzpatrick, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478639" data-person-id="478639">Rob Bresnahan</a> (Pa.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/81211" data-person-id="81211">Nick LaLota</a> (N.Y.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew</a> (N.J.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51627" data-person-id="51627">Chris Smith</a> (N.J.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/26827" data-person-id="26827">Riley Moore</a> (W.Va.) all voted against the legislation.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51135" data-person-id="51135">Pete Sessions</a> (R-Texas), a former Rules Committee chair, largely reserved judgment about the floor chaos. But he did note that “in the past, we focused on an entirely different process than I believe is done today.”</p> 
<p>Other GOP members granted anonymity to speak candidly about the episode were less restrained.</p> 
<p>“They didn’t even whip the fucking bill,” one House Republican said. “It was unbelievably dumb and unbelievably reckless,” said another.</p> 
<p>Members of the whip team led by Emmer checked in with key Republicans during House votes the night before about how they planned to vote on the labor bill. They heard concerns from some members, but not many hard "nos," according to three people granted anonymity to describe the internal process. A spokesperson for Emmer did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>“I let them know,” Moore said. “We need to be standing up for the American worker, not making it more difficult.”</p> 
<p>Van Drew said he didn’t decide to vote against the bill until the day of the vote and did not inform leaders in advance, but he also said they never asked about his view on it.</p> 
<p>“Our majority is so tight — it's a problem,” he said. “They should have whipped it, No. 1. And then secondly, my bad. I should have let them know, even if it was only a half-hour before.”</p> 
<p>The heads-up likely wouldn’t have made a difference. Other Republicans directly warned Emmer and Scalise of the labor problem, according to four people granted anonymity to describe private conversations about the legislation.</p> 
<p>Scalise said in the interview that when a bill is unanimously approved by Republicans on a committee — as was the case for the overtime bill — “then we're going to make our best effort to get it passed.”</p> 
<p>“You don't want days like yesterday,” he said. “But … on the bills that are the top priorities of our agenda, which we make very clear well in advance, we're moving those bills. We have moved them, and we've got a lot more we're going to be bringing this year, and we will pass those bills.”</p> 
<p>In other words, Scalise gave no indication GOP leaders plan to abandon their get-close-and-roll-the-dice approach in 2026.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, Johnson’s leadership team knew there would be some GOP absences, and at least some idea of the intraparty opposition, according to four other people with direct knowledge of the matter, but they believed they could wrangle enough votes to pass the scheduled bills.</p> 
<p>Among the Republicans leaders tried to work over was Smith — one of the longest-serving members of the House and one who has long held pro-labor positions. Smith held his ground, saying he had made commitments to people in his district and he was not going to vote for the legislation, according to three people who heard the conversation.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters Wednesday Smith was among a group of members “that didn't let us know in advance, and it was nobody's mistake.”</p> 
<p>“He was with his wife in an oncology appointment all morning, so he wasn't here to inform us,” he said. “But not a big deal, just part of the process.”</p> 
<p>The episode underscored how GOP leaders are effectively unable to move pro-business and anti-union labor legislation, a key plank of the party agenda. The slim majority allowed the small band of pro-labor Republicans to corner Johnson late last year, signing a Democratic-led discharge petition forcing a vote on a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/house-passes-bill-federal-workers-bargaining-rights-00687594" target="_blank">bill protecting federal worker unions</a>.</p> 
<p>Democrats are eager to push other discharge petitions on labor matters in the wake of the recess successes, while the GOP is unlikely to bring the issue to the floor themselves.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think you’re going to see another labor bill on the floor this year,” another House Republican said.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Judiciary Committee schedules Bondi testimony for Feb. 11</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/bondi-set-to-testify-00729891</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-be8e-d6ec-a99b-ffef40780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:16:03 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi will appear before the House Judiciary Committee Feb. 11, Rep. Jim Jordan, who chairs the panel, said in an interview Wednesday night.</p> 
<p>Her appearance, which had been postponed due to the government shutdown, comes at a perilous time for the Justice Department. Bipartisan lawmakers have criticized her agency's handling of the release of files in the case against Jeffrey Epstein as mandated by Congress under law and now will have to answer for the legality of President Donald Trump's actions in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Decisions under Bondi's watch to prosecute the president’s political adversaries, including former FBI Director James Comey and New York Attorney General Letitia James, have also drawn scrutiny after Trump ordered Bondi to pursue them. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slotkin says she is under investigation for November military video</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/slotkin-investigation-trump-00728241</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd66-d6ec-a99b-ff6f8eaf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:16:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Elissa Slotkin on Wednesday confirmed she is under federal investigation for her participation in a November video urging military members not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/SenatorSlotkin/status/2011472739693912187?s=20" target="_blank">In a video response</a> to the investigation, the Michigan Democrat said President Donald Trump was weaponizing the federal government against those who disagree with him. Slotkin is the latest video participant to face investigation from the administration.</p> 
<p>“To be clear, this is the president's playbook,” Slotkin said. “Truth doesn't matter. Facts don't matter, and anyone who disagrees with him becomes an enemy, and he then weaponizes the federal government against them. It's legal intimidation and physical intimidation meant to get you to shut up.”</p> 
<p>Slotkin, who was recruited by the CIA as a Middle East analyst and served three tours in Iraq, was among five other Democratic military veterans <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2558895077819811" target="_blank">featured in the video</a>, including Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.) and Reps. Maggie Goodlander (N.H.), Jason Crow (Colo.), Chris Deluzio (Pa.) and Chrissy Houlahan (Pa.).</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">Trump at the time called the lawmakers' actions</a> “seditious” and said they should face trial.</p> 
<p>Crow said he had been contacted by the Trump administration as well about the video.</p> 
<p>"Donald Trump is using the Department of Justice as a weapon to harass and intimidate me in particular, as well as the other members who filmed that video," he told reporters. "We are not going to stop it from us doing our job." </p> 
<p>Kelly this week <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/mark-kelly-pete-hegseth-lawsuit-00722382" target="_blank">filed a lawsuit</a> against Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth and other senior military leaders after his own investigation was announced and the Defense Department <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/hegseth-kelly-punish-video-00710555" target="_blank">began to take steps</a> to downgrade his retirement rank.</p> 
<p>Slotkin <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/13/us/politics/slotkin-pirro-trump-justice-dept-video.html" target="_blank">first told The New York Times</a> she had learned about the investigation from the office of Jeanine Pirro, the U.S. attorney for the District of Columbia. Pirro’s office told POLITICO it does not confirm or deny the existence of federal investigations.</p> 
<p>Following Trump’s response to the November video, Slotkin on Wednesday said that threats against her and her family “went through the roof.”</p> 
<p>“We had over 1,000 threats come in. Over 100 were credible and are being investigated,” she said. “I went on 24/7 security from Capitol Police. I had a bomb threat at my house. My parents were swatted in the middle of the night, and my siblings had cop cars placed in their driveways, and now [Trump] is using his political appointees at the FBI and the Department of Justice to follow through with his threats.”</p> 
<p>Slotkin said that freedom of speech is “worth fighting for.”</p> 
<p>“Right now, speaking out against the abuse of power is the most patriotic thing we can do,” she said.</p> 
<p><i>Nick Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-14T14:36:03-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>GOP scrambles to kill Venezuela war powers resolution</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/senate-war-powers-scramble-00728197</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd64-d6ec-a99b-ff6d11060000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 11:44:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate GOP leaders are working overtime to quash a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_SJRES_98" target="_blank">resolution</a> requiring President Donald Trump to come to Congress before taking additional military action in Venezuela. They don’t yet know if they have the votes.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said Wednesday they are in conversations with rank-and-file GOP members, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">five of whom voted with Democrats</a> to advance the measure last week. The administration has offered “assurances,” he said, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/admin-works-to-flip-republicans-on-war-powers-vote-00723922" target="_blank">by stating there are no U.S. troops currently in Venezuela</a> and no plan to send them in.</p> 
<p>“These are consequential, big decisions and people want to feel like they're honoring their obligations to the people that they represent and their own views on some of these issues,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans will first vote on a procedural off-ramp turning off the “privilege” of the resolution, Thune confirmed in a later interview. Under that strategy, senators will be asked to concur in a point of order that the resolution should not be subject to a simple-majority vote since there are no ongoing hostilities.</p> 
<p>One of the five, Missouri Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a>, told reporters earlier Wednesday that he would support that proposal if it is offered, pointing to Secretary of State Marco Rubio's pledge to abide by notification procedures if the administration sends in troops.</p> 
<p>Besides Hawley, GOP leaders would need to win one more of the four remaining Republicans who previously voted to advance the resolution. Thune said in the interview it was "to be determined" if leaders could win the necessary votes.</p> 
<p>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) said Wednesday she is going to continue to support the war powers resolution, while Sen. Rand Paul (R-Ky.) said he would also vote against the point of order. "I don't think they have the votes right now," he said about leadership's legislative gambit.</p> 
<p>Sen. Todd Young (R-Ind.), a key swing vote, said wouldn't say how he planned to vote on the procedural question but praised the Trump administration for being responsive to Congress' concerns.</p> 
<p><i>Connor O'Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hillary Clinton defies subpoena, skips deposition in congressional Epstein inquiry</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/hillary-clinton-skips-deposition-00728000</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bd3a-d22e-a1db-bf3f7fee0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 11:20:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Oversight and Government Reform Committee will vote next week to hold former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in contempt of Congress after she defied a subpoena and failed to appear Wednesday morning for her scheduled deposition.</p> 
<p>It follows former President Bill Clinton's refusal the day before to comply with a subpoena and sit for an interview with lawmakers as part of their investigation into Jeffrey Epstein — an outcome that resulted in Comer's pledge to hold him in contempt of Congress, too.</p> 
<p>“I think what's most disappointing to the Oversight Committee is the fact that we have, in good faith, negotiated with the Clintons’ attorney for five months,” Comer (R-Ky.) told reporters. “We felt like Hillary Clinton could offer some information on [Epstein associate Ghislaine] Maxwell.”</p> 
<p>Comer said his panel would vote on contempt for both Clintons during a markup slated for next Wednesday, which would then be brought to the House floor. A contempt vote could have implications ranging from symbolic to criminal. But the Justice Department has already shown an interest in prosecuting President Donald Trump's political adversaries, signaling there could be grave consequences for the couple — especially Hillary Clinton, who ran against Trump in 2016.</p> 
<p>In a public letter to Comer sent Tuesday, Bill and Hillary Clinton argued the subpoenas issued to them over the summer were invalid and maintained the exercise was designed to embarrass and put them in prison. They also said they have already given Congress whatever information they have about Epstein, the late convicted sex offender with whom Bill Clinton had a documented rapport.</p> 
<p>Comer also said Wednesday his panel would depose Maxwell, Epstein's co-conspirator who is now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in the sex trafficking scheme. He had previously indicated he did not intend to call her up to sit for an interview after issuing her a subpoena because her legal team had indicated she would not cooperate with their questioning.</p> 
<p>A committee spokesperson said the panel had reached out to Maxwell's attorney to schedule a deposition as a result of lawmakers' renewed interest, but is still expected she would invoke her Fifth Amendment rights. The deposition would require members and staff to visit Texas, where Maxwell remains incarcerated. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: More floor meltdowns threaten funding bills</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/14/congress/gop-floor-meltdowns-appropriations-funding-bills-00727200</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-bae8-dca0-ad9b-fbe957610000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders are losing control of the floor to non-stop intraparty revolts ahead of the rapidly approaching deadline to avoid another shutdown.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson needs his ranks united in order to keep federal operations afloat after Jan. 30. But the stark reality is settling in that Republicans are stuck with an essentially unworkable margin that could derail not only their government funding plans but their entire legislative agenda.</p> 
<p><b>— Hard math warning signs:</b> “We’re totally in control of the House,” Johnson insisted Tuesday. Yet <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-defections-labor-bill-overtime-rules-00725803" target="_blank">six Republican defectors</a> sunk a bill earlier that afternoon designed to incentivize employers to offer more training and education programs — at the expense of having to offer some overtime pay, Lawrence Ukenye reports.</p> 
<p>The measure’s collapse led leadership to scrap scheduled votes on two other labor-related bills Tuesday evening. Leaders are now expected to cancel consideration of yet another measure slated for Thursday — related to <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/07/house-advances-joint-employer-portable-benefits-bills-00470942" target="_blank">franchise stores’ liability for employee working conditions</a> — that Republicans privately say will also fail.</p> 
<p>It comes as Republicans have been dealing with a series of absences tightening their already threadbare majority. Rep. Jim Baird (R-Ind.) has returned after recovering from a recent car crash, but Reps. Derrick Van Orden (R-Wis.) and Greg Murphy (R-N.C.) will not be in Washington for at least the rest of the week, adding up to a harrowing single-vote margin for the speaker. They’re also running a deficit following the sudden death last week of Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.). </p> 
<p>None of this bodes well for Wednesday's floor vote to advance the State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services funding package, as rule votes are typically party-line affairs.</p> 
<p><b>— The Homeland fight:</b> Republican leaders are on a separate uphill climb to reach a deal with Democrats on the fiscal 2026 spending bill for DHS, which stalled after an ICE agent shot and killed a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis last week.</p> 
<p>Top Democrats are feverishly working to put new guardrails on immigration enforcement agencies and curb President Donald Trump’s immigration agenda. They’re facing the reality that the only way to do so is by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552" target="_blank">working through the process to fund DHS</a>.</p> 
<p>They’re hoping that Republicans who also have hesitations about the DHS bill will team up with them on provisions to enforce new rules for ICE agents, like requiring them to use body cameras and banning masks.</p> 
<p>It’s unclear, however, what concessions GOP leaders are willing to make, as there are unsavory results for each party if lawmakers can’t strike a deal. Nobody wants an extended stopgap funding measure that maintains the DHS status quo without new funding levels and policy changes.</p> 
<p>“We’re trying to work with our colleagues. I know they’re trying to get a bill. But I’m very sensitive to the political challenges they have on this particular bill,” House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) told reporters this week.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— GOP mulls war powers off-ramp: </b>Senate Republicans are discussing whether to use a procedural maneuver to effectively quash the Venezuela war powers resolution — challenging the resolution’s "privilege." Under that scenario, Republicans would call up a vote on a point of order that the resolution shouldn’t enjoy a privileged status because troops are not currently engaged in hostilities. If it is approved it would effectively kick the underlying war powers resolution off the floor agenda.</p> 
<p><b>— Jan. 6 committee hearing: </b>House Judiciary’s select subcommittee on Jan. 6 will have its first hearing at 2 p.m. Wednesday. The panel is expected to scrutinize the investigations into the pipe bombs left near the Democratic and Republican National Committee headquarters the day before the Capitol attack in 2021. </p> 
<p>Witnesses will include Chris Piehota, a former FBI special agent; John Nantz, a former FBI special agent; and Thomas Speciale, a former senior adviser for the Office of the Director of National Intelligence.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu, Katherine Tully-McManus, Jordain Carney and Lawrence Ukenye contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Abolish ICE’? Many Democrats are ready to fund it — with conditions</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/democrats-ice-funding-appropriations-00726552</link>
      <description>It's not clear a Homeland Security funding bill can get done, but furious negotiations are underway.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b99c-d65c-affb-bb9f90ce0009</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/29/4c/79c6270d401e88e2a9e946e9761b/u-s-congress-30098.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Top Democratic leaders, including California Rep. Pete Aguilar, say they want to restrain ICE — not defund it.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/29/4c/79c6270d401e88e2a9e946e9761b/u-s-congress-30098.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Nicholas Wu and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>New calls to “defund ICE” are reverberating through the Democratic Party following <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/minneapolis-republicans-democrats-dig-in-heels-00721471" target="_blank">last week’s deadly shooting</a> by a federal agent in Minneapolis. Behind the scenes, top Democrats are feverishly working to fund the agency — with strings attached.</p> 
<p>The mismatch between the anti-ICE rhetoric and the actions of Democratic appropriators reflects a Catch-22 of congressional power: The only way lawmakers can put guardrails on the controversial agency and curb President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda at this moment is to hand it billions of taxpayer dollars.</p> 
<p>As they negotiate fiscal 2026 funding for the Department of Homeland Security with Republicans ahead of a Jan. 30 shutdown deadline, Democrats are demanding new rules for DHS agents, such as forcing them to use body cameras, refrain from wearing masks and go through more extensive training.</p> 
<p>Even as <a href="https://d3nkl3psvxxpe9.cloudfront.net/documents/econtoplines_YpmxDW2.pdf" target="_blank">new polling fielded after</a> the fatal Jan. 7 shooting of Renee Good shows that a plurality of voters back ICE’s elimination, top Democrats on Capitol Hill are seeking to restrain the agency under Trump’s leadership — not disband it.</p> 
<p>“House Democrats want accountability and oversight of ICE,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/226960" data-person-id="226960">Pete Aguilar</a> of California, the No. 3 Democratic leader, told reporters Tuesday. “They should have to continue to testify to Congress as to what they are doing. But more importantly, we need to look out for the American people right now. They are terrorizing people in the streets of this country.”</p> 
<p>Among the rank-and-file, there is also a deep desire to rein in the agency. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189828" data-person-id="189828">Darren Soto</a> (D-Fla.), deputy chair of the Congressional Hispanic Caucus, said in an interview his group supports “reforms” for the agency.</p> 
<p>“It's not the CHC's position that we're terminating ICE,” Soto said. “But there is a culture of violence that's happening that does need to be addressed.”</p> 
<p>The Congressional Progressive Caucus, meanwhile, announced Tuesday it had “adopted an official position” opposing new DHS funding “unless there are meaningful and significant reforms to immigration enforcement practices.”</p> 
<p>It’s not clear what GOP leaders are willing to accept in return for the Democratic votes that will be necessary to pass any DHS funding bill. They have not publicly ruled out new rules for ICE, despite equating Democrats’ demands with support for lax immigration policies.</p> 
<p>“Understand, what happened last week gave them more things to yell about,” House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> told reporters this week, referring to Democrats’ response to the shooting. “But they've been against ICE — and frankly, they've been for open borders, more importantly — for years as well.”</p> 
<p>Part of a calculation for both sides is that the alternatives to a negotiated compromise are unsavory for each party. Democratic lawmakers are in no mood to default to a lengthy stopgap funding patch that would maintain the status quo on immigration enforcement and give the Trump administration more leeway to decide how the money is spent. And if Republicans refuse to enact restraints, they warn, funding for DHS could lapse altogether in a few weeks.</p> 
<p>“The question is for Republicans: Are they willing to shut down the government simply to endorse the most lawless Department of Homeland Security in the history of the country?” Connecticut Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a>, the top Democrat on the Homeland Security funding panel, said on NBC’s “Meet the Press” over the weekend.</p> 
<p>Despite the tough rhetoric, Murphy showed a willingness to compromise in comments to reporters this week. Appropriators, he said, are “not going to write a comprehensive immigration enforcement reform bill” within the DHS funding measure.</p> 
<p>“But in every bill there's language on how our money is spent. And I want to make sure that our money is spent lawfully,” he continued. “So yes, we're having conversations about how we can pass a bill — but a bill that makes sure that ICE is operating legally.”</p> 
<p>One of the challenges for lawmakers is that Republicans already gave ICE billions of dollars within the party-line tax and spending package they enacted over the summer. The “big, beautiful bill” included $75 billion for the agency over the following decade, above and beyond the nearly $11 billion it was granted in the fiscal year that ended in September.</p> 
<p>“It's important to understand that a lot of the funding that's being unleashed on the American people in such extreme ways right now was provided not through the traditional appropriations process,” House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> told reporters this week.</p> 
<p>In spite of the major roadblocks to clinching a bipartisan funding deal, there are lawmakers on both sides of the aisle who are interested in putting at least some fetters on immigration enforcement agencies.</p> 
<p>The day after the fatal shooting in Minnesota, GOP Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska said footage of the killing was “deeply disturbing” and called for “policy changes to help prevent future tragedies” that would ensure ICE agents work “safely — and with empathy and respect for human life.”</p> 
<p>Both Democrats and Republicans in the Senate objected to moving forward this week with the DHS funding bill, House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) said, forcing it to be stripped from a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-pulse/2026/01/13/congress-to-reject-trump-global-health-cuts-00723037" target="_blank">planned multibill package</a> at the 11th hour.</p> 
<p>“This one's tricky, just simply because of the political situation,” Cole told reporters. “We're trying to work with our colleagues. I know they're trying to get a bill. But I'm very sensitive to the political challenges they have on this particular bill.”</p> 
<p>Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) also acknowledged this week that “obviously the agency and some of its actions have raised questions lately,” adding that while a deal on DHS funding hasn’t yet been notched, “it doesn’t mean it won't be eventually.”</p> 
<p>Even before the shooting in Minnesota, lawmakers in both parties had <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/dhs-reprogramming-crackdown-00713569" target="_blank">agreed to new limits</a> on the Trump administration’s ability to redirect DHS money to purposes other than what Congress prescribes.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/177013" data-person-id="177013">Mark Amodei</a>, the Nevada Republican who chairs the Homeland Security funding panel, told reporters last week that House and Senate appropriators are crafting the spending measure to make it “harder to make the money mobile.”</p> 
<p>He called the Trump administration’s penchant for shifting around cash “bullshit” and acknowledged that Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem would not be fond of the new restrictions.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, Amodei struck an upbeat note on the negotiations, saying the DHS bill is “progressing nicely.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP tees up 2 amendment votes on latest funding package</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/amendment-votes-appropriations-funding-package-chip-roy-00726560</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b994-d65c-affb-bb9785570000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:10:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders are allowing floor votes this week on several proposed tweaks to the latest government funding package after hard-liners <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/appropriations-funding-bills-hardliners-chip-roy-00715032" target="_blank">demanded more input</a>. </p> 
<p>The House Rules Committee voted Tuesday to allow votes on two amendments to the package that would fund the departments of Treasury and State, as well as the IRS and the Federal Trade Commission. </p> 
<p>Texas Republican Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a>, a member of the panel, secured a vote on an amendment that would cut appeals court funding for the District of Columbia by 20 percent and eliminate the budgets of two judges. </p> 
<p>The panel’s top Democrat, Massachusetts Rep.<a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512"> Jim McGovern</a>, complained that the sponsors of that amendment didn’t even testify before the committee.</p> 
<p>“It seems like this process gets worse and worse and worse,” McGovern said. “Talk about revenge. I mean, we're going after judges and their staff. … This is not the way this place should be run.” </p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51389" data-person-id="51389">Virginia Foxx</a> (R-N.C), the panel’s chair, said House Republicans are ensuring the appropriations process is “member-driven and deliberate.”</p> 
<p>The House will also vote on an amendment from Rep.<a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/407516" data-person-id="407516"> Eli Crane</a> (R-Ariz.) that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-hardliners-amendment-vote-funding-national-endowment-democracy-00725512" target="_blank">bar funding for the National Endowment for Democracy</a>, an independent nonprofit that supports projects around the world with the stated goal of promoting democracy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers meet Danish officials to rebuke Trump’s Greenland grab</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/lawmakers-meet-danish-officials-rebuke-trump-greenland-00726166</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b941-da56-afff-bdd3f9ab0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 16:42:41 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Arctic Caucus co-Chairs <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine) will meet on Wednesday with Danish Ambassador Jesper Møller Sørensen to reaffirm their opposition to President Donald Trump’s effort to acquire Greenland.</p> 
<p>The closed-door meeting comes as Trump has floated the idea of obtaining Greenland “one way or another” — rhetoric that has drawn sharp rebukes from Copenhagen and Nuuk. The idea of taking over the Danish territory has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-lawmakers-denounce-trump-seize-greenland-00714611" target="_blank">met resistance from some senior Republicans</a> and outright opposition from Democrats.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she would support a war powers resolution to bar Trump from taking action to invade Greenland, if it were offered. A bipartisan group of House lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/house-lawmakers-introduce-bipartisan-nato-bill-00723206" target="_blank">has introduced like-minded legislation</a> that covers any NATO ally.</p> 
<p>“There’s been a lot of talk about that, which, in fairness, is crazy,” Murkowski said in an interview, referring to speculation that Congress could eventually invoke war powers authorities in connection with Greenland. “Who would have ever thought you would say the word Greenland in the same sentence as war powers resolution?”</p> 
<p>The new legislation comes as Hill Democrats search for ways to keep the Trump administration from taking further military action in Venezuela. The Senate is poised to vote this week on a war powers resolution tied to Venezuela, though its path in the House remains unclear.</p> 
<p>Trump administration officials, meanwhile, are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-greenland-military-force-00713315" target="_blank">openly discussing options</a> — including the use of force — to seize Greenland, a move that would trigger NATO’s mutual defense clause and risk shattering the alliance.</p> 
<p>“It’s easier,” <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/greenland-pm-wont-sell-country-jd-vance-meeting/" target="_blank">Trump said Sunday</a>, referring to buying the island. “But one way or the other, we’re going to have Greenland.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski said the goal of Wednesday’s meeting <b>—</b> with Møller Sørensen and other officials from Denmark and Greenland — is “a constructive dialogue” with Danish and Greenlandic officials and to underscore that Capitol Hill is not a bystander as Arctic tensions rise.</p> 
<p>“We here in this Congress actually have a role, have some input on whether or not it might be appropriate to take some of these actions that the president is suggesting,” she said.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she will travel to Copenhagen later this week with a small bipartisan bicameral group to reinforce congressional concerns directly with Danish leaders.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deepfake porn bill allowing victims to sue passes Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/deepfake-porn-bill-allowing-victims-to-sue-passes-senate-00725817</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b8e6-d65c-affb-bbe706610000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:49:28 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate passed legislation Tuesday to allow victims of nonconsensual deepfake pornography to sue the producers and distributors of such content.</p> 
<p>The proposal was put forward by Democratic Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/845fda6f-4459-46f0-a956-263e74780ae5" target="_blank">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.) on the Senate floor for unanimous consent, and is co-sponsored by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/aaf51c1d-d223-401e-8a6b-22ee557e6bdf" target="_blank">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.).</p> 
<p>It represents the latest in a line of congressional efforts to address harms caused by the distribution of nonconsensual deepfake imagery, including the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_146" target="_blank">TAKE IT DOWN Act</a>, which was championed by First Lady Melania Trump and was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/19/trump-signs-take-it-down-act-criminalizing-deepfake-and-revenge-porn-00357151" target="_blank">signed into law</a> last year by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>The bill, known as the Disrupt Explicit Forged Images and Non-Consensual Edits Act, or <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_118_S_3696" target="_blank">DEFIANCE Act</a>, cleared the Senate last Congress but failed to progress in the House. If it passes into law, the legislation would give victims the right to sue over deepfake pornography.</p> 
<p>Sen. Durbin highlighted the harm and profound consequences victims of such nonconsensual imagery suffer, and said he was proud to work with Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez on the issue, who has been a victim of explicit deepfakes.</p> 
<p>The number of nonconsensual deepfake porn videos available online has increased ninefold since 2019, according to <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-08-24/google-microsoft-tools-behind-surge-in-deepfake-ai-porn?embedded-checkout=true" target="_blank">one researcher</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP leaders throw cold water on Trump’s credit-card push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/trump-credit-cards-thune-johnson-00725061</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b855-da56-afff-bcd7550b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:11:06 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> voiced skepticism Tuesday on President Donald Trump’s move to temporarily cap credit card interest rates.</p> 
<p>“I think that would probably deprive an awful lot of people of access to credit around the country,” Thune told reporters. “Credit cards would probably become debit cards.”</p> 
<p>“That's not something I'm out there advocating for — let's put it that way,” he added.</p> 
<p>Thune’s comments come after Trump posted on Truth Social that he was calling for a one-year cap of 10 percent interest on credit cards starting Jan. 20.</p> 
<p>Johnson also appeared to tamp down the prospects for immediate action Tuesday, telling reporters he spoke to Trump about it on Monday. He called it among a "long list" of affordability ideas Trump has in mind.</p> 
<p>“The president is the ideas guy," Johnson said, adding later, "I wouldn't get too spun up about ideas that are out of the box, that are proposed or suggested."</p> 
<p>Johnson also raised similar concerns as Thune, saying credit-card issuers “would just stop lending money” if rates are capped.</p> 
<p>In addition to the proposed temporary cap on interest rates, Trump has also thrown his weight behind a long-controversial <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/02/congress/crypto-senate-genius-act-swipe-fees-00380677" target="_blank">bill limiting credit-card merchant fees</a> sponsored by Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259544" data-person-id="259544">Roger Marshall</a> (R-Kan.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.) that has been the subject of intense financial industry lobbying since its introduction in 2022.</p> 
<p>Republicans are on both sides of that bill, Thune noted, but he said he believed it would be up for a floor vote “at some point.”</p> 
<p>“That's what we do around here,” he said. “We cast hard votes.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Megabill 2.0? These House Republicans have some ideas.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/rsc-reconciliation-framework-megabill-00724594</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b814-d15b-abff-fc5ee0920000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:00:08 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A major House GOP faction unveiled its framework Tuesday for a new party-line Republican policy bill that aims to slash the costs of housing and health care.</p> 
<p>Among the <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/13NyKUdSH-uSrZi0YHkTZ3HO7J63Qv0R1" target="_blank">slew of proposals under the Republican Study Committee framework</a> is the “Don payment” — a program creating a new zero-to-low-down-payment option for mortgage shoppers. The plan would also create new tax-advantaged “health freedom accounts” that would allow Americans to directly receive federal subsidies for insurance.</p> 
<p>In addition, the plan suggests cutting energy costs by accelerating the permitting process and refilling the Department of Energy’s strategic oil reserve with “discounted Venezuelan oil.” Overall, the framework would include cuts of $1.6 trillion to government spending.</p> 
<p>“There’s three major things that I think are threatening the American dream right now: housing costs, health care costs and energy costs,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> (R-Texas), the RSC’s chair, at a Tuesday news conference. “We’ve got to get this done. We know we have a narrow window of time.”</p> 
<p>While the release of the framework signals buy-in from a large swath of House Republicans, a second massive party-line bill is sure to create further divisions within the GOP’s slim House majority. The chairs of critical House committees, including tax-writing chief <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> (R-Mo.), have expressed skepticism that there’s a path forward under the multistep budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>Vulnerable Republican moderates are especially wary of further changes to health policy as they maneuver to fight for their seats in November and defend against Democratic attacks on the Republicans’ steep cuts to Medicaid enacted last year.</p> 
<p>While Speaker Mike Johnson has not yet endorsed the RSC plan, he told reporters Monday that he hopes to do a narrower reconciliation bill in 2026 and that GOP leaders would work to build internal consensus around potential policies in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>Republicans’ House majority has dwindled in recent weeks with the retirement of Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and the death of Rep. Doug LaMalfa of California. Other members have been absent for health reasons, making the GOP’s control of the chamber especially tenuous.</p> 
<p>But Pfluger said, with the help of President Donald Trump, complete unity is within reach for the House GOP, and he called on the White House to get on board.</p> 
<p>“I hope that they take note of this plan,” he said. “When the president says, ‘Let’s go do this,’ I think … skepticism will fly out the window.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
