<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 20:45:55 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers seek to limit DHS power to shuffle cash in funding bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/dhs-reprogramming-crackdown-00713569</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9604-d651-a1ff-be6486900000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 20:45:55 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Top appropriators on Capitol Hill are seeking to tighten limits around how much money DHS can shift between accounts as they finalize funding bills ahead of the Jan. 30 shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/177013" data-person-id="177013">Mark Amodei</a>, the Nevada Republican who chairs the DHS funding panel, told reporters Tuesday night that House and Senate appropriators are crafting their spending measure to make it “harder to make the money mobile.” The effort comes as the Trump administration has spent the past year testing the limits of its power to disregard congressional intent and reprogram billions of dollars between accounts.</p> 
<p>“We did a bunch of reprogramming,” Amodei said of Republicans in the White House. “It’s like, hey, that's bullshit.”</p> 
<p>To limit the Trump administration’s ability to shift cash, appropriators plan to include tables within the bill that show exactly which accounts should be funded and lower the percentages of cash that can be used for other purposes, Amodei continued.</p> 
<p>Appropriators have briefed President Donald Trump’s budget office on the funding bill they hope to pass and have taken OMB’s input into account, Amodei said. Still, he acknowledged that some Trump administration officials, including Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem, will not be fond of new restrictions on moving around cash.</p> 
<p>“Now I know that the secretary doesn't like that,” Amodei said. “And it's like, well, we've all got our unlike departments. And so welcome to the club.”</p> 
<p>He also divulged that the funding bill will provide enough cash for DHS to keep 44,500 immigrants in detention facilities at any given time. Appropriators will be tracking detention capacity every month and expect the Trump administration to fill that “detention bed” capacity, he added.</p> 
<p>“They better, by God, be full,” said Amodei.</p> 
<p>Amodei is in the midst of final negotiations with senior Senate appropriators on the DHS funding bill. “We're real close,” he said. “We want to be able to publish the bill this week.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP-led Jan. 6 committee sets first hearing for next week</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/jan-6-hearing-scheduled-00713479</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-95d1-d78e-af9f-fdf749420000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 20:00:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The new Republican-led panel tasked with investigating the Jan. 6, 2021, Capitol attack will hold its first hearing next week, Rep. Barry Loudermilk said in an interview Tuesday — the five-year anniversary of the event.</p> 
<p>The Georgia Republican, who is the chair of the select subcommittee, said his panel was still ironing out its list of witnesses, but he anticipated the focus would be the pipe bombs left at the Democratic and Republican National Committee headquarters the day before the riots at the Capitol. </p> 
<p>“It’s gonna be sometime next week,” Loudermilk said. “We’re gonna be really looking at the pipe bomb and the FBI’s investigation — previous investigation. Why did it take five years?”</p> 
<p>News of the hearing that would look at the events of that day through the lens of security failures rather than attempts by President Donald Trump and his supporters to overturn the results of the 2020 election was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422" target="_blank">the culmination</a> of a daylong campaign from Republicans to offer an alternative memory of the Capitol attack. </p> 
<p>The White House published a website offering a largely false narrative of what unfolded at the Capitol five years ago — one that blamed then-Speaker Nancy Pelosi and forcefully denied Trump’s role in inciting the violence. Democrats and Republicans also fought over the fate of a commemorative plaque mandated by Congress to honor those who protected the Capitol on Jan. 6, with Speaker Mike Johnson maintaining the project was untenable.</p> 
<p>Loudermilk said he had not spoken to Johnson about the memorial tablet and hasn’t been following the controversy around it but suggested he wasn’t opposed to its display — something of a break with House GOP leadership have sought to either bury the matter or denigrate the effort.</p> 
<p>“I don’t have problem putting it up. I think you need to honor the police,” he said. “I mean, the rank and file police, they were just trying to do their job.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson: U.S. military action in Greenland ‘would not be appropriate’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/johnson-trump-greenland-military-force-00713476</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-95d1-d78e-af9f-fdf711160000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 19:39:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson Tuesday evening swatted down the idea of any U.S. military action to take over Greenland, just after the White House said President Donald Trump wanted to acquire the territory and would not take military action off the table.</p> 
<p>“No, I don't think that's appropriate,” Johnson told reporters Tuesday evening.</p> 
<p>White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-greenland-military-force-00713315" target="_blank">said in a statement Tuesday</a> that "utilizing the U.S. Military is always an option at the Commander in Chief’s disposal." </p> 
<p>The speaker, who said he hadn't seen the statement, appeared to not believe the White House would make such a comment. Johnson did say he believed “Greenland is viewed by a lot of people as something that would be a strategic positioning for the U.S." </p> 
<p>Johnson said the issue didn't come up in conversations with Trump earlier Tuesday at the House GOP retreat. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Jan. 6 was remembered — and rewritten — on its 5th anniversary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422</link>
      <description>At a march and a hearing, on a plaque and a website, the story of the Capitol riot was contested Tuesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-95a5-df0c-a5bb-b5f718560000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:51:35 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a2/cd/2c8cd8584d6f90726e7413ba7fc2/capitol-riot-anniversary-77658.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP Photo/Jose Luis Magana</media:credit>
        <media:title>Demonstrators march on Constitution Avenue in Washington as they rally during the Jan. 6 anniversary Tuesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a2/cd/2c8cd8584d6f90726e7413ba7fc2/capitol-riot-anniversary-77658.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu, Kyle Cheney and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu, Kyle Cheney and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Five years ago, Ryan Samsel <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/02/02/ryan-samsel-jan-6-defendant-00139344" target="_blank">ignited the Jan. 6 breach</a> of the Capitol grounds when he charged through a police barricade, injuring a police officer in the process.</p> 
<p>Samsel returned to the site Tuesday, part of a group of fellow mob members who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/03/07/proud-boys-march-toward-capitol-00085975" target="_blank">retraced the route</a> Trump supporters took from the Ellipse to the foot of the Capitol in 2021. They marched to celebrate their blanket pardon by President Donald Trump and attempt to reclaim Jan. 6 as a date of triumph, not tragedy.</p> 
<p>The march was the backdrop to a day marked by partisan sparring over a missing plaque and an endorsement by the White House of a torrent of conspiracy theories and lies about the attack and Trump’s pressure campaign to subvert the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>A new White House website, with ominous black-and-white images of former Speaker Nancy Pelosi and members of the Jan. 6 select committee, offered an alternate and largely false narrative of events at the Capitol that day — one that forcefully denied Trump’s role in stoking the riot and labeled those who stormed the Capitol “patriotic Americans.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Speaker Mike Johnson eschewed calls to mount a bronze marker legally mandated by Congress that would serve to honor those who protected the Capitol from the worst attack it had seen since the war of 1812.</p> 
<p>“He's trying to cover up for the fact that Republicans continue to disrespect those brave men and women of the Capitol Police department who defended our country on Jan. 6,” House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries said in a brief interview.</p> 
<p>Democrats held a mock hearing to mark the anniversary of the event featuring firsthand witnesses to the violence that day. Their testimony underscored the increasingly diverging narratives that continue to define the historic attack.</p> 
<p>Outside the Capitol, the former Jan. 6 defendants rallied without support from sitting lawmakers. Their most vocal champion, Georgia Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene, had resigned from Congress a day earlier. She was mentioned regretfully by some members of the crowd who soured on her after she began openly feuding with Trump last year.</p> 
<p>Democratic Rep. Tom Suozzi of New York exchanged tense words with Jake Lang — who was pardoned of numerous assault charges against police on Jan. 6 — from behind a line of officers as he walked past the participants as they prepared to lay flowers on the Capitol steps.</p> 
<p>Members of the march chanted, “Whose house? Our house!” — an echo of the rally cries from five years earlier. Mikki Witthoeft, the mother of Ashli Babbitt — the woman who was shot and killed by a Capitol Police officer outside the House chamber — described Jan. 6 as the day Congress “let the American people down.”</p> 
<p>Inside the Capitol, the missing plaque became a stand-in for the swirling controversy about how the infamous day will be remembered.</p> 
<p>Johnson said in a Monday statement that the plaque, which was authorized by a law passed in March 2022, was “not implementable" and that Democratic-led proposals for it were also not an option.</p> 
<p>That echoes arguments made by the Justice Department, which is trying to dismiss a federal lawsuit filed by two Capitol Police officers seeking to compel the plaque’s mounting.</p> 
<p>The law authorizing the marker requires it to list the names of all law enforcement officers who participated in the defense of the Capitol. DOJ lawyers argue in <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540.27.0_2.pdf" target="_blank">court filings</a> that the plaque that has been made does not comply with the law because it lists the departments who responded — not the individual officers. A deputy to the Architect of the Capitol said in a <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540/gov.uscourts.dcd.281540.27.2.pdf" target="_blank">separate court declaration</a> that a plaque listing the officers’ names has not been made.</p> 
<p>Rep. Zoe Lofgren (D-Calif.) called Johnson’s claim that the plaque does not comply with the law “ridiculous, and so is he.” Many Hill Democrats have placed <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/23/congress/democrats-replica-jan-6-plaques-00418859" target="_blank">replicas of the plaque</a> outside their offices as Johnson refuses to mount the genuine article.</p> 
<p>In one effort to resolve the issue, Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said Tuesday he would seek to change the law to accommodate the existing plaque, but it was not immediately clear if he would be able to garner the unanimous support necessary to quickly act.</p> 
<p>Testifying at the Democratic shadow hearing, former Rep. Adam Kinzinger — who served as a Republican on the House’s previous Jan. 6 panel — said he was “convinced” the plaque would be put on display by next January, when the next Congress begins.</p> 
<p>“I’ll humbly suggest maybe you can double the size of it by then,” he said.</p> 
<p>The Democrats’ event was held in the basement after the speaker’s office declined to allow them to use a dedicated hearing room or the larger auditorium in the Capitol Visitor Center, according to a person granted anonymity because they were not authorized to comment publicly. Johnson’s office did not respond to a request for comment on the claim.</p> 
<p>No sitting House Republicans attended. They spent their day across town holding a policy retreat at the Kennedy Center, where Trump addressed them and brought up the events of Jan. 6 without prompting. He complained that the media failed to report how he told people to march "peacefully and patriotically" to the Capitol that day and renewed old gripes against Pelosi, whom he blamed for rejecting National Guard troops to guard the Capitol — even though only Trump could call up the Guard.</p> 
<p>The new White House website also accuses Pelosi and members of the Jan. 6 select committee of maneuvering to unfairly blame Trump for the riot. Not mentioned are any of the many comments critical of Trump from inside the GOP at the time nor the 10 House and seven Senate Republicans who voted against him in subsequent impeachment proceedings.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune sidestepped a question Tuesday about the website’s claim that Capitol Police helped instigate the riot. He told reporters he hadn’t seen the site and offered general praise for the force.</p> 
<p>The history of Jan. 6 will remain a live issue on Capitol Hill for the remainder of the current Congress, with a new Republican-led panel investigating the attack and the work of the prior Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee.</p> 
<p>Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Texas), who serves on the new panel, attacked those on the Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee for seeking to malign Trump.</p> 
<p>“Their Select Committee wasn’t about transparency or the truth; it was political theatre,” he said in a statement. “My colleagues and I are focused on uncovering the truth and following the facts wherever they lead.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The House GOP confronts a shocking loss and a difficult road ahead</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/house-republicans-anxiety-margins-midterms-00713358</link>
      <description>Members who gathered for a pre-midterm policy retreat were stunned by the death of longtime colleague Doug LaMalfa.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-958c-df0c-a5bb-b5dfea110000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 18:05:36 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5c/35/9a970eca401a8c9836bc2fc203e5/trump-32522.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Evan Vucci/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Speaker Mike Johnson attends a GOP policy retreat in Washington, on Jan. 6, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5c/35/9a970eca401a8c9836bc2fc203e5/trump-32522.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tuesday was supposed to be a rah-rah day for House Republicans — a chance to strategize with President Donald Trump about their agenda for the tough election year ahead.</p> 
<p>Instead, 2026 got off to an unexpectedly somber start as they confronted the sudden death of a well-liked colleague and pondered the dire political and policy straits their dwindling majority has to navigate.</p> 
<p>Most members learned about <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">California Rep. Doug LaMalfa’s overnight passing</a> as they boarded buses outside the Capitol to head to the Kennedy Center for their annual policy meeting. That news — as well as word that another Republican, Rep. Jim Baird of Indiana, had been <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/jim-baird-hospitalized-00712230" target="_blank">badly hurt in a car crash</a> — cast an immediate pall.</p> 
<p>“This is coming as a shock to all of us,” said one House Republican who, like others quoted for this story, was granted anonymity to speak candidly about the mood.</p> 
<p>Even a characteristically freewheeling speech from Trump — delivered at the performing arts center his hand-picked board had recently renamed for him without congressional approval — hardly lightened the mood. He remembered LaMalfa, a rice farmer who represented a rural northern California district for seven terms, as a loyal supporter and said he considered skipping the speech out of respect for his death.</p> 
<p>"But then I decided that I have to do it in his honor,” Trump said. “I'll do it in his honor because he would have wanted it that way.”</p> 
<p>But reality soon set in that the House GOP would be facing challenges that went well beyond mourning. For one, LaMalfa’s death and Baird’s hospitalization represented another blow to their razor-thin majority, leaving many contemplating whether Republicans could ever muster the votes they would need to pass a laundry list of pre-midterm policy priorities.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa’s death and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/21/marjorie-taylor-greene-resigns-from-congress-after-clash-with-trump-00665972" target="_blank">Georgia Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene’s resignation</a> this week left the GOP with a bare 218 votes for at least until early March. With Baird’s indefinite absence and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/thomas-massie-trump-jeffrey-epstein-00654214" target="_blank">unreliable support</a> of libertarian Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), Speaker Mike Johnson has to confront a day-to-day struggle to maintain control of the House.</p> 
<p>His leadership circle, for instance, quickly had to calculate whether they would have enough Republicans in attendance to clear a procedural vote Wednesday allowing them to pass on a critical government funding package and several other bills this week.</p> 
<p>“We keep saying we are one breath away from the minority — that’s more true today than ever,” another House Republican said.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-health-abortion-restrictions-hyde-00712507" target="_blank">Trump’s 84-minute speech</a> ultimately veered into myriad topics. He at one point commented on his own mortality and pushed back on reports about his aging and declining health, admonishing some Republicans in attendance for calling to check if he was “dead” last year after he was away from cameras for several days.</p> 
<p>He also raised concerns about keeping the House majority next year — a topic that lawmakers and White House aides say is frequently on the president’s mind.</p> 
<p>"They say that when you win the presidency, you lose the midterm,” Trump said. “So you're all brilliant people: I wish you could explain to me what the hell's going on with the mind of the public, because we have the right policy.”</p> 
<p>He then proceeded to throw a bomb into those policy plans as Republicans struggle to address rising health care costs — a topic that’s become an albatross for the party after a bitter December fight over extending Obamacare tax credits that have now expired, raising premiums for millions of Americans.</p> 
<p>The president directed Republicans to be “flexible” on abortion issues in ongoing health care talks — essentially asking many in his party to cross a moral red line by abandoning the longstanding ban on taxpayer funding for abortion known as the Hyde amendment.</p> 
<p>The remark <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/conservatives-anti-abortion-trump-health-care-gop-00712565" target="_blank">stunned House conservatives</a> in the audience and those listening in the Senate.</p> 
<p>“I almost fell out of my chair,” said one who attended the meeting.</p> 
<p>“Everything depends on details, but Hyde is nonnegotiable for most conservatives,” added a senior House Republican aide. That person didn’t rule out a potential “creative solution” on the matter but said “caving on Hyde is not an option.”</p> 
<p>Asked for his reaction on Capitol Hill, Sen. James Lankford (R-Okla.) said, “I’m not flexible on the value of every child’s life.” Others took it as an encouraging sign that Trump wants to notch a deal this month on an especially nettlesome election year issue.</p> 
<p>But inside the House GOP policy sessions that followed the Trump speech Tuesday — touching on energy, housing and other issues — members continued to struggle with the way forward on their health care plans, according to six Republicans with direct knowledge of the conversations.</p> 
<p>Many hard-line conservatives — who see abortion protections as an essential element in any health care legislation — would prefer Republican leaders pursue a party-line bill under filibuster-skirting budget reconciliation rules rather than cut a deal with Democrats.</p> 
<p>Otherwise, according to two people with knowledge of the retreat discussions, key lawmakers ran through a well-known menu of legislative options — albeit one that is unlikely to offset the impact of the expired Obamacare subsidies before Election Day.</p> 
<p>House Ways and Means Chair Jason Smith (R-Mo.) discussed proposals to expand tax-advantaged health savings accounts, while Energy and Commerce Chair Brett Guthrie (R-Ky.) talked through potential overhauls to a key prescription drug program and bills that would crack down on intermediaries known as pharmacy benefit managers.</p> 
<p>Trump directed House Republicans in his earlier remarks to work on so-called <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/prescription-pulse/2025/05/02/trumps-most-favored-way-to-cut-drug-costs-returns-00321936" target="_blank">“most favored nation” drug pricing legislation</a> — something he’s pursued in executive orders and deals with health care giants as he moves to lower the cost of prescription drugs.</p> 
<p>But the issue is deeply divisive among Hill Republicans, and GOP leaders have continued to rebuff Trump’s attempts to attach it to numerous legislative vehicles — including the sprawling megabill Republicans passed this summer.</p> 
<p>Senior GOP aides on Capitol Hill say they have plans to address drug prices via HSAs and other policies, but they are leaving it to the White House to promote the most-favored-nation and other direct drug pricing plans.</p> 
<p>That, Trump said — along with being “flexible” on Hyde and “directly” giving Americans money to purchase coverage — would allow Republicans to “take away” the issue of health care from Democrats, Trump asserted at the House GOP meeting.</p> 
<p>"You could own health care, figure it out!” Trump said.</p> 
<p>But House Republicans privately acknowledged throughout the day Tuesday it’s far from that easy.</p> 
<p>"We're still far from a solution on health care,” one GOP lawmaker said.</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T16:50:24-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Thune outlines 3 pieces of possible health care deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/thune-outlines-three-pieces-of-possible-health-care-deal-00713102</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9525-d78e-af9f-fd77f5f70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 16:12:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> laid out Tuesday the three components any bipartisan health deal would have to address in order for it to pass the Senate.</p> 
<p>That includes instituting minimum premium payments and other new restrictions, providing “a bridge to HSAs” including an expansion of the health savings accounts and dealing with the “Hyde issue” — language that limits federal funding for abortions. All three of the ideas are Republican priorities.</p> 
<p>“Those are kind of the ‘big three’ when it comes to something that could get through the Senate,” Thune told reporters of what it would take to land a "healthy majority” in support of any health care deal.</p> 
<p>"We want to ensure that if we do anything it's done in a way that reforms these programs and ... ensures that those dollars aren't being used to go against the practice that's been in place for the last 50 years around here when it comes to taxpayer dollars being used to finance abortions and that it also has this movement in the future toward HSAs," he continued. </p> 
<p>A bipartisan group of senators is currently negotiating a possible agreement that would merge a two-year extension of the lapsed Affordable Care Act credits with new minimum premium payments and income restrictions, alongside broader cost-sharing reductions that would be phased in during the second year. The lapse of the beefed-up ACA subsidies reset the tax credits to their original 2010 Obamacare levels.</p> 
<p>The lawmakers met Monday night and they said they are making progress — but they don't yet have a deal.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> (R-Ohio), one of the key negotiators, updated Thune Tuesday morning. Thune also met earlier Tuesday with Senate Finance Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51173" data-person-id="51173">Mike Crapo</a> (R-Idaho) and Senate Health Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> (R-La.), who co-led the GOP proposal to expand health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>Cassidy said Tuesday he continued to work on the health savings accounts component, adding, “We’re gonna need the White House support to get something done.”</p> 
<p><i>Cheyenne Haslett contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T13:32:09-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Kemp sets date for special election to fill Greene’s seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/georgia-14-special-election-marjorie-taylor-greene-00712603</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-947a-dba9-addb-b7ffd31b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:15:06 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The race to replace Marjorie Taylor Greene in Congress is on.</p> 
<p>Georgia Gov. Brian Kemp authorized a special election to select a candidate to fill the remainder of the former MAGA acolyte’s term following her official resignation from the House late Monday night. Kemp’s office <a href="https://gov.georgia.gov/executive-action/executive-orders/2026" target="_blank">posted the signed writ of election</a> to his office’s website, setting the contest for March 10.</p> 
<p>Nearly two dozen candidates are already looking to run for the vacated northwest Georgia seat according to Federal Elections Commission filings — and almost all are Republicans hoping to represent the deeply conservative district.</p> 
<p>The race sets up as a potential test of what kind of candidate Republicans prefer in the deep-red district, following Greene’s controversial tenure in Congress.</p> 
<p>Republicans already in the race include District Attorney Clayton Fuller of the Lookout Mountain Judicial Circuit, state Sen. Colton Moore, and businessperson and former Paulding County Commissioner Brian Stover.</p> 
<p>Only two Democrats have entered the race so far: Greene’s unsuccessful 2024 challenger Shawn Harris, and Clarence Blalock, who had previously been running for state Labor Commissioner.</p> 
<p>House Republicans will be glad to have the seat filled: Greene’s resignation and the Monday death of Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.) means they have just a five-seat majority.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misnamed the California Representative who died Monday. It was Rep. Doug LaMalfa. An earlier version of this report also misspelled the county where Brian Stover was a commissioner.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Greenland war powers vote could be heading to Senate floor</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/greenland-war-powers-gallego-00712605</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9481-dba9-addb-b7bf49b50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:12:29 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189136" data-person-id="189136">Ruben Gallego</a> wants Congress to forestall a U.S. takeover of Greenland, requiring President Donald Trump to get lawmakers’ approval for any such action after this weekend’s military incursion into Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Gallego said he will introduce a war powers resolution focused on Greenland, an semiautonomous territory of Denmark that Trump has repeatedly suggested should be part of the U.S. instead.</p> 
<p>“We must stop him before he invades another country on a whim,” Gallego wrote on social media. “No more forever wars.”</p> 
<p>War powers resolutions are privileged under Senate rules, meaning Gallego and others can force the chamber to weigh in on the issue. Democrats have previously forced votes to rein in Trump’s strikes against suspected drug smuggling boats and on attacking Venezuela, though both efforts failed.</p> 
<p>Greenland could be different, however, given that it is territory belonging to a NATO ally. Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> is downplaying the chances of military action in Greenland, and other Republicans have ridiculed the idea of a hostile takeover.</p> 
<p>"That to me is not something anybody is contemplating seriously,” Thune said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>But Democrats are eager to put them on the record, with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.) hinting at many more attempts to rein in Trump.</p> 
<p>“He has repeatedly raised Greenland, Cuba, Mexico, Colombia. He's waged military action within Nigeria,” Kaine said. “So I think members of the Senate should go on the record about all of it.”</p> 
<p>The Senate is expected to vote Thursday on a bipartisan resolution to require congressional approval before Trump takes additional military action in Venezuela. But a similar push previously failed and Thune on Tuesday said he was “optimistic” it would fail again.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine), who opposed a previous Venezuela-focused measure, said she remained undecided but wanted the administration to further explain its strategy.</p> 
<p>“I don't understand what the president means when he says we will 'run' Venezuela,” she said. “The Venezuelans ought to run for Venezuela.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeSantis: Florida should require congressional candidates to answer about stock trades</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/desantis-florida-should-require-congressional-candidates-to-answer-about-stock-trades-00712308</link>
      <description>During his press conference, DeSantis called individual stock trading a “bipartisan ailment,” adding, “We need to clean both houses up there.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-943c-df0c-a5bb-b47f94010000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 12:15:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e0/f46abfb541e1bc13d70a2900721c/florida-budget-65894.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Chris O'Meara/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis speaks during a news conference.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e0/f46abfb541e1bc13d70a2900721c/florida-budget-65894.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gary Fineout</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gary Fineout</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>TALLAHASSEE, Florida — Gov. Ron DeSantis wants the state to take steps to discourage members of Congress from trading stocks, a topic that has seemingly divided Florida’s Hill delegation ahead of a potential vote in the House.</p> 
<p>DeSantis, during an event in Clearwater with GOP Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a>, gave his full backing to Luna’s proposed ban on individual stock trading for members. But he also said he is seeking state legislation to require people running for Congress in Florida to disclose ahead of time whether they intend to trade stocks if they are elected.</p> 
<p>During his press conference, DeSantis called individual stock trading a “bipartisan ailment,” adding, “We need to clean both houses up there.” He said members have either gotten windfalls — or avoided major losses — that defy normal investment patterns.</p> 
<p>In a social media post, <a href="https://x.com/RonDeSantis/status/2008555410584641803?s=20" target="_blank">he added that</a> “it is a farce how some members of Congress — including but not limited to Nancy Pelosi — suddenly become Warren Buffet on steroids when it comes to investment returns.”</p> 
<p>DeSantis acknowledged the state has limited authority to place restrictions on Florida’s congressional delegation. But he wants to require candidates to answer a question about stock trading on forms that are submitted at the time they qualify for the ballot. </p> 
<p>He said that would at least let voters know ahead of time what plan they to do. The governor added that such a requirement wouldn't really work for state legislators because they are only on the job part-time and many work in the financial sector.</p> 
<p>DeSantis also called on Florida’s congressional delegation to vote for Luna’s bill. <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/florida-playbook/2025/12/18/taking-stock-of-the-trading-ban-00697187#:~:text=Most%20of%20Florida's%20delegation%20didn,was%20by%20his%20adult%20son." target="_blank">Several Florida members signed on to a discharge petition</a>, but it’s not clear if all 28 will ultimately support the legislation.</p> 
<p>Luna said she’s spoken to House Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and she anticipates that her bill will be taken up during the first three months of the year.</p> 
<p>“It’s wrong and it needs to stop,” Luna said about individual stock trading.</p> 
<p>DeSantis’ support for the measure is not a surprise given his ongoing criticism of Congress. He has also advocated for congressional term limits.</p> 
<p>The governor made his stance amid the backdrop of 2026 elections, where the Republican front-runner for governor, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260201" data-person-id="260201">Byron Donalds</a>, has been dinged over his stock trading. Donalds <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/florida-playbook/2025/12/18/taking-stock-of-the-trading-ban-00697187#:~:text=Most%20of%20Florida's%20delegation%20didn,was%20by%20his%20adult%20son." target="_blank">has said previously that he relies on a financial adviser managing his IRA without his input</a> and that brokers who work for congressional clients should be required to publicly submit notes that would show whether members are directing trades.</p> 
<p>Donalds has been hit with ethics complaints alleging that he failed to disclose more than 100 stock trades in a timely fashion as required by federal law. He said <a href="https://donalds.house.gov/news/documentsingle.aspx?DocumentID=2423" target="_blank">during a radio interview in December</a> that he would vote for Luna’s bill, even though he wants a carve-out to allow stock trades if it is done by a broker on behalf of a member.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T11:45:49-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Indiana congressman Jim Baird and wife hospitalized after car crash</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/jim-baird-hospitalized-00712230</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-93e2-d651-a1ff-bfe2e62c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 10:32:33 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Indiana Rep. Jim Baird and his wife are being hospitalized following a serious car crash, President Donald Trump confirmed in televised comments to House Republicans on Monday. </p> 
<p>"They're going to be OK, but they had a pretty bad accident," Trump said at the top of his address to a House GOP legislative retreat, where he also paid tribute to the late California Rep. Doug LaMalfa following <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">his sudden death Monday</a>.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson also addressed LaMalfa's death and Baird's hospitalization before Trump spoke, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the closed-door comments. Johnson said he believed Baird was dealing with a spinal issue.</p> 
<p>Baird's office said in a statement that "his vehicle was struck in an accident."</p> 
<p>“Congressman Baird is in the hospital and is expected to make a full recovery, and he is extraordinarily grateful for everyone’s prayers during this time," the statement read.</p> 
<p>It is not clear when or where the crash involving Baird, 80, took place. Another Indiana Republican, Rep. Jackie Walorski, was killed in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/03/indiana-gop-rep-walorski-three-others-die-in-auto-accident-00049665" target="_blank">2022 auto collision</a> that also claimed the lives of two congressional aides and another driver.</p> 
<p>House Republicans are already dealing with a tight 218-213 margin following LaMalfa's death. Baird's hospitalization could further complicate Johnson's ability to wrangle his majority in the coming weeks — effectively leaving him with a two-vote margin.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misstated which day Trump spoke to House Republicans. It was Tuesday.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-06T11:01:47-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>GOP lawmaker Doug LaMalfa dies at 65</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222</link>
      <description>The Republican represented a rural northern California district.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-93b6-df0c-a5bb-b7f777590000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 09:35:05 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/36/a2/5ae1ba9643b49f079d8b7afa464a/house-republicans-press-conference-on-agriculture-and-food-production-93648.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.) speaks during a press conference on agriculture and food production on Capitol Hill June 15, 2022.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/36/a2/5ae1ba9643b49f079d8b7afa464a/house-republicans-press-conference-on-agriculture-and-food-production-93648.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jeremy B. White</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jeremy B. White</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Doug LaMalfa, a California Republican known for his expertise on water and forestry issues, has died at 65, according to statements from GOP officials.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa, a fourth-generation rice farmer and former state legislator, was serving his seventh term representing a rural district in the northeast corner of the state. He sat on the Agriculture, Natural Resources, and Transportation and Infrastructure committees.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump paid tribute to LaMalfa during a speech to House Republicans Tuesday as a reliable vote for his agenda.</p> 
<p><br>"And by the way, he wasn't a three-o'clock-in-the-morning person," Trump said, referring to GOP lawmakers who need presidential cajoling on critical votes. "With Doug, I never had to call. He was with us right from the beginning."</p> 
<p><br>His office said in a statement that LaMalfa is survived by his wife, Jill, four children and a grandchild. He "cared deeply for the people he served and worked tirelessly to hold the government to its word to fix our failing forests, build water storage, and leave people to be free to choose what is best for themselves," the statement said.</p> 
<p>Republicans who were close with LaMalfa were not aware of any health issues he had, and many were in shock Tuesday morning about his sudden passing, according to six GOP lawmakers who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss private matters.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa suffered an aneurysm and then a heart attack after being taken into surgery, according to one of the lawmakers and two others familiar with the matter.</p> 
<p>His death also further narrows an already slim Republican majority in the House. Now with a 218-213 advantage, Speaker Mike Johnson can afford no more than two defections on party-line votes where all members are present and voting.</p> 
<p>"We are mourning the loss of our friend and brother today and we send our respects for his life and work to his wife Jill and the LaMalfa family during this difficult time,” Johnson said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Rep. Richard Hudson (R-N.C.), chair of the House GOP campaign arm, remembered LaMalfa as a “real gearhead and motorsports fan" as well as a "principled conservative and a tireless advocate for the people of Northern California." </p> 
<p>"Doug brought grit, authenticity, and conviction to everything he did in public service," Hudson said.</p> 
<p>Under California law, Gov. Gavin Newsom has 14 days to set a date for a special election. He could set the date as soon as mid-May, though he could also schedule it to coincide with the state's June 2 primary. The winner would serve out LaMalfa's term under current district lines.</p> 
<p>His successor, however, will face a wildly different political landscape in the November election. LaMalfa's seat was among those targeted by California Democrats in their bid to redraw district lines to counter President Donald Trump's mid-decade redistricting push in Texas and other states. </p> 
<p>In November, California voters approved a gerrymandered House map that folded LaMalfa’s turf into a new, blue-leaning district — threatening to push him into a competitive race after years of cruising to reelection in a largely Republican district. He was up against a Democratic former state Senate leader who had already piled up money and endorsements.</p> 
<p>LaMalfa decried the gerrymander as anti-democratic even as he vowed to press ahead with meeting new constituents and holding onto office.</p> 
<p>“We've had a long-term relationship with people in northern California, and we’re not just going to walk away from that,” <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/california-gop-confronts-bleak-map-and-its-own-civil-war-00679331" target="_blank">LaMalfa told POLITICO</a> last month.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump huddles with House GOP</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/trump-house-gop-retreat-venezuela-briefing-00712179</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-91c1-df0c-a5bb-b5d7b9c10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans will hear directly from President Donald Trump on Tuesday for the first time since the administration’s extraordinary capture of Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>A wider group of lawmakers who want answers on the operation will have to wait till Wednesday, when all House and Senate members are expected to get briefed by administration officials. So far, both Democrats and Republicans are grumbling about the lack of details from the White House on what’s next for Venezuela.</p> 
<p><b>— Where things stand:</b> Speaker Mike Johnson emerged from a leadership briefing Monday night and said he does not believe the U.S. will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/venezuela-maduro-congress-briefing-mike-johnson-00712155" target="_blank">send troops to Venezuela</a>. And he played down concerns that Trump and his deputies reneged on pledges not to pursue regime change in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>“This is not a regime change,” Johnson said. “This is a demand for change of behavior by a regime.”</p> 
<p>But other Republicans struck a more skeptical note. “I think what the president was trying to communicate is hopefully facilitating a peaceful transition of power,” said Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), who was not at the briefing. “I don’t know how you do that without boots on the ground. And I don’t support boots on the ground.”</p> 
<p>The Senate is on track to take up a bipartisan war powers resolution Thursday aimed at constraining future Venezuela strikes. But don’t expect this attempt to succeed where prior ones have failed.</p> 
<p>Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.), who entertained supporting past resolutions, said he would not vote for the measure “at this time.”</p> 
<p><b>— Trump's turn to talk:&nbsp;</b>The president’s address to House Republicans Tuesday morning during their closed-door retreat at the Kennedy Center is expected to focus on touting GOP wins and rallying Republicans ahead of the midterms — not Venezuela.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders plan to discuss their 2026 legislative agenda with the rank-and-file. That includes whether Republicans will tackle another reconciliation bill and how to deal with health care and affordability issues.</p> 
<p>House Freedom Caucus members sent Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-9121-d78e-af9f-fd77beaf0000" target="_blank">a letter</a> Monday outlining policies they want to see accomplished in 2026, including reducing discretionary spending, codifying Trump’s border actions and preventing the Federal Reserve from issuing a digital currency.</p> 
<p><b>— What Democrats are doing:</b> Democrats are mulling options to force Venezuela-related votes, including during Tuesday's Rules Committee hearing. Democrats expect Reps. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) and Joaquin Castro (D-Texas) to reintroduce their own war powers resolution. And they are looking to keep the events of Jan. 6, 2021, in the spotlight on the five-year anniversary.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Jan. 6 anniversary split screen: </b>Johnson broke his silence Monday on the long-running saga of the missing plaque honoring the police who defended the Capitol during the Jan. 6, 2021, attack. His office made clear the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/23/congress/democrats-replica-jan-6-plaques-00418859" target="_blank">plaque now sitting in storage</a> won’t be hung on Johnson’s watch. The speaker’s comments come as House Democrats push to keep the attack in the public eye five years later. They are teeing up a Tuesday 10 a.m. presentation where they’re set to hear from former law enforcement officials, state officials, former members of the Democratic-led select panel and more.</p> 
<p><b>— Appropriations moves: </b>House and Senate GOP leaders are hoping to move a second funding package before the end-of-the-month shutdown deadline, according to four people granted anonymity to discuss the private strategy. That would be in addition to the three-bill package of Commerce-Justice-Science, Energy-Water and Interior-Environment, which the House will vote on this week and the Senate could take up as early as next week.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Don’t expect troops on the ground,’ Johnson says after Venezuela briefing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/venezuela-maduro-congress-briefing-mike-johnson-00712155</link>
      <description>Top Trump officials conducted a two-hour session with senior lawmakers — many of whom want more answers about what lies ahead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9125-dba9-addb-b3bfcb730000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 21:34:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d8/9e/2d56a47d4402939cbd12104a7166/u-s-congress-60959.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson speaks with reporters after a briefing with Trump administration officials on Capitol Hill Jan. 5, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d8/9e/2d56a47d4402939cbd12104a7166/u-s-congress-60959.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Connor O'Brien and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Connor O'Brien and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>U.S. troops will have a limited role in Venezuela, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said Monday, after top deputies to President Donald Trump briefed senior congressional leaders on the weekend operation that removed leader Nicolas Maduro from power.</p> 
<p>“We don’t expect troops on the ground,” Johnson told reporters after the two-hour evening briefing on Capitol Hill. “We don't expect direct involvement in any other way beyond just coercing the … the interim government to get that going. I expect that there will be an election called in Venezuela. … It should happen in short order.”</p> 
<p>The closed-door session was the first time top Trump administration officials briefed a group of lawmakers in person since the surprise Saturday morning raid that resulted in the capture of Maduro and his wife. Both pleaded not guilty Monday to drug trafficking and other charges in a federal courtroom in Manhattan.</p> 
<p>Hours later, Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth, Attorney General Pam Bondi, CIA Director John Ratcliffe and Joint Chiefs of Staff Chair Dan Caine met with top party leaders, as well as the bipartisan leaders of the Foreign Affairs, Foreign Relations, Armed Services and Intelligence committees.</p> 
<p>So far, the response to the administration’s actions in Venezuela has largely split along party lines. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> told reporters after the meeting that the briefing was “extensive” but it raised “far more questions than it answered.”</p> 
<p>“Their plan for the U.S. running Venezuela is vague … based on wishful thinking and unsatisfying,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Schumer added that he asked for “assurances that we would not try to do the same thing in other countries” but didn’t receive any.</p> 
<p>Johnson, meanwhile, sought to play down the broader implications of the military raid — and tamp down criticism that Trump and his deputies reneged on pledges not to pursue regime change in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>“The way this is being described — this is not a regime change,” Johnson said. “This is a demand for change of behavior by a regime.”</p> 
<p>The administration will brief all House members Wednesday, Johnson added. The Senate is also expected to get a briefing for all of its members that day, though that hasn’t been finalized.</p> 
<p>In addition to the operation over the weekend, administration officials and lawmakers in the room discussed explosions in Caracas that reportedly took place as the briefing unfolded, according to two people with knowledge of the briefing.</p> 
<p>A White House official granted anonymity to comment on the developing situation said the administration is closely tracking the reports of gunfire in Venezuela and that the U.S. is not involved.</p> 
<p>House Foreign Affairs Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259496" data-person-id="259496">Brian Mast</a> (R-Fla.), asked about the explosions, said in an interview that the briefers discussed everything “before, during and after” the U.S. operation. He later added, “I think it would be unreasonable to think there aren't disruptors there,” referencing the governments of Iran, China and Russia.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), the top Democrat on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, said she had some of her questions answered but added that “there are a significant number of questions that still need to be answered.”</p> 
<p>Asked if she believed that the Trump administration is considering similar actions in other countries, she said, “I don't think that's clear.”</p> 
<p>The top Democrat on the House Foreign Affairs Committee, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51521" data-person-id="51521">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.), voiced concerns about the Trump administration's plans for Venezuela following Maduro's ouster.</p> 
<p>"The military did its job. It had a plan," Meeks told reporters. "I don't like the orders that they were given. But I can't say the same for the plan after."</p> 
<p>But Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51675" data-person-id="51675">Roger Wicker</a> (R-Miss.), chair of the Senate Armed Services Committee, said “we have a lot of professionals running this, and I have confidence.”</p> 
<p>Some Republicans said they want more clarity from the administration on its ultimate endgame.</p> 
<p>“I've got to see what strategy there is,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.), who did not attend the briefing. “What the president was trying to communicate is hopefully facilitating a peaceful transition of power. We'll have to wait and see. I don't know how you do that without boots on the ground. And I don't support boots on the ground.”</p> 
<p>Other lawmakers grumbled not about the overall strategy but about the administration’s decision to brief lawmakers piecemeal instead of all at once. The Republican chair and ranking Democrat on the Senate Judiciary Committee, which has jurisdiction over the DOJ and FBI, jointly fumed about being cut out of the initial briefing despite administration officials describing Maduro’s capture as a law enforcement operation.</p> 
<p>“This business of coming over and just talking to some of us, I think is a special kind of stupid,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.) said in an interview Monday. “They need to sit down with every member of the Senate and explain what’s going on.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Daniella Cheslow contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ethics watchdog outlines allegations against Georgia Republican's chief of staff</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/new-ethics-allegations-00711424</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8fcf-df0c-a5bb-bfdfc1d70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 15:28:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A nonpartisan Congressional watchdog is alleging that Brandon Phillips, who has served as Rep. Mike Collins’ chief of staff, hired a romantic interest as an office intern and illicitly used his office’s Congressional resources.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://ethics.house.gov/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/OCC-Report-and-Findings-Brandon-Phillips-1.5.26.pdf" target="_blank">report from the Office of Congressional Conduct</a>, released Monday, also claims the intern “did not perform duties commensurate with her compensation.”</p> 
<p>“Based on the foregoing information, the Board finds that there is substantial reason to believe that Mr. Phillips discriminated unfairly by dispensing special favors or privileges by participating in the retention of an employee with whom Mr. Phillips had a personal relationship,” the report states.</p> 
<p>The status of Phillips' employment with Collins’ office at this point is unclear.</p> 
<p>Neither Phillips nor Collins, the Georgia Republican who is currently running for Senate, cooperated with the probe, though Collins’ office, in a statement, disputed the allegations.</p> 
<p>"This bogus complaint is a sad attempt to derail one of Georgia's most effective conservative legislators in Congress,” said a statement from Collins’ office. “Rep. Collins looks forward to providing the House Ethics Committee all factual information and putting these meritless allegations to rest.”</p> 
<p>The House Ethics Committee does not comment on ongoing investigations but said it is currently reviewing the allegations against both Collins and Phillips.</p> 
<p>The OCC, which fields allegations of misconduct against House members and staff, found evidence the Collins intern was paid thousands of dollars for her duties and appeared to have alternative employment while she remained on the congressional office payroll.</p> 
<p>Testimony from individuals who have worked in Collins’ district office said she never “perform[ed] any duties” there, while other people who worked for Collins in Washington said it did not appear that she ever interned for the Capitol Hill office, either.</p> 
<p>Some witnesses indicated that they were afraid of potential retaliation from Phillips, according to the OCC; the report cited a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/13/gop-operative-brandon-phillips-00073724" target="_blank">POLITICO story</a> alleging that Phllips kicked a dog.</p> 
<p>The report also detailed accusations that Phillips used Congressional funds for “Non-Official Travel-Related Expenses, Including Personal and Campaign-Related Expenses,” but OCC said it could not answer questions definitively about Phillips’ travel without Phillips’ and Collins’ cooperation.</p> 
<p>OCC recommended issuing subpoenas to Collins, Philips and the intern, among others.</p> 
<p>In a letter published with the report, Russell Duncan, a lawyer for Collins and Phillips, requested that the Ethics Committee vote to dismiss the allegations against his clients. Duncan claimed that the referrals were the result of testimony from “two disgruntled, former members of Congressman Collins staff.”</p> 
<p>Duncan also maintained that Phillips’ hiring of the intern was within his discretion, and she “provided valuable assistance to the Office throughout both years regarding communications and other work of the Office.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schumer calls out DOJ for not providing unredacted Epstein contacts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/schumer-doj-epstein-00711341</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8fa9-dba9-addb-bfbfb1b80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 14:45:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer on Monday blasted the Justice Department for not providing Congress with an unredacted report of political leaders referenced in documents related to convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/senschumer/status/2008232235673989381?s=46" target="_blank">In a post on X</a>, Schumer accused the Department of Justice of “lawlessness” as he vowed to “ensure all the files come out.”</p> 
<p>“Trump’s DOJ has failed to submit a report to Congress, which is required to include a list of all government officials and politically exposed persons named or referenced in the released materials, without redactions,” Schumer said. “What are they trying to hide?”</p> 
<p>The Justice Department did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>While the DOJ released thousands of documents in several waves last month in compliance with the Epstein Files Transparency Act, many were heavily redacted and some were deleted from the department’s website after initially being posted. Friday was the deadline for the Justice Department to explain the redactions.</p> 
<p>“It’s been 17 DAYS since the Trump DOJ first broke the law and failed to release all the Epstein files,” Schumer said. “It’s been 14 DAYS since Trump’s DOJ released anything at all — with the DOJ doing everything in its power to delay and obfuscate.”</p> 
<p>The Justice Department last month said it had uncovered <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/doj-epstein-documents-new-files-00706387" target="_blank">more than a million additional documents</a>potentially related to Epstein and that it may take “a few more weeks” before all could be released.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-05T11:28:23-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Krishnamoorthi steps down as top Democrat on House China panel</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/raja-krishnamoorthi-china-committee-00710551</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8eb2-dba9-addb-bfbf3b320003</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 10:08:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Illinois Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254656" data-person-id="254656">Raja Krishnamoorthi</a> is stepping down as the top Democrat on the select House committee on competition between the United States and the Chinese Communist Party, he announced Monday.</p> 
<p>Krishnamoorthi did not explain the reason for the move in a statement but is expected to focus on his Senate campaign for the seat being vacated by Democrat <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a>. </p> 
<p>The panel has been generally lauded as a bipartisan effort to investigate and analyze economic and political matters surrounding the Chinese government under President Xi Jinping.</p> 
<p>"I look forward to working closely with them to ensure that Democrats on this Committee continue to succeed, advancing policies that allow the United States to compete and win while remaining firmly grounded in the values that define us," Krishnamoorthi said.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> said Monday that Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/218327" data-person-id="218327">Ro Khanna</a> of California would take over as the top Democrat for the remainder of the 119th Congress.</p> 
<p>“We thank Ro for his continued determination, strong sense of purpose and commitment to the work needed to safeguard our economy, defend our national security and protect human rights around the world,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Congress confronts Venezuela fallout</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/05/congress/venezuela-maduro-rubio-briefing-trump-war-powers-00710422</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8c6b-d78e-af9f-fc7f79b10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Venezuela will dominate the congressional agenda this week, with Republicans lacking a unified vision on what happens next after the capture of Nicolás Maduro and the Senate poised to vote to limit further attacks without lawmaker approval.</p> 
<p><b>— Briefings incoming: </b>Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth, Attorney General Pam Bondi, CIA Director John Ratcliffe and Joint Chiefs of Staff Chair Dan Caine will brief top lawmakers on this weekend’s Venezuela attack at 5:30 p.m. Monday.</p> 
<p>The members receiving the briefing include the top four congressional leaders as well as senior House and Senate members of the Intelligence, Armed Services, Foreign Affairs and Foreign Relations committees.</p> 
<p>Trump himself will speak to House Republicans Tuesday at their annual retreat at the Kennedy Center.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune and Minority Leader Chuck Schumer are also working to schedule an all-senators briefing as soon as mid-week, according to two people granted anonymity.</p> 
<p><b>— The big question: Who will 'run' Venezuela? </b>Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/gop-hawks-trump-maduro-venezuela-00709776" target="_blank">largely rallied behind</a> the administration’s capture of Maduro and his wife, Cilia Flores. But there’s some daylight between them when it comes to what happens next — and some emerging distrust with the administration.</p> 
<p>Trump, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/04/trump-warns-acting-venezuelan-leader-00710314" target="_blank">at least initially</a>, praised Venezuelan Vice President Delcy Rodríguez — now the country’s acting leader — as someone he could work with. His comments were at odds with the wishes of Florida Republican lawmakers who prefer Venezuelan opposition leader María Corina Machado. Trump dismissed her as not having the “support” or “respect” to lead the country. Other Republicans including Rep. Bill Huizenga of Michigan and Sen. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana are calling on Trump to look to Edmundo González, who many nations <a href="https://apnews.com/article/venezuela-presidential-election-maduro-colombia-petro-g20-f2c27ee80ed50cae7109499a23c59552" target="_blank">consider the rightful winner</a> of Venezuela’s 2024 presidential election.</p> 
<p>Behind the scenes, some Republicans are entering the week, as many Democrats are saying publicly, feeling misled by Rubio and the others in the administration about what the endgame has been for Venezuela. Lawmakers have generally trusted Rubio, their former colleague, but the Venezuela attack is straining the relationship.</p> 
<p>Rubio on Sunday was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/04/marco-rubio-venezuela-future-maduro-00710161" target="_blank">vague on the administration’s transition plans</a> for Venezuela. Instead of outlining Trump’s pledge to “run” the country, he said the U.S. is not occupying Venezuela and is instead implementing a “quarantine that allows us to exert tremendous leverage over what happens next.”</p> 
<p><b>— The war powers vote:&nbsp;</b>Despite some bipartisan misgivings, it doesn’t yet appear there will be a groundswell of GOP opposition to Trump’s move if the Senate votes this week on whether to limit further military action in Venezuela without congressional approval. A <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/06/congress/senate-venezuela-vote-00640088" target="_blank">November vote on the issue</a> garnered support from just two Republicans, Sens. Rand Paul (Ky.) and Lisa Murkowski (Alaska). </p> 
<p>House Democrats in a private meeting Sunday discussed how they could force Speaker Mike Johnson to hold a vote on war powers, according to three people granted anonymity. House Republicans in December narrowly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-gop-narrowly-defeats-boat-strike-limits-00696784" target="_blank">defeated a resolution</a> to block military action in Venezuela, with Reps. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) and Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) breaking with their party to support it.</p> 
<p>Massie’s <a href="https://x.com/repthomasmassie/status/2007855570447913358" target="_blank">aggressive rebuke</a> of the weekend attack is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/thomas-massie-trump-venezuela-attack-america-first-00710350" target="_blank">opening a new front</a> in his primary as he faces off against Trump-backed challenger and former Navy SEAL Ed Gallrein.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Shutdown vibes not so bad: </b>House leaders are hoping to put a three-bill funding package on the floor Thursday covering Commerce-Justice-Science, Interior-Environment and Energy-Water. If the House passes it with Democratic support, it could also become a vehicle for a stop-gap continuing resolution in the Senate.</p> 
<p><b>— Health care action: </b>House Democrats will move as soon as Wednesday to force a vote on extending expired Affordable Care Act subsidies for three years, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal planning. The House could pass the bill by Thursday but it’s on track to die in the Senate.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Old headaches will plague Mike Johnson in the new year</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/mike-johnson-headaches-2026-00709400</link>
      <description>The speaker is working to refocus Republicans on cost-of-living matters. But he will find it hard to escape nasty internal clashes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-807d-df0c-a5bb-b47f87150000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/60/71/0ae8d3ed42dfa1069b21482c6453/u-s-congress-59984.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson (R-La.) speaks with reporters as he walks to a vote at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 18, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/60/71/0ae8d3ed42dfa1069b21482c6453/u-s-congress-59984.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is back for the new year. But Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> isn’t exactly getting a fresh start in 2026.</p> 
<p>The House returns from the holiday recess to confront old issues that continue to bedevil Johnson — from politically perilous battle over health care and the ongoing release of the Jeffrey Epstein files to a messy intra-GOP fight over lawmakers’ stock trading and another looming government shutdown cliff.</p> 
<p>The speaker is working to refocus Republicans, seeking to rally members around initiatives aimed at reducing housing prices and efforts to hammer Democrats over public-benefits fraud in Minnesota and other states. President Donald Trump’s decision to depose Venezuelan leader Nicolas Maduro by force has also given the GOP a new rallying point amid doubts about <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/trump-victory-lap-raid-maduro-00709641" target="_blank">Trump's plan to indefinitely “run”</a> the South American country.</p> 
<p>But Johnson will find it hard to escape internally divisive clashes as the GOP feels pressure to address the rising cost of living and otherwise firm up its standing ahead of the November midterms.</p> 
<p>He will immediately confront a growing battle within his ranks this week over how to tackle high health care costs after Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">allowed enhanced Obamacare tax credits to expire</a> at the end of 2025.</p> 
<p>Democrats plan to move as soon as Wednesday to force a floor vote on a three-year straight extension of the lapsed subsidies, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal planning. That comes after four House Republicans mounted a mini-mutiny against Johnson last month by signing a discharge petition backed by Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>.</p> 
<p>While this three-year extension could pass the House by Thursday, the bill is set to die in the Senate, where Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> has indicated he has no plans to move it forward after a similar measure failed to garner the necessary 60 votes in a test vote last month. But a group of moderate senators continue to discuss a compromise proposal, and the rebellious House Republicans are hoping consensus legislation will eventually come back across the Capitol for final action.</p> 
<p>The prospects for a bipartisan deal are dim, however, with Trump continuing to slam the Obamacare tax credits as wasteful while pushing Republicans to instead send money directly to taxpayers via health savings accounts. That’s in addition to the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698" target="_blank">internal GOP battle on Capitol Hill</a> over whether to pursue a party-line health care bill this year that could include sending checks to Americans to offset high health care costs.</p> 
<p>Johnson is projecting confidence going into 2026, writing in a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/opinion/house-republicans-had-a-great-year-04efce46" target="_blank">recent Wall Street Journal op-ed</a> that Republicans have “laid the groundwork for an extraordinary new year — from containing the border crisis and stabilizing inflation to securing historic tax, trade and peace deals.”</p> 
<p>“The best is yet to come,” he wrote, predicting that Americans would “experience the tangible results of common-sense governance” and reward the GOP at the ballot box.</p> 
<p>But that isn’t likely to keep internal rivalries in check. On Venezuela, for instance, Johnson will have to grapple with a pro-intervention Florida delegation while other elements of the conference could be more skeptical of Trump’s threats of long-term military engagement.</p> 
<p>Another headache from inside Johnson’s own conference is coming from hard-liners such as Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a> of Texas and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> of Florida, who are demanding a vote on legislation to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/20/congress/chip-roy-stock-trading-vote-00615272" target="_blank">ban congressional stock trading</a>.</p> 
<p>Johnson and House Administration Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/32319" data-person-id="32319">Bryan Steil</a> (R-Wis.) are seeking to head off threats of a discharge petition that would force a vote on that proposal by drafting their own framework for cracking down on insider trading. They plan to move it out of Steil’s panel and onto the floor in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>But the GOP leadership-backed bill would, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/johnson-steil-insider-trading-stocks-00698141" target="_blank">as POLITICO first reported</a>, still allow lawmakers to hold stocks they already own — a concession that might pass muster with Roy and Luna but is stoking others’ ire. Democrats are already raising alarms over the plan they say falls short of a full ban on congressional stock trading.</p> 
<p>An even more explosive issue — the Epstein files — threatens to continue dogging House GOP leaders as well, as the Justice Department is under increasing criticism across party lines for its slow and incomplete release of materials related to the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>While Congress required DOJ to make its Epstein case files fully public last month, department officials say millions of pages of records continue to be reviewed. And critics say the records that have been released have been subject to improper redactions and other irregularities.</p> 
<p>The issue could come to a head in the coming weeks, with House Judiciary Republicans looking to schedule a routine oversight hearing with Attorney General Pam Bondi that is now expected to focus heavily on the administration’s handling of the Epstein case.</p> 
<p>“They are blatantly ignoring the law,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.), who helped lead the effort to release the files and sits on the Judiciary Committee, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>He and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/218327" data-person-id="218327">Ro Khanna</a> (D-Calif.), who co-sponsored the legislation compelling the release of the files, have said they are preparing to push for a rare “inherent contempt” vote against Bondi that could include fines and other sanctions for DOJ’s alleged noncompliance.</p> 
<p>If there’s any encouraging news for Johnson heading into 2026, it’s on the appropriations front.</p> 
<p>With only a handful of legislative days left before the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid a shutdown — and with many Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/appropriations-talks-jan-30-00701426" target="_blank">worried about the potential</a> for another short-term punt — the top four House and Senate appropriators have been making quiet progress on a three-bill funding package as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/trump-shutdown-january-00700940" target="_blank">appetites fade for allowing the government to shutter</a> yet again.</p> 
<p>Talks around a full-fiscal-year “minibus” that would include the Interior, Energy-Water and Commerce-Justice-Science appropriations bills are close to being finalized, three other people granted anonymity to discuss internal deliberations said. GOP leaders are hoping to put the package on the House floor Thursday if a deal can be reached.</p> 
<p>In the meantime, House GOP leaders are navigating internal politics around a major bipartisan housing package the Financial Services Committee approved last month. While it remains unclear whether the House and Senate can reconcile competing housing plans, Johnson is pushing forward after Trump’s top pollster told a closed-door briefing of House Republicans last month they should focus more on housing affordability issues ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>This week, House GOP leaders are planning to hold votes on a bill from Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/173107" data-person-id="173107">Erin Houchin</a> (R-Ind.) that would cut red tape and relax energy efficiency standards for manufactured housing as well as a measure from Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/250906" data-person-id="250906">Russell Fry</a> (R-S.C.) that would codify Trump’s effort to roll back a regulation instituted under former President Joe Biden limiting water flow for shower nozzles.</p> 
<p>But even Republican leaders’ unity-building proposals — such as highlighting the fraud convictions in Minnesota — could end up sparking fights.</p> 
<p>A growing number of conservatives want Trump to reinstate Elon Musk in his prior role as efficiency czar to probe reports of Medicaid fraud and other related projects. But other Republicans, especially key moderates, are cool to the idea.</p> 
<p>“We have fraud experts in the government that can do this,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227109" data-person-id="227109">Don Bacon</a> (R-Neb.) said in an interview. “They should be able to do their jobs.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-03T16:44:50-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘Iraq 2.0’: Democrats seethe at Trump’s surprise Venezuela strike</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/congress-democrats-war-powers-venezuela-reaction-00709636</link>
      <description>The operation quickly united lawmakers behind a message that the president illegally bypassed Congress and has no plan for the aftermath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8451-df0c-a5bb-b457333f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 10:05:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/97/78/f815d1294d01a260ce4b513b8ad5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2253839665">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Luis Jaimes/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>A fire is seen at Fuerte Tiuna, Venezuela's largest military complex, after a series of explosions in Caracas, Venezuela, on Jan. 3, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/97/78/f815d1294d01a260ce4b513b8ad5/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2253839665" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy, Connor O'Brien and Leo Shane III</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy, Connor O'Brien and Leo Shane III</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are furious over President Donald Trump’s plans for Venezuela.</p> 
<p>The president’s latest show of force on the world stage, which Trump says saw the U.S. military capture Venezuelan President Nicolas Maduro and his wife, quickly united both party leaders and rank-and-file lawmakers behind one message: The White House illegally bypassed Congress and appears woefully underprepared for the aftermath of the surprise military operation.</p> 
<p>The top Democratic congressional leaders each released statements lambasting Trump after he revealed at a Mar-a-Lago news conference Saturday that the administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/trump-victory-lap-raid-maduro-00709641" target="_blank">plans to run Venezuela</a> for an undetermined amount of time.</p> 
<p>“The administration has assured me three separate times that it was not pursuing regime change or taking military action in Venezuela," Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said. "Clearly, they are not being straight with Americans. The idea that Trump plans to now run Venezuela should strike fear in the hearts of all Americans. The American people have seen this before and paid the devastating price."</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries was even more explicit in drawing parallels to recent U.S. efforts at regime change that were costly in both taxpayer dollars and American lives.</p> 
<p>"The promotion of security and stability in a region requires more than just military force as we painfully discovered in Iraq and Afghanistan," he said.</p> 
<p>Trump announced the strike in an <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115830428767897167" target="_blank">early morning post on Truth Social Saturday</a>, touching off a wave of praise from ideologically aligned members of his party. But while Democrats were largely careful not to defend Maduro, they had quick criticism for how Trump had secretly orchestrated the strike.</p> 
<p>The Gang of Eight, which includes senior congressional leaders and top members of the House and Senate Intelligence committees, was notified of the operation only after it had been launched, according to a person with direct knowledge granted anonymity to discuss private outreach.</p> 
<p>While several Republican lawmakers said Saturday they had been personally briefed by Secretary of State Marco Rubio, few if any Democrats appear to have gotten that courtesy.</p> 
<p>Schumer told reporters Saturday afternoon he still had not been briefed by the administration. In a separate joint statement, Schumer and Jeffries requested a Gang of Eight briefing as soon as Saturday, as well as a briefing for a wider group of lawmakers early next week.</p> 
<p>Trump defended the administration's tight lips in his news conference, telling reporters that "Congress has a tendency to leak."</p> 
<p>"This would not be good," he added. "If they leaked … I think this would be a very different result."</p> 
<p>But Schumer called that an “excuse for secrecy” that is “outrageous” and “dangerous.” Schumer said Saturday that he is already strategizing with top committee Democrats about what steps they could take to “hold the administration accountable.” House Democrats are scheduled to hold an emergency caucus meeting Sunday, according to an invitation sent to members.</p> 
<p>“Some of the Republican chairs, at least privately on the phone … have expressed a lot of troublesome comments about what Trump is doing and the way he is doing it, and those discussions will continue,” Schumer said, relaying private conversations between Democrats he had spoken to and the GOP chairs.</p> 
<p>Well before the top Democratic congressional leaders spoke out, rank-and-file lawmakers took the lead in angrily denouncing Trump’s decision to topple a foreign leader by military force without asking lawmakers for authorization first.</p> 
<p>“Congress did not authorize this war,” Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.) <a href="https://x.com/sethmoulton/status/2007419546458902795" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. “Venezuela posed no imminent threat to the United States. This is reckless, elective regime change risking American lives (Iraq 2.0) with no plan for the day after. Wars cost more than trophies.”</p> 
<p>Congress has not authorized military action against Venezuela, and lawmakers have been split for months on the legality of the Trump administration’s strikes against suspected drug smuggling vessels in the waters off Latin America and a potential move to oust Maduro. Republicans have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-gop-narrowly-defeats-boat-strike-limits-00696784" target="_blank">fended off several Democratic-led efforts</a> to require Trump to seek approval from Congress before attacking Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.), who sits on the Senate Armed Services Committee, announced Saturday he would again force the chamber to vote on his effort to constrain Trump’s war powers next week.</p> 
<p>"It’s time for Congress to get its ass off the couch and do what the Constitution mandates that we do,” Kaine told reporters during a call Saturday. “What we've seen is members of Congress who, frankly, lack the guts, lack the backbone, lack the courage to have that debate, and they've been willing to allow an increasingly declining and erratic president to make these decisions without them.”</p> 
<p>In addition to the war powers vote, Kaine raised the possibility that an upcoming government funding deadline could offer further leverage. Democrats, he said, would “press for a vote” to prohibit expenditures on military actions concerning Venezuela without congressional approval.</p> 
<p>Schumer, however, didn’t draw a red line on the spending fight, saying the immediate focus was on getting briefings and a war powers vote: “Let’s first get all the facts out,” he said.</p> 
<p>In addition to criticizing the murky legal justification for the operation, several Democrats said the move is an about-face for administration officials who they said argued regime change wasn’t the end goal of the administration’s aggressive military campaign in Latin America.</p> 
<p>“Secretaries Rubio and [Pete] Hegseth looked every Senator in the eye a few weeks ago and said this wasn’t about regime change. I didn’t trust them then and we see now that they blatantly lied to Congress,” Sen. Andy Kim (D-N.J.) <a href="https://x.com/SenatorAndyKim/status/2007399987596906501" target="_blank">said on X</a>. “Trump rejected our Constitutionally required approval process for armed conflict because the Administration knows the American people overwhelmingly reject risks pulling our nation into another war.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Sen. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.), a combat veteran who deployed to Iraq as an infantryman in 2005, wrote on X Saturday that “the American people did not ask for this.”</p> 
<p>And he wondered aloud about what comes next for the South American country, <a href="https://x.com/RubenGallego/status/2007448353584623708" target="_blank">asking on X</a>, “so who is in charge of Venezuela now?”</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/poll-trump-military-action-in-venezuela-00695694" target="_blank">December Quinnipiac poll</a> found that Americans overwhelmingly oppose military action against Venezuela, with just 25 percent of respondents saying they supported an intervention inside the country. Even the White House’s strategy of targeting boats with alleged drug traffickers proved broadly unpopular.</p> 
<p>“I fought in some of the hardest battles of the Iraq War,” <a href="https://x.com/RubenGallego/status/2007379621155930357" target="_blank">Gallego wrote</a>. “Saw my brothers die, saw civilians being caught in the crossfire all for an unjustified war. No matter the outcome we are in the wrong for starting this war in Venezuela.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Debbie Wasserman Schultz (D-Fla.), who is a co-chair of the Congressional Venezuela Democracy Caucus and represents a significant population of Venezuelan immigrants in South Florida, signaled agreement with the move to oust Maduro. She called his capture "welcome news" for Venezuela but argued Trump should have involved Congress before conducting the attack.</p> 
<p>"The absence of congressional involvement prior to this action risks the continuation of the illegitimate Venezuelan regime," Wasserman Schultz said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Other Democrats voiced stronger opposition to the administration’s military moves.</p> 
<p>“Millions of Americans voted in the last Presidential election to end frivolous conflicts and unnecessary foreign wars,” said Rep. Gabe Vasquez (D-N.M.), an Armed Services Committee member, in a statement. “This escalation of hostilities against Venezuela and the capture of a foreign leader without congressional authorization goes against the will of the Americans who put the president in power.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.), who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/democrats-trump-sedition-backfire-00670552" target="_blank">found himself accused of sedition by Trump in November</a> after encouraging American troops to disregard unlawful orders, urged Congress to reassert its war powers in this week's vote.</p> 
<p>“I want the people of Venezuela to be free to choose their own future, but if we learned anything from the Iraq war, it’s that dropping bombs or toppling a leader doesn’t guarantee democracy, stability, or make Americans safer,” he wrote in a statement. “More often, it leads to chaos or drags the U.S. into a war and lengthy occupation. I don’t trust that this administration has a plan, timeline, or price tag for what comes next.”</p> 
<p>But hawkish GOP Sen. Lindsey Graham of South Carolina <a href="https://x.com/lindseygrahamsc/status/2007466123009126597" target="_blank">offered a rejoinder on X</a> to critics of the operation who are "focus[ed] on absurd 'legal' theories" and "virtually AWOL for the cause of freedom."</p> 
<p>"To the pathetically weak and hand wringing liberal Democrats who seem to be okay with a perpetual drug caliphate in our backyard, the centerpiece of which is Venezuela," he wrote, "Get a grip."</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Mighty mad’: Democrats prepare to harness public anger over expired Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/02/democrats-obamacare-subsidies-midterms-00708576</link>
      <description>Efforts to extend them continue, but lawmakers and strategists are already moving to turn the lapsed tax credits into a potent election-year attack on Republicans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-752a-dba9-addb-77bfc5ea0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 06:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/34/10/8a36925f46f89f487cbbec0c15e1/house-democrats-20756.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>DCCC Chair Suzan DelBene (D-Wash.) said blame for rising health costs lies "squarely at the feet of House Republicans, and the American people know it."</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/34/10/8a36925f46f89f487cbbec0c15e1/house-democrats-20756.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Obamacare subsidies used by more than 20 million <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/obamacare-congress-negotiations-health-care-00688191" target="_blank">expired Thursday</a>. Now Democrats are ready to make them a centerpiece of their midterm campaigns.</p> 
<p>The lapse of enhanced premium tax credits, first passed as a pandemic-era relief measure under President Joe Biden in 2021, will immediately hit the pocketbooks of voters — some of whom will see their monthly insurance premiums rise by hundreds of dollars.</p> 
<p>Efforts to extend them in some fashion continue on Capitol Hill, but Democratic lawmakers and strategists are already moving to turn the expiration of the subsidies into a potent election-year attack on congressional Republicans. They note that unlike other Democratic messaging targets — such as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/13/dem-medicaid-midterms-00449115" target="_blank">recent GOP Medicaid cuts</a> that won’t kick in until after midterm ballots are cast — the lost tax credits are already tangible proof of what’s at stake on Election Day.</p> 
<p>“The public now gets that the subsidies are what's keeping health care costs down,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/199004" data-person-id="199004">Ami Bera</a> (D-Calif.). “I think the public's angry. So I think they will blame the party in charge.”</p> 
<p>The strategy has been months in the making. Mindful of how the GOP’s efforts to rein in Obamacare powered their massive gains in the 2018 midterms, top party leaders decided in September to make health care the focus of the government funding fight.</p> 
<p>That posture led to a record 43-day shutdown, and while some Senate Democrats ultimately agreed to reopen the government without securing an extension of the tax credits, many in the party are increasingly confident they succeeded in putting the issue into focus ahead of the election year.</p> 
<p>They also believe it will play into a broader messaging push around affordability — attacking President Donald Trump and congressional Republicans for their failure to address rising costs, of which insurance premiums are just one conspicuous challenge facing Republicans.</p> 
<p>“It's part of the top issue, which is cost of living — whether it's groceries, gas, housing, energy costs,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/410426" data-person-id="410426">Chris Deluzio</a> (D-Pa.). “Health care seems to be top of mind as something that Congress can actually do to bring down the costs.”</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.kff.org/public-opinion/2025-kff-marketplace-enrollees-survey/" target="_blank">KFF poll released in December</a> found that large majorities of enrollees in Obamacare marketplace plans want the subsidies to continue, regardless of party. About three-quarters of that group said they would blame Trump or Republicans in Congress if the subsidies were to lapse.</p> 
<p>Republicans have encountered difficulties forming a coherent counterattack. Trump has questioned whether affordability is even a problem, calling the focus on living costs a “hoax” perpetrated by Democrats and the media. He has instead focused on robust economic growth as a measure of his administration’s success.</p> 
<p>On Capitol Hill, top GOP leaders have criticized the expiring subsidies as wasteful — subsidizing some high-income households and susceptible to fraud — but they have not coalesced around a plan to offer relief to the millions of Americans who buy insurance on Obamacare marketplaces. A <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">package of health care measures</a> passed by the House last month on a party-line vote included some conservative proposals to deregulate insurance markets, but they would have little immediate effect before the midterms.</p> 
<p>Instead, Republicans are preparing to run on last year’s megabill, which included tax cuts and other provisions that will start kicking in this year. This, they believe, will help them hold onto their congressional majorities.</p> 
<p>“House Republicans delivered historic tax relief for working families and are building on it in the new year,” said NRCC spokesperson Mike Marinella. “Democrats spent the year blocking commonsense solutions [for the subsidies] and are now having a temper tantrum over a policy cliff of their own making. Their inability to find a consistent message that sticks proves how out of touch they are with the American people.”</p> 
<p>Democrats’ party campaign arm is already geared up to push a health-care focused message for the next 10 months. Its leaders have laid out why they believe it’s a <a href="https://dccc.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/DCCC-Interested-Parties-Memo-HOUSE-REPUBLICANS-FAILURE-TO-AVERT-HEALTH-CARE-CRISIS-WILL-COST-THEM-THE-MAJORITY.pdf" target="_blank">key issue</a> heading into the midterms and have already <a href="https://dccc.org/dccc-launches-digital-ads-to-call-out-vulnerable-house-republicans-for-refusing-to-fix-looming-health-care-crisis/" target="_blank">run</a> <a href="https://dccc.org/marjorie-taylor-greene-is-right-dccc-launches-digital-ad-buy-on-conservative-news-sites/" target="_blank">ads</a> and <a href="https://dccc.org/dccc-launches-the-congress-who-stole-health-care-billboard-campaign/" target="_blank">rented billboards</a> highlighting the GOP’s opposition to continuing the subsidies.</p> 
<p>“Make no mistake, the blame behind the skyrocketing health care costs millions are facing today is squarely at the feet of House Republicans, and the American people know it,” DCCC Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198811" data-person-id="198811">Suzan DelBene</a> (D-Wash.) said in a statement. “Instead of putting forth a serious proposal to address spiking health care costs, House Republicans chose to focus on delivering massive tax breaks for the wealthiest few — never even allowing a floor vote to save the tax credits before their expiration.”</p> 
<p>It is true no vote took place before the expiration, but jitters about an electoral backlash prompted a handful of House Republicans to take the rare step last month of circumventing GOP leadership and signing onto an effort backed by House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688" target="_blank">force a floor vote on a three-year extension</a> of the expired subsidies.</p> 
<p>That vote is now expected to take place in the coming weeks, though Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said he has no intention of holding a vote in his own chamber, and even Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> has played down the prospects of a bipartisan extension.</p> 
<p>“Once Jan. 1 comes and everyone is locked into their insurance proposals, you can’t put the toothpaste back in the tube,” he said last month.</p> 
<p>The purple-district Republicans said they intend to keep trying, and they are coordinating with a bipartisan group of senators that is trying to strike a late compromise to save the subsidies. But Democrats believe it is too little, too late — even as they say it is a telling move.</p> 
<p>For the vulnerable Republicans “to come on at the 11th hour shows they get it,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/194115" data-person-id="194115">Madeleine Dean</a> (D-Pa.). “Their constituents are going to be mighty mad, and they're feeling it already.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-01T17:43:08-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>7 takeaways from Jack Smith’s congressional testimony</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/takeaways-jack-smith-congressional-testimony-00708747</link>
      <description>The New Year’s Eve transcript release buries details from the former special counsel’s investigation into Donald Trump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-768d-dba9-addb-77bfa52b0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 18:14:04 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fb/93/5bde97cf4001b9ca2d6ca1bf5571/u-s-congress-64577.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former special counsel Jack Smith defended his investigations in a closed-door deposition on Dec. 17 in front of the House Judiciary Committee.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fb/93/5bde97cf4001b9ca2d6ca1bf5571/u-s-congress-64577.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Kyle Cheney, Hailey Fuchs and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Kyle Cheney, Hailey Fuchs and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans decided to publicly release the transcript of special counsel Jack Smith’s Dec. 17 closed-door deposition on New Year’s Eve — while most of Washington was tuned out for the holiday.</p> 
<p>Smith used <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-deposition-congress-00694730" target="_blank">the day-long grilling</a> before the House Judiciary Committee to mount a robust defense of his investigation into Donald Trump for seeking to subvert the 2020 election. He forcefully rebutted claims that his work was tainted by politics and delivered a granular defense of his office’s tactics and prosecution strategy — all while repeatedly restating his view that Trump was guilty of a historic crime. He also revealed some new information about his witness list, and gave Judiciary Republicans a new opening to attack Cassidy Hutchinson’s infamous testimony.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Smith declined to comment.</p> 
<p>Here’s what we learned from the <a href="https://judiciary.house.gov/sites/evo-subsites/republicans-judiciary.house.gov/files/2025-12/Smith-Depo-Transcript_Redacted-w-Errata.pdf" target="_blank">255-page transcript</a>:</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Smith built his case around Trump’s allies</h4> 
<p>Some of Smith’s most substantive testimony centered on his never-implemented trial strategy: using Republicans who believed in Trump to make the case against him.</p> 
<p>“The president was preying on the party allegiance of people who supported him,” Smith said. “The evidence that I felt was most powerful was the evidence that came from people in his own party who … put country before party and were willing to tell the truth to him, even though it could mean trouble for them.”</p> 
<p>Smith repeatedly drew on diehard Republicans to make the case against the man they wanted to become president but who they acknowledged had been defeated. Smith said former Vice President Mike Pence and several of the GOP elector nominees — like Pennsylvania’s Lawrence Tabas — would have fit that bill and made strong trial witnesses.</p> 
<p>“That witness, Mr. Tabas, was of a similar group of witnesses who — these are not enemies of the president. These are people in his party who supported him,” Smith continued. “And I think the fact that they were telling him these things … would have had great weight and great credibility with a jury.”</p> 
<p>Smith said he came to believe that Trump’s Jan. 6, 2021, tweet attacking Pence while he was at the Capitol “without question” exacerbated the danger to Pence’s life.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Smith hadn’t made his final charging decisions</h4> 
<p>The former special counsel said he never officially decided whether to bring additional charges against the figures he alleged were Trump’s co-conspirators — including attorneys Rudy Giuliani, Sidney Powell, Kenneth Chesebro, John Eastman and Boris Epshteyn.</p> 
<p>“I had not made final determinations about that at the time that President Trump won reelection, meaning that our office was going to be closed down,” Smith said.</p> 
<p>Smith said he had no plans to call Eastman — an architect of Trump’s last-ditch bid to stop Joe Biden’s Electoral College certification in January 2021 — as a trial witness but said he would have welcomed Trump calling Eastman to the stand as a defense witness.</p> 
<p>Smith noted he interviewed Epshteyn, Giuliani and other alleged co-conspirators in the course of the investigation.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Lawmakers failed to knock Smith off his game</h4> 
<p>The former special counsel repeatedly leaned into the defense of his probe and expressed confidence that a jury would have convicted Trump if the case went to trial.</p> 
<p>He refused to take Democrats’ bait to attack Republicans for refusing, so far, to give him a public hearing. And he avoided straying into discussions that might have forced him to reveal subjects still protected by grand jury secrecy or a federal judge’s order that barred him from disclosing details of his second investigation into President Trump’s hoarding of classified documents at Mar-a-Lago after leaving office in 2021.</p> 
<p>“Did you have the opportunity to interview Mr. Pence as part of your investigation?” a staffer asked Smith at one point.</p> 
<p>“I think the answer to that question might involve [grand jury information], and so I'm not going to answer that,” Smith said.</p> 
<p>When Rep. Dan Goldman (D-N.Y.) pressed Smith about the structure of his classified documents report, Smith again demurred.</p> 
<p>“I don't think I should even talk about that. I don't want to have any — any implication that I gave some sort of insight about how that report is constructed,’ he said.</p> 
<p>Smith repeatedly reminded lawmakers that he’s open to sharing the results of his classified documents investigation, but was restricted by the ruling from a federal judge in Florida who maintained Smith's report must stay under seal. The day of Smith’s deposition, the Department of Justice also sent an email to Smith’s team emphasizing the court order prevented him from sharing nonpublic information with Congress.</p> 
<p>At one point, a staffer questioning Smith suggested it would be far more difficult to retrieve materials from Mar-a-Lago compared to elsewhere.</p> 
<p>“I mean, a person can't just walk into Mar-a-Lago and try to abscond with these materials, right?” the person, whose identity was redacted, asked.</p> 
<p>“I would very much like to answer that question, but I cannot answer that question due to the final report,” Smith responded.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Smith forcefully rejected any hint of political bias</h4> 
<p>Republicans and Democrats repeatedly teed it up for him: Did politics influence Smith’s decision to become special counsel or the way he handled his investigation? Did the White House ever lean on him or senior Justice Department officials like former Attorney General Merrick Garland and his deputy Lisa Monaco?</p> 
<p>Each time Smith was unequivocal: Not for a moment.</p> 
<p>Smith maintained he never communicated with Biden or White House staff before or during his investigation. He also said the timing of Trump’s announcement for president, his crowded calendar of criminal cases leading up to the 2024 election and the sensitivity of certain allegations were nonfactors in his decisions. He emphasized that he regularly consulted with Justice Department officials to ensure he abided by its guidelines.</p> 
<p>“We certainly were not in any way intending to affect the outcome of the election. And to make sure we complied with the policy, we met with Public Integrity to make sure we were doing that,” Smith said.</p> 
<p>Multiple people also asked Smith if he would be surprised if Trump directs his Department of Justice to target him. The former special counsel responded no.</p> 
<p>“I have no doubt that the president wants to seek retribution against me,” Smith said.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers also pressed Smith about the executive order against his legal representation, Covington &amp; Burling, in which Trump suspended security clearances for firm employees who had worked with Smith. It was one of several major law firms hit with penalties in the beginning of the second Trump administration.</p> 
<p>“I think it's to chill people from having an association with me,” Smith said.</p> 
<p>During the deposition, Smith’s attorney Peter Koski said his firm was proud to represent Smith.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Smith didn’t pursue ‘uncooperative’ witnesses</h4> 
<p>Though there were few new details in Smith’s testimony, he disclosed that he didn’t pursue interviews with three figures close to Trump: Steve Bannon, Roger Stone and Peter Navarro. The reason, he said, was they were relatively uncooperative with congressional investigators and were unnecessary for his team to discern the details of Trump’s bid to subvert the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>“Given the highly uncooperative nature of the individuals you talked about, I didn't think it would be fruitful to try to question them,” Smith said. “And the sort of information that they could provide us, in my view, wasn't worth immunizing them for their possible conduct.”</p> 
<p>But Smith also described a text exchange between Bannon and Epshteyn on the evening of Jan. 6 in which Bannon described Trump as “still on fire” — an exchange he said was evidence that Trump did not see the riot as the end of his effort to prevent his defeat in the election.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Smith defends pursuit of lawmakers’ phone records</h4> 
<p>Republicans and Democrats pressed Smith extensively about his pursuit of the phone records of Republican lawmakers who Trump and his allies contacted during the days and weeks before Jan. 6, 2021.</p> 
<p>Smith said he wanted former Speaker Kevin McCarthy’s records because he knew McCarthy spoke to the White House as violence unfolded that day. He also said the records they pursued were limited and intended to shore up the case if it went to trial — and all were obtained in accordance with DOJ policies governing the handling of investigations that touch on congressional records.</p> 
<p>Smith also emphasized he was not special counsel when Justice Department investigators obtained a two-year batch of House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan’s phone records.</p> 
<p>The former special counsel displayed detailed knowledge about the way the Constitution’s Speech or Debate clause protects legislative activity from federal investigators and said he sought to comply with those limits. He noted that his office litigated Speech or Debate issues related to Pence and Rep. Scott Perry (R-Pa.) during the course of the probe.</p> 
<p>“My office and I personally take the protections of the Speech or Debate Clause seriously,” he said. “They're an important part of separation of powers.”</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">House GOP revel in Smith comments on Cassidy Hutchinson</h4> 
<p>In the aftermath of the transcript’s release, the Judiciary Republicans pointed to Smith’s comments about Cassidy Hutchinson, the former White House aide who in 2022 <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/06/28/january-6-hearings-cassidy-hutchinson-key-moments-video-analysis-00042914" target="_blank">testified against Trump</a> in a dramatic hearing before the Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee.</p> 
<p>Hutchinson famously said another Trump aide told her that a furious Trump lunged for the wheel after learning the vehicle he was in was headed for the White House instead of the Capitol after his incendiary Jan. 6 speech. Trump has long denied the incident.</p> 
<p>Smith told congressional investigators his office spoke to at least one officer who was in the SUV for Trump’s return to the White House that day.</p> 
<p>“[M]y recollection with Ms. Hutchinson, at least one of the issues was a number of the things that she gave evidence on were secondhand hearsay, were things that she had heard from other people and, as a result, that testimony may or may not be admissible, and it certainly wouldn’t be as powerful as firsthand testimony,” Smith said.</p> 
<p>“The partisan January 6th Committee’s ENTIRE case was just destroyed by… Jack Smith,” the Judiciary GOP <a href="https://x.com/JudiciaryGOP/status/2006460588776632801?s=20" target="_blank">posted on X</a>. “Star witness completely unreliable!”</p> 
<p>The Jan. 6 committee grilled Hutchinson in part because Mark Meadows, her direct boss, declined to sit for an interview. Though Hutchinson’s story was among the most explosive aspects of its public hearings, the case the committee made — that Trump systematically attempted to sow doubt about the 2020 election results and lean on state and federal officials to subvert it — was the product of hundreds of interviews, many from Trump’s closest aides and allies.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hill spy-powers fight comes down to 1 question: What does Trump want?</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/section-702-donald-trump-surveillance-00708042</link>
      <description>Presidential engagement could shape the latest clash over Section 702 surveillance authority.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-7095-df0c-a5bb-74d748310000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 16:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e6/fc/87d6068444db8bf06605a8474fc4/u-s-congress-21512.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan, center, and ranking member Jamie Raskin, right, have raised concerns about the expiring spy program.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e6/fc/87d6068444db8bf06605a8474fc4/u-s-congress-21512.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, John Sakellariadis and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, John Sakellariadis and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Privacy advocates have tried again and again over the past decade to rein in a major U.S. spy program that targets foreigners but also sweeps up data on Americans — and each time, they have fallen short.</p> 
<p>They believe 2026 might be different.</p> 
<p>The surveillance program in question, known as Section 702, expires in mid-April. Its critics, who believe it too easily allows Americans’ private communications to get caught up in government dragnets meant to ensnare overseas targets, are readying a major push to rewrite the law — and they are hoping they have a crucial new ally in President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>The president has long had an antagonistic relationship with the intelligence community, and some of his closest allies in Congress are among Section 702’s fiercest critics. But persistent lobbying from national security officials and backing from top congressional leaders has been enough to save the program in the past, including during Trump’s first term.</p> 
<p>Some of its congressional backers aren’t seeing the same level of engagement this time — at least not yet.</p> 
<p>“I spent the last week shaking cages with IC leaders saying, ‘You know, this is going to be a heavy lift,’” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66846" data-person-id="66846">Jim Himes</a> of Connecticut, the top Democrat on the House Intelligence Committee. “When we reauthorized it last time, Cabinet secretaries were taking random members of Congress out to Starbucks, and I don’t see that effort. So I’m very concerned.”</p> 
<p>The bipartisan coalition seeking a sweeping overhaul of the surveillance authority <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/04/29/trump-conservatives-spy-power-00154619" target="_blank">has reasons to be optimistic</a> that Trump might ultimately back their efforts, overruling intelligence officials who have long warned that requiring a warrant to search for any Americans’ data and putting in place other safeguards critics seek would make the program unworkable.</p> 
<p>“I think a lot of the rationale that was used against us has just basically dissipated,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189182" data-person-id="189182">Andy Biggs</a> (R-Ariz.), who has long pushed for the warrant requirement and continues lobbying various factions for it. “So I think we're real close to getting some agreements, but right now it's the warm-up phase.”</p> 
<p>Even those who want to keep the current spy authorities intact recognize the president’s potential to swing the debate at the 11th hour.</p> 
<p>Trump is "the 800-pound gorilla in the closet,” said one Democratic congressional aide, granted anonymity because they were not authorized to speak publicly about the coming reauthorization fight.</p> 
<p>As president in 2020, Trump helped upend three unrelated surveillance programs, all of which ultimately expired, after back-channeling with privacy hawks and breaking with his then-attorney general, Bill Barr.</p> 
<p>During the last reauthorization debate in 2024, then-candidate Trump urged Congress to “kill” the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act, the larger spy law that Section 702 is nested under. Trump’s decision frustrated supporters of the program — in part because they believe he conflated the foreign-target spy program with the broader surveillance law that was not up for reauthorization.</p> 
<p>A crucial Biggs-sponsored House amendment that would have added a warrant requirement for any communications involving Americans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/04/12/congress/government-surveillance-702-house-gop-pass-fisa-johnson-00151946" target="_blank">failed on a 212-212 tie</a>, with Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> casting a rare and decisive vote to kill it.</p> 
<p>Now the spy powers fight is a major headache for Johnson, who infuriated privacy hawks with his 2024 amendment vote after having advocated for more surveillance guardrails as a former member of the Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>Judiciary Committee Republicans — led by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51745" data-person-id="51745">Jim Jordan</a> of Ohio, a close Trump ally — have started discussing how to approach the reauthorization during their weekly meetings. Jordan said in an interview he is again hoping to impose a warrant requirement for searches involving Americans as well as a ban on data brokers selling consumer information to law enforcement.</p> 
<p>He said he has “had some discussions over this past year with some members of the administration” on this issue and plans to meet alongside House Intelligence Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/148088" data-person-id="148088">Rick Crawford</a> (R-Ark.) with White House officials on the matter early next year.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers on both sides of the debate are carefully watching Crawford, who opposed the warrant requirement in 2024 — along with every other House Intelligence Committee Republican. But Johnson has since added five Republicans to the panel who each voted for the Biggs amendment.</p> 
<p>A committee spokesperson said Crawford is working with House leadership, Jordan, the Senate and the administration “to determine the best way forward to extend 702 authority.”</p> 
<p>There are still, however, a majority of Intelligence Committee Republicans who are working to extend the program without adding a warrant requirement — and they are hoping administration officials whom they view as allies, including Vice President JD Vance, CIA Director John Ratcliffe and Secretary of State Marco Rubio, will be able to sway Trump.</p> 
<p>“Ultimately the president is going to have to make the decision on it, but I think the people weighing in have a record of not supporting the warrant requirement and knowing it jeopardizes national security,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/190794" data-person-id="190794">Darin LaHood</a> (R-Ill.), an Intelligence Committee member, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for the CIA, National Security Agency and the FBI declined to respond to questions about whether they are in contact with the White House, if they support a clean reauthorization of the current bill, and whether they have engaged with Congress on the issue. The Justice Department, White House and Office of the Director of National Intelligence did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Some House Republicans are privately hoping that the Senate takes the lead, believing it would be easier to get an extension without major changes across the finish line there. That, they believe, would ease its path to passage on the House side.</p> 
<p>Senate Intelligence Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198766" data-person-id="198766">Tom Cotton</a> (R-Ark.) is quietly pitching an 18-month extension of the authority, effectively punting the surveillance fight until the end of 2027, according to House and Senate Intelligence Committee Republicans. His panel and the Senate Armed Services Committee are expected to hold hearings early next year on Lt. Gen. Joshua Rudd’s nomination as commander of U.S. Cyber Command and director of the National Security Agency.</p> 
<p>Those hearings could be the first real indication of how some key lawmakers are approaching the impending reauthorization fight. While some Democrats such as Oregon Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51247" data-person-id="51247">Ron Wyden</a> have been longstanding critics of warrantless surveillance, others have generally been more sympathetic to intelligence officials.</p> 
<p>But now, with Trump instead of Joe Biden in the White House, that could be changing. For instance, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192069" data-person-id="192069">Jamie Raskin</a> of Maryland was among the majority of Democrats who voted against the warrant requirement amendment in 2024. But during a Judiciary subcommittee hearing this month, Raskin referred to “an assault on the FBI’s internal guardrails against abuse of Section 702 authorities” during Trump’s second term.</p> 
<p>"There is an inherent number [of House Democrats] that will reject their 'yes' vote and switch just because of Donald Trump,” the Democratic congressional aide said about the warrant requirement. Privacy hawks have also already polled first-term GOP lawmakers to gauge how they might come down, according to one person granted anonymity to discuss the private effort.</p> 
<p>Jordan predicted his pro-warrant coalition will “get more Democrat votes this time, and I’m hopeful that we can keep all the Republican votes we had last time.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 Predictions for American Politics in 2026</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/12/31/2026-politics-predictions-quiz-00708039</link>
      <description>This multiple-choice look at the year ahead offers predictions on Trump, Congress, the courts and the political surprises of 2026.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-705f-df0c-a5bb-745f5a230000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 08:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/0c/77/dbf139b14e23837b664070029360/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2252793758">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Tasos Katopodis/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>U.S. President Donald Trump takes the stage during a rally at the Rocky Mount Event Center on Dec.19, 2025 in Rocky Mount, North Carolina.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0c/77/dbf139b14e23837b664070029360/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2252793758" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jonathan Martin</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jonathan Martin</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the spirit of the late William Safire’s long-running “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/29/opinion/29safire.html?smid=url-share" target="_blank">Office Pool</a>,” I bring you this column’s predictions for 2026 — from Senate races to unexpected congressional resignations, and even the future of a certain controversial new college football hire.</p> 
<p>To make it easier, and have some fun, the soothsaying is multiple choice. Feel free to answer yourself, but worry not, accountability-seekers: My guesses will also be included under each question, along with some context. Yes, I’m borrowing an earlier era’s format. But the same can be said about end-of-year columns as is said for old yarns: no new stories, only new audiences.</p> 
<p>So with hopes that this will be new to most and bring back fond memories for others, let’s get to the guessing: 16 for ’26.</p> 
<p><b>1)</b> <b>What Washington landmark will President Donald Trump name after himself in conjunction with America’s 250th birthday?</b><br>A) Dulles Airport<br>B) The Dulles Airport “<a href="https://wjla.com/news/local/dulles-airport-people-movers-transportation-dulles-airport-expansion-international-terminal-domestic-flights-mobile-lounge-plane-mate-1962-dulles-airport-aerotrain" target="_blank">people-movers</a>”<br>C) Arlington Memorial Bridge<br>D) The National Mall<br></p><p><br><b>2)</b> <b>Should Justice Samuel Alito retire, or another vacancy open on the Supreme Court, who will Trump appoint?</b><br>A) Jeanine Pirro<br>B) Andrew Oldham<br>C) Aileen Cannon<br>D) Ted Cruz<br></p><p><b>3)</b> <b>How soon after appointing </b><a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6952f7cdd440de3aef667af1&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoNxFEKgDAIANATOW0Mgm4Tm7CB5ZiGdPt6H6-7TzsQIyJNleGjaqp64c1hwu68DPvTmjBmyhmp4L_oai8sFQHvDH5ONiCivG-FPg25HJA%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.politico.com" target="_blank"><b>his new</b></a><b> “My Kevin” — Kevin Hassett or Kevin Warsh — as Federal Reserve Chair will Trump pressure him to lower interest rates?</b><br>A) In the Truth Social post announcing his selection<br>B) In his remarks at the White House event making it official<br>C) In response to shouted press questions at said White House event<br>D) Never — Trump will fulfill his New Year’s resolution respecting the traditional independence of the Fed<br></p><p><br><b>4) Now that he’s ordered strikes on targets in Iran, Nigeria, Syria, Somalia, Yemen and over the Caribbean, what country will Trump attack next?</b><br>A) Venezuela<br>B) Iran, again<br>C) Russia<br>D) Canada, and specifically the provincial capitol building in Toronto, should Premier Doug Ford run another tariff ad on American TV<br></p><p><br><b>5) Trump will endorse the winning candidate in which Republican primary?</b><br>A) Kentucky’s Fourth Congressional District, represented by Rep. Thomas Massie<br>B) Indiana State Senate District 37, represented by Rod Bray, the president pro tempore who defied Trump’s redistricting demands<br>C) U.S. Senate in Texas<br>D) U.S. Senate in Louisiana<br></p><p><br><b>6) For all of the attention Democrats are lavishing on the Texas Senate campaign, which other Senate races will have a closer final margin in the general election?</b><br>A) Maine<br>B) North Carolina<br>C) Ohio<br>D) Nebraska<br>E) All of the above<br></p><p><br><b>7) Which 2028 Democratic presidential hopeful will unwittingly hurt their candidacy by writing a book?</b><br>A) Gov. Gavin Newsom of California, by revealing he’s still doing self-discovery in his late-50s<br>B) Gov. Josh Shapiro of Pennsylvania, by revisiting the arson of the governor’s mansion so much that a tragedy becomes an origin story for a campaign — and without much subtlety<br>C) Former Vice President Kamala Harris, by confusing book tour crowds and enthusiasm for the notion that Democrats want to relive anything relating to 2024<br>D) Former Transportation Secretary Pete Buttigieg, by showing, again, that he’s the smartest kid in class and affirming his future in appointive, not elective, politics<br></p><p><br><b>8) After next year’s election, the Trump-ordered redrawing of red state House maps and subsequent arms race will be seen as:</b><br>A) A political masterstroke<br>B) Having helped Democrats retake the House<br>C) The hinge point marking Trump’s slide from full control of the GOP<br>D) Close to a wash: Republicans picked up a few seats but between the Trump-imposed redraw and the new maps enacted after the Supreme Court guts the Voting Rights Act, the GOP got greedy and imperiled a few incumbents who lost in a difficult year after their previously-safe districts absorbed more Democrats.<br></p><p><br><b>9) Which House Republican, after Marjorie Taylor Greene, will resign before this session of Congress is over?</b><br>A) Rep. Don Bacon (Neb.)<br>B) Rep. Elise Stefanik (N.Y.)<br>C) Rep. Victoria Spartz (Ind.)<br>D) Rep. Cory Mills (Fla.)<br></p><p><br><b>10) By the end of 2026, which Republican will emerge as the best-positioned to challenge J.D. Vance for the 2028 GOP nomination?</b><br>A) Ted Cruz<br>B) Ivanka Trump<br>C) Tucker Carlson<br>D) Marco Rubio<br></p><p><br><b>11) The first major Trump appointee to leave his or her post will be:</b><br>A) Kash Patel<br>B) Kristi Noem<br>C) Robert F. Kennedy Jr.<br>D) Pete Hegseth<br></p><p><br><b>12) Who is finally able to convince Trump that Vladimir Putin has no interest in stopping the</b> <b>war and only wants to string Trump along?</b><br>A) Marco Rubio<br>B) Alex Stubb<br>C) Sylvester Stallone<br>D) Jared Kushner<br></p><p><br><b>13) What “</b><a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6952f7cdd440de3aef667af1&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoFwtENgCAMBcCJpP9uQ7AKBChpHyluT-4yMO0mcveAzGskVsQy8E-VyglB9COINCNd3V5uz9UjtOwDuzUXdg%3D%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.theuncertaintyproject.org" target="_blank"><b>known unknown</b></a><b>” will take place in 2026?</b><br>A) China invades Taiwan<br>B) Russia finds a pretext to attack another neighbor<br>C) <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/americas/trump-had-several-constructive-interactions-with-brazils-lula-trade-trade-2025-12-10/" target="_blank">Lula and Trump</a> begin to hit it off, and Trump offers the leftist leader his “total and complete endorsement” ahead of Brazil’s fall election<br>D) The west endures irregular but persistent terrorist attacks from non-state actors, like the massacre in Sydney<br></p><p><br><b>14) Democrats will flip the governorship of which state?</b><br>A) Florida<br>B) Ohio<br>C) Iowa<br>D) Alabama<br></p><p><br><b>15) NVDA shares will close 2026 at?</b><br>A) $300<br>B) $250<br>C) $175<br>D) $37 — the tech bubble finally bursts<br></p><p><br><b>16)&nbsp; The results from season one of the Lane Kiffin Experiment at LSU will be:</b><br>A) Drama and a debacle of a year<br>B) Drama and just good enough of a season to make the playoffs<br>C) Drama and dominance, with the Tigers poised to win the national title<br>D) Incomplete because Lane’s interest in hot yoga takes him away from football and he leaves Baton Rouge to embark on a midlife-crisis Eat Pray Love — but with naan, Hinduism and a nice co-ed on the subcontinent<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The federal government’s top watchdog has retired. Now Congress has to pick a replacement.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/30/congress-trump-gao-search-00706651</link>
      <description>The comptroller general’s 15-year term is up, triggering a search for a long-term replacement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-583c-d78e-af9f-fc7f91510000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ac/a2/585024f14ab4b2bf0b1d0ce588dc/congress-covid-investigation-47959.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">J. Scott Applewhite/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Rand Paul, R-Ky., left, and Sen. Gary Peters, D-Mich., will lead a search for the next head of the Government Accountability Office.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ac/a2/585024f14ab4b2bf0b1d0ce588dc/congress-covid-investigation-47959.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the first time in nearly two decades, Congress is on the hunt for a new boss at the federal government’s top watchdog agency.</p> 
<p>With the retirement of comptroller general Gene Dodaro, longtime Government Accountability Office employee Orice Williams Brown is stepping in to lead the more-than-3,000-person agency <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/10/congress/the-federal-governments-next-top-watchdog-is-queued-up-00685439" target="_blank">in an acting capacity</a>.</p> 
<p>Congressional leaders are now supposed to recommend candidates for President Donald Trump to nominate for a 15-year term. If confirmed by the Senate, that person will lead the agency as it works through dozens of investigations into whether the Trump administration broke the law throughout 2025 by withholding billions of dollars Congress previously approved.</p> 
<p>“We're going to look for someone who's honest,” Sen. Rand Paul said in an interview. “I think it would be a mistake to get somebody who's been real active in political processes.”</p> 
<p>As chair of the Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee, the Kentucky Republican is by law granted a seat on the bipartisan panel of 10 lawmakers tasked with recommending at least three potential replacements for Trump to consider nominating.</p> 
<p>Paul and many other top Republicans on Capitol Hill are fans of GAO. But this past year, other conservatives and Trump’s senior advisers have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/27/gop-declares-war-on-gao-00369762" target="_blank">openly ridiculed</a> the legislative branch office charged with auditing federal agencies, aiding lawmakers in carrying out their constitutional duties and challenging White House actions that encroach on Congress’ power.</p> 
<p>In recent months, the comptroller general has also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/07/gene-dodaro-gao-trump-impoundment-00679550" target="_blank">been under pressure</a> to take legal action against the Trump administration for withholding federal cash — especially after the Supreme Court <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/26/supreme-court-foreign-aid-impoundment-ruling-00583052" target="_blank">appeared to imply</a> this fall that the GAO head is the only plaintiff with standing to sue under decades-old impoundment law.</p> 
<p>The next comptroller general must be "willing to call balls and strikes regardless of which party occupies the White House,” Michigan Democratic Sen. Gary Peters, who will be on the panel to recommend candidates, said in a floor speech this month.</p> 
<p>Dodaro leaves “a legacy of tremendous credibility, integrity and independence,” said Peters, the top Democrat on the Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee.</p> 
<p>From the Senate, the bipartisan panel will also include Majority Leader John Thune, Minority Leader Chuck Schumer and Sen. Chuck Grassley (R-Iowa), the president pro tempore.</p> 
<p>In the House, the roster will include Speaker Mike Johnson, Majority Leader Steve Scalise, Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, House Oversight and Government Reform Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) and Rep. Robert Garcia of California, the Oversight panel’s top Democrat.</p> 
<p>Jeffries said this month that he will be talking to his caucus about what kind of candidates to support.</p> 
<p>Comer, meanwhile, used the GOP buzzphrase “waste, fraud, abuse and mismanagement” to describe the kind of oversight work he wants the next GAO head to focus on.</p> 
<p>“We want them to be aggressive, and we want them to work closely with us on identifying — not just problems, but solutions to the problem,” he said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Comer hailed Dodaro in a tribute speech on the House floor this month as “deeply respected across the government and the oversight community for his integrity, candor and dedication.”</p> 
<p>If history is any indication, it could take a while to seat a long-term replacement.</p> 
<p>Dodaro served as acting director for more than two years before the Senate confirmed him to the post in 2010. There was also a two-year gap before his predecessor, David Walker, was confirmed.</p> 
<p>Paul in a recent interview indicated there has been some discussion about launching the bipartisan selection commission, but “I don’t know much more than that.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The turbulent trajectory of Trump’s ‘Nazi streak’ acolyte</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/30/ingrassia-trump-trajectory-00707668</link>
      <description>Paul Ingrassia’s almost Trumpian survival demonstrates how ideological affinity and personal loyalty can outweigh all other considerations in this administration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-6bb4-d78e-af9f-fff7ee920001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/png" url="https://static.politico.com/c4/38/49f0abba43d8b5bc10c3ecb56799/mag-lippman-ingrassia-illustration.png">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">POLITICO illustration</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.Lippman.IngrassiaCapstone.Illustration</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c4/38/49f0abba43d8b5bc10c3ecb56799/mag-lippman-ingrassia-illustration.png" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Lippman, Daniel Barnes and Sophia Cai</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Lippman, Daniel Barnes and Sophia Cai</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A conservative activist who had caught Donald Trump’s attention with flattery via Substack ahead of the 2024 presidential election<b>&nbsp;</b>imagined a prominent role for himself in a future administration.</p> 
<p>In a group chat with half a dozen Republican operatives and influencers, Paul Ingrassia in October 2023 texted: “Trump needs me as his chief of staff,” according to a screenshot obtained by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“I’m not kidding.”</p> 
<p>Ingrassia, then in his late 20s, had only graduated from Cornell Law School the year before and had yet to be admitted to the New York Bar.</p> 
<p>The coveted job, of course, went to veteran political operator Susie Wiles, who typically shies from the limelight.</p> 
<p>But Ingrassia had gained confidence about his potential path to the White House after his Substack columns, which included arguments that Trump would defeat Ron DeSantis in the primary, caught the then-candidate’s eye.</p> 
<p>Trump responded with handwritten notes and Ingrassia <a href="https://x.com/PaulIngrassia/status/1675306121454657536" target="_blank">posted them on X</a>.</p> 
<p>“Great seeing you at Bedminster — young and handsome,” Trump <a href="https://x.com/PaulIngrassia/status/1672239086214553600" target="_blank" presentation="role" label="wrote to Ingrassia" class="Enhancement rte2-style-brightspot-rte-link-LinkRichTextElement rte2-style-brightspot-rte-link-LinkRichTextElement-start rte2-style-brightspot-rte-link-LinkRichTextElement-end">wrote to Ingrassia</a>.</p> 
<p>Another note, also posted on the social media site in the summer of 2023, read: “Paul, Great seeing you — the man behind the great writings — you are looking good.”</p> 
<p>Ingrassia, 30, would eventually land a series of administration jobs, though not as the president’s top aide. He’s now known in Washington for withdrawing from a Senate confirmation process to lead a federal whistleblower agency <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/20/paul-ingrassia-racist-text-messages-nazi-00613608" target="_blank">after a POLITICO report</a> in October revealed racist comments Ingrassia made in the same group chat where he mused about being chief of staff.</p> 
<p>Ingrassia and his lawyer, Edward Andrew Paltzik, did not respond to requests for comment for this article. In October, Paltzik did not confirm the texts were authentic, saying they could be manipulated and were provided without proper context.</p> 
<p>The GOP-led rejection of Ingrassia’s nomination was a rare break between the administration and a largely compliant Congress. It didn’t result in his ouster. Instead, Ingrassia got an invitation to meet Trump at the White House and another administration post — this time at the General Services Administration that manages federal buildings, IT services and government procurement.</p> 
<p>Alan Jacoby, the founder of Patriot Cigar Company who met Ingrassia through New York Republican circles several years ago, said Ingrassia’s goal before Trump was reelected was to get a position in the administration.</p> 
<p>“We don’t always agree when it comes to political issues even though we’re both conservatives. However, his support for President Trump is unmatched,” he said.</p> 
<p>Ingrassia’s almost Trumpian survival demonstrates how ideological affinity and personal loyalty can outweigh all other considerations in this administration. And while top officials in the Republican Party and White House have split between denouncing bigoted language exhibited by officials like Ingrassia — who said he has a “Nazi streak” according to the texts — and forming a defensive line around supporters, the messages don’t appear to have hurt his official standing.</p> 
<p>GSA spokesperson Marianne Copenhaver hailed Ingrassia’s “outstanding service” in a statement about <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/trump-ingrassia-gsa-texts-00651340" target="_blank">his new role</a> as GSA’s deputy general counsel just weeks after GOP Sen. Rick Scott of Florida <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/20/congress/rick-scott-to-oppose-ingrassia-00616006" target="_blank">said he wouldn’t support</a> his nomination to lead the Office of Special Counsel because he didn’t understand “how anybody can be antisemitic in this country.”</p> 
<p>The schism remains at the heart of an unsettled question about MAGA’s future and whether a Trump-style successor can emerge when others who’ve deployed a similarly bombastic and divisive approach to leadership have failed. Where many young Republican staffers lost government or party positions when inflammatory texts were made public in a different <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/private-chat-among-young-gop-club-members-00592146?fbclid=IwY2xjawNb9i1leHRuA2FlbQIxMQABHmKRzrB1VNFo-126u8LMDQr3o4kNQCTXFIFInRz1KQFKrtZ8pEAeO6p-fxhG_aem_mprW2U1IWF9k7Op3kebMoQ" target="_blank">POLITICO investigation</a> involving a separate text chain this year, Ingrassia got another senior administration post. In that sense he’s like Trump himself, who only gained more staying power during everything from the Access Hollywood video to the Jan. 6, 2021, riot.</p> 
<p>For this article about Ingrassia’s journey from a once-obscure MAGA acolyte to a Trump world fixture, POLITICO spoke to more than two dozen administration officials, senators, Capitol Hill staffers and others who know Ingrassia. POLITICO also reviewed contemporaneous messages of former law school classmates and fellow conservative influencers. Many of the people were granted anonymity to speak candidly about Ingrassia because of retaliation concerns or because they weren’t authorized to speak publicly. The White House did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Law school controversy</h5> 
<p>Ingrassia’s time in the administration has echoes of his law school experience.</p> 
<p>He had trouble fitting into his cohort at Cornell Law, three former classmates told POLITICO, describing him as a quiet and closely guarded person.</p> 
<p>But Ingrassia did draw attention — if unwanted — during his time at Cornell. In the wake of the 2020 election, while classes were partially virtual due to the Covid-19 pandemic, a classmate shared with other students a screenshot of a Twitter post by Ingrassia’s mother repeating claims that Trump was the legitimate winner of the 2020 presidential election, according to two of the former classmates.</p> 
<p>“For a little change of pace, here’s Paul’s batshit crazy mom,” the classmate who posted the screenshot wrote in a GroupMe chat for the entire Cornell Law class of 2022, according to the two classmates in the chat. The post was swiftly deleted.</p> 
<p>“Following some sage counsel here and issuing an unqualified apology. We obviously have some strong disagreements, but ‘your mom is batshit crazy’ is obviously well over the line and it’s incredibly unfortunate that I posted it here. My bad,” the classmate wrote a short time later, according to a copy of the message.</p> 
<p>Reached for comment by POLITICO, Ingrassia’s mother, Donna Gallo Ingrassia, a Long Island real estate broker, defended standing up for what she believes.</p> 
<p>“We are a family who stands up for what we believe in even if it is against the popular viewpoint,” she said in an email. “We fought for my daughter’s former classmate Gabby Petito [who was killed in Wyoming in 2021], fought against vaccine and mask mandates, we fought against the steal of 2020 and we campaigned hard for President Trump.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">A rocky entry</h5> 
<p>Years later, Ingrassia had the backing of his mother who <a href="https://www.notus.org/trump-white-house/paul-ingrassia-donna-ingrassia-raskin-garcia" target="_blank">trekked to the Hill</a> to confront Democratic lawmakers who criticized her son’s nomination. “Obviously, I am going to advocate for my kids,” she told POLITICO. “People who do not ‘go along to get along’ are usually called ‘crazy.’”</p> 
<p>Ingrassia’s bond with Trump only strengthened after those handwritten notes Ingrassia posted on X in 2023. In time, he would call himself “Trump’s favorite writer” after Trump reposted more than 100 of his Substack articles.</p> 
<p>So when Trump took office a second time, Ingrassia was poised to thrive. He landed a position as White House liaison to the Justice Department. While most incoming Trump appointees were partying at balls on the night of Trump’s inauguration, Ingrassia spent more than an hour inside the D.C. Central Detention Facility.</p> 
<p>He emerged to <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/01/20/politics/january-6-2021-capitol-riot-pardons-trump" target="_blank">announce that two people</a> who had pled guilty to assaulting police officers during the Jan. 6 riot at the Capitol were being released after receiving pardons from the president.</p> 
<p>It is “a monumental moment in our history,” Ingrassia told reporters.</p> 
<p>But Ingrassia’s time at DOJ quickly went downhill.</p> 
<p>Inside the department, he clashed with then-DOJ chief of staff Chad Mizelle after <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/after-clashes-ags-top-aide-white-house-liaison/story?id=119108504" target="_blank">Ingrassia reportedly complained</a> to the president that Mizelle was not working to advance his agenda. DOJ and Mizelle declined to comment.</p> 
<p>It didn’t help Ingrassia that he lacked a relationship with Attorney General Pam Bondi, according to a DOJ official. That official added that Ingrassia did not generally know anyone in the department.</p> 
<p>The official said he believes Ingrassia was a “Day 1” person sent by the White House, as the new administration placed loyalists across the government. The official added that people in the department knew Trump had done social media posts on Ingrassia’s writings.</p> 
<p>The connection wasn’t enough. A month after he arrived at Justice, he was reassigned to the Department of Homeland Security. But his time there was even rockier.</p> 
<p>Ingrassia seemed to want to build a rapport with colleagues, frequently attending DHS and administration happy hours to network, according to two people who saw him at the events. Despite his brashness on social media, Ingrassia was reserved in social settings, said the two people.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">The scandals</h5> 
<p>But Ingrassia quickly encountered problems at DHS. In July, he took a work trip to Florida where he shared a Ritz-Carlton hotel room with a female colleague. An internal investigation ensued. The attorney for Ingrassia and a DHS spokesperson said the investigation into him ended and cleared him. His attorney denied wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Ingrassia sued POLITICO for defamation in Warren County, Virginia, in October after POLITICO reported on the Florida trip.</p> 
<p>Ingrassia faced additional scrutiny over the summer after Trump nominated him in May to lead the Office of Special Counsel, which investigates complaints from federal whistleblowers.</p> 
<p>A day after the nomination, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/05/30/nx-s1-5417902/trump-ingrassia-antisemitism-ethics" target="_blank">NPR reported</a> that Ingrassia had called far-right influencer Andrew Tate an “extraordinary man” and “the embodiment of the ancient ideal of excellence.” Before joining the administration Ingrassia worked at a law firm Tate hired. Tate, who has been an advocate for “Holocaust revisionism,” has faced rape and human trafficking charges. He has denied the charges, which are pending.</p> 
<p>On Capitol Hill, staffers on the Senate Homeland Security Committee started looking into Ingrassia’s background. Three Democratic Senate aides <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/23/how-senate-republican-finally-said-no-to-ingrassia-00619273" target="_blank">said in an interview</a> that a staff vetting session on July 21 went poorly for Ingrassia. They said they were troubled he didn’t provide his full biographical information and that he pushed back when asked about the omission of numerous posts, podcasts, interviews and deleted writings.</p> 
<p>Several staffers from Republican offices also asked tough questions of Ingrassia. Among them were his views on the Oct. 7, 2023, attacks in Israel, which <a href="https://x.com/paulingrassia/status/1711033657065132504" target="_blank">he had called</a> “another psyop to distract Americans from celebrating Columbus Day.”</p> 
<p>Just before Ingrassia was set to testify on July 24, his appearance was postponed.</p> 
<p>“This big thing for our state is, he’s had some statements about antisemitism,” Scott, a member of the committee, said at the time.</p> 
<p>In August, Ingrassia also lost a key ally at the White House. Sergio Gor, another controversial Trump aide who had been serving as presidential personnel director, was nominated to serve as ambassador to India in a shakeup. Gor, who had <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/08/musk-trump-ceasefire-call-00393527?utm_content=user/politico&amp;utm_source=flipboard" target="_blank">drawn the personal antipathy of Elon Musk</a> for trying to wrest back control of agencies after a heated March Cabinet meeting, worked closely with Ingrassia and supported his nomination, according to three administration officials. His departure deprived Ingrassia of an influential defender.</p> 
<p>Replacing Gor was Dan Scavino, a White House deputy chief of staff and one of Trump’s closest aides, with whom Ingrassia was not as close, according to two of the administration officials.</p> 
<p>Ingrassia still had other defenders in the West Wing, including Trump aide Natalie Harp, according to two administration officials. Harp is known as Trump’s “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/25/us/politics/trump-natalie-harp.html" target="_blank">human printer</a>” because she prints out articles for him to read, including many of Ingrassia’s Substack pieces.</p> 
<p>“Natalie Harp in the White House is a big advocate of Paul’s,” one of the officials said.</p> 
<p>Gor and Harp were natural allies. Like Ingrassia, they rose to their positions thanks to their fierce loyalty to Trump. Like Ingrassia, they lacked establishment bona fides. Like Trump, they protected their own.</p> 
<p>Gor, Scavino and Harp did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>Two months after Gor’s August nomination, Ingrassia was scheduled to appear before the homeland security panel for a Senate confirmation hearing that was supposed to take place on a Thursday. He was in a “murder board” prep session on the preceding Monday afternoon to prepare for the expected avalanche of questions about his background and controversies, according to four administration officials.</p> 
<p>But that same afternoon, POLITICO <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/20/paul-ingrassia-racist-text-messages-nazi-00613608" target="_blank">published its</a> article on his inflammatory texts. The reporting revealed that on a January 2024 text chain with Republican operatives and influencers, Ingrassia said the MLK Jr. holiday should be “tossed in the seventh circle of hell” and that Juneteenth and Kwanza “should also be canceled,” according to the chat. Paltzik, Ingrassia’s lawyer, said at the time that even if they were authentic, they were meant to be self-deprecating and satirical.</p> 
<p>The reaction was swift. Senate Majority Leader John Thune <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/21/congress/john-thune-paul-ingrassia-hearing-00616569" target="_blank">told reporters</a> he hoped the White House would withdraw the nomination and that Ingrassia couldn’t pass.</p> 
<p>Hours later, Ingrassia <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/trump-pulls-ingrassia-nomination-racist-texts-00617041" target="_blank">posted on X</a> that he was withdrawing his nomination “because unfortunately I do not have enough Republican votes at this time.” He said he was grateful for the “overwhelming support” he received during the process “and will continue to serve President Trump and this administration to Make America Great Again!”</p> 
<p>Even people close to the White House with knowledge of how staffers felt about Ingrassia said the revelations of the text messages were not a surprise given his association to extremists like Tate and white nationalist Nick Fuentes.</p> 
<p>But since nominations are ultimately chosen by Trump, West Wing staffers back candidates until it becomes evident there are simply not enough votes to confirm them, according to two people who were involved in the process.</p> 
<p>Some White House staffers were ultimately “relieved” that he withdrew his nomination, said the first person close to the administration.</p> 
<p>“The writing was on the wall early on, and I think the recent changes at [the White House Presidential Personnel Office] allow this nomination to finally die,” the first person added, noting that there was “the onslaught of accusations and many people [questioned] his qualifications to begin with” when Trump tapped him.</p> 
<p>Even if staffers aren’t fully on board with everyone Trump chooses, the first person said, the feeling is “let’s have the process work itself out” and “be loyal to the pick but be realistic and move on when needed.”</p> 
<p>“Not sure anyone is like heartbroken,” the second person added. “It was never expected that it would go through, at least I never did.”</p> 
<p>One reason he has kept a job is because Trump rewards his personal champions.</p> 
<p>“Paul’s been a steadfast supporter of President Trump and a leader in the America First movement,” said Caroline Wren, a Republican strategist <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/09/january-6-rally-contempt-ruling-00444812" target="_blank">who served as a liaison</a> between the Trump White House and participants in the Jan. 6 rally preceding the Capitol riot.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">More trouble ahead?</h5> 
<p>Already there are questions about Ingrassia’s credentials at GSA, where he quickly moved from deputy general counsel to acting general counsel in a few weeks. An <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/about-us/organization/leadership-directory/acting-general-counsel" target="_blank">announcement</a> about his elevation to a position that oversees more than 100 attorneys cites his key role in swiftly filling the DOJ and DHS with trusted political appointees.</p> 
<p>“What are we? A halfway house for bigots who can’t find jobs anywhere else in this administration?” a GSA official said. Ingrassia’s predecessor at GSA, Russell “Rusty” McGranahan, had a three-decade career at top firms, including BlackRock and White &amp; Case. He recently became a senior adviser to the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p> 
<p>“Rusty was well qualified and served the administration well. I just want the government to be staffed with experienced people who are taken seriously,” the official added.</p> 
<p>Another person familiar with the internal workings of GSA said that Ingrassia “basically won’t be given anything meaningful because [agency] leadership doesn’t really want him.”</p> 
<p>“I don’t know what he is or is not, but no one cares for him,” the person added.</p> 
<p>Earlier this month, six Senate Democrats <a href="https://static.politico.com/d7/e5/6a4a2b364c0d980542f1de696e4e/letter-to-gsa-and-ppo-re-ingrassia-final242.pdf" target="_blank">sent a letter</a> to the White House and the GSA calling Ingrassia’s continued employment in the federal government “unacceptable,” citing POLITICO’s reporting.</p> 
<p>“The Democrats clearly understand that Paul is a very intelligent, strong supporter of President Trump, which is why they want him out,” Ingrassia’s mother said.</p> 
<p>Copenhaver, the GSA spokesperson, said that Ingrassia has a bright future at the agency.</p> 
<p>“Paul Ingrassia is a well-regarded attorney who has provided outstanding service to President Trump and will continue to do so as GSA’s acting general counsel,” Copenhaver said. “The GSA has complete confidence in his ability to further both its mission and the president’s priorities.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 ways China-US relations could fracture in 2026</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/26/china-u-s-relations-could-fracture-2026-00703020</link>
      <description>Dozens of lawmakers foresee a surge in tensions over trade, Taiwan or supply chain disruptions possibly scuttling the current pause in US-China economic hostilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4876-d78e-af9f-fc77749d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/73/7a/9ed320de418fa652c64c42fcfea0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2243542833">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Andrew Caballero-Reynolds/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Lawmakers predict that the easing of U.S.-China tensions that President Donald Trump and China's leader Xi Jinping brokered in South Korea in October will be short-lived.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/73/7a/9ed320de418fa652c64c42fcfea0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2243542833" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Phelim Kine</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Phelim Kine</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The message from Capitol Hill on both sides of the aisle is clear: Get ready for U.S. relations with China to spiral all over again in the new year.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/fact-sheets/2025/11/fact-sheet-president-donald-j-trump-strikes-deal-on-economic-and-trade-relations-with-china/" target="_blank">The one-year trade truce</a> brokered in October between President Donald Trump and Chinese leader Xi Jinping <a href="https://asiatimes.com/2025/11/us-china-in-a-hot-and-fragile-truce/" target="_blank">is already looking shaky</a>. And lawmakers are preparing to reup clashes over trade, Taiwan and cyber-intrusions when they return in January.</p> 
<p><b>“</b>It's like a heavyweight fight, and we're in that short time period in-between rounds, but both sides need to be preparing for what is next after the truce,” Rep. Greg Stanton (D-Ariz.), a member of the House Select Committee on China, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>POLITICO talked to more than 25 lawmakers, including those on the House Select Committee on China, the House Foreign Affairs Committee’s East Asia subcommittee and the Congressional Executive Commission on China, for their views on the durability of the trade treaty. Both Republicans and Democrats warned of turbulence ahead.</p> 
<p>More than 20 of the lawmakers said they doubt Xi will deliver on key pledges the White House said he made in October, including <a href="https://www.politico.eu/newsletter/china-watcher/china-committee-busts-beijings-fentanyl-racket/" target="_blank">reducing the flow of precursor chemicals</a> to Mexico that cartels process into fentanyl and buying agreed volumes of U.S. agricultural goods.</p> 
<p>“China can never be trusted. They’re always looking for an angle,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) said.</p> 
<p>That pessimism comes despite an easing in U.S.-China tensions since the Trump-Xi meeting in South Korea. The bruising cycle of tit-for-tat tariffs that briefly hit triple digits earlier this year is currently on pause. Both countries have relaxed export restrictions on essential items (<a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/national-security-daily/2025/06/11/trade-deals-cant-stop-chinas-rare-earth-edge-00400475" target="_blank">rare earths for the U.S.</a>, chip design software for China), while Beijing has committed to <a href="https://english.mofcom.gov.cn/News/SpokesmansRemarks/art/2025/art_d3b018b922a4458989e43a46a04be6fe.html" target="_blank">"expanding agricultural product trade"</a> in an apparent reference to the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/28/soybeans-sacrificed-in-trumps-china-gamble-00583232" target="_blank">suspension of imports of U.S. agricultural products</a> it imposed earlier this year.</p> 
<p>This trend may continue, given that Trump is likely to want stability in the U.S.-China relationship ahead of a summit with Xi planned for April in Beijing. “We’re starting to see some movement now on some of their tariff issues and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/01/white-house-china-trade-truce-00632759" target="_blank">the fentanyl precursor issue</a>,” Sen. Steve Daines (R-Mont.) said.</p> 
<p>But a series of issues have been brushed aside in negotiations or left in limbo — a status quo the Trump administration can only maintain for so long. The U.S.-China trade deal on rare earths that Bessent said the two countries <a href="https://www.scmp.com/news/us/economy-trade-business/article/3333010/china-rare-earths-deal-will-hopefully-be-done-thanksgiving-says-scott-bessent" target="_blank">would finalize by Thanksgiving</a> remains unsettled. And the White House hasn’t confirmed <a href="https://apnews.com/article/tiktok-divestment-deal-trump-2fdb915cac5b6d06907a5a2de6764376" target="_blank">reporting from earlier this month</a> that Beijing-based ByteDance has finalized the sale of the TikTok social media app ahead of the Jan. 23 deadline for that agreement.</p> 
<p>“The idea that we’re in a period of stability with Beijing is simply not accurate,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), ranking member of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.</p> 
<p>Shaheen has been sounding the alarm on China’s national security threats since she entered the Senate in 2009. But even some lawmakers who have been more open to engagement with Beijing — such as California Democratic Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/218327" data-person-id="218327">Ro Khanna</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/199004" data-person-id="199004">Ami Bera</a> — said that they don’t expect the armistice to last.</p> 
<p>The White House is more upbeat about the prospects for U.S.-China trade ties. </p> 
<p>"President Trump’s close relationship with President Xi is helping ensure that both countries are able to continue building on progress and continue resolving outstanding issues," the White House said in a statement, adding that the administration "continues to monitor China’s compliance with our trade agreement." It declined to comment on the TikTok deal.</p> 
<p>Still, the lawmakers POLITICO spoke with described four issues that could derail U.S.-China ties in the New Year:</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">A soybean spoiler</h4> 
<p>U.S. soybean farmers' reliance on the Chinese market gives Beijing a powerful non-tariff trade weapon — and China doesn’t appear to be following through on promises to renew purchases.</p> 
<p>The standoff over soybeans started in May, when China <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/28/soybeans-sacrificed-in-trumps-china-gamble-00583232" target="_blank">halted those purchases</a>, raising the prospect of financial ruin across farming states including Illinois, Iowa, Minnesota, Nebraska and Indiana — key political constituencies for the GOP in the congressional midterm elections next year.</p> 
<p>The White House said last month that Xi committed to buying 12 million metric tons of U.S. soybeans in November and December. But so far, Beijing has only purchased a fraction of that agreed total, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/09/china-buys-us-soybeans-trump-trade-agreement.html" target="_blank">NBC reported this month</a>.</p> 
<p>“What agitates Trump and causes him to react quickly are things that are more domestic and closer to home,” Rep. Jill Tokuda (D-Hawaii) said. China’s foot-dragging on soybean purchases “is the most triggering because it’s hurting American farmers and consumers, so that’s where we could see the most volatility in the relationship,” she said.</p> 
<p>That trigger could come on Feb. 28 — the new deadline for that 12 million metric ton purchase, which Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent <a href="https://www.agriculture.com/partners-china-soybean-buying-deadline-now-february-bessent-says-11863378" target="_blank">announced earlier this month</a>.</p> 
<p>The Chinese embassy in Washington declined to comment on whether Beijing plans to meet this deadline.</p> 
<p>The White House said one of the aspects of the trade deal it is monitoring is soybean purchases through this growing season.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">The Taiwan tinderbox</h4> 
<p>Beijing’s threats to invade Taiwan are another near-term potential flashpoint, even though the U.S. hasn’t prioritized the issue in its national security strategy or <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115605897178712132" target="_blank">talks between Xi and Trump</a>.</p> 
<p>China has increased its preparations for a Taiwan invasion this year. In October, the Chinese military debuted <a href="https://www.navalnews.com/naval-news/2025/01/china-suddenly-building-fleet-of-special-barges-suitable-for-taiwan-landings/" target="_blank">a new military barge system</a> that addresses some of the challenges of landing on the island’s beaches by deploying a bridge for cargo ships to unload tanks or trucks directly onto the shore.</p> 
<p>“China is tightening the noose around the island,” said Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), who joined a bipartisan congressional delegation to China in September and returned <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/national-security-daily/2025/09/29/potential-opening-on-military-comms-with-beijing-00585427" target="_blank">calling for better communications</a> between the U.S. and Chinese militaries.</p> 
<p>Some of the tension around Taiwan is playing out in the wider region, as Beijing pushes to expand its military reach and its influence. Chinese <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c5yqe197ypno" target="_blank">fighter jets locked radar</a> — a prelude to opening fire — on Japanese aircraft earlier this month in the East China Sea.</p> 
<p>“There is a real chance that Xi overplays his hand on antagonizing our allies, particularly Australia and Japan,” Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.) said. “There is still a line [China] cannot cross without making this truce impossible to sustain.”</p> 
<p>The U.S. has a decades-long <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/09/19/biden-leaves-no-doubt-strategic-ambiguity-toward-taiwan-is-dead-00057658" target="_blank">policy of “strategic ambiguity”</a> under which it refuses to spell out how the U.S. would respond to Chinese aggression against Taiwan. Trump has also adhered to that policy. “You’ll find out if it happens,” Trump said in <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/world/asia/trump-says-chinas-xi-assured-wont-take-action-taiwan-during-his-term-rcna241521" target="_blank">an interview with 60 Minutes in November.</a></p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">More export restrictions on the way</h4> 
<p>Beijing has eased its export restrictions on rare earths — metallic elements essential to both civilian and military applications — but could reimpose those blocks at any time.</p> 
<p>Ten of the 25 lawmakers who spoke to POLITICO said they suspect Beijing will reimpose those export curbs as a convenient pressure point in the coming months.</p> 
<p>“At the center of the crack in the truce is China’s ability to levy export restrictions, especially its chokehold on the global supply of rare earths and other critical minerals,” Rep. André Carson (D-Ind.) said.</p> 
<p>Others are worried China will choose to expand its export controls to another product category for which it has market dominance — pharmaceuticals. Beijing supplies <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/politics/supply-chain-ai-company-sounds-alarm-over-americas-reliance-chinese-made-pharmaceuticals" target="_blank">80 percent of the U.S. supply</a> of active pharmaceutical ingredients — the foundations of common drugs to treat everything from high blood pressure to type 2 diabetes.</p> 
<p>“Overnight, China could turn off the spigot and many basic pharmaceuticals, including things like aspirin, go away from the supply chain in the United States,” Rep. Nathaniel Moran (R-Texas) said.</p> 
<p>China restarted exports of rare earths earlier this month, and its Commerce Ministry pledged “timely approval” of such exports under a new licensing system, <a href="https://english.news.cn/20251204/2e83b4e979a44409a86f33e4263a7a15/c.html" target="_blank">state media reported</a>. Beijing has not indicated its intent to restrict the export of pharmaceuticals or their components as a trade weapon. But the U.S.-China Economic and Security Review Commission urged the Food and Drug Administration to reduce U.S. reliance on Chinese sources of pharmaceuticals in its <a href="https://www.uscc.gov/sites/default/files/2025-11/2025_Annual_Report_to_Congress.pdf" target="_blank">annual report last month</a>.</p> 
<p>The Chinese embassy in Washington didn’t respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Growing Chinese military muscle</h4> 
<p>China’s drive to develop a world-class military that can challenge traditional U.S. dominion of the Indo-Pacific could also derail relations between Washington and Beijing in 2026.</p> 
<p>China’s <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4gmnpg31xlo" target="_blank">expanding navy</a>— which, at more than 200 warships, is now <a href="https://www.csis.org/analysis/unpacking-chinas-naval-buildup" target="_blank">the world’s largest</a> — is helping Beijing show off its power across the region.</p> 
<p>The centerpiece of that effort in 2025 has been the addition of a third aircraft carrier, the Fujian, which entered into service last month. The Fujian is two-thirds the size of the USS Gerald R. Ford carrier. But like the Ford, it boasts state-of-the-art <a href="https://www.globaltimes.cn/page/202511/1347603.shtml" target="_blank">electromagnetic catapults</a> to launch J-35 and J-15T fighter jets.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration sees that as a threat.</p> 
<p>The U.S. aims to insulate allies and partners in the Indo-Pacific from possible Chinese “sustained successful military aggression” powered by Beijing’s “historic military buildup,” Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth <a href="https://www.war.gov/News/Speeches/Speech/Article/4354431/remarks-by-secretary-of-war-pete-hegseth-at-the-reagan-national-defense-forum-a/" target="_blank">said earlier this month</a> at the Reagan National Defense Forum.</p> 
<p>Five lawmakers said they see China’s increasingly aggressive regional military footprint as incompatible with U.S. efforts to maintain a stable relationship with Beijing in the months ahead.</p> 
<p>“We know the long-term goal of China is really economic and diplomatic and military domination around the world, and they see the United States as an adversary,” Moran said.</p> 
<p><i>Daniel Desrochers contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 policy heavyweights endangered by redistricting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/three-policy-heavyweights-endangered-by-redistricting-00704852</link>
      <description>New House lines are set to reverberate through key committees where at-risk lawmakers have shaped policy for decades.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4cd9-dba9-addb-7fff95ff0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9f/fa/f419fc5542238b61d7e2ff925d7e/congress-house-appropriations-39899.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">J. Scott Applewhite/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Ken Calvert, R-Calif., chairman of the House Appropriations Defense Subcommittee arrives for a closed markup hearing on the Fiscal Year 2024 spending bill for the Pentagon, at the Capitol in Washington, Thursday, June 15, 2023.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9f/fa/f419fc5542238b61d7e2ff925d7e/congress-house-appropriations-39899.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Members of both parties have yet to reckon with one inevitable consequence of the redistricting fight that’s rippling across the country — the loss of years of policy expertise on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>While many of the lawmakers at risk of losing their seats in the redistricting wars have only a few years under their belt, several senior lawmakers who have spent decades building their legislative portfolios and climbing the ranks of the most powerful House committees are also now seeing their political futures threatened.</p> 
<p>They include Rep. Rob Wittman (R-Va.), who aims to be the next chair of the Armed Services Committee, and Rep. Ken Calvert (R-Calif.), an appropriations “cardinal” who oversees funds for the military and defense agencies.</p> 
<p>And then there’s Rep. Lloyd Doggett (D-Texas), a vocal progressive and the second-most senior Democrat on the Ways and Means Committee, who is choosing to retire rather than compete against his younger colleague, rising progressive star Greg Casar.</p> 
<p>The departure of any one of these members would go beyond simply scrambling party ratios and potentially determining the House majority in the 2026 midterms; their displacement would impact the ideological makeups of their respective committees and leave gaping knowledge voids.</p> 
<p>Here’s how a House without Doggett, Calvert and Wittman could change how Congress approaches taxation, health, defense and national security.</p> 
<h2><b>A progressive policy voice</b></h2> 
<p><br>Doggett has spent 50 years in politics and three decades in the House. As the top Democrat on the House Ways and Means Subcommittee on Health, the Austin-area lawmaker is known for his attacks on corporate influence over politics and the machinations of Big Pharma, and worked to end lower tax rates for American companies that offshore their profits.</p> 
<p>And as the second-most-senior Democrat on the committee, Doggett also has a reputation for representing the interests of progressives on a panel stacked with moderates. He has over the years been one of the only Democratic tax writers willing to privately challenge Ways and Means ranking member Richard Neal (D-Mass.), who has been criticized at times for being <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/10/24/richard-neal-son-congress-lobbying-00181853" target="_blank"><u>too close to special interests</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“He’s been sort of a lone voice fighting against Big Pharma, against [pharmacy benefit managers], against Medicare Advantage, against price-gouging,” said fellow committee member Don Beyer (D-Va.) in an interview. “He’s never hesitated to disagree with Richie, too … Lloyd doesn’t just roll over.”</p> 
<p>Doggett, in an interview, recalled efforts to amend drug pricing legislation authored by then-Speaker Nancy Pelosi during a 2019 committee markup, ignoring instructions from leadership not to do so.</p> 
<p>“I offered amendments that were opposed and defeated by Chairman Neal … to extend coverage to the uninsured,” said Doggett. “The committee’s position was that it had to be done just the way Pelosi submitted it.”</p> 
<p>Asked for comment, a Neal spokesperson referred to the lawmaker’s statement at the time of Doggett’s retirement, which recognized the Texan as “a bulldog in the fight for the little guy.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.), the former chair of the Congressional Progressive Caucus, recalled in an interview that Doggett helped keep the Democrats’ signature party-line legislation of 2022 from straying too far to the middle.</p> 
<p>“Lloyd was our leader on Ways and Means, definitely around billionaire taxes and stock buybacks,” she said. “He’s willing to stand up to party leadership, which is often necessary on that committee and, in general, on some of these tax issues.”</p> 
<h2><b>A defense appropriations guru</b></h2> 
<p><br>California’s redistricting plans have set the stage for a contentious primary fight between GOP Reps. Ken Calvert and Young Kim. It has many Republicans openly fretting about the implications of losing Calvert, who has spent two-and-a-half decades working on defense policy on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>A fellow California Republican, Rep. Darrell Issa, was caught on hot mic in early December<a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/5635469-darrell-issa-concerns-california-map/" target="_blank"><u>saying Kim should step aside</u></a> and consider a position in the administration because “with Ken, we need him exactly where he is.”</p> 
<p>Another defense appropriator, Rep. Mario Diaz-Balart (R-Fla.), said in a recent interview that “for the national security of the United States, it’s hard to find somebody who is more important than Ken Calvert. … He knows defense, the intricacies, the details like nobody — like nobody.”</p> 
<p>Calvert’s expertise is so revered he obtained a waiver from House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) to serve beyond his term limit as the head of the Defense subcommittee in the current Congress; he’s not likely to get a waiver for the next one.</p> 
<p>Still, colleagues say Calvert is regarded as an institutional encyclopedia on defense spending matters, regularly citing data points from his vast knowledge of military history, the history of weapons systems, various bureaucracies within the defense sphere and the strategies of rival world powers.</p> 
<p>Calvert has also taken the lead on infusing new money into defense programs focused on innovative weapons and logistics systems, launching a $100 million dollar initiative in 2022 to speed up the production and acquisition of cutting-edge military technology.</p> 
<p>“He’s got institutional knowledge that is very rare. There’s only a few members who have that much time in the House,” said Defense subcommittee vice chair Jake Ellzey (R-Texas) in an interview. “And that institutional knowledge is irreplaceable, unless you get somebody who’s been working it that long, and there’s nobody that even comes close.”</p> 
<p>Calvert, in a statement, called himself “uniquely qualified to work with the Trump Administration” as “a senior member of the Appropriations Committee and having worked in this space for many years.”</p> 
<h2><b>An advocate for Virginia’s defense community</b></h2> 
<p><br>Wittman, who was first elected in 2007, has long been eyeing the opportunity to ascend to the top GOP position on the House Armed Services Committee once the current chair, Rep. Mike Rogers (R-Ala.), completes his three-term tenure at the end of 2026. The Virginia Republican has held leadership roles across multiple subcommittees and now presides over the Tactical Air &amp; Land Forces subpanel.</p> 
<p>“[He is] very knowledgeable, carries himself very well, very well respected,” said Rep. Carlos Gimenez (R-Fla.), a member of Wittman’s subcommittee, in an interview.</p> 
<p>But Wittman’s seat has been a top target of Democrats’ mid-decade redistricting plans, which could result in making the 1st Congressional District much bluer.</p> 
<p>Wittman has been a fierce advocate of his state’s shipbuilding industry — which is responsible for producing aircraft carriers and a fleet of nuclear-attack submarines — and sees the equipment as critical to the U.S. military’s readiness for potential conflict with China in the Pacific.</p> 
<p>One House GOP aide who works on national security issues, granted anonymity to speak candidly, argued that Democrats’ targeting of Wittman in its proposed redistricting map is risky for the future of Virginia’s defense infrastructure and industry at large.</p> 
<p>The aide speculated that the Trump administration could someday slow the construction of aircraft carriers in light of questions about their efficacy in modern warfare or even target bases in Virginia for realignment and closure.</p> 
<p>“They’re taking a gamble,” the aide said of Democratic attempts to unseat a champion of the state’s defense industry with influence and seniority. “They’re trading political dominance for potential irrelevance in the defense sphere.”</p> 
<p>Abigail Gost, a spokesperson for Wittman, said that the congressman has no plans to leave Congress and “believes continuity and experience matter — especially at a time of heightened global instability and rapid change”</p> 
<p><i>Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The internal dispute that could derail the GOP’s 2026 agenda</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698</link>
      <description>With the midterms around the corner, top Republican voices are clashing about the prospects for another reconciliation bill.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4c64-d78e-af9f-fc775af40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5b/9a/9e79e6a247629a62d12f4ebf8994/u-s-congress-78162.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Texas Reps. August Pfluger (left) and Jodey Arrington (right) are among the most prominent Republicans pushing another reconciliation bill.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5b/9a/9e79e6a247629a62d12f4ebf8994/u-s-congress-78162.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With the midterms bearing down on them, Republicans are facing a nasty intraparty fight early next year over their legislative agenda: Should they attempt to pass a party-line bill focused on health care after failing to address expiring insurance subsidies?</p> 
<p>GOP factions have been divided for months about the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/05/second-megabill-doubts-republicans-00545855" target="_blank">prospect of a second reconciliation bill</a>. Some see it as the party’s last, best chance to put wins on the board before Election Day, while others believe it is a recipe for failure given the small Republican majorities in the House and Senate and major internal divides over health policy.</p> 
<p>But Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> is publicly leaning into the possibility as he tries to appease hard-liners who wanted the House GOP to go much farther <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">than it did this month</a> in pushing a conservative health care overhaul.</p> 
<p>Some rank-and-file conservatives in the House and Senate are privately discussing a potential centerpiece for a second reconciliation bill: using tariff revenues to send taxpayers cash to address rising health care costs after enhanced Obamacare subsidies expire Dec. 31, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the talks.</p> 
<p>The pressure from the right is threatening to outweigh skepticism from many senior Republicans who are deeply wary about moving forward. At least one key Republican <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/jason-smith-reconciliation-2026-00698324" target="_blank">is publicly questioning</a> whether the GOP can muster the unity necessary to navigate the reconciliation process a second time after last summer’s struggle to enact the tax-cuts-focused megabill.</p> 
<p>“I don't see a path of a second reconciliation ever passing,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> of Missouri, who as Ways and Means Committee chair oversees tax policy and some health care matters.</p> 
<p>Furthermore, nearly every other House chair has shared similar doubts in private conversations with GOP leaders and senior Republicans, according to three other people granted anonymity to discuss internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>The most prominent voices in the senior GOP ranks in either chamber arguing for a fresh push are the chairs of the Budget committees. They hold powerful roles as gatekeepers for the reconciliation process and get to define the fiscal parameters for legislation that could skirt a Senate Democratic filibuster and pass without bipartisan cooperation.</p> 
<p>“We need to actually follow through on the policies we've been popping off about for years that we believe will actually help everybody,” said House Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259549" data-person-id="259549">Jodey Arrington</a> (R-Texas), who recently <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/11/congress/jodey-arrington-retire-house-budget-00646259" target="_blank">announced his retirement</a>. “I feel like there's a critical mass to start that process.”</p> 
<p>Senate Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) has been similarly bullish, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/06/congress/lindsey-graham-reconciliation-00640338" target="_blank">pushing alongside members of his committee</a> to advance a reconciliation blueprint early next year. He recently <a href="https://www.semafor.com/article/12/22/2025/budget-chair-graham-plots-next-republican-party-line-bill" target="_blank">told Semafor</a> he wants the bill to focus on health care, military funding and immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>Other committee chairs, who have to actually craft the bills sketched out in the budget blueprint, aren’t as convinced. Many GOP health initiatives, they believe, won’t comply with the strict fiscal rules governing reconciliation — a point they’ve made privately to senators pushing for a second bill. And some members of leadership are cool to the idea of tapping tariff revenue for anything other than deficit reduction.</p> 
<p>That’s not to mention the pushback coming from vulnerable House Republicans, many of whom had to take big political risks in backing the summer megabill, which included deep cuts to Medicaid spending. They are now wary of engaging in another divisive health care debate.</p> 
<p>In one heated closed-door meeting this month where Johnson was present, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) shot down talk of another GOP party-line bill, saying it would “never” happen. Even one House Republican who supports the idea acknowledged it would be “like having a baby” — both in terms of the level of political pain and the laborious process.</p> 
<p>But there are plenty of other Republicans in the House rank-and-file who believe their party needs to do more to address high health care costs and other cost-of-living issues with a conservative stamp — and many of them were not around in 2017, when the last big GOP health care push ran aground.</p> 
<p>As moderates tried to force a floor vote on a bipartisan extension of the Obamacare subsidies, House GOP hard-liners privately pressured party leaders for assurances that a party-line bill focused on health care would move early next year. As those talks were happening last week, the Republican Study Committee — an influential group of nearly 200 House conservatives — discussed the idea of a second party-line bill during a closed-door lunch.</p> 
<p>According to three people granted anonymity to discuss the meeting, the group’s chair, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> of Texas, pitched a possible list of items for a second reconciliation package focused on affordability concerns. Pfluger and other senior RSC members are pushing to include an expansion of health savings accounts that GOP leaders left out of the narrow health care bill the House recently passed.</p> 
<p>“I don't think it has to be divisive,” Pfluger said in an interview last week. “Let's come together and coalesce around policy that works.”</p> 
<p>He added that “the trick” is figuring out what President Donald Trump is interested in pushing forward. His top political aide, White House deputy chief of staff James Blair, recently <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">said the administration was open</a> to a second reconciliation bill to pursue affordability matters.</p> 
<p>There is recent precedent for a major reconciliation bill passing late in a midterm year: Democrats under former President Joe Biden struggled through for months of rollercoaster internal negotiations before Sen. Joe Manchin of West Virginia finally <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/07/27/manchin-schumer-senate-deal-energy-taxes-00048325" target="_blank">agreed to get on board</a>. The Inflation Reduction Act passed just three months before Election Day, though Democrats had a wider margin to work with in the House.</p> 
<p>But top GOP leaders have been treading carefully. Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> told reporters this month that reconciliation is “always hard, but it’s an option.”</p> 
<p>“You don’t just do reconciliation for the heck of it, you’ve got to have, you know, a specific purpose,” he added. “That purpose may start getting some traction — we’ll see.”</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> coordinated early talks around a possible second reconciliation package this fall. But GOP chairs came up with only a handful of policies to include, mostly submitting ideas that had already been left out of the earlier megabill. In an interview last week, Scalise said Republicans would return in January with “a very full agenda … but reconciliation is one thing we're going to try to build.”</p> 
<p>“We're trying to see if there's consensus,” he added. “We obviously would like to get one.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-23T08:53:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>These 3 Republican senators are giving John Thune headaches</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/senate-gop-conservatives-lee-johnson-scott-00703034</link>
      <description>Veteran hard-liners have new perches of authority and rising influence among Republican senators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4789-dba9-addb-77bfb9af0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5d/b0/18fde74f4ce18d929fb32850cef3/u-s-senate-43949.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Along with Sen. Mike Lee of Utah, Johnson (center) and Scott (right) have emerged as leaders of the Senate GOP's rising right wing.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5d/b0/18fde74f4ce18d929fb32850cef3/u-s-senate-43949.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> rushed to advance a new funding package this month, he faced a familiar roadblock: a trio of conservatives from his conference’s right flank.</p> 
<p>Republican Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> of Florida, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151822" data-person-id="151822">Ron Johnson</a> of Wisconsin and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151827" data-person-id="151827">Mike Lee</a> of Utah banded together as they sought to advance key conservative priorities, including an end to spending earmarks — <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/01/congress/thune-casts-doubt-on-passing-government-funding-bills-before-christmas-00671973" target="_blank">holding out for weeks</a> as Thune strained to keep the 2026 funding process on track and avoid another costly government shutdown on Jan. 30.</p> 
<p>The tensions between the fiscal hawks, who want to drastically slash spending, and more pragmatic corners of the Senate GOP, including members of leadership and the Appropriations Committee, are nothing new. But these hard-liners have now found a larger pool of allies as the conference’s center of gravity slowly shifts right. They also have new perches of authority that give each a powerful megaphone.</p> 
<p>Thune ultimately wore the three Republicans down with some outside assistance from President Donald Trump, cutting deals to win their consent to advance the proposed trillion-dollar “minibus” funding package. Ultimately, it was Democratic objections that <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/senators-leave-for-the-holidays-without-passing-funding-package-00699651" target="_blank">prevented the Senate from acting</a> in the final legislative days of 2025.</p> 
<p>But Lee, Johnson and Scott are unapologetic about using their power amid the growing perception among some of their colleagues that they are frequent thorns in Thune’s side.</p> 
<p>“We're actually trying to do important things,” Johnson said in an interview. “No matter what I would have done, Democrats would have held out until the very last minute, too. So, I mean, sorry about your frustrations, colleagues.”</p> 
<p>Since January, the trio has chosen to exert their leverage during key moments where GOP leaders have sought party unity. As Thune worked to advance the party’s sprawling domestic policy bill over the summer, the three Republicans haggled repeatedly over the measure’s parameters — including during a procedural vote that was left open for hours as they negotiated. Last month, they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/09/government-funding-deal-on-track-to-advance-sunday-night-00644110" target="_blank">briefly withheld support for the bill</a> that ultimately ended the 43-day government shutdown, huddling with Thune before ultimately voting in favor.</p> 
<p>Publicly, their colleagues are respectful and note that every senator has a right to use the legislative tools available to advance their own agenda.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151837" data-person-id="151837">John Hoeven</a> (R-N.D.), an appropriator and Thune ally, noted that Johnson, Scott and Lee “reflect a bigger share of the caucus” that is decidedly conservative, while “folks on the other end of the caucus” also use their leverage from time to time.</p> 
<p>“That's just how it works,” Hoeven said.</p> 
<p>But behind the scenes, the hardball tactics have rankled Republican senators. As the spending standoff dragged on in recent weeks, some privately urged Thune to call the fiscal hawks’ bluff by putting the spending package on the floor, essentially daring Johnson or others to publicly object.</p> 
<p>“He’s going to keep doing it until they call his hand,” one GOP senator said about Johnson, adding that Thune risked being “miserable” unless he asserted himself.</p> 
<p>A second GOP senator, who was also granted anonymity to speak candidly about internal conference dynamics, added that the trio has been more “emboldened” this year than under prior GOP leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51216" data-person-id="51216">Mitch McConnell</a> of Kentucky. The senator said that’s due to Thune’s “looser” leadership style and his determination to move funding bills individually rather than simply banking on a single omnibus deal.</p> 
<p>“We haven’t done an appropriations process in a long time,” the senator added.</p> 
<p>Those tensions have played out quietly behind the scenes in GOP lunches, with the conservative trio at times sparring with Senate Appropriations Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) and other members of the government funding panel who want to revise spending levels enacted under former President Joe Biden.</p> 
<p>But the two GOP senators agreed that they did not think Lee, Scott and Johnson would be engaging in their current tactics were McConnell still in charge, or <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/19/richard-shelby-appropriations-gop-spending-bill-00074398" target="_blank">even under Collins’ predecessor</a> as Appropriations chair, Sen. Richard Shelby (R-Ala.).</p> 
<p>“Shelby would have taken away every one of their projects,” the first GOP senator said.</p> 
<p>The shift in leadership style was by design. The same GOP senators kvetched that McConnell was too centralized, with Scott unsuccessfully challenging him in 2022. In his bid to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/11/13/john-thune-senate-republican-leader-00189305" target="_blank">take over as Republican leader</a> two years later, Thune pledged to shift power back to individual senators and committee chairs — and the three conservative malcontents, once dismissed as outliers, are now more difficult to ignore.</p> 
<p>Scott leads the Senate GOP’s Steering Committee, holding weekly meetings with the conservative-oriented group as well as hosting a weekly lunch for the larger conference. Lee chairs the Energy and Natural Resources Committee, one of several one-time rebels who received gavels in January. And Johnson — long been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/13/ron-johnson-reconciliation-gop-agenda-spending-cuts-00347100" target="_blank">willing to be a squeaky wheel</a> — leads the Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs panel’s investigative subcommittee in addition to having seats on the powerful Finance and Budget committees.</p> 
<p>At the same time, the Senate GOP conference has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/29/senate-gop-dealmakers-depart-just-as-congress-control-splits-00075068" target="_blank">undergone a subtle transformation</a> in recent election cycles, inching toward the right as the most pragmatic Republican dealmakers are replaced by senators more closely aligned with the MAGA movement — giving Scott, Johnson and Lee a growing set of allies.</p> 
<p>Thune has been dealing with the hard-liners one step at a time. Gaining their approval for the recent funding package, for instance, required promising several amendment votes as well as a path forward for a pet Johnson priority — a bill that would exempt some federal employees from furloughs during government shutdowns.</p> 
<p>“He has more patience than any three of the rest of us do,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/221844" data-person-id="221844">Mike Rounds</a> (R-S.D.).</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) added that Thune wants “to the maximum degree possible to make sure that people in his conference are heard and respected” — even if, she said, he “has a lot of frogs that keep hopping around.”</p> 
<p>Asked about his message to the holdouts, Thune pitched the funding package as being in “everybody’s best interest” and better than the alternatives — a new shutdown, another short-term stopgap or a mammoth omnibus loathed by conservatives. Thune also helped facilitate a potential path toward enactment for Johnson’s shutdown bill, connecting him with Speaker Mike Johnson.</p> 
<p>“I think you always have to keep the perspective in this job … that the most important vote isn’t the last vote, it’s the next vote,” Thune said about his broader approach to leadership this past year.</p> 
<p>The conservative trio is looking ahead to the next fight, as well. Even after Scott cut a deal to advance the funding bill, he rekindled the earmarks fight, <a href="https://x.com/SenRickScott/status/2001706927085215849" target="_blank">accusing Democrats in an X post</a> of “packing the latest appropriations package with taxpayer-funded earmarks” and trying to “undermine Pres. Trump’s agenda.”</p> 
<p>Republicans, Scott said, must “stand strong.”</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misstated the year Sen. Rick Scott challenged Mitch McConnell as Senate Republican leader. It was 2022.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New York Republicans are excited about a race they’re probably going to lose</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/hes-facing-very-long-odds-so-why-are-new-york-republicans-betting-on-bruce-blakeman-00703744</link>
      <description>Struggling blue state Republicans need a strong top of the ticket to win key House races.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-47f6-dba9-addb-77ff02bd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 16:59:51 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/82/31/d19003274557aae1710a365d128d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172980382">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Michael M. Santiago/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman is expected to deliver a strong top-of-the-ticket result for down-ballot GOP candidates.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/82/31/d19003274557aae1710a365d128d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172980382" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nick Reisman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nick Reisman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Empire State Republicans expect Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman to turbo charge down-ballot turnout as their party’s gubernatorial nominee — boosting GOP candidates in crucial suburban swing races as he mounts an otherwise uphill battle to unseat Democratic Gov. Kathy Hochul.</p> 
<p>If Blakeman falls short in an underdog bid, New York Republicans can still be successful in what’s shaping up to be a tough political environment.</p> 
<p>“Blakeman’s top appeal for Republicans, particularly in swing suburbs, can be realized even if he loses,” said Larry Levy, dean of the National Center for Suburban Studies at Hofstra University. “He could help them on Long Island, Westchester and the Hudson Valley to possibly win seats that could make a difference on which party controls the gavels in Congress. Blakeman is in a position to do that.”</p> 
<p>Who leads the Republican ticket in this deep blue state will have critical implications for competitive House races that stand to determine which party will control the narrowly divided chamber and the course of President Donald Trump’s final two years in office. Blakeman’s coattails offer one possible remedy to GOP headwinds in next year’s midterm elections, as Democrats seize on affordability issues and stoke their base’s anger at the sitting president’s policies.</p> 
<p>Blakeman, 70, is now the likely Republican nominee for governor after Rep. Elise Stefanik <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/rep-elise-stefanik-set-to-drop-her-bid-for-nys-governor-00700879" target="_blank">abruptly suspended</a> her campaign last week. Stefanik and Blakeman are both Trump allies, and the 41-year-old upstate New York House member is far better known statewide.</p> 
<p>Unlike Stefanik, Blakeman hails from a vote rich political bellwether in a state that’s otherwise dominated by Democrats. He is a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/11/19/gops-2026-abortion-conundrum-00658469" target="_blank">self-described “pro-choice” Republican</a> — a stance that will likely attract some independent and conservative Democratic voters. And he has cultivated a <a href="https://nypost.com/2024/12/16/us-news/new-york-post-to-expand-long-island-coverage-in-2025/" target="_blank">mutually beneficial relationship</a> with The New York Post, the influential conservative tabloid that’s part of Trump’s media diet.</p> 
<p>His bid is still considered a longshot against Hochul, <a href="https://sri.siena.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/SNY1225-Crosstabs_12-15_Final.pdf" target="_blank">who led Blakeman by 25 points</a> in a Siena University poll this month. He remains largely unknown to most New Yorkers, and Republicans are trying to reverse a 23-year losing streak in statewide elections. Blakeman’s prior statewide bid for a U.S. Senate seat ended with a loss.</p> 
<p>In an interview, Blakeman pointed to his ability to win in a large, diverse suburban county as a sign that he can be successful statewide.</p> 
<p>“I want our congressional and Senate and Assembly and local candidates to be successful as well,” he said. “If you look at the demographics of Nassau County, we match the state almost as a mirror image. I feel very confident we’re going to win.”</p> 
<p>New York Republicans know the power the top of their party’s ticket can wield in a midterm election. Then-Rep. Lee Zeldin’s 2022 campaign came within 6 points of defeating Hochul, but the Long Islander’s strong suburban showing was credited with helping sweep several House Republicans into office. GOP leaders are poised to replicate that plan in 2026 — a doubling down on a suburban strategy <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/01/democrats-fret-the-zohran-mamdani-effect-will-cost-them-next-year-00531906" target="_blank">that will also tie all Democrats</a>, including Hochul, to New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani.</p> 
<p>Republicans want to cast the 34-year-old democratic socialist as a lightning rod. Blakeman, whose day-to-day movements are covered in the Big Apple’s media market, would have easy access to blast the left-leaning mayor’s policies.</p> 
<p>The most immediate impact may be on the Long Island districts led by moderate Democratic Reps. Tom Suozzi and Laura Gillen — both of which will be top GOP targets.</p> 
<p>“It’s definitely going to put those two Nassau seats, Suozzi and Gillen seats into play,” said Conservative Party Chair Gerard Kassar. “I already thought the Gillen seat would be a top seat in the nation. Suozzi has a number of solid candidates nipping at his toes there to begin with. If I was residing in Nassau County and looking for some very positive results in 2026, I think I just hit the jackpot.”</p> 
<p>Suozzi and Gillen campaign representatives pointed to their work with Republicans and ability to win swing seats regardless of the top of the ticket.</p> 
<p>“Everyone knows that Tom Suozzi works across the aisle in Congress to take on the affordability crisis, lower healthcare costs, fix the immigration mess and keep our communities safe,” said Kim Devlin, a Suozzi senior advisor. “That’s why he was able to win his district, even while Trump won it as well. People are sick of partisanship and that’s why they will re-elect Tom Suozzi.”</p> 
<p>The Gillen campaign offered a similar assessment, noting that she "has a proven record of embracing bipartisanship to achieve results to lower the costs of living and improve public safety.”</p> 
<p>“In fact, Bruce Blakeman endorsed her and served as her deputy Supervisor,” a campaign spokesperson said. “Her moderate approach, that prioritizes Long Islanders over politics, is why Rep. Gillen will be re-elected in November."</p> 
<p>Democrats have dominated New York statewide elections since George Pataki left office in 2006. The party lost its final toehold on power in Albany after losing control of the state Senate in 2018. But Republicans continue to maintain competitive races in suburban enclaves, where voters are sensitive to high taxes and concerned about public safety.</p> 
<p>“You’re always more likely to lose than win as a Republican in New York, but I think he's going to be our strongest statewide candidate since George Pataki,” said Republican operative Chapin Fay. “He’s winning in a blue area and he’s sort of MAGA without a lot of the baggage.”</p> 
<p>Ensuring success in down-ballot races will be paramount for local Republican leaders with many municipal races switching from low-turnout odd-years <a href="https://www.cityandstateny.com/policy/2025/10/even-year-local-elections-are-coming-some/408917/" target="_blank">to even-numbered years</a>, when more people are expected to vote. That means races for GOP-held seats on some town and village boards and county legislatures may take on a more competitive tilt — threatening Republican power on the local level.</p> 
<p>In Nassau County, where Blakeman has served as the top elected official since his 2021 victory, Republicans maintain a robust political operation led by Chair Joe Cairo. Despite widespread GOP losses last month, Nassau County Republican candidates overperformed, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/bellwether-suburban-countys-red-shift-is-now-at-the-center-of-both-parties-future-identities-in-new-york-00683750" target="_blank">POLITICO reported</a>. Those results underscore the potential strength of Cairo’s voter turnout effort.</p> 
<p>“To me, it’s a good strategy,” said Assemblymember Ed Ra, a Nassau County Republican. “It helps when we have a couple of House races that we think are going to be very competitive. For us in the Legislature, we think having a suburban, well-known, well-liked candidate is going to be a positive.”</p> 
<p>Long Island is a major prize for any statewide candidate — and the suburbs have been trending Republican this decade with voters activated by concerns over crime and Democratic-backed criminal justice reforms.</p> 
<p>New York Democrats acknowledge Blakeman’s strength in Nassau County in particular will present a challenge for down-ballot candidates.</p> 
<p>“He will have an organization working for him in Nassau County,” said Jay Jacobs, who serves as both the statewide Democratic Committee chair and the Nassau County Democratic leader. “But I would say that while it certainly will be a factor that we have to take into account in those congressional races and down-ballot races, he likes to tout his great win and his perceived popularity, but we don’t see it that way and our polling doesn’t show it that way.”</p> 
<p>Hochul, a Buffalo native, has struggled in the New York City suburbs.</p> 
<p>The governor and Jacobs publicly disagreed over supporting Mamdani’s candidacy as her hand-picked party chair moved to distance suburban Democrats from the incoming mayor. She lost Nassau and Suffolk counties to Zeldin three years ago. Hochul was also forced to retool a controversial home building and zoning proposal amid a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/02/11/hochul-faces-uprising-housing-plan-00080949" target="_blank">bipartisan revolt on Long Island</a>.</p> 
<p>Hochul on Monday pointed to her efforts addressing crime, housing and jobs on Long Island.</p> 
<p>“We will do very well on Long Island,” she predicted. “I’ve spent an enormous amount of time on Long Island.”</p> 
<p>Blakeman’s political vulnerabilities may still complicate matters for Republicans. A liberal stance on abortion is unnerving conservative voters the party can’t afford to have stay home. Upstate Republicans, slighted by yet another New York City-area nominee, will have to be won over. <a href="https://sri.siena.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/SNY1225-Crosstabs_12-15_Final.pdf" target="_blank">Trump’s unpopularity</a> in his native state is also expected to work against Blakeman, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/20/trump-new-york-governor-endorsement-bruce-blakeman-00702013" target="_blank">was endorsed by the president</a> over the weekend.</p> 
<p>Hochul, too, is expected to be a more formidable incumbent than she was three years ago when she was still a rookie governor and running in a backlash year for her party. The Democratic governor is a formidable fundraiser and she has also worked to build up the state Democrats’ political infrastructure to buttress vulnerable candidates running below her on the ballot.</p> 
<p>Her campaign moved swiftly to define Blakeman, who remains unknown to 70 percent of voters, <a href="https://sri.siena.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/SNY1225-Crosstabs_12-15_Final.pdf" target="_blank">the Siena poll found</a>, saying Blakeman “has gone all-in on Donald Trump’s deeply unpopular MAGA movement.” And Hochul questioned whether he ultimately would be the nominee.</p> 
<p>“The Republican Party is in such chaos, I’m not even sure he’s going to end up being the nominee. This changes by the hour,” Hochul told POLITICO at a news conference. “I’m not going to speculate about the prospective opposition, other than knowing it’s going to be a MAGA, Trump-endorsed Republican.”</p> 
<p><i>Bill Mahoney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
