<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:10:25 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP tees up 2 amendment votes on latest funding package</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/amendment-votes-appropriations-funding-package-chip-roy-00726560</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b994-d65c-affb-bb9785570000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:10:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders are allowing floor votes this week on several proposed tweaks to the latest government funding package after hard-liners <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/appropriations-funding-bills-hardliners-chip-roy-00715032" target="_blank">demanded more input</a>. </p> 
<p>The House Rules Committee voted Tuesday to allow votes on two amendments to the package that would fund the departments of Treasury and State, as well as the IRS and the Federal Trade Commission. </p> 
<p>Texas Republican Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a>, a member of the panel, secured a vote on an amendment that would cut appeals court funding for the District of Columbia by 20 percent and eliminate the budgets of two judges. </p> 
<p>The panel’s top Democrat, Massachusetts Rep.<a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512"> Jim McGovern</a>, complained that the sponsors of that amendment didn’t even testify before the committee.</p> 
<p>“It seems like this process gets worse and worse and worse,” McGovern said. “Talk about revenge. I mean, we're going after judges and their staff. … This is not the way this place should be run.” </p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51389" data-person-id="51389">Virginia Foxx</a> (R-N.C), the panel’s chair, said House Republicans are ensuring the appropriations process is “member-driven and deliberate.”</p> 
<p>The House will also vote on an amendment from Rep.<a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/407516" data-person-id="407516"> Eli Crane</a> (R-Ariz.) that would <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/gop-hardliners-amendment-vote-funding-national-endowment-democracy-00725512" target="_blank">bar funding for the National Endowment for Democracy</a>, an independent nonprofit that supports projects around the world with the stated goal of promoting democracy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers meet Danish officials to rebuke Trump’s Greenland grab</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/lawmakers-meet-danish-officials-rebuke-trump-greenland-00726166</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b941-da56-afff-bdd3f9ab0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 16:42:41 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Arctic Caucus co-Chairs <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine) will meet on Wednesday with Danish Ambassador Jesper Møller Sørensen to reaffirm their opposition to President Donald Trump’s effort to acquire Greenland.</p> 
<p>The closed-door meeting comes as Trump has floated the idea of obtaining Greenland “one way or another” — rhetoric that has drawn sharp rebukes from Copenhagen and Nuuk. The idea of taking over the Danish territory has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-lawmakers-denounce-trump-seize-greenland-00714611" target="_blank">met resistance from some senior Republicans</a> and outright opposition from Democrats.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she would support a war powers resolution to bar Trump from taking action to invade Greenland, if it were offered. A bipartisan group of House lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/house-lawmakers-introduce-bipartisan-nato-bill-00723206" target="_blank">has introduced like-minded legislation</a> that covers any NATO ally.</p> 
<p>“There’s been a lot of talk about that, which, in fairness, is crazy,” Murkowski said in an interview, referring to speculation that Congress could eventually invoke war powers authorities in connection with Greenland. “Who would have ever thought you would say the word Greenland in the same sentence as war powers resolution?”</p> 
<p>The new legislation comes as Hill Democrats search for ways to keep the Trump administration from taking further military action in Venezuela. The Senate is poised to vote this week on a war powers resolution tied to Venezuela, though its path in the House remains unclear.</p> 
<p>Trump administration officials, meanwhile, are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-greenland-military-force-00713315" target="_blank">openly discussing options</a> — including the use of force — to seize Greenland, a move that would trigger NATO’s mutual defense clause and risk shattering the alliance.</p> 
<p>“It’s easier,” <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/greenland-pm-wont-sell-country-jd-vance-meeting/" target="_blank">Trump said Sunday</a>, referring to buying the island. “But one way or the other, we’re going to have Greenland.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski said the goal of Wednesday’s meeting <b>—</b> with Møller Sørensen and other officials from Denmark and Greenland — is “a constructive dialogue” with Danish and Greenlandic officials and to underscore that Capitol Hill is not a bystander as Arctic tensions rise.</p> 
<p>“We here in this Congress actually have a role, have some input on whether or not it might be appropriate to take some of these actions that the president is suggesting,” she said.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said she will travel to Copenhagen later this week with a small bipartisan bicameral group to reinforce congressional concerns directly with Danish leaders.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deepfake porn bill allowing victims to sue passes Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/deepfake-porn-bill-allowing-victims-to-sue-passes-senate-00725817</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b8e6-d65c-affb-bbe706610000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 14:49:28 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate passed legislation Tuesday to allow victims of nonconsensual deepfake pornography to sue the producers and distributors of such content.</p> 
<p>The proposal was put forward by Democratic Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/845fda6f-4459-46f0-a956-263e74780ae5" target="_blank">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.) on the Senate floor for unanimous consent, and is co-sponsored by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/aaf51c1d-d223-401e-8a6b-22ee557e6bdf" target="_blank">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.).</p> 
<p>It represents the latest in a line of congressional efforts to address harms caused by the distribution of nonconsensual deepfake imagery, including the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_146" target="_blank">TAKE IT DOWN Act</a>, which was championed by First Lady Melania Trump and was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/19/trump-signs-take-it-down-act-criminalizing-deepfake-and-revenge-porn-00357151" target="_blank">signed into law</a> last year by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>The bill, known as the Disrupt Explicit Forged Images and Non-Consensual Edits Act, or <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_118_S_3696" target="_blank">DEFIANCE Act</a>, cleared the Senate last Congress but failed to progress in the House. If it passes into law, the legislation would give victims the right to sue over deepfake pornography.</p> 
<p>Sen. Durbin highlighted the harm and profound consequences victims of such nonconsensual imagery suffer, and said he was proud to work with Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez on the issue, who has been a victim of explicit deepfakes.</p> 
<p>The number of nonconsensual deepfake porn videos available online has increased ninefold since 2019, according to <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-08-24/google-microsoft-tools-behind-surge-in-deepfake-ai-porn?embedded-checkout=true" target="_blank">one researcher</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP leaders throw cold water on Trump’s credit-card push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/trump-credit-cards-thune-johnson-00725061</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b855-da56-afff-bcd7550b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:11:06 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> voiced skepticism Tuesday on President Donald Trump’s move to temporarily cap credit card interest rates.</p> 
<p>“I think that would probably deprive an awful lot of people of access to credit around the country,” Thune told reporters. “Credit cards would probably become debit cards.”</p> 
<p>“That's not something I'm out there advocating for — let's put it that way,” he added.</p> 
<p>Thune’s comments come after Trump posted on Truth Social that he was calling for a one-year cap of 10 percent interest on credit cards starting Jan. 20.</p> 
<p>Johnson also appeared to tamp down the prospects for immediate action Tuesday, telling reporters he spoke to Trump about it on Monday. He called it among a "long list" of affordability ideas Trump has in mind.</p> 
<p>“The president is the ideas guy," Johnson said, adding later, "I wouldn't get too spun up about ideas that are out of the box, that are proposed or suggested."</p> 
<p>Johnson also raised similar concerns as Thune, saying credit-card issuers “would just stop lending money” if rates are capped.</p> 
<p>In addition to the proposed temporary cap on interest rates, Trump has also thrown his weight behind a long-controversial <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/02/congress/crypto-senate-genius-act-swipe-fees-00380677" target="_blank">bill limiting credit-card merchant fees</a> sponsored by Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259544" data-person-id="259544">Roger Marshall</a> (R-Kan.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.) that has been the subject of intense financial industry lobbying since its introduction in 2022.</p> 
<p>Republicans are on both sides of that bill, Thune noted, but he said he believed it would be up for a floor vote “at some point.”</p> 
<p>“That's what we do around here,” he said. “We cast hard votes.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Megabill 2.0? These House Republicans have some ideas.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/rsc-reconciliation-framework-megabill-00724594</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b814-d15b-abff-fc5ee0920000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 11:00:08 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A major House GOP faction unveiled its framework Tuesday for a new party-line Republican policy bill that aims to slash the costs of housing and health care.</p> 
<p>Among the <a href="https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/13NyKUdSH-uSrZi0YHkTZ3HO7J63Qv0R1" target="_blank">slew of proposals under the Republican Study Committee framework</a> is the “Don payment” — a program creating a new zero-to-low-down-payment option for mortgage shoppers. The plan would also create new tax-advantaged “health freedom accounts” that would allow Americans to directly receive federal subsidies for insurance.</p> 
<p>In addition, the plan suggests cutting energy costs by accelerating the permitting process and refilling the Department of Energy’s strategic oil reserve with “discounted Venezuelan oil.” Overall, the framework would include cuts of $1.6 trillion to government spending.</p> 
<p>“There’s three major things that I think are threatening the American dream right now: housing costs, health care costs and energy costs,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> (R-Texas), the RSC’s chair, at a Tuesday news conference. “We’ve got to get this done. We know we have a narrow window of time.”</p> 
<p>While the release of the framework signals buy-in from a large swath of House Republicans, a second massive party-line bill is sure to create further divisions within the GOP’s slim House majority. The chairs of critical House committees, including tax-writing chief <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> (R-Mo.), have expressed skepticism that there’s a path forward under the multistep budget reconciliation process.</p> 
<p>Vulnerable Republican moderates are especially wary of further changes to health policy as they maneuver to fight for their seats in November and defend against Democratic attacks on the Republicans’ steep cuts to Medicaid enacted last year.</p> 
<p>While Speaker Mike Johnson has not yet endorsed the RSC plan, he told reporters Monday that he hopes to do a narrower reconciliation bill in 2026 and that GOP leaders would work to build internal consensus around potential policies in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>Republicans’ House majority has dwindled in recent weeks with the retirement of Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and the death of Rep. Doug LaMalfa of California. Other members have been absent for health reasons, making the GOP’s control of the chamber especially tenuous.</p> 
<p>But Pfluger said, with the help of President Donald Trump, complete unity is within reach for the House GOP, and he called on the White House to get on board.</p> 
<p>“I hope that they take note of this plan,” he said. “When the president says, ‘Let’s go do this,’ I think … skepticism will fly out the window.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-13T15:10:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Clintons defy subpoena to testify in Epstein investigation, risking being held in contempt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/clintons-defy-subpoena-to-testify-in-epstein-investigation-risking-being-held-in-contempt-00724394</link>
      <description>House Oversight Chair James Comer says he will have members vote to hold Bill Clinton in contempt of Congress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b7e2-dca0-ad9b-ffeb2fdd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:43:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b0/50/c7d3de49468b90e6c467c7255c94/u-s-congress-22015.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Oversight Committee Chair James Comer (R-Ky.), flanked by Reps. Lauren Boebert (R-Colo.), Michael Cloud (R-Texas), Andy Biggs (R-Ariz.), and Scott Perry (R-Pa.), speaks with reporters after former President Bill Clinton did not appear for a deposition on Capitol Hill Jan. 13, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b0/50/c7d3de49468b90e6c467c7255c94/u-s-congress-22015.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bill and Hillary Clinton have officially refused to testify in the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee's investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein — defying subpoenas and risking being held in contempt of Congress.</p> 
<p>The former president and Secretary of State were scheduled to appear on Capitol Hill for closed-door depositions Tuesday and Wednesday. But, <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-b7df-d15b-abff-ffdfa3490000" target="_blank"><u>in a letter</u></a> to House Oversight Chair James Comer, attorneys for the Clintons said their clients would not be complying.</p> 
<p>The letter, obtained by POLITICO, claims both Clintons have already provided all the information they have regarding the late Epstein and his co-conspirator, Ghislaine Maxwell, who is now serving a 20-year sentence for her part in the sex trafficking scheme.</p> 
<p>The attorneys called the episode “nothing more than a ploy to attempt to embarrass political rivals, as President Trump has directed.”</p> 
<p>They also brushed off threats of legal action by arguing that, because the subpoenas issued to the Clintons are "not related to a valid legislative purpose," the subpoenas are therefore "invalid and legally unenforceable."</p> 
<p>Speaking to reporters Tuesday morning outside the hearing room where the interview with Bill Clinton was due to take place, Comer, a Kentucky Republican, announced a vote to hold Bill Clinton in contempt of Congress would be scheduled to take place during next week's committee markup.</p> 
<p>“We've communicated with President Clinton's legal team for months now, giving them opportunity after opportunity to come in, to give us a day, and they continue to delay, delay, delay to the point where we had no idea whether they were going to show up today or not,” Comer said. “I think it's very disappointing.”</p> 
<p>A similar vote could be scheduled for Hillary Clinton, assuming she does not appear Wednesday.</p> 
<p>In a separate letter to Comer <a href="https://x.com/billclinton/status/2011098958236697021?s=46" target="_blank"><u>published on X</u></a> dated Jan. 13, the Clintons said the committee leader’s focus should be on preventing crimes like Epstein’s from happening again, but is instead playing “partisan politics.”</p> 
<p>“Despite everything that needs to be done to help our country, you are on the cusp of bringing Congress to a halt to pursue a rarely used process literally designed to result in our imprisonment,” they wrote. “This is not the way out of America’s ills, and we will forcefully defend ourselves.”</p> 
<p>They also suggested they might be willing to appear in a public hearing: "We are prepared to make our case to your 45 committee members and, if need be, more importantly, we also will defend ourselves in the public arena to ensure this country knows exactly what you are doing and why you are doing so, instead of helping the American people who need this Congress's work and protection."</p> 
<p>The seldom-used congressional power to hold someone in contempt of Congress can range in implications — from a symbolic action to a precursor to forcing jail time. But there’s reason to believe a contempt vote at this time, for these individuals, could have dramatic consequences.</p> 
<p>The Trump Justice Department has not hesitated in the past to go after its perceived enemies. The administration has sought to cast Bill Clinton at the center of the Epstein files saga, despite there being no evidence of misconduct against him.</p> 
<p>Hillary Clinton, meanwhile, was the subject of a “lock her up” rallying cry among President Donald Trump’s supporters during the 2016 presidential campaign, largely amid revelations she used a private email server while serving in the Obama administration.</p> 
<p>In previous examples of the potential serious consequences to contempt of Congress charges, two Trump associates, Steve Bannon and Peter Navarro, were sentenced to prison time for failing to cooperate with subpoenas from the Democratic-led select committee investigating the Jan. 6, 2021 attacks on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>"We trust you will engage in good faith to de-escalate this dispute," the attorneys wrote in the letter, dated Jan. 12 — a day before Bill Clinton's scheduled appearance.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Member stock-trading is the latest target for a Democratic discharge petition</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/stock-trading-discharge-petition-00724344</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b800-da56-afff-bc92f5ae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:38:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A senior House Democrat, in a long-shot move to force a member stock-trading ban to the floor, said Tuesday he will launch a discharge petition after Republican leaders moved to sidestep bipartisan efforts to address the issue.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7008" target="_blank">GOP-written bill</a> is expected to move through the House Administration Committee on Wednesday, and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196354" data-person-id="196354">Joe Morelle</a> of New York — the top Democrat on the panel — said he is "troubled" by that legislation, which would allow members to keep stocks they currently own.</p> 
<p>“I'm also troubled by the notion that it's being sold as a stock-trading ban — it is not that at all,” said Morelle, who is pushing alternative legislation with other Democrats that would force members to divest individual stocks, as well as the president. But with the GOP bill on offer, it's not clear whether the discharge petition can pick up enough Republican support to force Morelle's bill to the House floor.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, the Republican-backed bill has so far picked up support from one Hill Democrat, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/65300" data-person-id="65300">Josh Riley</a> of New York.</p> 
<p>“I don't look at this as a Democratic issue or Republican issue," he said in an interview Tuesday. "And frankly I don't give a shit who's scoring political points in this place.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Powell probe stiffens GOP spines</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/republicans-react-powell-fed-doj-investigation-00724102</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b5d3-d15b-abff-fddfc8b50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Justice Department’s move to investigate Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell is shaping up to be one of the Trump administration’s most unpopular actions yet among Capitol Hill Republicans.</p> 
<p><b>— Republicans recoil:</b> The <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679" target="_blank">DOJ probe into Powell’s June hearing testimony</a> is causing heartburn in the Senate, which controls the fate of his successor. After Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) threatened Sunday to vote against any nominee until the criminal investigation is resolved, other Senate Banking Republicans like Sens. Kevin Cramer (N.D.) and Dave McCormick (Pa.) joined in to signal their disapproval Monday.</p> 
<p>Cramer is no fan of Powell and called him a “bad” Fed chair. But he added, “I do not believe, however, that he is a criminal.”</p> 
<p>Few Republicans are openly cheering the decision. Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), who referred perjury allegations against Powell to the DOJ last summer, is <a href="https://x.com/RepLuna/status/2010755530005069992" target="_blank">the exception</a>. Even other hard-liners who have long wanted to see Powell gone declined to comment on whether the probe was justified.</p> 
<p>“That’s way outside my jurisdiction,” House Freedom Caucus Chair Andy Harris (R-Md.) told POLITICO when asked if the probe was warranted.</p> 
<p><b>— A notable silence:&nbsp;</b>Despite the critiques from members of his committee, Banking Chair Tim Scott has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/tim-scott-jerome-powell-silence-00723902" target="_blank">stayed mum</a>. It’s not unusual for Scott, who declines hallway interviews, to stay quiet. But it’s conspicuous as others in the GOP speak up on behalf of the Fed’s independence.</p> 
<p>Scott’s silence contrasts with public statements from the likes of Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who called for the probe to be “resolved quickly,” and House Financial Services Chair French Hill (R-Ark.), who said it “creates an unnecessary distraction” that “could undermine this and future Administrations’ ability to make sound monetary policy decisions.”</p> 
<p>Asked if the investigation would make it hard to confirm the next Fed leader, Thune acknowledged “it could make it challenging.”</p> 
<p><b>— Powell's staying power: </b>At this point, it seems almost certain Powell will stay on until his term as chair ends in May. Many expect him to leave after that, forgoing his longer term as a rank-and-file Fed governor.</p> 
<p>But that probability has dropped amid the DOJ's probe, and Powell could stick around. And the likelihood that he might ever be prosecuted for his June testimony is remote. </p> 
<p>“The kind of things we’re talking about here is whether Powell lied when he said there were ‘no rooftop gardens’ when there will in fact be ‘vegetated roof spaces,’” Victoria Guida writes <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2026/01/13/why-powell-isnt-flinching-at-trumps-attack-00723847" target="_blank">in her latest column</a>. "Of course, the investigation might also cover the cost overruns themselves ... but mismanaging a project is not in and of itself a crime."</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House math: </b>Speaker Mike Johnson’s margins in the House could pose a problem for party-line action this week, including passing the rule teeing up a final vote on the bundled State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services funding bills. </p> 
<p>The recent passing of Rep. Doug LaMalfa (R-Calif.) brought the balance of the House to 218-213. But with Rep. Jim Baird (R-Ind.) recovering from a car accident and Rep. Derrick Van Orden (R-Wis.) expected to be out indefinitely as his wife undergoes surgery, Johnson is facing some harrowing math.</p> 
<p><b>— Dem joins GOP stock trading bill: </b>The new GOP-leadership-backed bill to ban lawmaker stock buying has its first Democratic co-sponsor, New York Rep. Josh Riley. The bill, drafted by House Administration Chair Bryan Steil (R-Wis.), now has 71 GOP co-sponsors. </p> 
<p>The legislation is on track for a Wednesday morning markup. Senior Democrats who oppose the bill — which allows lawmakers to hold onto the stocks they already own — say they’ll try to force changes.</p> 
<p><b>— Health care talks shape up: </b>The bipartisan group of senators working to craft an agreement to revive the expired Affordable Care Act subsidies is honing in on a potential compromise around abortion language. According to a Senate GOP aide briefed on the group’s discussions and another person granted anonymity to describe the private talks, the lawmakers are considering increasing penalties and audits for insurance plans to ensure funds for abortion are properly segregated from funds for nonabortion health services.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jack Smith to testify publicly before Congress next week</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/jack-smith-to-testify-publicly-00724047</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b55d-d65c-affb-bfdf8ea20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 22:38:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former special counsel Jack Smith will testify in a public hearing next week, setting up a potentially dramatic retelling of his investigations into President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan said Monday that Smith will appear Jan. 22 as part of the congressional probe of the investigation into Trump's efforts to subvert the 2020 election. </p> 
<p>The former special counsel testified for eight hours in a closed-door Judiciary Committee hearing in December and transcripts were later released. </p> 
<p>Smith’s legal team requested he be permitted to appear in public. </p> 
<p>On Friday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/jack-smith-will-testify-in-public-00718945" target="_blank">Jordan told POLITICO</a> he planned to invite Smith to a public hearing.</p> 
<p>The public hearing will allow Republicans to openly question Smith’s investigation, which the president and many Republicans in Congress have labeled a witch hunt. It will allow Democrats to highlight the evidence that led the special counsel to charge Trump with attempting to reverse the 2020 presidential election and mishandle classified documents.</p> 
<p>In his closed-door testimony, Smith defended his investigation and said he is interested in sharing the results but that the Department of Justice prevented him based on its interpretation of a court order keeping details of the case under seal.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans are speaking out on behalf of the Fed. Not Banking Chair Tim Scott.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/tim-scott-jerome-powell-silence-00723902</link>
      <description>The South Carolina Republican has not weighed in on the central bank’s independence after a hearing he led comes under DOJ scrutiny.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b504-dca0-ad9b-fd8d541d0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 20:47:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0b/d0/16b8fa524a5fb63bed25816f43c2/u-s-congress-19641.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tim Scott, seen in December, repeatedly refused to comment to reporters about Jerome Powell on Monday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0b/d0/16b8fa524a5fb63bed25816f43c2/u-s-congress-19641.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Washington erupted over the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679" target="_blank">Justice Department’s subpoena</a> of Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell, a Republican lawmaker at the center of the dispute is keeping silent.</p> 
<p>That would be Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> of South Carolina, who presided over a June hearing of the Senate Banking Committee where he and other Republicans quizzed Powell about the Fed’s pending renovation projects. Powell’s answers from the meeting are now the subject of a perjury investigation, the Fed chair revealed Sunday — the apparent culmination of months of attacks from the president.</p> 
<p>Many lawmakers of both parties <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/gop-angst-grows-powell-investigation-00721939" target="_blank">quickly spoke out in protest</a> of the probe and in favor of Fed independence — including several Republican members of Scott’s own committee — but Scott himself has so far remained mum as he tries to advance major cryptocurrency legislation this week. In addition to serving as Banking chair — where he leads oversight of the Federal Reserve — Scott also chairs the Senate GOP campaign arm, which requires him to work closely with Trump and his orbit.</p> 
<p>“I already said no,” he told reporters who repeatedly pressed him for comment as he entered the Capitol Monday.</p> 
<p>Scott’s silence is not unusual — he does not respond to questions in the Capital hallways. Still, it was conspicuous as Republican after Republican spoke out against the apparent targeting of the Fed chairman — starting almost immediately Sunday night when Sen. Thom Tillis of North Carolina not only objected to the move but said he would use his vote on the Banking Committee to block any future Fed nominee until the investigation is resolved.</p> 
<p>Also speaking out Monday was Scott’s House counterpart, Financial Services Chair French Hill, who called Powell a “man of integrity” and said the investigation threatened “sound monetary policy decisions.” Senate Majority Leader John Thune, meanwhile, called for the probe to be “resolved quickly.”</p> 
<p>"I want to see [the Fed] operate in an independent way free of politics,” he added.</p> 
<p>Among the questions left unaddressed by Scott is whether he shares his GOP colleagues' concerns about Fed independence or feels misled by the June testimony, where Powell sought to rebut allegations that Fed officials had let the costs of an ambitious headquarters renovation spiral out of control.</p> 
<p>Pressed by Scott on accusations that the rehab project was needlessly lavish — many of them amplified by Trump and his allies, such as reports of a private elevator and garden terrace — Powell responded that many of the claims were “flatly misleading” and had long since been dropped from the plans.</p> 
<p>Scott has generally avoided weighing in on questions about the Fed’s independence as Trump has taken aim at the central bank and its longtime chair. He appeared with Trump last year when the president went to tour the renovation project at the Fed’s Constitution Avenue headquarters. He unsuccessfully ran for president against Trump for the 2024 nomination, but never broke with him personally, was on Trump’s VP shortlist and has won praise from the president after he took office a second time.</p> 
<p>Neither the Justice Department nor the Federal Reserve have detailed what information investigators are seeking, but a <a href="https://d12t4t5x3vyizu.cloudfront.net/luna.house.gov/uploads/2025/07/APL-Referral-Letter-on-Powell.pdf" target="_blank">prior Justice Department perjury referral</a> brought by Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) cited contradictions between Powell’s statements and plans the Fed submitted to a federal review agency. Luna’s letter references answers Powell gave to Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.) during the Banking hearing last year after Scott first aired concerns about the renovation.</p> 
<p>News of the probe caught some White House aides, GOP lawmakers and Wall Street players off guard — especially after Powell himself recorded a videotaped statement calling it part of a Trump administration intimidation campaign.</p> 
<p>That includes members of Scott’s committee. Republicans on the panel met privately Monday evening to discuss the cryptocurrency bill he wants to push through the panel this week — a measure that is backed by the Trump administration and many of the president’s allies in the crypto industry.</p> 
<p>During the meeting, Scott did not address how he or how the panel would approach the Powell investigation, according to one attendee, who said the South Carolina Republican has his hands full trying to get an agreement on the cryptocurrency bill.</p> 
<p>A bigger headache could be coming down the pike: Scott could find it difficult to move a successor through his committee later this year when Powell’s term as Fed chair expires — with even Thune acknowledging moving a nominee could be a challenge.</p> 
<p>Tillis said Sunday night he would not advance a Fed nominee, including filling the upcoming chair vacancy, “until this legal matter is fully resolved.”</p> 
<p>Tillis’ opposition alone is enough to block the panel from being able to advance a Trump nominee to the full Senate on party lines given its 13-11 member breakdown.</p> 
<p>But he’s far from alone among Banking Committee Republicans who have raised alarm bells over the investigation. While Sen. Kevin Cramer (R-N.D.) called Powell a “bad” Fed chair, he added, “I do not believe, however, that he is a criminal.”</p> 
<p>Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.), a Banking Committee member, said if administration officials thought Powell had committed perjury, then they needed to back up the accusations. He added, “I would be stunned if he had done anything wrong.”</p> 
<p>“We need this like we need a hole to the head,” Kennedy said, warning of a possible spike in interest rates as markets lose faith in Fed independence.</p> 
<p>Powell also reached out to at least two Republicans who do not serve on the Banking Committee, with Sens. Susan Collins of Maine and Lisa Murkowski of Alaska describing calls from the Fed chair to reporters. Thune said in a brief interview that Powell had not called him, but that he’s spoken to other GOP senators who had contact.</p> 
<p>“I believe strongly in the independence of the Federal Reserve, and I know Jay Powell to be a person of integrity,” Collins told reporters Monday, cautioning that she had not yet reviewed his comments at the hearing.</p> 
<p>But she added that “one can't help but wonder if it has more to do with the chairman's resistance to pressure from the White House when it comes to interest rates than it does his testimony at the hearing.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes and Jasper Goodman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T19:13:40-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Bipartisan group of lawmakers introduces bill to prevent military action against NATO members</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/house-lawmakers-introduce-bipartisan-nato-bill-00723206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b442-dca0-ad9b-fdcb3eae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:29:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan group of lawmakers is introducing legislation to prevent President Donald Trump from taking action to invade a NATO country or territory, like Greenland. </p> 
<p>“This is about our fundamental shared goals and our fundamental security, not just not just in Europe, but in the United States itself,” said Rep. Bill Keating (D-Mass.), who’s leading the legislation along with retiring centrist Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.), Rep. Steny Hoyer (D-Md.) and Rep. Brendan Boyle (D-Pa.). The lawmakers are starting to round up support for the legislation Monday night and hope more Republicans will join the effort, Keating said.</p> 
<p>Keating said he thinks targeting funding is a stronger way to pressure the administration. </p> 
<p>“War powers are important, but we've seen with Democratic and Republican presidents that that's not as effective,” he said. “It's hard to get around having no funds or not allowing personnel to do it.”</p> 
<p>The new legislation comes as Hill Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/house-democrats-venezuela-war-powers-00713669" target="_blank">search for ways</a> to constrain further military action in Venezuela by the Trump administration after the ousting of President Nicolás Maduro. The Senate could clear a war powers measure on Venezuela later this week, though it faces an uncertain future in the House.</p> 
<p>Trump officials are openly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-greenland-military-force-00713315" target="_blank">weighing options</a> including military force to take Greenland, a Danish territory. Doing so would violate NATO’s Article V, which states an attack on one member is an attack on all of them, and could end the 76-year-old alliance. The prospect of military force has drawn a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/06/congress/johnson-trump-greenland-military-force-00713476" target="_blank">skeptical response</a> from some top Republicans and universal opposition from Democrats.</p> 
<p>In a letter to colleagues obtained by POLITICO, Keating told lawmakers “this legislation takes a clear stand against such action and further supports NATO allies and partners.”</p> 
<p>Although the legislation doesn’t name any specific countries, it’s a clear reference to Trump’s threats against Greenland. The omission was deliberate, said Keating, who wanted to broaden the legislation’s focus. He said he met with the Danish Ambassador and the head of Greenland representation as the legislation came together.</p> 
<p>"This isn't just about Greenland. This is about our security,” Keating said.</p> 
<p><i>Eric Bazail-Eimil contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Civil rights board slips into Dem hands amid ‘threats’ to oust chair</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/trump-thune-gop-civil-rights-commission-00722667</link>
      <description>The board has a Democratic majority after GOP lawmakers failed to make an appointment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b3e4-d65c-affb-bbe7e3b20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:20:53 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0d/03/384579cf48ceb7bed10e6711759a/u-s-congress-27046.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks with reporters as he walks into his office at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 15, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0d/03/384579cf48ceb7bed10e6711759a/u-s-congress-27046.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hassan Ali Kanu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hassan Ali Kanu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Inaction by Republican lawmakers has stymied <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/11/trump-civil-rights-commission-00286049" target="_blank">the Trump administration's efforts</a> to wrest control of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, allowing the panel to slip back into Democratic hands for the time being.</p> 
<p>That could have significant implications for the commission’s ongoing investigation into antisemitism on college campuses — making it more likely that the probe will scrutinize the Trump administration’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/31/trump-institutions-grovel-law-media-business-028840?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nrid=d052e1a9-e4d0-4466-9680-7f67289b5341" target="_blank">unprecedented</a> <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/11/federal-judge-restricts-trumps-pressure-campaign-against-the-university-of-california-00653371" target="_blank">pressure campaign</a> against universities and dismantling of federal civil rights offices.</p> 
<p>The commission lapsed into a 4-3 Democratic majority in December, after Senate Majority Leader John Thune failed to appoint a member to the 8-seat commission after a GOP appointee’s term expired.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Thune told POLITICO that the senator’s staff is “working on a number of appointments right now and look forward to filling this slot.”</p> 
<p>Until then, the commission’s work will continue under a Democratic majority and Democrat-appointed Chair Rochelle Garza, who has maintained her role <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/30/trump-firings-federal-agencies-00432223" target="_blank">despite a purported demotion</a> by the White House — and more recent threats that she would be detained by federal authorities and forcibly removed from her position.</p> 
<p>“A lot of this is about intimidation and it's about bullying and ... taking over the commission,” she told POLITICO. “If we are here to champion civil rights we have to do it above board and we cannot let anybody push us around, it doesn’t matter if you're the president of the United States, there are rules.”</p> 
<p>The White House did not respond to requests for comment for this story. White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt told POLITICO in April that Trump “reserves the right to fire anyone he wants” within the executive branch, shortly after Garza <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/11/trump-civil-rights-commission-00286049" target="_blank">declined to comply</a> with the administration’s decision to replace her as chair.</p> 
<p>There’s an open seat on the panel after commissioner Gail Heriot’s term expired on Dec. 12. Heriot, an affirmative action critic who is formally listed as an independent, has been appointed by Republicans to multiple terms, <a href="https://www.congress.gov/congressional-record/volume-165/issue-198/senate-section/article/S6995-2?" target="_blank">most recently in 2019</a>.</p> 
<p>She stunned commission members and staffers last year by alleging a campaign of threats against Democratic members during an unusually contentious business meeting, according to four people who attended the meeting and spoke on condition of anonymity due to the sensitive circumstances.</p> 
<p>The alleged threats also include freezing the pay of staffers who work for Democrat appointees and terminating others if their bosses do not accede to the White House’s moves to demote Garza and the Democratic vice chair, Heriot said during the September meeting.</p> 
<p>“I would love to be able to move full speed ahead on all of this and vote in favor of the President's” nominees to replace the panel’s leadership, <a href="https://youtu.be/DAHNkRRfdhA?t=1515" target="_blank">the former commissioner said</a>. “But there is a much deeper problem … and that is that threats have been made to get the four Democratic Commissioners to vote ‘yes.’ I cannot be a party to that.”</p> 
<p>Three other commission staff members familiar with the developments confirmed that employees heard about vague threats to their jobs and to physically remove the Democratic chair. The White House said last spring that it was “de-designating” Garza from her post, and elevating a Republican member instead. But the commission has not put the White House’s directive to a vote.</p> 
<p>“I have no reason to believe that these threats are coming from President Trump himself or from his top advisors … but it does seem to be coming from somewhere in the administration,” Heriot said at the meeting, adding that she could not offer further details.</p> 
<p>Heriot, whose term expired Dec. 12, did not respond to multiple requests for comment.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the commission told POLITICO that its campus antisemitism investigation is ongoing and a final report is expected in September.</p> 
<p>Colleges and universities “are cooperating with the investigation” and have sent back some interrogatories and data, the commission said. “Relevant agencies such as the Department of Education, the Department of Justice, and the Department of Health and Human Services, have been in communication with the Commission [and we are] currently awaiting responses and information from these federal agencies.”</p> 
<p>Garza told POLITICO she would continue to resist the moves to oust her, which she views as unlawful. “I’m not going to let anyone threaten or intimidate me into doing something I know is wrong,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boozman delays Senate Ag crypto markup</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/boozman-delays-senate-ag-crypto-markup-00723101</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b43b-d15b-abff-fc7f8d240000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:03:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Agriculture Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51287" data-person-id="51287">John Boozman</a> is delaying a markup on major cryptocurrency legislation in order to allow bipartisan talks to continue, punting a committee vote until the last week of January.</p> 
<p>The Arkansas Republican, who was initially preparing to hold a markup on Thursday, said in a statement that he remains “committed to advancing bipartisan crypto market structure legislation.”</p> 
<p>Boozman has been negotiating for months over the bill with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/211545" data-person-id="211545">Cory Booker</a> (D-N.J.).</p> 
<p>“We have made meaningful progress and had constructive discussions as we work toward this goal,” he said. “I appreciate the leadership and engagement of Senator Booker and his team as we address these complex policy issues. To finalize the remaining details and ensure the broad support this legislation requires, additional time is needed before moving to markup. The committee will mark up this legislation during the last week of January.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T17:07:05-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump phones Warren on affordability</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/trump-phones-warren-affordability-00722747</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b408-d65c-affb-bf8b272b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:08:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Monday called Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> (D-Mass.) after she slammed him in a speech criticizing his efforts to address rising costs.</p> 
<p>“After my speech, the President called me, and I delivered this same message on affordability to him directly,” Warren said in a statement. “I told him that Congress can pass legislation to cap credit card rates if he will actually fight for it.”</p> 
<p>The president on Friday via Truth Social <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/09/trump-says-he-will-temporarily-cap-credit-card-rates-00721147" target="_blank">called for a one year cap</a> of 10 percent for credit card interest rates in the name of affordability, starting Jan. 20.</p> 
<p>Warren, in a previous statement, said she told Trump a year ago that she would work on legislation to cap interest rates.</p> 
<p>In her speech on Monday at the National Press Club on the Democratic party’s future, Warren said she made clear that if the president “really wants to get something done, including capping credit card interest rates or lowering housing costs, he would use his leverage and pick up the phone.”</p> 
<p>"President Trump and Sen. Warren had a productive call about credit card interest rates and housing affordability for the American people," said a White House official.</p> 
<p>The Democratic lawmaker also said she urged Trump to put pressure on House Republicans to pass the Senate’s bipartisan legislation aimed at addressing housing costs.</p> 
<p>Trump previously gave his nod of approval to the Senate’s massive, bipartisan housing package. However, the House Financial Services Committee has been hard at work advancing their own major housing legislation, with a floor vote expected in the next several weeks.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T17:02:06-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Kelly sues Hegseth over effort to punish him for anti-Trump video</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/mark-kelly-pete-hegseth-lawsuit-00722382</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b3be-d65c-affb-bbbfada20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:47:22 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/163882" data-person-id="163882">Mark Kelly</a> is suing Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth and other senior military leaders over the Pentagon's attempt to punish him for telling troops not to follow illegal orders.</p> 
<p>The Arizona Democrat, <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.288365/gov.uscourts.dcd.288365.1.0.pdf" target="_blank">in filings made public Monday</a>, asked a federal court to block a review that could demote the former Navy captain’s rank and reduce his retirement pay. Hegseth <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/hegseth-kelly-punish-video-00710555" target="_blank">announced the review this month</a> and censured Kelly for his comments against the administration.</p> 
<p>The lawsuit is the latest salvo in a fight that began in November after Kelly and five other Democrats with national security backgrounds released a video reminding troops of their duty not to follow illegal orders. President Donald Trump and Hegseth have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">attacked their remarks</a> as “seditious.”</p> 
<p>The suit names Hegseth as a defendant along with Navy Secretary John Phelan, the Defense Department and the Navy. Kelly served for 25 years in the military, including time as a NASA astronaut and a fighter pilot who flew missions in Operation Desert Storm.</p> 
<p>Kelly said in a statement that the lawsuit is necessary to stand up to improper and baseless behavior by Hegseth.</p> 
<p>“His unconstitutional crusade against me sends a chilling message to every retired member of the military: if you speak out and say something that the president or secretary of Defense doesn’t like, you will be censured, threatened with demotion, or even prosecuted,” he said. “That’s not the way things work in the United States of America, and I won’t stand for it.”</p> 
<p>The Pentagon declined to comment on the suit, citing pending legislation. </p> 
<p>While Kelly and the other lawmakers did not specify in the video what orders they considered illegal, Democrats in recent weeks have argued Trump is putting the military in a legal gray area with deadly strikes against suspect drug smuggling boats in Latin America, the capture and arrest of Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro and by deploying the National Guard to U.S. cities.</p> 
<p>The Pentagon <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894" target="_blank">announced an investigation into Kelly</a> in November for “serious allegations of misconduct” that could result in recalling him to active duty for a court martial. The department last week stopped short of that, with Hegseth announcing proceedings to demote Kelly to a lower rank and reduce his retirement pay.</p> 
<p>Kelly’s lawyers argue in the filing that the attacks from Hegseth “violate numerous constitutional guarantees and have no basis in statute” and “should proceed no further.”</p> 
<p>Kelly contends Hegseth and Trump’s attacks on him pointed toward a preordained outcome that deprived him of a legitimate opportunity to rebut the allegations against him.</p> 
<p>“If permitted to stand, the Secretary’s censure and the grade-determination proceedings that he has directed will inflict immediate and irreparable harm,” his lawyers wrote. “The Constitution does not permit the government to announce the verdict in advance and then subject Senator Kelly or anyone else to a nominal process designed only to fulfill it.”</p> 
<p>Kelly said he’s being targeted over commentary on issues that are central to his role as a lawmaker: the management of the military by Hegseth, legislation related to war crimes and the military justice system.</p> 
<p>The lawsuit argues that punishment for his comments would violate protections — codified in the Constitution’s speech or debate clause — meant to insulate Congress from executive branch pressure.</p> 
<p>Kelly and his lawyers also note that “a sitting Member of Congress has never been subject to military punishment based solely on his speech."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T15:31:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>GOP angst grows over Powell investigation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/gop-angst-grows-powell-investigation-00721939</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b2ef-d15b-abff-feff179f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:00:33 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A growing number of Republicans on Capitol Hill are expressing unease with the Justice Department’s move to investigate Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell, a sign that the probe could become a major inflection point over GOP lawmakers’ concerns about central bank independence.</p> 
<p>Powell <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679?vct=1.76818488101e9" target="_blank">announced Sunday</a> that the DOJ is investigating him over statements to Congress about renovations of the Fed’s headquarters in Washington. He said the issue was a pretext to target him in response to President Donald Trump’s frustration over the Fed’s hesitance to aggressively lower interest rates.</p> 
<p>House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) rebuked the probe in a statement Monday, saying it “creates an unnecessary distraction” that “could undermine this and future Administrations’ ability to make sound monetary policy decisions.”</p> 
<p>“I’ve known Chairman Powell since we worked together at Treasury during the George H.W. Bush Administration," he said. "Then, as now, I know Mr. Powell to be a man of integrity with a strong commitment to public service. While over the years we have had our policy disagreements, I found him to be forthright, candid, and a person of the highest integrity."</p> 
<p>In the Senate, at least four Republicans — including three members of the Banking Committee, which oversees the Fed — have signaled opposition to the DOJ moving against Powell, including close Trump allies like Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422906" data-person-id="422906">Dave McCormick</a> (R-Pa.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198816" data-person-id="198816">Kevin Cramer</a> (R-N.D.).</p> 
<p>GOP lawmakers on Capitol Hill, Republican senators in particular, have heard conflicting views from inside the White House about the Powell probe, according to three Republicans with direct knowledge of the matter. One of the Republicans noted "the internal disagreements are intense" inside the White House and Trump's circle, about whether DOJ should pursue its probe into Powell.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said Monday that he hadn't seen the specific allegations, "but I would say they better — they better be real and they better be serious."</p> 
<p>Cramer, a Powell critic who sits on Senate Banking, said in a statement Monday that “Jerome Powell is a bad Fed Chair who has been elusive with Congress, especially regarding the overruns of the elaborate renovations of the building.”</p> 
<p>“I do not believe however, he is a criminal,” he said. “I hope this criminal investigation can be put to rest quickly along with the remainder of Jerome Powell's term. We need to restore confidence in the Fed.”</p> 
<p>McCormick, who served as CEO of the hedge fund Bridgewater Associates prior to running for Senate, said in a statement that he believes “strongly in an independent Federal Reserve."</p> 
<p>“I also agree with President Trump that Chairman Powell has been slow to cut interest rates," he said. "I think the Federal Reserve renovation may well have wasted taxpayer dollars, but the proper place to fix this is through Congressional oversight. I do not think Chairman Powell is guilty of criminal activity.”</p> 
<p>Separately, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) on Monday offered among the harshest GOP <a href="https://x.com/lisamurkowski/status/2010743755603948017?s=20" target="_blank">rebukes yet on X</a>, writing that "the administration’s investigation is nothing more than an attempt at coercion."</p> 
<p>"If the Department of Justice believes an investigation into Chair Powell is warranted based on project cost overruns—which are not unusual—then Congress needs to investigate the Department of Justice," she said. "The stakes are too high to look the other way: if the Federal Reserve loses its independence, the stability of our markets and the broader economy will suffer."</p> 
<p>Senate Banking Republicans are expected to meet Monday night to discuss major cryptocurrency legislation the panel is aiming to hold a vote on this week — and some members are expecting to discuss the Powell probe as well, according to two Republicans with knowledge of the plan who were granted anonymity to discuss closed-door matters.</p> 
<p>“There will be a lot of chatter,” said one of the Republicans.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.), who sits on the House Financial Services Committee, told POLITICO: “While I fundamentally believe Chairman Powell was late in addressing inflation under Joe Biden and has been woefully slow in lowering interest rates over the past year, the independence of the Federal Reserve is paramount and I oppose any effort to pressure them into action."</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51492" data-person-id="51492">Frank Lucas</a> (R-Okla.), who chairs a House Financial Services task force on monetary policy, said in a statement that the "president is laser focused on creating the best economic outcomes possible."</p> 
<p>"The independence of the Fed is critical in doing so, and I’m confident the judicial system will produce the right results, while setting the appropriate precedents for future administrations and FOMCs," he said.</p> 
<p>Other Republicans are signaling less concern about the probe. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66891" data-person-id="66891">Cynthia Lummis</a> (R-Wyo.) said in a statement that “whether Chairman Powell was unprepared for his testimony or intentionally misled Congress about the Fed’s extravagant spending, the American people deserve answers."</p> 
<p>"I will wait for the DOJ to release its findings before commenting further,” she said.</p> 
<p>Asked about the Powell investigation on Fox Business on Monday, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259544" data-person-id="259544">Roger Marshall</a> (R-Kan.) bashed the central bank chief and said the “president is sending a message to everybody that we're going to be looking out for fraud, waste and abuse.” But, pressed by host Maria Bartiromo about whether Powell lied to Congress, Marshall said he would “let the system play through here,” and added: “I think there's other issues that we should be focused on.”</p> 
<p>The controversy over the renovations to the Fed’s Washington headquarters has been amplified by Senate Banking Republicans, including Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> (R-S.C.), who pressed Powell about the issue during a hearing last June following a New York Post article about cost overruns on the project.</p> 
<p>Now, the DOJ probe is threatening to derail the Senate’s consideration of future Fed nominees. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a>, a retiring North Carolina Republican who sits on the Banking panel, said Sunday he will “oppose the confirmation of any nominee for the Fed — including the upcoming Fed Chair vacancy — until this legal matter is fully resolved.” Murkowski, who does not sit on Banking but is a key swing vote on the Senate floor, said on X that Tillis "is right in blocking any Federal Reserve nominees until this is resolved."</p> 
<p>“If there were any remaining doubt whether advisers within the Trump Administration are actively pushing to end the independence of the Federal Reserve, there should now be none,” Tillis said in his statement. “It is now the independence and credibility of the Department of Justice that are in question.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: A previous version of this story misstated the state of Sen. Kevin Cramer.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP stock trading ban bill set for Wednesday markup</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/stock-trading-bill-markup-scheduled-00721884</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b2cf-dca0-ad9b-fbcf52aa0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:27:39 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Administration Committee will hold a markup Wednesday morning on a closely watched plan from GOP leadership to crack down on lawmaker insider trading, according to three people granted anonymity to share scheduling plans not yet made public.</p> 
<p>The legislation from Chair Bryan Steil and House GOP leaders would allow lawmakers to hold the current stocks they own but require a seven-day notice before making sales, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/johnson-steil-insider-trading-stocks-00698141" target="_blank">as POLITICO first reported</a>. It also would bar lawmakers and their spouses from buying new stocks.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson and GOP leaders have been searching for a legislative compromise to appease Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) and other rank-and-file House Republicans, who have for months been threatening to launch a discharge petition effort to circumvent leadership and force a floor vote on a full congressional stock trading ban.</p> 
<p>Luna, in a promising sign for Johnson, said in an interview last week she supports the current legislation pending before the House Administration Committee because it would force a "disgorgement" period.</p> 
<p>But the bill still faces an uphill climb. Senior House Democrats are deeply opposed to the plan and will seek to make changes, arguing the legislation does not constitute a full ban on congressional stock trading.</p> 
<p>Key senators, including many Republicans, also deeply oppose any changes to the current rules around lawmaker stock trading, and it's possible the Senate doesn't take up the legislation at all should the measure pass the House.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump tests GOP with Fed probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/trump-gop-doj-fed-jerome-powell-00721769</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b07f-d65c-affb-bbff33d40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is once again forcing a tough fealty test on GOP lawmakers — this time over the fate of the Federal Reserve and Chair Jerome Powell.</p> 
<p>The Fed chair’s Sunday night revelation of a DOJ probe into the central bank immediately rattled a number of Capitol Hill Republicans and raised serious doubts about the confirmation of Trump’s upcoming pick to succeed Powell.</p> 
<p>“Will they stop at nothing to force their way on everything?” one senior House Republican granted anonymity told POLITICO. “The administration is setting a standard they cannot achieve themselves and will haunt us all for a generation.”</p> 
<p>The DOJ move is the epic culmination of Trump’s years of enmity toward Powell over interest rates. It may be the point at which Republicans who believe in Fed independence — and who are generally fans of Powell — can no longer stand on the sidelines.</p> 
<p>Powell himself, whom DOJ is scrutinizing over Senate testimony about office building renovations, is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679?vct=1.76818488101e9" target="_blank">pushing back like never before</a>. Powell is warning out loud that it all comes down to whether monetary policy “will be directed by political pressure or intimidation.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) is now threatening to use his seat on Senate Banking to derail the confirmation of Powell’s successor. Assuming no Democrats voted for the yet-to-be-named nominee, it would take only Tillis to stand in the way of the pick from being reported out of committee.</p> 
<p>“If there were any remaining doubt whether advisers within the Trump Administration are actively pushing to end the independence of the Federal Reserve, there should now be none,” Tillis said. “It is now the independence and credibility of the Department of Justice that are in question.”</p> 
<p>The latest Trump rift comes as Senate Republicans are poised to defy the president later this week when the chamber votes on whether to check his war powers in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>The Senate is currently looking at Wednesday to hold a vote-a-rama before final passage of the war powers resolution. Republican leaders are trying to flip at least some of <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">the five GOP senators</a> who agreed to advance the measure last week and enraged Trump.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see what happens,” Senate Majority Leader John Thune told POLITICO. “I can’t make any predictions at this point, but I think you have to be prepared for all contingencies but also realize you’ve got to pivot and move forward.”</p> 
<p>Democrats hope GOP support stays firm — or even increases — as Trump floats the prospect of military action elsewhere, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/trump-briefed-options-iran-00721524" target="_blank">including Iran</a>.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— What’s next in government funding: </b>House GOP leaders want to pass the latest bicameral, bipartisan funding deal as soon as Wednesday, after appropriators <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/appropriators-release-two-bill-funding-package-ahead-of-january-shutdown-deadline-00721280" target="_blank">nailed down a two-bill package</a> consisting of State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services.</p> 
<p>Appropriators were hoping to include a third bill to fund DHS but were unable to reach an agreement after last week’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/minneapolis-immigration-crackdown-shooting-00714034" target="_blank">fatal ICE shooting in Minneapolis</a> created new complications.</p> 
<p>Senate leaders are working to clear the previous appropriations minibus the House passed last week for the departments of Justice, Interior, Energy and Commerce.</p> 
<p><b>— Senate negotiators close in on ACA deal: </b>A bipartisan Senate group is poised to release a plan as soon as Tuesday or Wednesday to revive expired Obamacare subsidies, according to Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio), one of the negotiators.</p> 
<p>The main sticking point is how to address the use of federal funds for abortions. The bipartisan Senate group is expected to meet Monday night to continue talks.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Jennifer Scholtes and Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This GOP senator says reviving Obamacare subsidies would be ‘putting America first’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/bernie-moreno-obamacare-talks-00719585</link>
      <description>Ohio Sen. Bernie Moreno is part of an unlikely new generation of Senate dealmakers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a4cf-da56-afff-acdfbf66000b</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0f/04/70ad978241c1ba3e7396df85e970/u-s-congress-93131.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“Putting America first means putting Americans first,” Sen. Bernie Moreno said, reconciling his pro-Trump views with his health care efforts.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0f/04/70ad978241c1ba3e7396df85e970/u-s-congress-93131.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If the Senate is going to strike a deal to revive a signature Democratic policy, it will be in part because of an unlikely broker: a freshman Republican from the party’s MAGA wing.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> of Ohio is, on paper, an odd fit in the core group of about a dozen senators <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/senate-deal-obamacare-subsidies-00714048" target="_blank">in talks to extend Obamacare credits</a> that lapsed Jan. 1. Most are well-known bipartisan dealmakers, such as Republican <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> and Democrat <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a>.</p> 
<p>Moreno, on the other hand, joined the Senate a year ago as a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/03/19/trump-backed-moreno-wins-ohio-senate-primary-00147945" target="_blank">President Donald Trump-anointed loyalist</a> who had just defeated longtime Democratic Sen. Sherrod Brown with hard-line attacks focused mainly on immigration. But he has a key asset — a close relationship with Trump, who will need to bless or at least tacitly accept any agreement to smooth its passage through Congress.</p> 
<p>Asked in an interview about his decision to take a leading role in the politically fraught health care negotiations, Moreno deployed one of Trump’s best-known slogans.</p> 
<p>“Putting America first means putting Americans first,” he said. “People are being affected, and I want to help the people who need help. That’s what we should be doing.”</p> 
<p>He said his goal is to get roughly 35 of the Senate’s 53 GOP senators to support an eventual deal — not just a handful joining Democrats on a “defection vote” — and that he’s keeping the White House and Senate leaders closely apprised of the discussions.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> praised Moreno in an interview as “whip-smart” and “willing to do the work.”</p> 
<p>“He’s willing to sit down with people and try and find common ground, which I think on an issue like this is challenging,” he said. “Around here, that’s worth a lot.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ef/c5/3f9e764b4ad3840cb1a23ae91295/u-s-congress-99303.jpg" alt="Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine) speaks with reporters as she arrives for a Senate Republican Conference meeting at the Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown Nov. 7, 2025. " data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine) speaks with reporters as she arrives for a Senate Republican Conference meeting at the Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown Nov. 7, 2025. "/><p>His involvement is also a sign that a new generation of bipartisan dealmakers might be starting to emerge after some of the Senate’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/29/senate-gop-dealmakers-depart-just-as-congress-control-splits-00075068" target="_blank">old hands headed for the exits</a> in recent cycles. Moreno is now in close touch with not only Collins and Shaheen but other Senate pragmatists such as <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine).</p> 
<p>Moreno’s text chain with the dozen-member group is labeled the “EPTC OG gang” — a reference to the enhanced premium tax credits, the technical name for the Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>At times, Moreno’s new-kid-on-the-block status has been on display. After Moreno and Collins convened a meeting in December near the Capitol Rotunda, the Ohio Republican asked a reporter for directions to the room, inadvertently tipping off its location.</p> 
<p>Minutes later, Collins walked toward the meeting seemingly astounded that word had gotten out about what she said was a “secret meeting.” Told about Moreno’s request for help, a bemused Collins put a hand to the side of her face.</p> 
<p>Moreno said his freshman status means he doesn’t have “scars” from previous congressional fights.</p> 
<p>“‘Oh, I don’t want to be working with this person,’ or ‘They screwed me back in 1972,’ you know?” he said. “I was in Kindergarten, so it doesn’t affect me.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/00/de/21413c30406bb51223a756478777/u-s-congress-13168.jpg" alt="Moreno sprints to a vote at the U.S. Capitol on the 41st day of a government shutdown, Nov. 10, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25315750013168" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Moreno sprints to a vote at the U.S. Capitol on the 41st day of a government shutdown, Nov. 10, 2025."/><p>At 58, Moreno is on the younger side for the Senate, but he is already airing frustrations about the chamber’s growing polarization and making points about addressing it that jibe closely with complaints frequently heard from older generations of senators.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think there’s enough muscle memory here about actually going in with good faith, good intentions and getting together and seeing if the deal can be cut,” he said.</p> 
<p>The group of negotiators have their work cut out for them. They are discussing a two-year extension of the Obamacare tax credits that were beefed up under former President Joe Biden. Since their lapse at the end of last year, the tax credits — which were used by more than 500,000 Ohioans, <a href="https://www.kff.org/affordable-care-act/state-indicator/average-monthly-advance-premium-tax-credit-aptc/?currentTimeframe=0&amp;sortModel=%7B%22colId%22:%22Location%22,%22sort%22:%22asc%22%7D" target="_blank">according to KFF data</a> — have reverted to their original 2010 levels, benefiting only those with incomes under 400 percent of the federal poverty level.</p> 
<p>The Senate group’s proposed extension would include new restrictions including a $5 a month minimum premium payment and an income cap set at 700 percent of the federal poverty level. In the second year, the proposal would also give enrollees to take their subsidy as cash in pre-funded health savings accounts — an arrangement favored by Trump.</p> 
<p>Moreno believes the group is in the “red zone,” and could be ready with text as soon as Tuesday or Wednesday. But some Democrats involved in the discussions have been more circumspect, wary about a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/republicans-trump-obamacare-abortion-00669389" target="_blank">thorny dispute over abortion</a>.</p> 
<p>Many Republicans say they will not be able to support a compromise unless the subsidies are tightened so they cannot fund abortions in any manner. Democrats say the safeguards built into the Affordable Care Act upon its passage in 2010 are sufficient.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/8a/d5/2f6151f4488b96693d0a219aac91/u-s-congress-51941.jpg" alt="Sen. Dick Durbin (D-Ill.) arrives for a Senate Judiciary Committee hearing on Capitol Hill, on Oct. 7, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Sen. Dick Durbin (D-Ill.) arrives for a Senate Judiciary Committee hearing on Capitol Hill, on Oct. 7, 2025."/><p>“I think we’ve made clear from the start, the Democrats feel we have to come to the rescue and I hope we can do it,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> of Illinois, the No. 2 party leader. But he warned that if the Republicans “decide they want to make this an abortion issue, I’m afraid that’s the end of the conversation.”</p> 
<p>Moreno said the group wasn’t trying to relitigate questions over federal funding for abortions but acknowledged there is a “dispute” over whether that is currently happening.</p> 
<p>Republicans’ heartburn over the issue flared last week after Trump suggested in remarks to House members that they should be “flexible” on abortion language — sparking <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/conservatives-anti-abortion-trump-health-care-gop-00712565" target="_blank">outrage from outside conservative groups</a> that ricocheted back on Congress.</p> 
<p>A person granted anonymity to discuss the negotiations said Republicans in a larger negotiating group of roughly two dozen senators haven’t yet landed on a consensus position — much less the entire Senate GOP conference.</p> 
<p>“There’s no need to come to a compromise because it’s already been dealt with in the Affordable Care Act,” Shaheen said when asked about the issue.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/59/a0/7b46c3ee4a4299cea1d74b5438ba/u-s-congress-64774.jpg" alt="Sen. Jon Husted (R-Ohio) displays data about major health insurance company stock performance after Obamacare as he speaks with reporters at the U.S. Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown, Nov. 7, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25312009964774" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Sen. Jon Husted (R-Ohio) displays data about major health insurance company stock performance after Obamacare as he speaks with reporters at the U.S. Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown, Nov. 7, 2025."/><p>While the abortion question is a powerful force pulling some Republicans away from a deal, there are also compelling reasons for many to embrace a compromise — not least of which is the threat the expiring subsidies pose to the GOP majorities in November.</p> 
<p>Among the vulnerable lawmakers is Moreno’s GOP partner in the Ohio delegation, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307927" data-person-id="307927">Jon Husted</a>, who is facing a likely matchup with Brown.</p> 
<p>Moreno acknowledged that despite a feeling among negotiators that they are close to an agreement, it could all come to naught. Lawmakers “are on the clock,” he said, and getting a deal is an “if.”</p> 
<p>“Capital I, capital F,” he said. “75-point font.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rep. Salazar touts Venezuela's Machado before her visit</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/salazar-throws-support-behind-venezuela-machado-00721587</link>
      <description>The Florida Republican said Trump will be ‘highly pleased’ with the opposition leader and winner of the Nobel Peace Prize.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ae86-dca0-ad9b-ff8f70c80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 15:20:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/ff/0b/4134def9479cbb2f3f98fb29abd2/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2250564219">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Odd Andersen/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump will be "highly, highly pleased” with Maria Corina Machado when she visits Washington this week, said Rep. Maria Elvira Salazar.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ff/0b/4134def9479cbb2f3f98fb29abd2/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2250564219" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307604" data-person-id="307604">Maria Elvira Salazar</a> on Sunday said Venezuela’s opposition leader Maria Corina Machado has “earned” enough to receive President Donald Trump’s backing as the South American country recovers from the capture of Nicolas Maduro.</p> 
<p>“She proved to the international community that they, the opposition forces, had won the election,” the Florida Republican told CBS’ “Face the Nation.”</p> 
<p>Salazar, who said she was in contact with Machado during the time she was in hiding during Maduro’s rule, added that Trump will be ”highly, highly pleased” with Machado when she visits Washington this week.</p> 
<p>“I am sure that she will have a very good, long, solid conversation with the President,” Salazar said. “I think we are going to welcome her in Congress, and I'm sure that President Trump is going to be highly, highly pleased with that meeting.</p> 
<p>Salazar’s optimism comes as the organization that oversees the Nobel Peace Prize announced Machado cannot give her recent award to Trump.</p> 
<p>Machado won the prestigious prize in October, and quickly dedicated the award to the president. Trump had repeatedly expressed his desire to be awarded the prize, particularly in light of his work to end the Israel-Hamas war and other conflicts.</p> 
<p>Trump declined to endorse Machado as the nation's new leader in the wake of the raid that netted Maduro and left Venezuela at least temporarily leaderless. But Salazar on Sunday said Machado “is part of the transition” in Venezuela now that Maduro is no longer in power — a sharp difference from Trump’s previous statements that the U.S. will run Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Salazar said there are things that the U.S. may not know about what is happening in Venezuela under Maduro’s allies, Delcy Rodríguez and Diosdado Cabello.</p> 
<p>Still, her optimism continued as she said she is confident American prisoners will soon be released.</p> 
<p>“We do not want to make any mistakes and I am sure that the political prisoners will be coming out and that we're not giving them, meaning Diosdado and Delcy, any type of leeway for them to really run the country,” said Salazar. “We will see. I happened two, three weeks ago. Let's give them a little bit more time before we see more results.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rand Paul: Bombing Iran ‘is not the answer’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/rand-paul-bombing-iran-not-the-answer-00721432</link>
      <description>“I don’t think it’s the job of the American government to be involved with every freedom movement around the world,” the Kentucky senator said.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ae15-d65c-affb-af9761340000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 12:52:48 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8e/bb/9ae9b2134ed28a6db68a873f1ae7/u-s-congress-65498.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Rand Paul speaks during a hearing on Capitol Hill on July 15, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8e/bb/9ae9b2134ed28a6db68a873f1ae7/u-s-congress-65498.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Rand Paul expressed concerns Sunday over President Donald Trump’s threats to bomb Iran as the Middle Eastern country sees widespread protests continue.</p> 
<p>Speaking with ABC’s “This Week,” the Kentucky Republican said he is not sure striking Iran “will have the effects intended.”</p> 
<p>“We wish freedom and liberation the best around the world, but I don’t think it’s the job of the American government to be involved with every freedom movement around the world,” Paul said.</p> 
<p>Paul also expressed concerns over how the administration would distinguish between Iranian protesters and law enforcement if Trump were to approve military action in the region.</p> 
<p>“How do you drop a bomb in the middle of a crowd or a protest and protect the people there?” Paul said. “Plus there's the constitution that we don't let presidents bomb countries when they feel like it. They are supposed to ask the people through the Congress for permission.”</p> 
<p>Protests erupted in the Islamic Republic late last month as Iranians expressed dissatisfaction over the country’s economic free fall. But as demonstrations have continued, many have begun to demand total regime change.</p> 
<p>Reports indicate thousands have been arrested, and agencies have been unable to confirm the total death toll due to an internet blackout as the regime works to quell the dissent. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/iranian-death-toll-spikes-00721390" target="_blank">The latest Associated Press report</a> put the figure as at least 538.</p> 
<p>Trump on Friday warned Iranian leaders, “You better not start shooting, because we’ll start shooting, too.” And an a post to Truth Social on Saturday, the president wrote that “Iran is looking at FREEDOM, perhaps like never before. The USA stands ready to help!!!”</p> 
<p>But Paul on Sunday said that U.S. involvement may unintentionally rally protesters behind the Ayatollah.</p> 
<p>“If you bomb the government, do you then rally people to their flag who are upset with the Ayatollah but then say, gosh, we can't have a foreign government invading or bombing our country?” Paul said. “It tends to have people rally to the cause.”</p> 
<p>He added that the protests are justifiable.</p> 
<p>“The best way is to encourage them and say, we would recognize a government that is a freedom-loving government, that allows free elections, but bombing is not the answer,” Paul said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How John Thune is trying to save the Senate for Republicans</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/10/john-thune-senate-midterms-campaign-00721008</link>
      <description>The Senate majority leader appeared at the U.S.-Mexico border to rekindle interest in the GOP’s legislative accomplishments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a52e-d65c-affb-afafbbb70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d8/0a/b24184f44185abe431eebe5a817f/thune2.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jordain Carney/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Thune led a campaign delegation at the U.S.-Mexico border to tout provisions in the Republican megabill.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d8/0a/b24184f44185abe431eebe5a817f/thune2.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>McALLEN, Texas — John Thune is ramping up his sales pitch as he tries to turn the GOP’s attention toward November and keeping the Senate majority.</p> 
<p>But as the majority leader campaigned along the U.S.-Mexico border Friday with a coalition of Republicans up for reelection this year, he acknowledged challenges so far in promoting the legislative centerpiece of the party’s message — not to mention what he called the midterm “headwinds” facing any party in power.</p> 
<p>Thune is betting that an aggressive campaign blitz between now and the fall, and a hopefully burgeoning economy, will help Republicans keep and potentially grow their 53-seat majority — even as voters seem indifferent about the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/house-passes-gop-megabill-00438206" target="_blank">GOP’s “big, beautiful bill”</a> and President Donald Trump struggles in sticking to a kitchen-table script.</p> 
<p>Having Republicans back home touting the party line, Thune said, will help.</p> 
<p>“Last year, our members were in many cases, for obvious reasons, in Washington, trying to get the job done,” Thune said in an interview. “But now that we're in an even-numbered year and people are out running for reelection, I think having us as a body focus very directly on the message that we're delivering to the American people is going to make a big difference.”</p> 
<p>He also acknowledged that Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/democrats-megabill-obbba-attacks-00439786" target="_blank">leapt out of the gate</a> last year in hammering the GOP megabill even before it was finished, adding that “they have the advantage of being the opposition party.”</p> 
<p>On Friday, Thune &amp; Co. attempted to turn the tide by highlighting the border security resources that were included in the sprawling policy package that also included tax cuts, defense spending and energy initiatives, among other legislative potpourri.</p> 
<p>Republicans started out the 2026 cycle as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/10/04/republicans-senate-2026-primaries-thune-trump-00593428" target="_blank">odds-on favorites for keeping control</a> of the Senate. They still have an edge, according to most forecasters. But Democrats have made a dent in the GOP’s advantage by securing big-name recruits in key races as Republicans face some heated and costly intraparty primaries.</p> 
<p>Success will depend in large part on the Republicans who joined Thune Friday in Texas. Michael Whatley, who is running to succeed North Carolina Sen. Thom Tillis, and former Rep. Mike Rogers, who is looking to flip the seat held by retiring Democratic Sen. Gary Peters in Michigan, joined several in-cycle GOP incumbents, including Texas Sen. John Cornyn.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/8d/aa/0edf59d246ffa279b06d903c9937/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2161701949" alt="Former RNC chair Michael Whatley is among the Republican candidates Thune is counting on." data-portal-copyright="Angela Weiss/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AFP via Getty Images" data-title="Former RNC chair Michael Whatley is among the Republican candidates Thune is counting on."/><p>Thune showered particular praise on Cornyn, who is fighting for his political life in a three-way primary. Underscoring the nasty internal fight facing the GOP, rival Ken Paxton — the state attorney general and one of Cornyn’s primary opponents — accused Cornyn of trying to “rewrite history” with the border trip and predicted that his career will end in “national embarrassment.”</p> 
<p>Thune’s effort to use his bully pulpit to focus on the party’s legislative accomplishments comes as Republicans continue to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/21/republicans-trump-vance-megabill-00516964" target="_blank">fret that they haven’t done enough</a> to sell the megabill. Many wonder in hindsight whether their decision to pack so many priorities together into a single piece of legislation — a decision driven in part by the party-line budget reconciliation process — was ill-conceived.</p> 
<p>“We’ve talked about that,” Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.) said in an interview Friday on the sidelines of a news conference at the border wall where it took four placards to display all the highlights from the megabill.</p> 
<p>“Secure Border, More Money, New Opportunities,” read a sign on the podium summarizing the legislation.</p> 
<p>But an overstuffed domestic policy bill is far from the top concern for Republicans who remain nervous about addressing Americans’ anxieties about the steeply rising cost of living.</p> 
<p>While many GOP leaders spent the final months of 2025 vowing to focus on affordability issues — and Thune vowed Friday Republicans would in 2026 — the opening days of the year have been focused abroad after Trump ousted Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro. The military action sparked a fiery debate in Congress about presidential war powers that threaten to blot out other matters.</p> 
<p>“It’s certainly going to consume the news cycle for a while,” said Sen. John Hoeven of North Dakota in an interview in the Capitol this week.</p> 
<p>It certainly has preoccupied Trump, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/trump-war-powers-republicans-election-00716332" target="_blank">lashed out at five Senate Republicans</a> who joined with Democrats Thursday to advance a measure constraining his future military moves in Venezuela. One of them, Susan Collins of Maine, is up for reelection, and Trump announced publicly that she and the other four “should never be elected to office again.”</p> 
<p>Thune <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/john-thune-trump-war-powers-00719369" target="_blank">said he had a “very spirited” conversation</a> with Trump before he delivered the attacks and acknowledged his frustrations. But Thune said he was focused on keeping Republicans “united as much as possible and work[ing] with the president.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/24/86/b934239c498b8fc4bc72d39f4310/white-house-46217.jpg" alt="Trump and Thune had a productive working relationship in 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25199838746217" data-licensor-name="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-title="Trump and Thune had a productive working relationship in 2025."/><p>The two are viewed as having a good personal relationship, with Trump publicly praising Thune throughout 2025 — a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/03/14/john-thune-south-dakota-profile-00223248" target="_blank">transformation from just a few years before</a>, when Trump threatened to back a primary challenger against the South Dakotan. Thune, in turn, repeatedly praised Trump and his work on the border Friday.</p> 
<p>That doesn’t mean they don’t have their differences. Thune, with the backing of his conference, has rebuffed Trump’s demands to nix the filibuster and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/b-00686585" target="_blank">other Senate norms</a> that preserve minority power. They have also clashed on policy — most conspicuously on the president’s aggressive use of tariffs which have negatively impacted farmers in Thune’s home state.</p> 
<p>Thune acknowledged they sometimes don’t see eye-to-eye but added he views his job as needing to “protect the institution … maintain it as the founders intended as a check and balance.”</p> 
<p>Thune reiterated Friday that he’s labored to hash out most of those differences behind the scenes, seeking to avoid any public blowups that would suck up political oxygen and potentially force his members to choose sides.</p> 
<p>That said, he added, “there are times, yes, where you have to push back” — pointing back to the conversation on the war powers resolution, which Thune opposed.</p> 
<p>Pushing back could be trickier in an election year, when Republicans need to be in lockstep as they make their case for another two years in power on Capitol Hill while Trump seeks to lock in a presidential legacy and otherwise enforce his will over the party.</p> 
<p>Beyond dealing with Trump’s angry outburst, Thune is trying to keep the party — and the president — singing from the same hymnal heading into November.</p> 
<p>“Obviously, yesterday he was frustrated, but I think there's going to be a lot to point to in terms of a record of accomplishment for him and for him working with us,” Thune said of Trump. “As we get out there and talk about it, I think it’ll start to change the perceptions and the views in the public.”</p> 
<p><i>Alex Gangitano contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Thune and Donald Trump had a ‘spirited’ conversation over Senate war powers vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/john-thune-trump-war-powers-00719369</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a442-d15b-abff-fc5e798a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 14:45:09 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>McALLEN, Texas — Shortly after <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">five Republican senators</a> broke with Donald Trump and voted Thursday to advance a measure constraining his military options in Venezuela, the president lashed out and called for them to lose their seats.</p> 
<p>Before he turned to Truth Social, however, he connected with John Thune and gave him a piece of his mind.</p> 
<p>The Senate majority leader acknowledged the “very spirited” conversation with the angry president in an interview Friday after appearing with several Republican senators and candidates along the U.S.-Mexico border to promote last year’s GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>“There’s a level of frustration at the White House — and with us, too, on a vote like that,” he said.</p> 
<p>A White House spokesperson did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>The war-powers fight is hardly over — the Senate still needs to debate and pass the resolution that was advanced Thursday, and even if the House passes it, which is unlikely, Trump could still veto it. But the surprising procedural vote contributed to a narrative that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/donald-trump-congress-weak-00718030" target="_blank">Trump is losing his grip</a> on congressional Republicans after running roughshod over potential GOP renegades in 2025.</p> 
<p>Two of the five senators — Rand Paul of Kentucky and Lisa Murkowski of Alaska — supported a previous effort to rein Trump in on Venezuela. Three others — Susan Collins of Maine, Josh Hawley of Missouri and Todd Young of Indiana — were more surprising.</p> 
<p>Thune declined to predict whether he would be able to flip at least two to block the resolution’s passage next week, but he signaled a lobbying effort is underway.</p> 
<p>“Obviously we’d love to have some of our colleagues come back around on that issue,” he said. “The constitutional questions, the legal questions, are being more sufficiently answered as people have probed into it.”</p> 
<p>But he added that, for his part, no grudges would be held — no matter the outcome.</p> 
<p>“The most important vote isn’t the last vote, it’s the next vote,” he said. “At the end of the day, there are going to be a lot more votes coming, and circumstances in which we’re going to have our team united as much as possible and work with the president.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Oversight GOP threatens to hold Clintons in contempt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/clintons-in-contempt-00719084</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a3ca-da56-afff-afdab5460000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 12:34:31 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Republican-led House Oversight and Government Reform Committee is threatening to hold former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in contempt of Congress if they fail to appear for closed-door depositions next week as part of the panel’s investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>The panel previously issued a subpoena for Bill Clinton, who has been tied to Epstein, to appear before congressional investigators Jan. 13; Hillary Clinton has been provided a subpoena to testify Jan. 14. But a committee spokesperson said Friday that, so far, neither had confirmed they would participate.</p> 
<p>“They are obligated under the law to appear and we expect them to do so,” the spokesperson said in a statement. “If the Clintons do not appear for their depositions, the House Oversight Committee will initiate contempt of Congress proceedings.”</p> 
<p>This seldom-used congressional power can range in implications from a symbolic action to a precursor to forcing jail time.</p> 
<p>In examples of the potential serious consequences to contempt of Congress charges, two Trump associates, Steve Bannon and Peter Navarro, were sentenced to prison time for failing to cooperate with subpoenas from the Democratic-led select committee investigating the Jan. 6, 2021 attacks on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>The GOP-controlled House voted to hold former Attorney General Merrick Garland <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/06/12/congress/house-gop-clears-garland-contempt-00163046" target="_blank">in contempt in 2024</a> over the Justice Department’s decision not to provide the audio of then-President Joe Biden’s interview with former special counsel Robert Hur.</p> 
<p>The Biden-era DOJ did not prosecute the case, and that audio was ultimately released by the Trump-era department.</p> 
<p>A lawyer for the Clintons did not immediately return a request for comment.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Bill Clinton <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/1148357927625023490" target="_blank">has insisted the former president</a> did not know about Epstein’s crimes and that, as of 2019, had not spoken to Epstein in over a decade. In wake of the initial release of materials in the Justice Department's possession in the Epstein case in which Bill Clinton appeared in multiple photos, the same spokesperson has called for the Trump administration to release all materials in its possession related to the former president.</p> 
<p>“We need no such protection,” <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/2003166064969154839" target="_blank">the statement read</a>.</p> 
<p>Sara Guerrero, a Democratic spokesperson for the panel, said in a statement Friday, “Oversight Democrats have always said that the Committee is willing to talk to any person who has information about Jeffrey Epstein. We support former President Bill Clinton’s calls on President Trump to direct Attorney General Bondi to immediately release the full Epstein files, including any material including the former President."</p> 
<p>She added, "Compliance with subpoenas from Congress are important and critical to our investigation."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jim Jordan commits to public hearing for Jack Smith</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/jack-smith-will-testify-in-public-00718945</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a392-d15b-abff-ffde6f3b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 11:32:15 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan said in an interview Friday he will invite former special counsel Jack Smith to testify in an open hearing as soon as this month in what would be a politically high-stakes event for members of both parties and the White House.</p> 
<p>“He’s coming in,” the Ohio Republican said of Smith, who led the federal criminal cases against President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Smith <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-deposition-congress-00694730" target="_blank">sat for over eight hours</a>, with breaks, before Judiciary Committee members and staff investigators last month behind closed doors while his legal team has repeatedly requested a public forum for their client to argue his case.</p> 
<p>Jordan <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/takeaways-jack-smith-congressional-testimony-00708747" target="_blank">released a transcript</a> and video record on New Year’s Eve and said Friday he now wants Smith to stand before the public and defend his claims of misconduct against the president.</p> 
<p>Smith found Trump guilty of working to circumvent the results of the 2020 election, mishandling classified documents and obstruction of justice, but was forced to drop the charges when Trump won reelection in 2024.</p> 
<p>“One of the key takeaways in the transcript is, we said, ‘did you [have] any evidence that President Trump was responsible for the violence that took place at the Capitol?’ He had no evidence of that whatsoever,” Jordan said of the committee’s December interview with Smith.</p> 
<p>Jordan said he is eager for Smith to answer that question, and others, before live cameras.</p> 
<p>When asked during his deposition whether he had evidence that Trump instructed rioters to storm the Capitol on Jan. 6, 2021, Smith responded that "our evidence is that he, in the weeks leading up to January 6th, created a level of distrust ... to get people to believe fraud claims that weren't true. He made false statements to State legislatures, to his supporters in all sorts of contexts."</p> 
<p>Lanny Breuer, one of Smith’s lawyers and a partner at the firm Covington &amp; Burling, said in a statement that “Jack has been clear for months he is ready and willing to answer questions in a public hearing about his investigations into President Trump’s alleged unlawful efforts to overturn the 2020 election and his mishandling of classified documents.”</p> 
<p>Republicans have been going after Smith for years with allegations that he was presiding over a partisan witch hunt with the support of the Biden administration, but they have redoubled their efforts after revelations that Smith’s office secretly obtained phone records for GOP lawmakers in the days around the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>Smith has maintained he never spoke to Biden or White House staff during his investigation.</p> 
<p>Smith defended his work last month to House Judiciary members and staff, but his testimony was hamstrung, in part, by a federal court order that has kept the second volume of his report surrounding the classified documents case under seal. He has maintained he is interested in sharing the results of this investigation, but the Justice Department has interpreted that the order precludes him from discussing details with Congress.</p> 
<p>These potential restrictions on his testimony back in December will likely be the same for a public hearing in the near future.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, is celebrating the opportunity for Smith to discuss his work publicly, believing he has information that will damage the president.</p> 
<p>“After Republicans forced Jack Smith into a backroom interrogation and rejected our calls for an open public hearing, now they decide they want a public hearing with Jack Smith after all," Raskin said in a statement. "Their backroom strategy backfired in historic fashion."</p> 
<p>"Even with many hours of private testimony, Republicans could not lay a glove on Jack Smith, his evidence, or his case. That will not change now that they have finally heeded our call to have him come testify publicly," he added. "This upcoming hearing is a win for truth-seeking Americans and yet another looming humiliation for Donald Trump and Congressional Republicans, who depend on a daily diet of lies to keep their administration afloat.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson says Minneapolis shooting appears to be ‘self-defense’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/mike-johnson-on-minneapolis-shooting-00718731</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a328-d65c-affb-ababb89f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 09:42:20 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson told reporters Friday there needs to be "a full investigation" into the shooting death of a woman in Minneapolis by an ICE agent while asserting that the officer was "operating in self-defense."</p> 
<p>Johnson said he understood many people on social media, including "elected officials," are commenting on the video of the shooting. "But we all understand there has to be a full investigation," he added. "That's the appropriate thing. That will happen."</p> 
<p>Johnson quickly added it "appears to us that the officer involved was operating in self-defense" and "he made a snap judgment, as they do." </p> 
<p>He also mentioned reports that the ICE officer responsible for the shooting had been involved an incident last year where <a href="https://www.startribune.com/ice-agent-who-fatally-shot-woman-in-minneapolis-is-identified/601560214" target="_blank">he had been dragged by a car and injured</a> and thus had reason to think his life "was in danger."</p> 
<p>"We'll have to see," Johnson said, referring to the investigation.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP pushes back on Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/gop-pushback-trump-votes-health-care-war-powers-00718544</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a111-d15b-abff-fd5f85040000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump’s grip on congressional Republicans is slipping.</p> 
<p>A series of rebukes on the Hill on Thursday highlighted how rank-and-file Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/donald-trump-congress-weak-00718030" target="_blank">starting to move with less regard</a> for the president heading into the midterms.</p> 
<p>Here’s what comes next on three fronts:</p> 
<p><b>— Bringing back ACA credits:</b> Seventeen House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/17-republicans-vote-to-restore-lapsed-obamacare-subsidies-00717497" target="_blank">broke ranks</a> to support a clean three-year restoration of enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies that expired last month. The <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/the-gops-obamacare-defectors-were-more-numerous-than-expected-00718102" target="_blank">bigger-than-anticipated revolt</a> showed how politically dangerous skyrocketing insurance premiums could be.</p> 
<p>The bill is expected to die in the Senate, as Majority Leader John Thune has no plans to bring it up for a vote.</p> 
<p>But the Republican proponents hope the strong bipartisan support pushes the Senate to produce its own ACA solution. Senators are considering a plan that would reestablish the credits for two years with reforms. Text could come as soon as Tuesday, per Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio), as lawmakers race to get a deal over the finish line before open enrollment ends Jan. 15 in most states.</p> 
<p><b>— Limiting Trump's war powers:&nbsp;</b>The Senate gave one of its strongest admonishments of the president Thursday when five Republicans helped advance a measure to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">constrain Trump’s military action abroad</a>. An outraged president took to social media to say they “should never be elected to office again.”</p> 
<p>The measure now heads to a final Senate vote next week. But it would still need to pass the House, which could prove more challenging. If Thursday’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/trump-vetoes-sustained-00717160" target="_blank">failed veto override votes</a> were any indication, House Republicans are less willing to break with the administration than their Senate counterparts.</p> 
<p>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) told POLITICO he was “inclined” to support the war powers resolution after this week’s briefings on the Venezuela operation, but that Trump’s Thursday attack was a tipping point.</p> 
<p>“Reading the ugly response to those senators sort of convinced me to vote yes,” he said.</p> 
<p>The House may soon vote on its own war powers measure from Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.). </p> 
<p><b>— Installing the Jan. 6 plaque:&nbsp;</b>The Senate voted Thursday to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/senate-unanimous-approves-jan-6-plaque-law-enforcement-00717799" target="_blank">unanimously approve a measure</a>, led by Sens. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) and Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.), to install a plaque in the Capitol honoring the officers who protected it on Jan. 6, 2021.</p> 
<p>The stark moment of bipartisanship was a significant rebuke of Speaker Mike Johnson and the Trump DOJ, which argues the plaque — which has been made but not installed — does not comply with a 2022 law mandating its display because it lists the departments that responded, not individual officers.</p> 
<p>The resolution does not need House approval, but it does put pressure on Johnson. It’s unclear when the Senate will install the plaque, which will remain in the chamber until a permanent location is identified on the west front of the Capitol.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Thune’s border trip: </b>Thune is leading a trip to the border in Texas on Friday with several GOP senators and Senate hopefuls to sell the “big, beautiful bill” Republicans passed last summer. <b>&nbsp;</b></p> 
<p><b>— Funding progress: </b>Appropriators hope to release bill text Sunday night of the next spending package they want to pass before the month-end funding cliff. It’s expected to include the State-Foreign Operations, Financial Services and Homeland Security bills, though the DHS portion is in flux after an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent fatally shot a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky, Simon J. Levien, Hailey Fuchs and Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Donald Trump can’t count on Congress to have his back any more</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/donald-trump-congress-weak-00718030</link>
      <description>Republicans dealt the president a series of rebukes Thursday that cast fresh doubt about his sway on Capitol Hill.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9ff7-da56-afff-9ff77b320000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 18:48:14 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/6f/0c/3b154a8d4d7a85593d016dfa96e0/u-s-congress-70134.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) voted to constrain Trump's war powers then brushed off a presidential attack. “I love the president," he said. "I understand he’s ticked.”</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/6f/0c/3b154a8d4d7a85593d016dfa96e0/u-s-congress-70134.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A cadre of congressional Republicans dealt President Donald Trump significant defeats Thursday — a series of rebukes that demonstrate <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/06/donald-trump-lame-duck-00639349" target="_blank">how his iron grip</a> on Capitol Hill has weakened at the start of a critical election year.</p> 
<p>The defiance kicked off in the Senate with a stunning vote, backed by <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">five GOP senators</a>, to move ahead with a measure that would constrain Trump on a matter he has presented as a signature triumph — his military intervention in Venezuela. Later in the day, 17 House Republicans joined with Democrats to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/17-gop-defections-on-obamacare-vote-00717883" target="_blank">rescue Obamacare subsidies</a> Trump has repeatedly railed against.</p> 
<p>And in a surprise move, senators of both parties agreed unanimously to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/senate-unanimous-approves-jan-6-plaque-law-enforcement-00717799" target="_blank">erect a plaque</a> honoring the officers who fought the mob at the Capitol on Jan, 6, 2021 — breaking from Trump's false narrative about that day.</p> 
<p>Trump took notice of the disloyalty in the first instance. Almost immediately, he shot off a social media post accusing the five Republicans of “attempting to take away our Powers to fight and defend the United States of America” and declaring that they “should never be elected to office again.”</p> 
<p>None of the Republicans who voted crosswise with the White House Thursday said they intended to deal a personal brushback to Trump. But several said they were determined to assert congressional authority that many on Capitol Hill fear has withered over the past year.</p> 
<p>Sen. Todd Young of Indiana insisted “any future commitment of U.S. forces in Venezuela must be subject to debate and authorization in Congress.”</p> 
<p>“President Trump campaigned against forever wars, and I strongly support him in that position,” Young said in a statement. “A drawn-out campaign in Venezuela involving the American military, even if unintended, would be the opposite of President Trump’s goal of ending foreign entanglements.”</p> 
<p>Speaking at the White House after the Senate vote, Vice President JD Vance rejected the notion that Trump’s grip on Congress was slipping, saying the GOP opposition was “based more on a legal technicality than any disagreement on policy.”</p> 
<p>But the internal GOP dissent came to the delight of Democratic leaders, who are growing jubilant over their ability to highlight the splits and hammer Republicans heading into the midterms.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries told reporters “Republicans need to get their act together in terms of their leadership,” saying the party had been badly distracted from addressing Americans’ cost-of-living concerns.</p> 
<p>After the war powers vote, Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer hailed it as “a critical step” for the chamber in “reasserting its constitutional authority" and pushing back on an imperious president.</p> 
<p>Still, there were signs that Trump’s sway over the GOP had not entirely eroded.</p> 
<p>Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.), while voting to constrain Trump’s war powers, downplayed the break and reiterated multiple times that he supports the president.</p> 
<p>“I don’t take any offense to that,” he said about Trump’s suggestion that he should not be reelected. “I think the president is great. I love the president. … I understand he’s ticked.”</p> 
<p>And in a particularly stark demonstration of Trump’s continued sway over the House GOP, most Republicans in the chamber voted with him Thursday to sustain his veto of two bills they had allowed to pass unanimously just weeks before.</p> 
<p>One bill <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/2025/12/congressional-bill-h-r-504-vetoed/" target="_blank">benefited the Miccosukee Tribe</a> of Florida, which opposed his administration’s attempt to build a vast migrant detention center in the Everglades. Another <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/2025/12/congressional-bill-h-r-131-vetoed/" target="_blank">authorized a water project</a> backed by Colorado politicians who have clashed with Trump, including Democratic Gov. Jared Polis and GOP Rep. Lauren Boebert.</p> 
<p>“I am disappointed to see the lack of leadership, the amount of people that will fold, that will cave, that will not take a stand,” Boebert said after the vote. “This had nothing to do with policy. … Folks are afraid of getting a mean tweet or attacked.”</p> 
<p>Some House Republicans who opposed the veto override cited White House officials who circled the chamber as the votes unfolded. It was clear they were taking note of the defectors, one GOP lawmaker said. Trump going nuclear on the five Republican senators who had defied him earlier in the day helped convince others to not stick their neck out.</p> 
<p>“It wasn't worth it,” another House Republican said. “It's not my bill.”</p> 
<p>Still, 35 Republicans broke ranks with Trump on the Colorado project while 24 did so on the tribal bill. Two committee chairs voted to override both vetoes.</p> 
<p>Later in the day, a critical mass of House Republicans sent an incontrovertible message on an issue much more central to the GOP’s midterm prospects than expanding a tribal reservation — addressing health care costs.</p> 
<p>Seventeen GOP members joined with Democrats to pass a bill that would revive lapsed Obamacare tax credits for three years. Trump, with the encouragement of Republican leaders on Capitol Hill, has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/gop-obamacare-subsidies-expire-00684115" target="_blank">refused to engage in bipartisan negotiations</a> — instead slamming the subsidies as wasteful and calling on lawmakers to set up an alternate system where Americans get direct payments to help afford coverage.</p> 
<p>But multiple Republicans, while still blaming Democrats for the morass, said Thursday they were not willing to stand by and do nothing amid the standoff. The expired subsidies were used by more than 20 million Americans, lowering their premiums in many cases by thousands of dollars per year.</p> 
<p>“I have a bunch of my constituents that are depending on these programs, and I'm not going to leave them hanging because the Democrats broke the damn system,” said GOP Rep. Derrick Van Orden, who represents a swing Wisconsin district and referred to the bill as a “bridging mechanism.”</p> 
<p>Asked if his vote could be seen as a rebuke of Trump, Van Orden said he “didn't even think of it like that.”</p> 
<p>Republicans were similarly roundabout when it came to the Senate’s action Thursday to display the contentious Jan. 6 plaque, which was created pursuant to a 2022 law but has remained in storage as Speaker Mike Johnson refuses to install it.</p> 
<p>But the timing spoke volumes, coming two days after the fifth anniversary of the Capitol attack and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422" target="_blank">White House publication of a website</a> casting the riot as the fault of Democrats and the Capitol Police itself.</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), without mentioning Trump, said the plaque was a commemoration of “what I would consider to be one of the most significant stress tests for this institution since it was founded."</p> 
<p>"It was a great day for democracy because of the law enforcement officers,” he said. “We took a brief recess, we got ourselves together, the Capitol was secured and before we left the compound we came back and completed our constitutional duty" to certify the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, the fallout of the war powers vote is likely to continue. Thursday’s vote sets up final consideration of the resolution next week, where Trump’s commitment to an “America First” foreign policy will be debated. In addition to the pushback on his plans for Venezuela, many Republicans aired deep misgivings this week about his overt attempts to seize control of Greenland, a Danish territory.</p> 
<p>The House is on track to take up a similar vote later this month after Democrats introduced a companion measure Thursday and expressed cautious optimism that more Republicans might vote to constrain the president.</p> 
<p>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) said he was already “inclined” to support the war powers resolution after hearing from top administration officials in briefings this week and after hearing about Trump’s threats against Greenland. But he said the president’s attack on the five GOP senators Thursday cemented his position.</p> 
<p>“Reading the ugly response to those senators sort of convinced me to vote yes,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate unanimously approves installing Jan. 6, 2021 plaque</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/senate-unanimous-approves-jan-6-plaque-law-enforcement-00717799</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9fac-d65c-affb-bfaf86130000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:50:24 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate unanimously approved a measure Thursday to display an existing plaque honoring the officers who protected the Capitol during the Jan. 6, 2021 riot.</p> 
<p>Congress passed a law in March 2022 mandating the plaque, but years later it has yet to be installed. Speaker Mike Johnson has argued the project is "not implementable," and the Justice Department has maintained in litigation that an existing plaque does not comply with the law because it lists the departments who responded, not the individual officers.</p> 
<p>The measure on Thursday, led by Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) and Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.), sought to address the long-running political squabble.</p> 
<p>“On January 6, 2021, courageous law enforcement officers from the United States Capitol Police and other agencies risked their lives to defend the United States Capitol and protect Members of Congress and their staff,” Tillis said in a statement. “Prominently displaying this plaque in the United States Senate ensures their heroism and sacrifice are properly recognized.”</p> 
<p>It’s not clear when the Senate will install the plaque, which will remain in the Senate until a permanent location is identified on the west front of the Capitol. The resolution does not need to be approved by the House.</p> 
<p>The stark moment of bipartisanship came just after the 5-year anniversary of the Capitol attack was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422" target="_blank">marred by political bickering</a>. The White House published a website to rebut the narrative of the riot filled largely with false information, and Republicans continued to villainize the previous Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee that investigated the attack in its aftermath.</p> 
<p>At the beginning of his second term, President Donald Trump, who has repeatedly downplayed and mischaracterized the attack, pardoned those who took part in the riot, including some convicted of violent offenses.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-08T18:30:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>17 Republicans vote to restore lapsed Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/17-republicans-vote-to-restore-lapsed-obamacare-subsidies-00717497</link>
      <description>Democrats and moderate Republicans hope the bill's passage will put pressure on the Senate to come up a bipartisan compromise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9fb5-d65c-affb-bfb7c2f80001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:24:39 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0b/c5/72ecd1634b34b7dc6aaa0dfe2e45/u-s-congress-54112.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.) and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries (D-N.Y.) hold a press conference on Capitol Hill Jan. 8, 2026. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0b/c5/72ecd1634b34b7dc6aaa0dfe2e45/u-s-congress-54112.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Seventeen Republicans joined Democrats in passing legislation Thursday that would revive enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies for three years, rebuffing opposition from GOP leadership.</p> 
<p>The 230-196 vote <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/house-advances-three-year-extension-of-obamacare-subsidies-00714710" target="_blank"><u>follows a procedural vote</u></a> Wednesday to advance the bill, where nine Republicans joined Democrats in favor of moving forward.</p> 
<p>Thursday’s final passage vote had eight additional Republicans supporting the bill, including House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino of New York and Rep. David Joyce of Ohio, a senior appropriator.</p> 
<p>The vote was met with applause and loud cheering from Democrats, who said it was a vindication of their party’s strategy to pursue a clean extension of the subsidies.</p> 
<p>“This is a tribute to [House Minority Leader] Hakeem Jeffries and our leadership, and to every member of our caucus who stood for him,” said Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) after the vote.</p> 
<p>While the measure is destined to die in the Senate, Democrats and some Republicans hope it will lay the groundwork for a bipartisan agreement to tame skyrocketing health insurance premiums — the result of Congress allowing the tax credits to lapse Dec. 31.</p> 
<p>“The Senate could put together a product that could ultimately get sent back over to the House that we can then conference on and hopefully move across the finish line,” said Rep. Rob Bresnahan (R-Pa.), who supported the Democratic-led bill.</p> 
<p>A bipartisan group of senators are scrambling to make headway on that framework that could extend the credits while instituting new income caps for eligibility and lengthening the ACA open enrollment period to soften the blow of premium hikes.</p> 
<p>Earlier Thursday, members of the bipartisan House Problem Solvers Caucus met with senators to discuss a potential solution. Rep. Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) said that the meeting — and senators’ plea to show a strong force on this vote in the House — influenced his decision to vote for the measure after initially being inclined to vote against it.</p> 
<p>“There was a sentiment conveyed that if we could get a bill out of the House that had a meaningful amount of bipartisan support, that that would increase the likelihood that the Senate would take this up, pass a bill that has some reforms in it, and send it back,” Hurd said in an interview about the message communicated during the bicameral meeting.</p> 
<p>The lawmakers continue to project optimism about reaching a deal, though thorny issues remain over how to address the so-called Hyde amendment, which restricts federal funding for abortion. Rep. Nicole Malliotakis, a centrist New York Republican who opposed the Thursday vote, said she continued to be concerned about “how riddled with abuse and fraud” the subsidy program is.</p> 
<p>“We need to do something that actually simultaneously reins in insurance companies,” she said.</p> 
<p>Democrats hope the House vote will pressure Republican leaders in both chambers to compromise on the issue. At a news conference Thursday morning, Jeffries and Chuck Schumer blasted Republicans for repeatedly refusing to back a clean extension before the subsidies expired last year.</p> 
<p>“The American people should ask [Senate Majority Leader John Thune], ‘Are you willing to put this bill that the House now is moving forward on the floor of the Senate?’” Schumer said. “Most of the Republicans in the House and the Senate want to put poison pill riders about abortion on it. They are standing in the way.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries is now especially emboldened, having made the calculation last fall that enough centrist Republicans would join Democrats in supporting a discharge petition to circumvent their own leadership and force a vote on three-year extension legislation.</p> 
<p>And in a sign the pressure campaign might be working, Rep. Derrick Van Orden (R-Wis.) said Thursday night he couldn’t ignore the reality on the ground any longer.</p> 
<p>“I have a bunch of my constituents that are depending on these programs, and I'm not going to leave them hanging because the Democrats broke the damn system,” he said.</p> 
<p>The question of whether to extend the enhanced subsidies, which were established in a 2021 Covid relief package under a Democratic majority, has been one of the most divisive policy issues of the 119th Congress.</p> 
<p>Republican moderates <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/15/kiggans-house-gop-aca-00561747" target="_blank"><u>started raising alarms early in the fall that their constituents</u></a> were staring down massive premium spikes in 2026 due to the looming expiration of the subsidies. But they quickly encountered strong headwinds from conservatives who lambasted the credits as rife with fraud and giveaways to insurance companies — a message that has been echoed by Speaker Mike Johnson and House Majority Leader Steve Scalise.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s office, in a last-ditch effort Thursday morning to undermine the effort, blasted out a memo accusing “Democrats [of] want[ing] to expand a COVID subsidy system already flagged for massive fraud and abuse, with absolutely zero reforms.”</p> 
<p>After the vote Thursday evening, Johnson said in an interview of the Republicans who defected, “I think it's a really bad policy, and I wish they hadn't, but everybody had a vote.”</p> 
<p>Last fall, Johnson finally extended GOP moderates the opportunity to have a floor vote on an amendment to a Republican-authored bill intended to lower health care costs, but talks broke down. It led four Republicans to agree to help Democrats get the requisite 218 signatures on their discharge petition to force a vote on the three-year extension bill.</p> 
<p>"I've been asking for a vote on this for at least six months, if not eight, telling leadership it just needs to be resolved,” said Rep. David Valadao (R-Calif.), who voted for the Democratic-led measure, in an interview. “At some point we got to pull the trigger."</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
