<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 10:00:00 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>4 ways China-US relations could fracture in 2026</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/26/china-u-s-relations-could-fracture-2026-00703020</link>
      <description>Dozens of lawmakers foresee a surge in tensions over trade, Taiwan or supply chain disruptions possibly scuttling the current pause in US-China economic hostilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4876-d78e-af9f-fc77749d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/73/7a/9ed320de418fa652c64c42fcfea0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2243542833">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Andrew Caballero-Reynolds/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Lawmakers predict that the easing of U.S.-China tensions that President Donald Trump and China's leader Xi Jinping brokered in South Korea in October will be short-lived.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/73/7a/9ed320de418fa652c64c42fcfea0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2243542833" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Phelim Kine</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Phelim Kine</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The message from Capitol Hill on both sides of the aisle is clear: Get ready for U.S. relations with China to spiral all over again in the new year.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/fact-sheets/2025/11/fact-sheet-president-donald-j-trump-strikes-deal-on-economic-and-trade-relations-with-china/" target="_blank">The one-year trade truce</a> brokered in October between President Donald Trump and Chinese leader Xi Jinping <a href="https://asiatimes.com/2025/11/us-china-in-a-hot-and-fragile-truce/" target="_blank">is already looking shaky</a>. And lawmakers are preparing to reup clashes over trade, Taiwan and cyber-intrusions when they return in January.</p> 
<p><b>“</b>It's like a heavyweight fight, and we're in that short time period in-between rounds, but both sides need to be preparing for what is next after the truce,” Rep. Greg Stanton (D-Ariz.), a member of the House Select Committee on China, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>POLITICO talked to more than 25 lawmakers, including those on the House Select Committee on China, the House Foreign Affairs Committee’s East Asia subcommittee and the Congressional Executive Commission on China, for their views on the durability of the trade treaty. Both Republicans and Democrats warned of turbulence ahead.</p> 
<p>More than 20 of the lawmakers said they doubt Xi will deliver on key pledges the White House said he made in October, including <a href="https://www.politico.eu/newsletter/china-watcher/china-committee-busts-beijings-fentanyl-racket/" target="_blank">reducing the flow of precursor chemicals</a> to Mexico that cartels process into fentanyl and buying agreed volumes of U.S. agricultural goods.</p> 
<p>“China can never be trusted. They’re always looking for an angle,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.) said.</p> 
<p>That pessimism comes despite an easing in U.S.-China tensions since the Trump-Xi meeting in South Korea. The bruising cycle of tit-for-tat tariffs that briefly hit triple digits earlier this year is currently on pause. Both countries have relaxed export restrictions on essential items (<a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/national-security-daily/2025/06/11/trade-deals-cant-stop-chinas-rare-earth-edge-00400475" target="_blank">rare earths for the U.S.</a>, chip design software for China), while Beijing has committed to <a href="https://english.mofcom.gov.cn/News/SpokesmansRemarks/art/2025/art_d3b018b922a4458989e43a46a04be6fe.html" target="_blank">"expanding agricultural product trade"</a> in an apparent reference to the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/28/soybeans-sacrificed-in-trumps-china-gamble-00583232" target="_blank">suspension of imports of U.S. agricultural products</a> it imposed earlier this year.</p> 
<p>This trend may continue, given that Trump is likely to want stability in the U.S.-China relationship ahead of a summit with Xi planned for April in Beijing. “We’re starting to see some movement now on some of their tariff issues and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/01/white-house-china-trade-truce-00632759" target="_blank">the fentanyl precursor issue</a>,” Sen. Steve Daines (R-Mont.) said.</p> 
<p>But a series of issues have been brushed aside in negotiations or left in limbo — a status quo the Trump administration can only maintain for so long. The U.S.-China trade deal on rare earths that Bessent said the two countries <a href="https://www.scmp.com/news/us/economy-trade-business/article/3333010/china-rare-earths-deal-will-hopefully-be-done-thanksgiving-says-scott-bessent" target="_blank">would finalize by Thanksgiving</a> remains unsettled. And the White House hasn’t confirmed <a href="https://apnews.com/article/tiktok-divestment-deal-trump-2fdb915cac5b6d06907a5a2de6764376" target="_blank">reporting from earlier this month</a> that Beijing-based ByteDance has finalized the sale of the TikTok social media app ahead of the Jan. 23 deadline for that agreement.</p> 
<p>“The idea that we’re in a period of stability with Beijing is simply not accurate,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), ranking member of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.</p> 
<p>Shaheen has been sounding the alarm on China’s national security threats since she entered the Senate in 2009. But even some lawmakers who have been more open to engagement with Beijing — such as California Democratic Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/218327" data-person-id="218327">Ro Khanna</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/199004" data-person-id="199004">Ami Bera</a> — said that they don’t expect the armistice to last.</p> 
<p>The White House is more upbeat about the prospects for U.S.-China trade ties. </p> 
<p>"President Trump’s close relationship with President Xi is helping ensure that both countries are able to continue building on progress and continue resolving outstanding issues," the White House said in a statement, adding that the administration "continues to monitor China’s compliance with our trade agreement." It declined to comment on the TikTok deal.</p> 
<p>Still, the lawmakers POLITICO spoke with described four issues that could derail U.S.-China ties in the New Year:</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">A soybean spoiler</h4> 
<p>U.S. soybean farmers' reliance on the Chinese market gives Beijing a powerful non-tariff trade weapon — and China doesn’t appear to be following through on promises to renew purchases.</p> 
<p>The standoff over soybeans started in May, when China <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/28/soybeans-sacrificed-in-trumps-china-gamble-00583232" target="_blank">halted those purchases</a>, raising the prospect of financial ruin across farming states including Illinois, Iowa, Minnesota, Nebraska and Indiana — key political constituencies for the GOP in the congressional midterm elections next year.</p> 
<p>The White House said last month that Xi committed to buying 12 million metric tons of U.S. soybeans in November and December. But so far, Beijing has only purchased a fraction of that agreed total, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/09/china-buys-us-soybeans-trump-trade-agreement.html" target="_blank">NBC reported this month</a>.</p> 
<p>“What agitates Trump and causes him to react quickly are things that are more domestic and closer to home,” Rep. Jill Tokuda (D-Hawaii) said. China’s foot-dragging on soybean purchases “is the most triggering because it’s hurting American farmers and consumers, so that’s where we could see the most volatility in the relationship,” she said.</p> 
<p>That trigger could come on Feb. 28 — the new deadline for that 12 million metric ton purchase, which Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent <a href="https://www.agriculture.com/partners-china-soybean-buying-deadline-now-february-bessent-says-11863378" target="_blank">announced earlier this month</a>.</p> 
<p>The Chinese embassy in Washington declined to comment on whether Beijing plans to meet this deadline.</p> 
<p>The White House said one of the aspects of the trade deal it is monitoring is soybean purchases through this growing season.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">The Taiwan tinderbox</h4> 
<p>Beijing’s threats to invade Taiwan are another near-term potential flashpoint, even though the U.S. hasn’t prioritized the issue in its national security strategy or <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115605897178712132" target="_blank">talks between Xi and Trump</a>.</p> 
<p>China has increased its preparations for a Taiwan invasion this year. In October, the Chinese military debuted <a href="https://www.navalnews.com/naval-news/2025/01/china-suddenly-building-fleet-of-special-barges-suitable-for-taiwan-landings/" target="_blank">a new military barge system</a> that addresses some of the challenges of landing on the island’s beaches by deploying a bridge for cargo ships to unload tanks or trucks directly onto the shore.</p> 
<p>“China is tightening the noose around the island,” said Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), who joined a bipartisan congressional delegation to China in September and returned <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/national-security-daily/2025/09/29/potential-opening-on-military-comms-with-beijing-00585427" target="_blank">calling for better communications</a> between the U.S. and Chinese militaries.</p> 
<p>Some of the tension around Taiwan is playing out in the wider region, as Beijing pushes to expand its military reach and its influence. Chinese <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c5yqe197ypno" target="_blank">fighter jets locked radar</a> — a prelude to opening fire — on Japanese aircraft earlier this month in the East China Sea.</p> 
<p>“There is a real chance that Xi overplays his hand on antagonizing our allies, particularly Australia and Japan,” Rep. Seth Moulton (D-Mass.) said. “There is still a line [China] cannot cross without making this truce impossible to sustain.”</p> 
<p>The U.S. has a decades-long <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/09/19/biden-leaves-no-doubt-strategic-ambiguity-toward-taiwan-is-dead-00057658" target="_blank">policy of “strategic ambiguity”</a> under which it refuses to spell out how the U.S. would respond to Chinese aggression against Taiwan. Trump has also adhered to that policy. “You’ll find out if it happens,” Trump said in <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/world/asia/trump-says-chinas-xi-assured-wont-take-action-taiwan-during-his-term-rcna241521" target="_blank">an interview with 60 Minutes in November.</a></p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">More export restrictions on the way</h4> 
<p>Beijing has eased its export restrictions on rare earths — metallic elements essential to both civilian and military applications — but could reimpose those blocks at any time.</p> 
<p>Ten of the 25 lawmakers who spoke to POLITICO said they suspect Beijing will reimpose those export curbs as a convenient pressure point in the coming months.</p> 
<p>“At the center of the crack in the truce is China’s ability to levy export restrictions, especially its chokehold on the global supply of rare earths and other critical minerals,” Rep. André Carson (D-Ind.) said.</p> 
<p>Others are worried China will choose to expand its export controls to another product category for which it has market dominance — pharmaceuticals. Beijing supplies <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com/politics/supply-chain-ai-company-sounds-alarm-over-americas-reliance-chinese-made-pharmaceuticals" target="_blank">80 percent of the U.S. supply</a> of active pharmaceutical ingredients — the foundations of common drugs to treat everything from high blood pressure to type 2 diabetes.</p> 
<p>“Overnight, China could turn off the spigot and many basic pharmaceuticals, including things like aspirin, go away from the supply chain in the United States,” Rep. Nathaniel Moran (R-Texas) said.</p> 
<p>China restarted exports of rare earths earlier this month, and its Commerce Ministry pledged “timely approval” of such exports under a new licensing system, <a href="https://english.news.cn/20251204/2e83b4e979a44409a86f33e4263a7a15/c.html" target="_blank">state media reported</a>. Beijing has not indicated its intent to restrict the export of pharmaceuticals or their components as a trade weapon. But the U.S.-China Economic and Security Review Commission urged the Food and Drug Administration to reduce U.S. reliance on Chinese sources of pharmaceuticals in its <a href="https://www.uscc.gov/sites/default/files/2025-11/2025_Annual_Report_to_Congress.pdf" target="_blank">annual report last month</a>.</p> 
<p>The Chinese embassy in Washington didn’t respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Growing Chinese military muscle</h4> 
<p>China’s drive to develop a world-class military that can challenge traditional U.S. dominion of the Indo-Pacific could also derail relations between Washington and Beijing in 2026.</p> 
<p>China’s <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4gmnpg31xlo" target="_blank">expanding navy</a>— which, at more than 200 warships, is now <a href="https://www.csis.org/analysis/unpacking-chinas-naval-buildup" target="_blank">the world’s largest</a> — is helping Beijing show off its power across the region.</p> 
<p>The centerpiece of that effort in 2025 has been the addition of a third aircraft carrier, the Fujian, which entered into service last month. The Fujian is two-thirds the size of the USS Gerald R. Ford carrier. But like the Ford, it boasts state-of-the-art <a href="https://www.globaltimes.cn/page/202511/1347603.shtml" target="_blank">electromagnetic catapults</a> to launch J-35 and J-15T fighter jets.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration sees that as a threat.</p> 
<p>The U.S. aims to insulate allies and partners in the Indo-Pacific from possible Chinese “sustained successful military aggression” powered by Beijing’s “historic military buildup,” Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth <a href="https://www.war.gov/News/Speeches/Speech/Article/4354431/remarks-by-secretary-of-war-pete-hegseth-at-the-reagan-national-defense-forum-a/" target="_blank">said earlier this month</a> at the Reagan National Defense Forum.</p> 
<p>Five lawmakers said they see China’s increasingly aggressive regional military footprint as incompatible with U.S. efforts to maintain a stable relationship with Beijing in the months ahead.</p> 
<p>“We know the long-term goal of China is really economic and diplomatic and military domination around the world, and they see the United States as an adversary,” Moran said.</p> 
<p><i>Daniel Desrochers contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The internal dispute that could derail the GOP’s 2026 agenda</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/gop-reconciliation-bill-health-care-00704698</link>
      <description>With the midterms around the corner, top Republican voices are clashing about the prospects for another reconciliation bill.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4c64-d78e-af9f-fc775af40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5b/9a/9e79e6a247629a62d12f4ebf8994/u-s-congress-78162.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Texas Reps. August Pfluger (left) and Jodey Arrington (right) are among the most prominent Republicans pushing another reconciliation bill.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5b/9a/9e79e6a247629a62d12f4ebf8994/u-s-congress-78162.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With the midterms bearing down on them, Republicans are facing a nasty intraparty fight early next year over their legislative agenda: Should they attempt to pass a party-line bill focused on health care after failing to address expiring insurance subsidies?</p> 
<p>GOP factions have been divided for months about the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/05/second-megabill-doubts-republicans-00545855" target="_blank">prospect of a second reconciliation bill</a>. Some see it as the party’s last, best chance to put wins on the board before Election Day, while others believe it is a recipe for failure given the small Republican majorities in the House and Senate and major internal divides over health policy.</p> 
<p>But Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> is publicly leaning into the possibility as he tries to appease hard-liners who wanted the House GOP to go much farther <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">than it did this month</a> in pushing a conservative health care overhaul.</p> 
<p>Some rank-and-file conservatives in the House and Senate are privately discussing a potential centerpiece for a second reconciliation bill: using tariff revenues to send taxpayers cash to address rising health care costs after enhanced Obamacare subsidies expire Dec. 31, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the talks.</p> 
<p>The pressure from the right is threatening to outweigh skepticism from many senior Republicans who are deeply wary about moving forward. At least one key Republican <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/jason-smith-reconciliation-2026-00698324" target="_blank">is publicly questioning</a> whether the GOP can muster the unity necessary to navigate the reconciliation process a second time after last summer’s struggle to enact the tax-cuts-focused megabill.</p> 
<p>“I don't see a path of a second reconciliation ever passing,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> of Missouri, who as Ways and Means Committee chair oversees tax policy and some health care matters.</p> 
<p>Furthermore, nearly every other House chair has shared similar doubts in private conversations with GOP leaders and senior Republicans, according to three other people granted anonymity to discuss internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>The most prominent voices in the senior GOP ranks in either chamber arguing for a fresh push are the chairs of the Budget committees. They hold powerful roles as gatekeepers for the reconciliation process and get to define the fiscal parameters for legislation that could skirt a Senate Democratic filibuster and pass without bipartisan cooperation.</p> 
<p>“We need to actually follow through on the policies we've been popping off about for years that we believe will actually help everybody,” said House Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259549" data-person-id="259549">Jodey Arrington</a> (R-Texas), who recently <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/11/congress/jodey-arrington-retire-house-budget-00646259" target="_blank">announced his retirement</a>. “I feel like there's a critical mass to start that process.”</p> 
<p>Senate Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) has been similarly bullish, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/06/congress/lindsey-graham-reconciliation-00640338" target="_blank">pushing alongside members of his committee</a> to advance a reconciliation blueprint early next year. He recently <a href="https://www.semafor.com/article/12/22/2025/budget-chair-graham-plots-next-republican-party-line-bill" target="_blank">told Semafor</a> he wants the bill to focus on health care, military funding and immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>Other committee chairs, who have to actually craft the bills sketched out in the budget blueprint, aren’t as convinced. Many GOP health initiatives, they believe, won’t comply with the strict fiscal rules governing reconciliation — a point they’ve made privately to senators pushing for a second bill. And some members of leadership are cool to the idea of tapping tariff revenue for anything other than deficit reduction.</p> 
<p>That’s not to mention the pushback coming from vulnerable House Republicans, many of whom had to take big political risks in backing the summer megabill, which included deep cuts to Medicaid spending. They are now wary of engaging in another divisive health care debate.</p> 
<p>In one heated closed-door meeting this month where Johnson was present, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) shot down talk of another GOP party-line bill, saying it would “never” happen. Even one House Republican who supports the idea acknowledged it would be “like having a baby” — both in terms of the level of political pain and the laborious process.</p> 
<p>But there are plenty of other Republicans in the House rank-and-file who believe their party needs to do more to address high health care costs and other cost-of-living issues with a conservative stamp — and many of them were not around in 2017, when the last big GOP health care push ran aground.</p> 
<p>As moderates tried to force a floor vote on a bipartisan extension of the Obamacare subsidies, House GOP hard-liners privately pressured party leaders for assurances that a party-line bill focused on health care would move early next year. As those talks were happening last week, the Republican Study Committee — an influential group of nearly 200 House conservatives — discussed the idea of a second party-line bill during a closed-door lunch.</p> 
<p>According to three people granted anonymity to discuss the meeting, the group’s chair, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/355320" data-person-id="355320">August Pfluger</a> of Texas, pitched a possible list of items for a second reconciliation package focused on affordability concerns. Pfluger and other senior RSC members are pushing to include an expansion of health savings accounts that GOP leaders left out of the narrow health care bill the House recently passed.</p> 
<p>“I don't think it has to be divisive,” Pfluger said in an interview last week. “Let's come together and coalesce around policy that works.”</p> 
<p>He added that “the trick” is figuring out what President Donald Trump is interested in pushing forward. His top political aide, White House deputy chief of staff James Blair, recently <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/trump-congress-agenda-reconciliation-00658591" target="_blank">said the administration was open</a> to a second reconciliation bill to pursue affordability matters.</p> 
<p>There is recent precedent for a major reconciliation bill passing late in a midterm year: Democrats under former President Joe Biden struggled through for months of rollercoaster internal negotiations before Sen. Joe Manchin of West Virginia finally <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/07/27/manchin-schumer-senate-deal-energy-taxes-00048325" target="_blank">agreed to get on board</a>. The Inflation Reduction Act passed just three months before Election Day, though Democrats had a wider margin to work with in the House.</p> 
<p>But top GOP leaders have been treading carefully. Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> told reporters this month that reconciliation is “always hard, but it’s an option.”</p> 
<p>“You don’t just do reconciliation for the heck of it, you’ve got to have, you know, a specific purpose,” he added. “That purpose may start getting some traction — we’ll see.”</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> coordinated early talks around a possible second reconciliation package this fall. But GOP chairs came up with only a handful of policies to include, mostly submitting ideas that had already been left out of the earlier megabill. In an interview last week, Scalise said Republicans would return in January with “a very full agenda … but reconciliation is one thing we're going to try to build.”</p> 
<p>“We're trying to see if there's consensus,” he added. “We obviously would like to get one.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 policy heavyweights endangered by redistricting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/three-policy-heavyweights-endangered-by-redistricting-00704852</link>
      <description>New House lines are set to reverberate through key committees where at-risk lawmakers have shaped policy for decades.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4cd9-dba9-addb-7fff95ff0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9f/fa/f419fc5542238b61d7e2ff925d7e/congress-house-appropriations-39899.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">J. Scott Applewhite/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Ken Calvert, R-Calif., chairman of the House Appropriations Defense Subcommittee arrives for a closed markup hearing on the Fiscal Year 2024 spending bill for the Pentagon, at the Capitol in Washington, Thursday, June 15, 2023.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9f/fa/f419fc5542238b61d7e2ff925d7e/congress-house-appropriations-39899.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Members of both parties have yet to reckon with one inevitable consequence of the redistricting fight that’s rippling across the country — the loss of years of policy expertise on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>While many of the lawmakers at risk of losing their seats in the redistricting wars have only a few years under their belt, several senior lawmakers who have spent decades building their legislative portfolios and climbing the ranks of the most powerful House committees are also now seeing their political futures threatened.</p> 
<p>They include Rep. Rob Wittman (R-Va.), who aims to be the next chair of the Armed Services Committee, and Rep. Ken Calvert (R-Calif.), an appropriations “cardinal” who oversees funds for the military and defense agencies.</p> 
<p>And then there’s Rep. Lloyd Doggett (D-Texas), a vocal progressive and the second-most senior Democrat on the Ways and Means Committee, who is choosing to retire rather than compete against his younger colleague, rising progressive star Greg Casar.</p> 
<p>The departure of any one of these members would go beyond simply scrambling party ratios and potentially determining the House majority in the 2026 midterms; their displacement would impact the ideological makeups of their respective committees and leave gaping knowledge voids.</p> 
<p>Here’s how a House without Doggett, Calvert and Wittman could change how Congress approaches taxation, health, defense and national security.</p> 
<h2><b>A progressive policy voice</b></h2> 
<p><br>Doggett has spent 50 years in politics and three decades in the House. As the top Democrat on the House Ways and Means Subcommittee on Health, the Austin-area lawmaker is known for his attacks on corporate influence over politics and the machinations of Big Pharma, and worked to end lower tax rates for American companies that offshore their profits.</p> 
<p>And as the second-most-senior Democrat on the committee, Doggett also has a reputation for representing the interests of progressives on a panel stacked with moderates. He has over the years been one of the only Democratic tax writers willing to privately challenge Ways and Means ranking member Richard Neal (D-Mass.), who has been criticized at times for being <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/10/24/richard-neal-son-congress-lobbying-00181853" target="_blank"><u>too close to special interests</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“He’s been sort of a lone voice fighting against Big Pharma, against [pharmacy benefit managers], against Medicare Advantage, against price-gouging,” said fellow committee member Don Beyer (D-Va.) in an interview. “He’s never hesitated to disagree with Richie, too … Lloyd doesn’t just roll over.”</p> 
<p>Doggett, in an interview, recalled efforts to amend drug pricing legislation authored by then-Speaker Nancy Pelosi during a 2019 committee markup, ignoring instructions from leadership not to do so.</p> 
<p>“I offered amendments that were opposed and defeated by Chairman Neal … to extend coverage to the uninsured,” said Doggett. “The committee’s position was that it had to be done just the way Pelosi submitted it.”</p> 
<p>Asked for comment, a Neal spokesperson referred to the lawmaker’s statement at the time of Doggett’s retirement, which recognized the Texan as “a bulldog in the fight for the little guy.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.), the former chair of the Congressional Progressive Caucus, recalled in an interview that Doggett helped keep the Democrats’ signature party-line legislation of 2022 from straying too far to the middle.</p> 
<p>“Lloyd was our leader on Ways and Means, definitely around billionaire taxes and stock buybacks,” she said. “He’s willing to stand up to party leadership, which is often necessary on that committee and, in general, on some of these tax issues.”</p> 
<h2><b>A defense appropriations guru</b></h2> 
<p><br>California’s redistricting plans have set the stage for a contentious primary fight between GOP Reps. Ken Calvert and Young Kim. It has many Republicans openly fretting about the implications of losing Calvert, who has spent two-and-a-half decades working on defense policy on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>A fellow California Republican, Rep. Darrell Issa, was caught on hot mic in early December<a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/5635469-darrell-issa-concerns-california-map/" target="_blank"><u>saying Kim should step aside</u></a> and consider a position in the administration because “with Ken, we need him exactly where he is.”</p> 
<p>Another defense appropriator, Rep. Mario Diaz-Balart (R-Fla.), said in a recent interview that “for the national security of the United States, it’s hard to find somebody who is more important than Ken Calvert. … He knows defense, the intricacies, the details like nobody — like nobody.”</p> 
<p>Calvert’s expertise is so revered he obtained a waiver from House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) to serve beyond his term limit as the head of the Defense subcommittee in the current Congress; he’s not likely to get a waiver for the next one.</p> 
<p>Still, colleagues say Calvert is regarded as an institutional encyclopedia on defense spending matters, regularly citing data points from his vast knowledge of military history, the history of weapons systems, various bureaucracies within the defense sphere and the strategies of rival world powers.</p> 
<p>Calvert has also taken the lead on infusing new money into defense programs focused on innovative weapons and logistics systems, launching a $100 million dollar initiative in 2022 to speed up the production and acquisition of cutting-edge military technology.</p> 
<p>“He’s got institutional knowledge that is very rare. There’s only a few members who have that much time in the House,” said Defense subcommittee vice chair Jake Ellzey (R-Texas) in an interview. “And that institutional knowledge is irreplaceable, unless you get somebody who’s been working it that long, and there’s nobody that even comes close.”</p> 
<p>Calvert, in a statement, called himself “uniquely qualified to work with the Trump Administration” as “a senior member of the Appropriations Committee and having worked in this space for many years.”</p> 
<h2><b>An advocate for Virginia’s defense community</b></h2> 
<p><br>Wittman, who was first elected in 2007, has long been eyeing the opportunity to ascend to the top GOP position on the House Armed Services Committee once the current chair, Rep. Mike Rogers (R-Ala.), completes his three-term tenure at the end of 2026. The Virginia Republican has held leadership roles across multiple subcommittees and now presides over the Tactical Air &amp; Land Forces subpanel.</p> 
<p>“[He is] very knowledgeable, carries himself very well, very well respected,” said Rep. Carlos Gimenez (R-Fla.), a member of Wittman’s subcommittee, in an interview.</p> 
<p>But Wittman’s seat has been a top target of Democrats’ mid-decade redistricting plans, which could result in making the 1st Congressional District much bluer.</p> 
<p>Wittman has been a fierce advocate of his state’s shipbuilding industry — which is responsible for producing aircraft carriers and a fleet of nuclear-attack submarines — and sees the equipment as critical to the U.S. military’s readiness for potential conflict with China in the Pacific.</p> 
<p>One House GOP aide who works on national security issues, granted anonymity to speak candidly, argued that Democrats’ targeting of Wittman in its proposed redistricting map is risky for the future of Virginia’s defense infrastructure and industry at large.</p> 
<p>The aide speculated that the Trump administration could someday slow the construction of aircraft carriers in light of questions about their efficacy in modern warfare or even target bases in Virginia for realignment and closure.</p> 
<p>“They’re taking a gamble,” the aide said of Democratic attempts to unseat a champion of the state’s defense industry with influence and seniority. “They’re trading political dominance for potential irrelevance in the defense sphere.”</p> 
<p>Abigail Gost, a spokesperson for Wittman, said that the congressman has no plans to leave Congress and “believes continuity and experience matter — especially at a time of heightened global instability and rapid change”</p> 
<p><i>Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-23T08:53:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>These 3 Republican senators are giving John Thune headaches</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/senate-gop-conservatives-lee-johnson-scott-00703034</link>
      <description>Veteran hard-liners have new perches of authority and rising influence among Republican senators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4789-dba9-addb-77bfb9af0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5d/b0/18fde74f4ce18d929fb32850cef3/u-s-senate-43949.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Along with Sen. Mike Lee of Utah, Johnson (center) and Scott (right) have emerged as leaders of the Senate GOP's rising right wing.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5d/b0/18fde74f4ce18d929fb32850cef3/u-s-senate-43949.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> rushed to advance a new funding package this month, he faced a familiar roadblock: a trio of conservatives from his conference’s right flank.</p> 
<p>Republican Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> of Florida, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151822" data-person-id="151822">Ron Johnson</a> of Wisconsin and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151827" data-person-id="151827">Mike Lee</a> of Utah banded together as they sought to advance key conservative priorities, including an end to spending earmarks — <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/01/congress/thune-casts-doubt-on-passing-government-funding-bills-before-christmas-00671973" target="_blank">holding out for weeks</a> as Thune strained to keep the 2026 funding process on track and avoid another costly government shutdown on Jan. 30.</p> 
<p>The tensions between the fiscal hawks, who want to drastically slash spending, and more pragmatic corners of the Senate GOP, including members of leadership and the Appropriations Committee, are nothing new. But these hard-liners have now found a larger pool of allies as the conference’s center of gravity slowly shifts right. They also have new perches of authority that give each a powerful megaphone.</p> 
<p>Thune ultimately wore the three Republicans down with some outside assistance from President Donald Trump, cutting deals to win their consent to advance the proposed trillion-dollar “minibus” funding package. Ultimately, it was Democratic objections that <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/senators-leave-for-the-holidays-without-passing-funding-package-00699651" target="_blank">prevented the Senate from acting</a> in the final legislative days of 2025.</p> 
<p>But Lee, Johnson and Scott are unapologetic about using their power amid the growing perception among some of their colleagues that they are frequent thorns in Thune’s side.</p> 
<p>“We're actually trying to do important things,” Johnson said in an interview. “No matter what I would have done, Democrats would have held out until the very last minute, too. So, I mean, sorry about your frustrations, colleagues.”</p> 
<p>Since January, the trio has chosen to exert their leverage during key moments where GOP leaders have sought party unity. As Thune worked to advance the party’s sprawling domestic policy bill over the summer, the three Republicans haggled repeatedly over the measure’s parameters — including during a procedural vote that was left open for hours as they negotiated. Last month, they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/09/government-funding-deal-on-track-to-advance-sunday-night-00644110" target="_blank">briefly withheld support for the bill</a> that ultimately ended the 43-day government shutdown, huddling with Thune before ultimately voting in favor.</p> 
<p>Publicly, their colleagues are respectful and note that every senator has a right to use the legislative tools available to advance their own agenda.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151837" data-person-id="151837">John Hoeven</a> (R-N.D.), an appropriator and Thune ally, noted that Johnson, Scott and Lee “reflect a bigger share of the caucus” that is decidedly conservative, while “folks on the other end of the caucus” also use their leverage from time to time.</p> 
<p>“That's just how it works,” Hoeven said.</p> 
<p>But behind the scenes, the hardball tactics have rankled Republican senators. As the spending standoff dragged on in recent weeks, some privately urged Thune to call the fiscal hawks’ bluff by putting the spending package on the floor, essentially daring Johnson or others to publicly object.</p> 
<p>“He’s going to keep doing it until they call his hand,” one GOP senator said about Johnson, adding that Thune risked being “miserable” unless he asserted himself.</p> 
<p>A second GOP senator, who was also granted anonymity to speak candidly about internal conference dynamics, added that the trio has been more “emboldened” this year than under prior GOP leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51216" data-person-id="51216">Mitch McConnell</a> of Kentucky. The senator said that’s due to Thune’s “looser” leadership style and his determination to move funding bills individually rather than simply banking on a single omnibus deal.</p> 
<p>“We haven’t done an appropriations process in a long time,” the senator added.</p> 
<p>Those tensions have played out quietly behind the scenes in GOP lunches, with the conservative trio at times sparring with Senate Appropriations Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) and other members of the government funding panel who want to revise spending levels enacted under former President Joe Biden.</p> 
<p>But the two GOP senators agreed that they did not think Lee, Scott and Johnson would be engaging in their current tactics were McConnell still in charge, or <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/19/richard-shelby-appropriations-gop-spending-bill-00074398" target="_blank">even under Collins’ predecessor</a> as Appropriations chair, Sen. Richard Shelby (R-Ala.).</p> 
<p>“Shelby would have taken away every one of their projects,” the first GOP senator said.</p> 
<p>The shift in leadership style was by design. The same GOP senators kvetched that McConnell was too centralized, with Scott unsuccessfully challenging him in 2022. In his bid to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/11/13/john-thune-senate-republican-leader-00189305" target="_blank">take over as Republican leader</a> two years later, Thune pledged to shift power back to individual senators and committee chairs — and the three conservative malcontents, once dismissed as outliers, are now more difficult to ignore.</p> 
<p>Scott leads the Senate GOP’s Steering Committee, holding weekly meetings with the conservative-oriented group as well as hosting a weekly lunch for the larger conference. Lee chairs the Energy and Natural Resources Committee, one of several one-time rebels who received gavels in January. And Johnson — long been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/13/ron-johnson-reconciliation-gop-agenda-spending-cuts-00347100" target="_blank">willing to be a squeaky wheel</a> — leads the Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs panel’s investigative subcommittee in addition to having seats on the powerful Finance and Budget committees.</p> 
<p>At the same time, the Senate GOP conference has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/29/senate-gop-dealmakers-depart-just-as-congress-control-splits-00075068" target="_blank">undergone a subtle transformation</a> in recent election cycles, inching toward the right as the most pragmatic Republican dealmakers are replaced by senators more closely aligned with the MAGA movement — giving Scott, Johnson and Lee a growing set of allies.</p> 
<p>Thune has been dealing with the hard-liners one step at a time. Gaining their approval for the recent funding package, for instance, required promising several amendment votes as well as a path forward for a pet Johnson priority — a bill that would exempt some federal employees from furloughs during government shutdowns.</p> 
<p>“He has more patience than any three of the rest of us do,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/221844" data-person-id="221844">Mike Rounds</a> (R-S.D.).</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) added that Thune wants “to the maximum degree possible to make sure that people in his conference are heard and respected” — even if, she said, he “has a lot of frogs that keep hopping around.”</p> 
<p>Asked about his message to the holdouts, Thune pitched the funding package as being in “everybody’s best interest” and better than the alternatives — a new shutdown, another short-term stopgap or a mammoth omnibus loathed by conservatives. Thune also helped facilitate a potential path toward enactment for Johnson’s shutdown bill, connecting him with Speaker Mike Johnson.</p> 
<p>“I think you always have to keep the perspective in this job … that the most important vote isn’t the last vote, it’s the next vote,” Thune said about his broader approach to leadership this past year.</p> 
<p>The conservative trio is looking ahead to the next fight, as well. Even after Scott cut a deal to advance the funding bill, he rekindled the earmarks fight, <a href="https://x.com/SenRickScott/status/2001706927085215849" target="_blank">accusing Democrats in an X post</a> of “packing the latest appropriations package with taxpayer-funded earmarks” and trying to “undermine Pres. Trump’s agenda.”</p> 
<p>Republicans, Scott said, must “stand strong.”</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misstated the year Sen. Rick Scott challenged Mitch McConnell as Senate Republican leader. It was 2022.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New York Republicans are excited about a race they’re probably going to lose</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/hes-facing-very-long-odds-so-why-are-new-york-republicans-betting-on-bruce-blakeman-00703744</link>
      <description>Struggling blue state Republicans need a strong top of the ticket to win key House races.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-47f6-dba9-addb-77ff02bd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 16:59:51 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/82/31/d19003274557aae1710a365d128d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172980382">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Michael M. Santiago/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman is expected to deliver a strong top-of-the-ticket result for down-ballot GOP candidates.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/82/31/d19003274557aae1710a365d128d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2172980382" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nick Reisman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nick Reisman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>ALBANY, New York — Empire State Republicans expect Nassau County Executive Bruce Blakeman to turbo charge down-ballot turnout as their party’s gubernatorial nominee — boosting GOP candidates in crucial suburban swing races as he mounts an otherwise uphill battle to unseat Democratic Gov. Kathy Hochul.</p> 
<p>If Blakeman falls short in an underdog bid, New York Republicans can still be successful in what’s shaping up to be a tough political environment.</p> 
<p>“Blakeman’s top appeal for Republicans, particularly in swing suburbs, can be realized even if he loses,” said Larry Levy, dean of the National Center for Suburban Studies at Hofstra University. “He could help them on Long Island, Westchester and the Hudson Valley to possibly win seats that could make a difference on which party controls the gavels in Congress. Blakeman is in a position to do that.”</p> 
<p>Who leads the Republican ticket in this deep blue state will have critical implications for competitive House races that stand to determine which party will control the narrowly divided chamber and the course of President Donald Trump’s final two years in office. Blakeman’s coattails offer one possible remedy to GOP headwinds in next year’s midterm elections, as Democrats seize on affordability issues and stoke their base’s anger at the sitting president’s policies.</p> 
<p>Blakeman, 70, is now the likely Republican nominee for governor after Rep. Elise Stefanik <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/rep-elise-stefanik-set-to-drop-her-bid-for-nys-governor-00700879" target="_blank">abruptly suspended</a> her campaign last week. Stefanik and Blakeman are both Trump allies, and the 41-year-old upstate New York House member is far better known statewide.</p> 
<p>Unlike Stefanik, Blakeman hails from a vote rich political bellwether in a state that’s otherwise dominated by Democrats. He is a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook/2025/11/19/gops-2026-abortion-conundrum-00658469" target="_blank">self-described “pro-choice” Republican</a> — a stance that will likely attract some independent and conservative Democratic voters. And he has cultivated a <a href="https://nypost.com/2024/12/16/us-news/new-york-post-to-expand-long-island-coverage-in-2025/" target="_blank">mutually beneficial relationship</a> with The New York Post, the influential conservative tabloid that’s part of Trump’s media diet.</p> 
<p>His bid is still considered a longshot against Hochul, <a href="https://sri.siena.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/SNY1225-Crosstabs_12-15_Final.pdf" target="_blank">who led Blakeman by 25 points</a> in a Siena University poll this month. He remains largely unknown to most New Yorkers, and Republicans are trying to reverse a 23-year losing streak in statewide elections. Blakeman’s prior statewide bid for a U.S. Senate seat ended with a loss.</p> 
<p>In an interview, Blakeman pointed to his ability to win in a large, diverse suburban county as a sign that he can be successful statewide.</p> 
<p>“I want our congressional and Senate and Assembly and local candidates to be successful as well,” he said. “If you look at the demographics of Nassau County, we match the state almost as a mirror image. I feel very confident we’re going to win.”</p> 
<p>New York Republicans know the power the top of their party’s ticket can wield in a midterm election. Then-Rep. Lee Zeldin’s 2022 campaign came within 6 points of defeating Hochul, but the Long Islander’s strong suburban showing was credited with helping sweep several House Republicans into office. GOP leaders are poised to replicate that plan in 2026 — a doubling down on a suburban strategy <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/01/democrats-fret-the-zohran-mamdani-effect-will-cost-them-next-year-00531906" target="_blank">that will also tie all Democrats</a>, including Hochul, to New York City Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani.</p> 
<p>Republicans want to cast the 34-year-old democratic socialist as a lightning rod. Blakeman, whose day-to-day movements are covered in the Big Apple’s media market, would have easy access to blast the left-leaning mayor’s policies.</p> 
<p>The most immediate impact may be on the Long Island districts led by moderate Democratic Reps. Tom Suozzi and Laura Gillen — both of which will be top GOP targets.</p> 
<p>“It’s definitely going to put those two Nassau seats, Suozzi and Gillen seats into play,” said Conservative Party Chair Gerard Kassar. “I already thought the Gillen seat would be a top seat in the nation. Suozzi has a number of solid candidates nipping at his toes there to begin with. If I was residing in Nassau County and looking for some very positive results in 2026, I think I just hit the jackpot.”</p> 
<p>Suozzi and Gillen campaign representatives pointed to their work with Republicans and ability to win swing seats regardless of the top of the ticket.</p> 
<p>“Everyone knows that Tom Suozzi works across the aisle in Congress to take on the affordability crisis, lower healthcare costs, fix the immigration mess and keep our communities safe,” said Kim Devlin, a Suozzi senior advisor. “That’s why he was able to win his district, even while Trump won it as well. People are sick of partisanship and that’s why they will re-elect Tom Suozzi.”</p> 
<p>The Gillen campaign offered a similar assessment, noting that she "has a proven record of embracing bipartisanship to achieve results to lower the costs of living and improve public safety.”</p> 
<p>“In fact, Bruce Blakeman endorsed her and served as her deputy Supervisor,” a campaign spokesperson said. “Her moderate approach, that prioritizes Long Islanders over politics, is why Rep. Gillen will be re-elected in November."</p> 
<p>Democrats have dominated New York statewide elections since George Pataki left office in 2006. The party lost its final toehold on power in Albany after losing control of the state Senate in 2018. But Republicans continue to maintain competitive races in suburban enclaves, where voters are sensitive to high taxes and concerned about public safety.</p> 
<p>“You’re always more likely to lose than win as a Republican in New York, but I think he's going to be our strongest statewide candidate since George Pataki,” said Republican operative Chapin Fay. “He’s winning in a blue area and he’s sort of MAGA without a lot of the baggage.”</p> 
<p>Ensuring success in down-ballot races will be paramount for local Republican leaders with many municipal races switching from low-turnout odd-years <a href="https://www.cityandstateny.com/policy/2025/10/even-year-local-elections-are-coming-some/408917/" target="_blank">to even-numbered years</a>, when more people are expected to vote. That means races for GOP-held seats on some town and village boards and county legislatures may take on a more competitive tilt — threatening Republican power on the local level.</p> 
<p>In Nassau County, where Blakeman has served as the top elected official since his 2021 victory, Republicans maintain a robust political operation led by Chair Joe Cairo. Despite widespread GOP losses last month, Nassau County Republican candidates overperformed, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/bellwether-suburban-countys-red-shift-is-now-at-the-center-of-both-parties-future-identities-in-new-york-00683750" target="_blank">POLITICO reported</a>. Those results underscore the potential strength of Cairo’s voter turnout effort.</p> 
<p>“To me, it’s a good strategy,” said Assemblymember Ed Ra, a Nassau County Republican. “It helps when we have a couple of House races that we think are going to be very competitive. For us in the Legislature, we think having a suburban, well-known, well-liked candidate is going to be a positive.”</p> 
<p>Long Island is a major prize for any statewide candidate — and the suburbs have been trending Republican this decade with voters activated by concerns over crime and Democratic-backed criminal justice reforms.</p> 
<p>New York Democrats acknowledge Blakeman’s strength in Nassau County in particular will present a challenge for down-ballot candidates.</p> 
<p>“He will have an organization working for him in Nassau County,” said Jay Jacobs, who serves as both the statewide Democratic Committee chair and the Nassau County Democratic leader. “But I would say that while it certainly will be a factor that we have to take into account in those congressional races and down-ballot races, he likes to tout his great win and his perceived popularity, but we don’t see it that way and our polling doesn’t show it that way.”</p> 
<p>Hochul, a Buffalo native, has struggled in the New York City suburbs.</p> 
<p>The governor and Jacobs publicly disagreed over supporting Mamdani’s candidacy as her hand-picked party chair moved to distance suburban Democrats from the incoming mayor. She lost Nassau and Suffolk counties to Zeldin three years ago. Hochul was also forced to retool a controversial home building and zoning proposal amid a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/02/11/hochul-faces-uprising-housing-plan-00080949" target="_blank">bipartisan revolt on Long Island</a>.</p> 
<p>Hochul on Monday pointed to her efforts addressing crime, housing and jobs on Long Island.</p> 
<p>“We will do very well on Long Island,” she predicted. “I’ve spent an enormous amount of time on Long Island.”</p> 
<p>Blakeman’s political vulnerabilities may still complicate matters for Republicans. A liberal stance on abortion is unnerving conservative voters the party can’t afford to have stay home. Upstate Republicans, slighted by yet another New York City-area nominee, will have to be won over. <a href="https://sri.siena.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/SNY1225-Crosstabs_12-15_Final.pdf" target="_blank">Trump’s unpopularity</a> in his native state is also expected to work against Blakeman, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/20/trump-new-york-governor-endorsement-bruce-blakeman-00702013" target="_blank">was endorsed by the president</a> over the weekend.</p> 
<p>Hochul, too, is expected to be a more formidable incumbent than she was three years ago when she was still a rookie governor and running in a backlash year for her party. The Democratic governor is a formidable fundraiser and she has also worked to build up the state Democrats’ political infrastructure to buttress vulnerable candidates running below her on the ballot.</p> 
<p>Her campaign moved swiftly to define Blakeman, who remains unknown to 70 percent of voters, <a href="https://sri.siena.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/SNY1225-Crosstabs_12-15_Final.pdf" target="_blank">the Siena poll found</a>, saying Blakeman “has gone all-in on Donald Trump’s deeply unpopular MAGA movement.” And Hochul questioned whether he ultimately would be the nominee.</p> 
<p>“The Republican Party is in such chaos, I’m not even sure he’s going to end up being the nominee. This changes by the hour,” Hochul told POLITICO at a news conference. “I’m not going to speculate about the prospective opposition, other than knowing it’s going to be a MAGA, Trump-endorsed Republican.”</p> 
<p><i>Bill Mahoney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Schumer moves to sue the Trump administration over Epstein files rollout</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/schumer-trump-epstein-files-00702725</link>
      <description>The DOJ is facing accusations of not complying with the law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-46d8-dba9-addb-77ffa2950001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 12:15:34 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e3/19/05a3808c46ae8e52e3a832a3e5e1/u-s-congress-95791.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer speaks during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol on Dec. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e3/19/05a3808c46ae8e52e3a832a3e5e1/u-s-congress-95791.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> plans to force a vote on a measure to allow the chamber to jump-start litigation against the Trump administration for failing to comply with the new law requiring the full release of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>“The law Congress passed is crystal clear: release the Epstein files in full so Americans can see the truth,” the New York Democrat said in a statement Monday. “Instead, the Trump Department of Justice dumped redactions and withheld the evidence — that breaks the law. Today, I am introducing a resolution to force the Senate to take legal action and compel this administration to comply.”</p> 
<p>The resolution would establish “authority to initiate litigation for actions by the President and Department of Justice officials inconsistent with their duties under the laws of the United States.” </p> 
<p>It’s unlikely that enough Republicans would join Democrats in supporting the measure, but Schumer intends to put his colleagues on the spot in January, bringing the resolution to the floor when the Senate reconvenes after the holiday recess.</p> 
<p>It follows Friday’s long-awaited rollout of materials from the Justice Department in its case against the late, convicted sex offender. That day, Dec. 19, marked the legislation’s deadline for public disclosure — but DOJ has said it would instead slowly release materials over the course of weeks, sparking bipartisan outrage.</p> 
<p>The White House on Monday pointed to Deputy Attorney General Todd Blanche’s <a href="https://x.com/rapidresponse47/status/2002752854079979837?s=46" target="_blank">recent interview with NBC News</a>, in which he claimed his department was doing everything in its power to comply with the law. </p> 
<p>Asked about potential threats about impeachment proceedings, contempt or criminal referrals, Blanche responded: “Bring it on.”</p> 
<p>The White House referred further comment to the Justice Department. The Justice Department did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Congress passed legislation last month granting the Justice Department 30 days to publicly release its materials. The bill provided few exceptions for when files could obtain redactions — primarily in instances where DOJ wanted to protect the identities of Epstein's victims.</p> 
<p>The White House and congressional GOP leadership had led a long campaign to thwart passage the bill. However, it ultimately advanced unanimously in the Senate and with only one nay vote in the House: Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260129" data-person-id="260129">Clay Higgins</a> (R-La.), who argued it could jeopardize the privacy of Epstein’s victims and others.</p> 
<p>After an initial dump of materials Friday and Saturday, Democrats were quick to blast the administration for failing to release the Epstein files in full and accused the administration of unlawfully redacting information. </p> 
<p>Relatively little new information was included in the batches of materials that have been released so far.</p> 
<p>Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/218327" data-person-id="218327">Ro Khanna</a> (D-Calif.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> (R-Ky.) — who championed the legislation and led the effort to force a floor vote in the House to release the files — suggested they would urge the House to invoke its long-dormant power to hold Attorney General Pam Bondi in inherent contempt of Congress for her agency's failure to comply with the law.</p> 
<p>On Monday, Khanna <a href="https://x.com/RoKhanna/status/2003127350884479253" target="_blank">posted on X</a> that he, Massie and Epstein’s accusers are eager to see the draft indictment, interviews in which witnesses name other men who might have perpetuated sex crimes, emails from Epstein’s computer and the Epstein prosecution memo. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘We wasted a lot of time’: The next shutdown deadline will be here sooner than you think</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/appropriations-talks-jan-30-00701426</link>
      <description>No tangible progress toward funding the government was made before lawmakers left for the holidays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-38d0-d78e-af9f-fcf7da150008</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5a/c2/1ab7a3074a46b263b0fbfd2c0be7/u-s-congress-28265.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“When they're ready to negotiate, we can move fast,” House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.), right, said of his funding partners.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5a/c2/1ab7a3074a46b263b0fbfd2c0be7/u-s-congress-28265.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress has adjourned for the holidays having made no tangible progress toward funding the government ahead of a shutdown looming less than six weeks away.</p> 
<p>The most conspicuous sign that Congress faces real obstacles before the Jan. 30 funding deadline came late Thursday, when Senate leaders <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6945d8013f0a319f78586f24&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoVzEEOwyAMAMEXOYZIiZr-xgIHUClG2Cnq75ue9rKabNb1iTjnXLrUYiXIEuSNtXwYrh7JWHF164Z-Rf_AIC0NVkXlRiZDoTLd6ykDLDPkG4n0VZjFslwGnVRLS3BeLf7bKbwoMTi3H8e--R8KhS5v&amp;@OriginalLink=www.politico.com" target="_blank">gave up on passing a spending package</a> and sent members home for two weeks, despite working for more than a month to appease senators who had objections.</p> 
<p>But the impediments to reaching a deal that can pass both chambers are more extensive, starting with the fact that Republicans and Democrats on both ends of the Capitol have yet to start negotiating the details of the nine pending funding bills. The lack of bipartisan offer-trading is raising the likelihood of another short-term punt — or another shutdown.</p> 
<p>“We wasted a lot of time because the Senate’s not negotiating yet,” House Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51327" data-person-id="51327">Tom Cole</a> (R-Okla.) said in an interview last week. “When they're ready to negotiate, we can move fast.”</p> 
<p>Cole and his counterpart, Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine), just <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/top-appropriators-clinch-funding-totals-to-jumpstart-house-senate-negotiations-00701902" target="_blank">reached an agreement</a> over the weekend on overall totals for the remaining spending bills Congress needs to pass. Lawmakers already passed three as part of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/senate-passes-shutdown-ending-deal-00646020" target="_blank">package that ended the shutdown</a> last month — funding veterans and agriculture agencies, federal food aid and the Food and Drug Administration, along with Congress itself, through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>For more than a month Cole and Collins had been trying to bridge differences on key numbers while Senate leaders tried to advance a funding package that reflects consensus from only their side of the Capitol. Last week’s heave failed, but senators expect to try again in early January.</p> 
<p>“We have different dynamics in our caucuses that we need to deal with,” Collins said this month as she left a meeting with Cole.</p> 
<p>Democrats have been growing impatient. “They wasted all that time during the summer,” said Connecticut Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a>, the House’s top Democratic appropriator, about House Republicans spending the better part of this year crafting partisan funding bills.</p> 
<p>Then Democrats had to wait for their GOP counterparts to strike the “majority to majority” deal on funding totals that finally arrived Saturday.</p> 
<p>“Democrats are prepared. We're ready to move. Let's go,” DeLauro said.</p> 
<p>Even if top appropriators can manage to agree on the nine remaining funding bills, other thorny dynamics threaten to complicate final passage in each chamber. The pitfalls include the mismatch between what appropriators want to spend and the demands of House fiscal hawks <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6945d8013f0a319f78586f24&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoFwgEOgCAIAMAXEczlVv3GzIqV0ETH99vd3ftnG6K7T5--3DnrlLWiFDcMFCLSgjRjVrlaMQM2UAEbtZYGeyvpgXPIwXJBvpMaJE_cDYjmZY0x_Kq7IbI%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.politico.com" target="_blank">seeking flat funding for agencies</a> — as well as the fact that Democrats will need to help pass any spending bills in the Senate, as they acutely illustrated with this fall’s <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6945d8013f0a319f78586f24&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoFwlEKwCAIANATmf-7jZQsoVSmTXb78d7M9LgQq6q5LUnp1rptvO3lRzdrQsyTw0pBuQKOD0oOIKX1hcQPWVYZ6g%3D%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.politico.com" target="_blank">record 43-day shutdown</a>.</p> 
<p>The totals top Republican appropriators just agreed upon are not public. But Cole said the deal will ensure overall funding would be below the level laid out in the stopgap funding patch enacted last month.</p> 
<p>Maryland Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151768" data-person-id="151768">Andy Harris</a>, chair of the House Freedom Caucus and a top Republican appropriator, said last week that he wants funding for the Pentagon and the largest nondefense agencies to be “no more than what was enacted” for the fiscal year that ended in September.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/3265" data-person-id="3265">Chip Roy</a> (R-Texas) has the same idea: “I don't want any spending higher than current-level spending,” he said. “If they're busting the current levels, then they're going to have to demonstrate to me why.”</p> 
<p>If House hard-liners aren’t appeased when the funding bills come together, they could start making threats to Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and other GOP leaders, who already are on the outs with House Republicans over their handling of health care assistance this month.</p> 
<p>“You can expect the smoke to start coming up from over that hill and that hill and that hill,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/177013" data-person-id="177013">Mark Amodei</a> (R-Nev.), who chairs the Homeland Security spending panel. “And there might even be some open flame.”</p> 
<p>Amodei said some of his colleagues are openly talking about the potential for another shutdown. But many others think it is more likely that Congress is headed for another punt at current funding levels for the remaining nine bills.</p> 
<p>Last week, Johnson told his conference in a closed-door meeting that he wants to pass those bills by the Jan. 30 deadline — a goal that many in the GOP ranks consider aspirational at best. One House Republican granted anonymity to describe the private meeting said he turned to one of his colleagues and whispered, “I wouldn't bet on that on Polymarket,” referring to an online prediction market.</p> 
<p>Senate leaders have their own conflicting demands to manage. Fiscal conservatives repeatedly objected to starting debate on a five-bill funding package in recent weeks, citing opposition to earmarks as they also sought promises related to other legislation.</p> 
<p>But it was Democrats who blocked movement in the final days before the Senate adjourned Thursday. One late-breaking demand by Colorado’s senators was to reverse the White House’s move last week to <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6945d8013f0a319f78586f24&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoNyEkOgCAMAMAXlSJx_w02jRLZUkr4vs5xHtXaTsQxhqklBg1UDJWEmUdDZ92Ck8NpQ5WeKij7BJewf0O-of9RKlAMySuDcGMv9ABxVhawdj3mfd8-8x8ihA%3D%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.politico.com" target="_blank">dismantle a federal center in the state</a> that supports research in climate and weather science.</p> 
<p>Still, following the acrimony of the shutdown this fall, Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> and Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> are at least projecting a unified front on government funding ahead of the January deadline.</p> 
<p>“Both Thune and I are in agreement that we’re going to work through the process and get the appropriations bills done,” Schumer told reporters late Thursday after Senate leaders decided to adjourn without passing the funding package.</p> 
<p>Since top Republican appropriators reached an agreement on overall totals after Congress adjourned, lawmakers hope some negotiating can be done before they return to town Jan. 5.</p> 
<p>“Staff has been instructed to — whatever they're doing — take their laptops with them,” DeLauro said.</p> 
<p>When Congress reconvenes, both chambers are only scheduled to be in session for three weeks before the shutdown deadline — with the House slated to be out of session the week immediately before.</p> 
<p>Texas Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/338556" data-person-id="338556">Tony Gonzales</a>, a Republican appropriator, said he was hopeful his party’s leaders would keep lawmakers in town to pass any deal that might come together.</p> 
<p>“This is people's political livelihood on the line,” he said. “We’ve got to get this done. Nobody leaves.”</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This Indiana Democrat wants a redistricting ceasefire</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/20/indiana-democrats-redistricting-frank-mrvan-00700392</link>
      <description>After a political near-death experience, Rep. Frank Mrvan said it's time for both parties to lay down arms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-37d9-df0c-a5bb-37dfcd780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2025 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/51/1a/81b556bc40a88a2a81d7debfecd1/election-2026-redistricting-indiana-07660.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP Photo/Charles Rex Arbogast</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Frank Mrvan (D-Ind.) thanked GOP legislators in his state “for their act of courage and for unifying our state.”</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/51/1a/81b556bc40a88a2a81d7debfecd1/election-2026-redistricting-indiana-07660.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Republicans in his state’s legislature considered joining a Donald Trump-backed effort to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/15/white-house-officials-turn-up-the-heat-on-indiana-redistricting-00512106" target="_blank">redraw congressional maps</a> in the GOP’s favor, Rep. Frank Mrvan kept quiet.</p> 
<p>The new lines would have doomed the low-key Democrat representing Indiana’s northwest corner, but only now — after Republicans in the state Senate roundly rejected the Trump push — is he speaking out with a message for both parties: It’s time to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/redistricting-indiana-illinois-virginia-florida-maryland-00689748" target="_blank">lay down arms</a> on redistricting.</p> 
<p>“I do not believe all-blue and all-red states benefit anyone,” Mrvan said in an interview. “We need to have unifying factors that bring our country together again, like lowering health care costs and being able to make sure that when someone goes to a grocery store, they can afford beef and provide for their families and have safe communities. I don't know if it's a priority to manipulate maps for one party or the other to be in the majority.”</p> 
<p>While Indiana’s attempt at mid-decade redistricting is now in the rearview mirror, other states have not ruled it out. The GOP-controlled Florida legislature is now <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/florida-gop-house-speaker-insists-white-house-is-not-pushing-redistricting-00684542" target="_blank">exploring new maps</a>, but so are the Democratic majorities in Maryland and Virginia. Both parties are also closely watching a forthcoming Supreme Court decision on the Voting Rights Act that could prompt new maps in southern states.</p> 
<p>After Trump kicked off the mid-cycle redistricting push by prodding Texas Republicans to draw new lines that could oust as many as five Democrats in 2026, many House lawmakers aired private concerns about the disruptive and divisive process that was not guaranteed to net GOP seats in the midterms. Many fewer spoke out publicly, given fear of retribution from Trump.</p> 
<p>Now a growing number of Democrats are eager to exact revenge. California Gov. Gavin Newsom pushed through a ballot measure that will allow Democrats to offset the Texas losses, but some are eager for more — with Mrvan among the few who have been willing to say that would be a bad idea.</p> 
<p>Rep. André Carson, the other Indiana Democrat whose district was at grave risk in a redistricting scenario, defended the blue states that are still looking to act, saying it was “all a reaction to what happened in Texas.”</p> 
<p>“My hope is that this will inspire other legislative bodies to push back against Donald Trump's very extremist agenda that is helping himself but hurting Americans,” Carson said. Pressed on blue-state redistricting, he said those legislatures “are going to have to make that decision on their own.”</p> 
<p>Carson and Mrvan among a dwindling number of midwestern Democrats in an increasingly coastal caucus who just survived a political near-death experience. The fact is, they might have only gotten a temporary reprieve: Post-census redistricting just six years away could put them in peril once again.</p> 
<p>Mrvan has already been targeted by national Republicans, winning a costly 2022 race by about 6 points. But he described working quietly behind the scenes to convince statehouse leaders that drawing him out of his seat would be a bad idea.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/indiana-republicans-redistricting-vote-trump-00687714" target="_blank">31-19 final vote killing the proposal</a> didn’t have anything to do with pressure from him, Mrvan emphasized, but he had been in touch with GOP state senators who had been victims of harassment <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/indiana-republican-trump-redistricting-swatted-00654098" target="_blank">including “swatting” incidents</a> to check on their safety.</p> 
<p>“I think it was very clear they were going to vote their conscience and what they believed in, and there is no inside track that they were sharing with me the process and what was going on,” he said — while also personally thanking <a href="https://www.indianasenaterepublicans.com/bohacek" target="_blank">four</a> <a href="https://www.indianasenaterepublicans.com/charbonneau" target="_blank">GOP</a> <a href="https://www.indianasenaterepublicans.com/dernulc" target="_blank">state</a> <a href="https://www.indianasenaterepublicans.com/niemeyer" target="_blank">senators</a> in his district who opposed the redraw “for their act of courage and for unifying our state.”</p> 
<p>One message Mrvan did send, he said, was that “redistricting would not benefit the state of Indiana.” As the only Hoosier on the powerful House Appropriations Committee, he argued, his ouster would “take away that leverage” in Congress on major state projects requiring bipartisan cooperation.</p> 
<p>He cited recent indications from the owners of the NFL’s Chicago Bears that they could relocate the team from its longtime lakefront stadium just over the state line <a href="https://blockclubchicago.org/2025/12/17/bears-threaten-move-to-northwest-indiana-after-state-leaders-balk-at-arlington-heights-stadium-aid/" target="_blank">to Mrvan’s district</a>. “We're already gathering in a bipartisan way to say we welcome the Bears,” he said.</p> 
<p>Carson said he, too, took a soft-touch approach — remaining in communication with GOP members of the congressional delegation and state legislators but allowing them “the freedom and the sovereignty that they have to make decisions, because it is their body.”</p> 
<p>“But all hands were on deck,” Carson added.</p> 
<p>Both Democrats also said they were in touch with House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries starting over the summer as the redistricting push began. Carson recalled that Jeffries pledged support and resources and was “sensitive” to the dynamics of the fight as a former state legislator.</p> 
<p>In the end, Carson said, a respectful approach and Indiana’s distinctly midwestern political culture won out over <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/trump-indiana-redistricting-republicans-rodric-bray-00686257" target="_blank">national browbeating</a>.</p> 
<p>“I've said all along, Hoosiers do things very differently,” he said. “The majority of Hoosiers did not agree with this new unfair map, and Hoosiers made sure the statehouse knew it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jack Smith’s lawyers ask Jordan for open hearing after closed-door testimony</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/jack-smith-jim-jordan-trump-00699653</link>
      <description>The former special counsel’s attorneys also want the full videotape of Smith’s deposition to be released.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3494-dba9-addb-37bfe1110000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fb/93/5bde97cf4001b9ca2d6ca1bf5571/u-s-congress-64577.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Department of Justice Special Counsel Jack Smith emerges from a closed deposition before the House Judiciary Committee on Capitol Hill Dec. 17, 2025. At right, attorney Lanny Breuer is seen.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fb/93/5bde97cf4001b9ca2d6ca1bf5571/u-s-congress-64577.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After appearing in a closed-door deposition with the House Judiciary Committee earlier this week, Jack Smith, the former special counsel who led the criminal cases against President Donald Trump, still wants the chance to defend his work in a public hearing – and defend himself against continued Republican attacks.</p> 
<p>Attorneys for Smith are pressing for their client to be allowed to testify in an open forum in a new letter to House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan, obtained first by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“[We] reiterate our request for an open and public hearing,” Smith’s lawyers<b>,</b> Lanny Breuer and Peter Koski<b>,</b> wrote to Jordan. “During the investigation of President Trump, Mr. Smith steadfastly followed Justice Department policies, observed all legal requirements, and took actions based on the facts and the law. He stands by his decisions.”</p> 
<p>Breuer and Koski also requested that the videotape of Smith’s testimony be released in full so that he can speak to the public directly “rather than through second-hand accounts.”</p> 
<p>Smith’s deposition spanned more than eight hours Wednesday, as he spoke to House Judiciary members under oath and stood by his decisions to levy criminal charges against the then-former president for allegedly mishandling classified documents and attempting to subvert the results of the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>According to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-deposition-congress-00694730" target="_blank">portions of his statement</a> shared with POLITICO, Smith argued the evidence in his office’s possession would have provided proof of the President’s criminal behavior “beyond a reasonable doubt.”</p> 
<p>He never got to fully present that evidence, as Smith was forced to drop both his cases as a result of Justice Department policy that prevents prosecuting the current occupant of the White House. But Trump and his allies have continued to paint Smith as a villainous leader in the campaign to politicize the Biden-era Justice Department.</p> 
<p>House and Senate Republicans have vowed to investigate Smith and his office’s work in a crusade that has only become more intense in the wake of revelations that Smith requested phone data for Republican members of Congress as part of his election subversion probe.</p> 
<p>Jordan, who has separately already referred Smith’s senior assistant special counsel for criminal prosecution for failing to cooperate with his investigation, said he has not ruled out allowing the Biden era special counsel to testify in an open forum.</p> 
<p>There are relatively few details about Smith’s remarks and the exchanges with lawmakers, beyond the portions of his statements shared with reporters. Members of the Judiciary Committee leaving the deposition Wednesday provided relatively few details.</p> 
<p>Amid an ongoing Justice Department campaign to levy criminal charges against the president’s perceived enemies, Smith is also navigating <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-congress-investigations-00693884" target="_blank">a complicated legal minefield</a>: His testimony is hamstrung by grand jury secrecy rules, DOJ policy and an order from a federal judge that a volume of his report surrounding the classified documents case remain under seal.</p> 
<p>It’s not clear to what extent Smith told Congressional investigators he could not provide certain information due to the various restrictions on his testimony.</p> 
<p>Democrats have argued the decision to hold the private deposition deprived the American public of important information about the president and amounted to an effort to distort the record of Smith’s testimony.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, was still hopeful Smith could be given the chance to speak publicly.</p> 
<p>“I think somebody should prepare Donald Trump for it, because he will be devastated and humiliated by what he hears,” Raskin said in a brief interview Thursday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘You cannot hide’: Democrats’ swaggering approach stymies House Republicans</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/house-democrats-gop-agenda-00699385</link>
      <description>Under Hakeem Jeffries, the minority party has kept GOP leaders on the back foot since September.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-342e-dba9-addb-37bf28e00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5a/26/d1ba90af4552a9cb40e9bad90eaa/u-s-congress-26502.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>"You can run, but you cannot hide," Jeffries (center) bellowed at Republicans a day after four GOP members joined his discharge petition.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5a/26/d1ba90af4552a9cb40e9bad90eaa/u-s-congress-26502.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On paper, Democrats are locked out of legislative power in the majority-rules House. In practice over the past several months, they have been a swaggering force.</p> 
<p>Time and again this year, Democrats under Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries have maneuvered to successfully undercut the GOP agenda and put its leaders on the back foot. From a daily drumbeat on health care to the long-running saga over the late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein to a new focus on the rising cost of living, they believe they’re succeeding by making the party in power talk about Democratic priorities, not its own.</p> 
<p>Their success was underscored this week when four House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688" target="_blank">joined a Jeffries-led effort to force a vote</a> on expiring Obamacare insurance subsidies — a major embarrassment for the GOP speaker.</p> 
<p>“Our message to Mike Johnson is clear — you can run, but you cannot hide,” Jeffries said as he took a victory lap on the House steps Thursday.</p> 
<p>The New Yorker was referring to his party’s effort to address a so-called health care “crisis” brought about by Republican governance. But it could just as well apply to the overall Democratic attitude at the moment, with the party increasingly buoyant about its political fortunes heading into next year’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>Johnson and his leadership allies have been able to put some wins on the board since lawmakers returned from their summer recess. Republicans ultimately triumphed and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/trump-signs-bill-ending-longest-government-shutdown-in-us-history-00650189" target="_blank">ended a record-long shutdown</a> without agreeing to a costly extension of the Obamacare subsidies. They managed to unite and pass a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">small-bore health care package</a> this week as well as a bipartisan permitting reform bill.</p> 
<p>But it has come at a cost. To win the shutdown fight, Johnson kept the House out of session — giving up roughly a fifth of the year’s scheduled legislative days. And managing a razor-thin majority with its constantly clashing factions has left many of his members airing dissatisfaction with the status quo.</p> 
<p>“I think the House as a whole has not been nearly as proactive as we should have been in recent months,” said Rep. Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.). “It certainly didn't help that we weren't even here for two of those months.”</p> 
<p>“I believe that we’re behind,” added Rep. Nancy Mace (R-S.C.). “We’ve got a lot of work to do between now and the midterms.”</p> 
<p>With a sizable band of Republican malcontents willing to buck their party’s leadership, Democrats have sought opportunities to divide the majority party — often by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/house-discharge-petitions-mike-johnson-00666557?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b4be0000&amp;nname=inside-congress&amp;nrid=57f86b65-7edd-42e7-85ae-241ab5c69500" target="_blank">using discharge petitions</a>, one of the few legislative tools available to the minority party.</p> 
<p>Already this year three discharge petitions have garnered the necessary 218 signatures, forcing votes Johnson tried to avoid on releasing the Epstein files, restoring federal workers’ collective bargaining rights and now extending the Obamacare subsidies for three years. Each one succeeded with the vast majority of Democrats signing on at Jeffries’ direction, with a handful of GOP rebels joining in.</p> 
<p>“We're in the minority, but our ideas are still really good, and they deserve bipartisan support,” said Rep. Greg Stanton (D-Ariz.).</p> 
<p>Democrats, Jeffries said, have already “won more discharge petitions in the last three weeks than have been successful in the last 30 years.” More could be coming next year, with more lawmakers planning to move on Russia sanctions legislation and a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/johnson-steil-insider-trading-stocks-00698141" target="_blank">ban on congressional stock trading</a>.</p> 
<p>Beyond the discharge petitions, House and Senate Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/11/congress/democrats-heath-care-shutdown-demand-00557516" target="_blank">made a larger strategic calculation</a> in September that has since dominated the congressional agenda: centering a government shutdown fight on health care — in particular, the pending Dec. 31 expiration of enhanced Affordable Care Act tax credits enacted and extended under former president Joe Biden.</p> 
<p>The decision shifted the conversation on Capitol Hill away from President Donald Trump’s controversial but popular assault on federal spending to much more favorable political ground for Democrats. The party knew well that health care was a minefield for Republicans — one that many in both parties blamed for the GOP’s massive House losses in the 2018 midterms.</p> 
<p>Ultimately, the shutdown ended after 43 days when a handful of Democratic senators decided the standoff had run its course. But House Democrats strategized to keep health care center stage, with Jeffries filing a discharge petition seeking a vote on a straight three-year extension of the expiring tax credits before moderate Republicans started filing their own discharge petitions.</p> 
<p>Within a week, it had more than 200 signatures, and as the vulnerable Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-johnson-confronted-gop-moderates-00693242" target="_blank">scrambled for an off-ramp</a>, Jeffries frequently noted the simplest solution would be for a handful of GOP members to sign on to the Democratic effort. Some moderate Democrats mulled backing a competing discharge petition from Rep. Josh Gottheimer (D-N.J.) that would force a vote on his bipartisan plan for a shorter extension with strings attached. But the vast majority of Democrats kept away, signaling they wanted to stay behind Jeffries’ approach.</p> 
<p>“Nobody wanted Gottheimer to dictate strategy for the whole caucus,” said one person directly involved who was granted anonymity to speak candidly about strategy.</p> 
<p>The maneuvering paid off. While Jeffries kept Republicans and some of his own members guessing by suggesting he might get behind one of the bipartisan plans, he ultimately never wavered on the straight three-year approach.</p> 
<p>When, as many Democrats expected, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-johnson-aca-vote-00692703" target="_blank">Johnson refused</a> to put one of the compromise extensions on the floor, GOP moderates were left with no choice but to join the Jeffries effort.</p> 
<p>Rep. Troy Carter (D-La.) called it an “incredibly strategic move” by Jeffries “to have a discharge petition in place and create a safe space for members to do the right thing.”</p> 
<p>The completion of the discharge petition has amounted to an internal debacle for Johnson, whose members are now unhappy that GOP leaders got outplayed and will now vote on a measure that the vast majority of them loathe.</p> 
<p>“I hate that we are voting on a three-year clean extension and not a bipartisan bill that has smart reforms to the tax credits,” Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) said. “The worst option is being put on the floor — and one that the Senate will not pass.”</p> 
<p>Republican leaders, for their part, initially underestimated whether enough of the moderate holdouts would be willing to break ranks and sign on to Jeffries' discharge petition. They viewed two in particular — Pennsylvania Reps. Rob Bresnahan and Ryan Mackenzie — as unlikely to sign given their willingness to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/house-passes-gop-megabill-00438206" target="_blank">fall in line on the GOP megabill</a> over the summer, according to two people granted anonymity to describe internal conversations.</p> 
<p>But as each side dug in early this week and leaders moved away from allowing a floor vote on a compromise amendment, the moderates made clear to GOP leaders they would retaliate via the Jeffries discharge petition. Bresnahan and Mackenzie were among the four who signed, pushing it over the top.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader Steve Scalise said in an interview that the possibility of the moderates linking arms with Democrats “was heavily discussed” and that leaders “didn’t want it to happen.”</p> 
<p>“But, you know, we tried to find a different way to address it,” he said. “I mean, nobody was blindsided.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loudermilk looks to early 2026 for first Jan. 6 hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/jan-6-hearing-coming-soon-00698723</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-336c-dba9-addb-33ffb4bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 16:50:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The new Republican-led subcommittee investigating the events around the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the Capitol will have its first hearing next month, panel Chair Barry Loudermilk said Thursday.</p> 
<p>The Georgia Republican said the hearing will focus on the Biden-era FBI’s inquiry into the pipe bombs left at the headquarters of the Republican and Democratic National Committees the day before Congress gathered to certify the results of the 2020 presidential election.</p> 
<p>It will also come on the heels of the recent arrest of a suspect in the pipe bombs case, nearly five years after the fact: The Justice Department earlier this month charged a 30-year-old Virginia man with transporting the explosive devices.</p> 
<p>“We’re looking at … January” for a hearing, Loudermilk said in a brief interview. “We’re nailing down the date — I think it’s probably going to be around the third week or so.”</p> 
<p>The select subcommittee’s hearing will officially launch the next chapter in the GOP’s attempts to rewrite the narrative around the violent riot at the Capitol.</p> 
<p>Republicans have long argued that the previous incarnation of the Jan. 6 committee, led by Democrats, was unfair to President Donald Trump; they allege it was more focused on maligning Republicans than exploring the security failures that allowed the violent events to take place.</p> 
<p>Trump and his allies have also continued to brood over the Biden DOJ’s handling of the aftermath of the attacks and efforts to hold bad actors accountable for their actions. Just this past week, former special counsel Jack Smith — who led the investigation into Trump’s efforts to subvert the results of the 2020 election — sat for an hourslong deposition with the House Judiciary Committee to defend his probe.</p> 
<p>In a brief interview Thursday, Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland — the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee who also sits as an ex officio member of the newly reconstituted Jan. 6 panel — suggested that Loudermilk invite Smith to testify about the political motives of the pipe bombs suspect.</p> 
<p>“Undoubtedly, the fact that this guy was a supporter of Donald Trump's big lie, and the various activities of January 6, suggests that there was no cover-up of who the person was,” said Raskin, who served on the now-disbanded, Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House passes major GOP-led permitting overhaul after late drama</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/house-passes-gop-permitting-overhaul-00697554</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3359-d651-a1ff-3f79d14f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 16:30:43 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House passed bipartisan legislation by a 221-196 vote Thursday aimed at overhauling federal permitting reviews in a bid to accelerate the construction of new energy and infrastructure projects amid surging power demand and rising electricity prices.</p> 
<p>By approving the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_4776" target="_blank">SPEED Act</a>, which <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/11/westermans-bipartisan-nepa-permitting-overhaul-advances-to-house-floor-00663191" target="_blank">overhauls the National Environmental Policy Act</a>, House Republicans were able to put their stamp on a bipartisan priority of easing the regulatory hurdles blamed for hampering the development of both fossil fuel and renewable energy projects.</p> 
<p>Eleven Democrats voted for the bill, and one Republican opposed it.</p> 
<p>"For too long, America’s broken permitting process has stifled economic development and innovation," said Natural Resources Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189075" target="_blank" data-person-id="189075">Bruce Westerman</a>, the architect of the bill. "This historic vote on the SPEED Act will fix the system by establishing the project certainty that’s currently lacking in the permitting process and allow America to build again."</p> 
<p>But GOP leaders' late change to the SPEED Act to appease offshore wind foes on the right wing of the caucus irked Democrats and prompted some defections. That could make it harder to strike a deal on comprehensive permitting reform with the Senate.</p> 
<p>Westerman, though, argued the bipartisan result created momentum. "We got 11 Democrats, even after all the theatrics. We said our goal was to have a bipartisan permitting bill in the Senate before the end of the year and we did it. We've sent them a really good piece of legislation."</p> 
<p>Democrats and some moderate House Republicans said they were leaning on the Senate — where broader Democratic support is required to overcome a filibuster — to negotiate a more bipartisan product that would remove the language pushed by hard-liners and strengthen protections for clean energy.</p> 
<p>“There is Democratic support for permitting reform,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/199009" target="_blank" data-person-id="199009">Scott Peters</a> (D-Calif). “We always knew that the Democrats in the Senate were going to have a big role to play to bring it toward us.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘No path’ for another GOP party-line bill, Ways and Means chair says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/jason-smith-reconciliation-2026-00698324</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3320-df0c-a5bb-3777d8a80005</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 15:23:34 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Ways and Means Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192689" data-person-id="192689">Jason Smith</a> is swatting down some of his colleagues' hopes for a party-line policy bill next year, even as Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> publicly tries to keep the idea alive.</p> 
<p>“I don't see a path of a second reconciliation ever passing,” Smith (R-Mo.) said in an interview as he left the Capitol on Wednesday, referring to the special budgetary procedures that can allow legislation to avoid a Senate filibuster.</p> 
<p>The comment came just hours after Johnson said in a CNBC interview that Republicans could still attempt another second reconciliation bill early next year — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-gop-leaders-pitch-members-on-unaffordable-care-act-00656362" target="_blank">especially to address health care</a> with the party facing pressure to act as key Obamacare subsidies expire. The promise of another party-line bill figured into conversations Johnson had with GOP hard-liners over the past week as they pushed for assurances for further action before Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">pushed through a narrow health care bill</a> Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Smith, on the other hand, has long been skeptical that Republicans will get more than one bite at the reconciliation apple in the 119th Congress. He was a key proponent of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/01/18/jason-smith-reconciliation-plan-00199094" target="_blank">pursing "one big, beautiful bill"</a> this year encompassing tax cuts and other GOP priorities rather than splitting it up into multiple pieces.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-18T18:30:27-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>New Johnson, Steil plan would allow lawmakers to keep their existing stocks</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/johnson-steil-insider-trading-stocks-00698141</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-32dd-d78e-af9f-feff18de0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 14:29:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders are working on a proposal that would ban members from buying individual stocks but allow them to hold the ones they already own, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss private conversations. </p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and House Administration Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/32319" data-person-id="32319">Bryan Steil</a> (R-Wis.) briefed a group of GOP members Thursday about their new plan. It would also mandate seven days of public notice before selling what they own. They're still negotiating other details like penalties and which assets the new rules would apply to.</p> 
<p>Johnson and Steil indicated the legislation could get a floor vote as soon as January, according to two of the people. Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said in a brief interview his goal is to put the legislation on the floor “early next year,” but he said he would not commit to January.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s move comes as Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna </a>(R-Fla.) and a group of Republicans have been pushing their own discharge petition to force a vote on a bipartisan consensus bill to ban members of Congress and their spouses from trading stocks — but senior and some rank-and-file Republicans are opposed to that legislation, saying it's too restrictive.</p> 
<p>Instead, the new proposal Steil is expected to shepherd through his panel would have a lighter touch. It could crack down on members of Congress participating in insider trading while building consensus with skeptical Republicans, including those on the financial services panel.</p> 
<p>The plan will likely incorporate some pieces of legislation to ban stock trading that Luna and other Republicans have been working on this year.</p> 
<p>Luna told reporters leaving the meeting there have been discussions about potentially changing the House rules in order to implement part of the crackdown.</p> 
<p>House Democrats are also pushing for a broader stock-trading bill that would include the executive branch. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/431425" data-person-id="431425">Seth Magaziner</a> (D-R.I.), the lead sponsor, said they're aiming to introduce a discharge petition to attempt to force it to the House floor. </p> 
<p>“Anything short of an actual ban on members owning and trading stocks won't solve the problem, and won't be enough for a public that expects a full ban, and so I'm hopeful that the speaker will bring a strong bill to the floor,” Magaziner said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats release more photos from Epstein estate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/congress-photos-release-epstein-files-00697565</link>
      <description>The 70-photo tranche comes on the eve of the deadline for the Justice Department to release the most broad swath of Epstein-related materials yet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3264-df0c-a5bb-367767e50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 12:22:12 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/94/8e/943601c34fa59bbf66dcd7ba5585/u-s-congress-78561.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Reps. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.), and Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) stand alongside victims of convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a press conference on the Epstein Files Transparency Act outside the U.S. Capitol, on Nov. 18, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/94/8e/943601c34fa59bbf66dcd7ba5585/u-s-congress-78561.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats on the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee released 70 additional photos Thursday obtained from the estate of Jeffrey Epstein, part of their last-ditch pressure campaign to force the Justice Department to comply with a Friday deadline to release a massive trove of files related to the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>The photos are among the 95,000 images that have been selectively released by Democrats so far from materials obtained from the Epstein estate through a subpoena from the House Oversight Committee over the summer.</p> 
<p>They also follow <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/trump-clinton-gates-included-in-epstein-photo-trove-00688628" target="_blank"><u>last week’s release of photos</u></a> highlighting Epstein’s relationship with powerful men, including President Donald Trump, former President Bill Clinton, tech giant Bill Gates and former White House chief strategist Steve Bannon.</p> 
<p>“Oversight Democrats will continue to release photographs and documents from the Epstein estate to provide transparency for the American people,” said the Oversight panel’s top Democrat, Rep. Robert Garcia of California, in a statement. “As we approach the deadline for the Epstein Files Transparency Act, these new images raise more questions about what exactly the Department of Justice has in its possession. We must end this White House cover-up, and the DOJ must release the Epstein files now.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the Justice Department did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Two of the new photographs made public by Democrats Thursday depict Gates beside a woman whose face has been obscured to protect her identity. A spokesperson for Gates, whose relationship with Epstein has been previously documented, did not immediately respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>One photo shows a page of a woman’s passport and another is a screenshot of a series of text messages where an unknown sender says they have found “some girls” for “1000$ per girl … Maybe someone will be good for J?”</p> 
<p>Trump has maintained he had a falling out with Epstein years ago. A spokesperson for Clinton has said the former president disassociated himself with Epstein before his 2019 arrest and had no knowledge of his crimes. Bannon has not publicly commented on the photos or his relationship with Epstein.</p> 
<p>The GOP-led panel launched its own probe into Epstein over the summer as Republican leaders sought to thwart a vote on legislation compelling the Justice Department to release all the Epstein-related materials it can produce while also protecting victims and not running afoul of ongoing criminal investigations.</p> 
<p>Republicans, with Trump’s blessing, eventually let this vote go through, starting the 30-day countdown clock for the DOJ to comply. But information requested by the Oversight panel is continuing to be delivered to Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>It remains to be seen, however, whether the DOJ release will quell calls for transparency and complaints about obfuscation. Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) — who co-led the insurgent, bipartisan effort to force a floor vote on the bill requiring the release of the Epstein case materials — is <a href="https://x.com/RoKhanna/status/2001492676395536491" target="_blank"><u>already questioning whether House Republicans</u></a> had cancelled votes on Friday because of the expected files’ publication.</p> 
<p>House Oversight Democrats also noted that the estate did not provide context for the images and that the young women's faces were redacted given a lack of certainty around whether they could be identified as victims of Epstein.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Republicans on the House Oversight committee did not immediately return a request for comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Congress leaves health mess for January</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/18/congress/health-care-insurance-cost-obamacare-midterms-00697147</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2fa6-d305-abdb-ffa7db200000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is about to leave town for the holidays — and put off their health care troubles until January.</p> 
<p>The House and Senate will take their last votes of the year Thursday, officially allowing Affordable Care Act subsidies to expire Dec. 31. The House <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/house-republicans-obamacare-subsidies-00695982" target="_blank">passed its GOP-led health care package</a> Wednesday night, though the Senate has no plans to take it up. </p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson vowed to work “much more” on health care in the new year, after moderate Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688" target="_blank">joined a Democrat-led discharge petition</a> for a clean three-year extension of the subsidies. Johnson said “it’s inevitable” that the discharge petition comes up after lawmakers return.</p> 
<p>“We’ll deal with it in January,” House Majority Leader Steve Scalise told reporters Wednesday. “These things take a lot of twists and turns. Just this week, we’ve had a lot of twists and turns.”</p> 
<p>The Democrats’ discharge petition is a shell bill, which means lawmakers could add Senate-passed language to it — though it’s not clear what could reach 60 votes in the Senate. GOP Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick of Pennsylvania said the plan for now is to send the clean three-year extension.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, moderate rank-and-file members in both chambers are trying to come up with a last-minute consensus plan that could pass the House and Senate. But nothing could come together until January, when Congress will have less than a month until the next funding cliff.</p> 
<p>At the center of these health care talks is Fitzpatrick, who is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-discharge-petition-00696644" target="_blank">working behind the scenes</a> to get an ACA fix even after the subsidy expiration date.</p> 
<p>“I think it’s a mistake,” Fitzpatrick told POLITICO of allowing the credits to lapse. “I’m going to exhaust every single option I have to get this done.”</p> 
<p>It’s unclear if they can pull it off. The lawmakers already failed to secure an extension before the expiration date — it’ll be much harder to revive them after.</p> 
<p>In the meantime: Interest groups on both sides are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/its-now-time-for-the-obamacare-blame-game-00696022" target="_blank">diving furiously into the blame game</a> over the subsidies lapse. It’s an early test of the messaging battle over health care — an issue that could define the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Appropriations movement:</b> Senate GOP leaders have won over all the Republicans who objected to moving a five-bill package of government funding measures this week. Now it’s Democrats’ turn to check for holds on their side for the “minibus,” which contains the Labor-HHS-Education, Defense, Transportation-HUD, Commerce-Justice-Science and Interior-Environment bills.</p> 
<p><b>— Stock trading talks:</b> Reps. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) and Tim Burchett (R-Tenn.) expect to meet with Johnson Thursday to discuss a ban on congressional stock trading. So far, their discharge petition is <a href="https://clerk.house.gov/DischargePetition/2025120211" target="_blank">nowhere close</a> to the 218 signees necessary to force a vote in the House.</p> 
<p><b>— A fight over broadband money:</b> Senate Armed Services Chair Roger Wicker (R-Miss.) will introduce a bill Thursday that would give states access to an estimated $20 to $22 billion in broadband deployment funding — a proposal at odds with efforts from Senate Commerce Chair Ted Cruz (R-Texas) and Sen. Joni Ernst (R-Iowa) that would claw back the funding entirely.</p> 
<p><i>Benjamin Guggenheim, Meredith Lee Hill, Nicholas Wu, Amanda Chu, Jennifer Scholtes and Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: A previous version of this report misidentified Ted Cruz's state affiliation.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-17T18:30:40-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>The day Brian Fitzpatrick finally said enough</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/brian-fitzpatrick-obamacare-discharge-petition-00696644</link>
      <description>The purple-district Pennsylvanian had staked out an aisle-crossing persona without impeding GOP prerogatives. Until Wednesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2e92-d369-affb-6fbe94d30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 18:16:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/05/bb/f20d5791449f958f50f5e7898320/u-s-congress-97689.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I’ve made it clear where this was all headed,” Fitzpatrick said Wednesday. “This was never a secret.”</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/05/bb/f20d5791449f958f50f5e7898320/u-s-congress-97689.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Brian Fitzpatrick, the five-term House Republican and perennial campaign target for Democrats, has long been viewed by GOP leaders as a team player. Until now.</p> 
<p>On Wednesday, his 52nd birthday, the congenial Pennsylvanian led a GOP mutiny against Speaker Mike Johnson over his handling of expiring Obamacare subsidies used by more than 20 million Americans. Fitzpatrick became the first Republican to back a Democratic-led effort to sidestep the speaker and force action on an extension of the tax credits. Three fellow GOP moderates quickly followed, cementing a January vote.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick, who has consistently won re-election in one of the most competitive districts in the country, said in an interview the rebellion should have come as no surprise to Johnson.</p> 
<p>“I’ve made it clear where this was all headed,” he said Wednesday. “This was never a secret.”</p> 
<p>But it stunned many who have watched Fitzpatrick maneuver over the past decade, staking out an aisle-crossing persona while also being careful not to impede leadership prerogatives. He voted at several key junctures to advance the GOP’s party-line megabill this year, for instance, while eventually <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/brian-fitzpatrick-trump-megabill-obbba-00439788" target="_blank">voting against its final passage</a>.</p> 
<p>Now he is earning some begrudging praise from Democrats for, they say, finally walking the bipartisan walk instead of just talking the talk.</p> 
<p>“It was politically the smart thing for him to do in such a challenging district, but it also is a courageous thing, and I want to acknowledge that,” said Rep. Greg Stanton (D-Ariz.).</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick’s decision to embrace a discharge petition filed by House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries has infuriated allies of Johnson, however, who argue that he is merely scrambling for political cover after moving too late to prevent a Dec. 31 lapse in the subsidies.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman (R-S.C.), a House Rules Committee member, blasted the “horrible” move from Fitzpatrick and allies and said he would try to kill the effort in the panel.</p> 
<p>“I’ll do everything I can to block it,” he said.</p> 
<p>Wednesday morning’s drama was the culmination of weeks of mostly behind-the-scenes wrangling between a small group of moderate House Republicans and party leaders, who knew that there was a limited appetite in the GOP ranks for any sort of extension for the Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>As co-chair of the centrist Problem Solvers Caucus, Fitzpatrick was at the middle of those contentious dealings as he sought to build support for a two-year extension of the subsidies that would also include new eligibility restrictions and anti-fraud guardrails. But the effort was caught between Democratic leaders who wanted their members to unite behind a straight three-year extension and GOP leaders who wanted none at all.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick last week filed a discharge petition for his two-year proposal, drawing a dozen GOP colleagues but limited buy-in from Democrats. Jeffries wanted his own discharge petition on a three-year bill — which already had 214 Democratic signatures — to remain the most viable option to force a House vote.</p> 
<p>At the same time, Johnson was moving to assemble a much more limited response to the expiring subsidies — a bill that would tinker around the edges of the insurance markets but do nothing to extend the subsidies.</p> 
<p>When a POLITICO reporter informed Fitzpatrick last week that his GOP leadership was working on a health care framework that would not include a subsidy extension, he accused GOP leaders of living in a “fantasyland” and suggested Republicans would be hurting their own constituents for ideological reasons.</p> 
<p>“These are people that we care about — these are our friends and neighbors that are receiving these subsidies,” Fitzpatrick said. “This is a personal thing for me.”</p> 
<p>In the days that followed, a group of moderates that included Fitzpatrick as well as Reps. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.), Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.), Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.), Nick LaLota (R-N.Y.) and others sought to cut a deal that would allow some sort of a House vote on a subsidy extension.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders, Fitzpatrick said, denied their requests to take one of their compromise measures directly to the floor. They were encouraged to file an amendment to the Johnson-backed health bill with the Rules Committee, but making their measures comply with GOP conference requirements became “unnecessarily complicated,” he said, as they forged ahead.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s allies counter that Fitzpatrick and the GOP moderates weren’t completely united and simply couldn’t deliver on the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/fitzpatrick-declines-to-turn-off-aca-discharge-petition-as-amendment-talks-drag-on-00694065" target="_blank">basic criteria</a> Johnson laid out to strike a deal for an amendment. The speaker himself told reporters Tuesday, “I thought there was an agreement on the Fitzpatrick amendment and then they made different decisions.”</p> 
<p>Ultimately, late Tuesday night, the Rules Committee voted to send a bill to the floor with no amendments.</p> 
<p>“So that's what led us to today,” Fitzpatrick said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>There is one silver lining for Johnson: Fitzpatrick went back to playing team ball soon after signing the Democratic discharge petition and voted to send Johnson’s health bill to the floor. He went on to vote to pass it: “I’m not going to vote against something out of spite.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick’s careful political balancing act will get a serious test this year as Democrats redouble their efforts to oust him from his swingy Bucks County district. He won his last race in 2024 by more than a dozen percentage points even as former Vice President Kamala Harris carried his district.</p> 
<p>“I think it demonstrates how much danger they're in politically by siding with the MAGA majority, which was just throwing caution to the winds in terms of people's health care,” said Rep. Jamie Raskin (D-Md.). ”These are the desperate members of the Republican majority who are trying to hang on to their seats, and good for them that they understand what America wants.”</p> 
<p>As Johnson was swarmed by reporters Wednesday morning asking about Fitzpatrick and the discharge petition, he said, “I have not lost control of the House.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick was a close ally of former Speaker Kevin McCarthy and is not seen as being especially close to Johnson. He could engage in additional freelancing in the coming year that would make governing the tiny Republican majority even more difficult for top party leaders.</p> 
<p>In addition to the five discharge petitions he’s already signed this year, he is working with Rep. Gregory Meeks (D-N.Y.) to introduce another, on Russian sanctions.</p> 
<p>“Every time somebody says that's a tool of the minority, I correct them — it's a tool of the rank-and-file,” Fitzpatrick said earlier this month. “To weaken the discharge would be just to empower the [party leaders], and we need more rank-and-file empowerment.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-time NASA nominee confirmed to lead space agency</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/jared-isaacman-nasa-head-00695557</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2e0f-d020-a7ff-2f0f99f10006</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 15:47:41 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate on Wednesday approved Jared Isaacman for the top job at NASA — an unprecedented comeback after President Donald Trump yanked his nomination this spring.</p> 
<p>Senators confirmed the billionaire private astronaut in a 67-30 vote.</p> 
<p>Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/trump-nominates-isaacman-nasa-administrator-00636497" target="_blank">renominated Isaacman</a> for NASA administrator in November, after pulling his original nomination in May. He cited Isaacman’s relationship with SpaceX CEO Elon Musk, with whom Trump had just had a falling out, as the rationale for his decision.</p> 
<p>Isaacman’s surprise rebound followed months of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/22/nasa-issacman-duffy-second-chance-00618595?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nrid=27cbdb93-64bc-42e1-9b60-42d49331f42f" target="_blank">political jockeying</a> and help from high-profile figures in Trump’s orbit.</p> 
<p>Isaacman was the CEO of the payment processing company Shift4, and has done business with Musk. He has pushed back in recent weeks about his ties to Musk, arguing that they aren’t friends and he has no connections to the space company.</p> 
<p>“Every story I see that writes about my nomination refers to the Musk ally or the Musk friend,” Isaacman said at his second confirmation hearing in December. “It's funny that in a world where everybody has a phone with a camera on it, there are no pictures of us at dinner, at a bar, on an airplane or on a yacht, because they don't exist.”</p> 
<p>Isaacman garnered backing from lawmakers during his hearing by confirming his support for NASA’s Artemis moon-landing mission, a key prerogative for Capitol Hill. He also committed to instilling urgency at the space agency, citing China’s space ambitions.</p> 
<p>“This is not the time for delay, but for action,” Isaacman said. “If we fall behind, if we make a mistake, we may never catch up, and the consequences could shift the balance of power here on Earth.</p> 
<p>Senate Commerce committee heads <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175665" data-person-id="175665">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Tx.) and ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51160" data-person-id="51160">Maria Cantwell</a> (D-Wa.), have said they want to see him in the role before the end of the year.</p> 
<p>A permanent head at NASA will come as a relief for the space agency, as it grapples with budget uncertainty and the exodus of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/09/nasa-staff-departures-00444674" target="_blank">thousands of senior employees</a>. Isaacman will also need to solidify plans for numerous high-profile programs, such as plans to land humans on the moon and replace the International Space Station.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartisan group discusses using discharged House bill for compromise health plan</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/problem-solvers-meeting-obamacare-00695105</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2d94-d71a-abff-7fff29ad0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 13:32:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan group of moderate lawmakers privately strategized Wednesday about how to pass an extension of expiring Obamacare subsidies early next year — possibly by using a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_1834" target="_blank">newly discharged House bill</a> as a vehicle for a Senate-backed bipartisan compromise.</p> 
<p>The closed-door discussion among House and Senate members about amending the discharged measure was described by four people who were granted anonymity to comment on the sensitive negotiations. It took place at a Capitol Hill meeting hosted by the bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus, whose members have spent weeks exploring possible compromises to extend the subsidies past Dec. 31.</p> 
<p>The effort hit a wall this week, after talks with Speaker Mike Johnson to get a floor vote on a compromise extension proposal failed. Four of them, including Problem Solvers Co-chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.), broke ranks Wednesday and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688" target="_blank">completed a discharge petition</a> led by Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>.</p> 
<p>Not all members of the Problem Solvers coalition are convinced that amending the Jeffries-backed bill — a straight three-year extension of the enhanced subsidies enacted under former President Joe Biden — would be the most viable proposal.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats privately noted that the three-year extension is already drafted and has support from a majority of House and Senate lawmakers. They also pointed out that other subsidy extension proposals, which include new eligibility limitations and anti-fraud measures, have less support in the House.</p> 
<p>But Republicans involved in the talks argue the three-year extension won’t be able to pass the Senate — it fell short of the necessary 60 votes last week — and are trying to rally support behind a compromise proposal that could pick up additional GOP support. In any case, no action is expected before Congress adjourns for the year.</p> 
<p>"They're going to have to put something on the floor,” Fitzpatrick said of the Senate in an interview. “We're going to send them a vehicle. … I mean, that was the whole point of the meeting with the senators."</p> 
<p>Senators who attended included <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/232351" data-person-id="232351">Maggie Hassan</a> (D-N.H.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> (R-Alaska) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> (R-Ohio). </p> 
<p>Moreno, who has put forward his own compromise proposal with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine), said the group was talking in “good faith” and “working together to get something done.”</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers in the meeting suggested that a deal could encompass more than proposals to extend the enhanced premium tax credits. Republicans have also endorsed ideas to expand tax-advantaged health savings accounts and make it easier for small businesses to create insurance plans.</p> 
<p>“The talks about what we might be able to come together around included other provisions, and I’m not going to get into any of those details,” said Shaheen, one of the lead Senate Democratic negotiators.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cruz seeks fast-track passage of military helicopter safety bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/cruz-aims-to-fast-track-passage-of-rotor-act-00694954</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2d76-dc54-a3df-6d7ec8960000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 12:59:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Commerce Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175665" data-person-id="175665">Ted Cruz</a> (R-Texas) is hoping to quickly pass a bill Wednesday dealing with military helicopter safety. </p> 
<p>According to a person familiar with the negotiations who was granted anonymity to speak candidly, Cruz plans to bring his bipartisan <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2503?q=s+2503" target="_blank">ROTOR Act</a> legislation to the floor via unanimous consent, a fast-track procedure. </p> 
<p>The bill would include a new provision striking a contentious helicopters-related section of the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_1071" target="_blank">National Defense Authorization Act</a>, according to the person.</p> 
<p>Cruz plans to speak around 2 p.m. and seek the unanimous consent agreement, the person said. Cruz’s office has struck an agreement with other senators, including Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a>, to pass the legislation via this fast-track mechanism, said the person, who added that they are making progress with the White House and Pentagon.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Thune didn’t immediately provide comment.</p> 
<p>The Senate cleared the NDAA earlier Wednesday, 77-20. Cruz voted for the bill.</p> 
<p>Cruz's ROTOR Act, which is cosponsored by Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51160" data-person-id="51160">Maria Cantwell</a> of Washington, the committee’s top Democrat, seeks to address a litany of issues raised following January’s midair collision near Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport between a regional jet and an Army Black Hawk helicopter.</p> 
<p>The two lawmakers had raised safety concerns about the NDAA provision, which the nation’s top transportation accident investigator argued would allow certain military helicopters to fly without using an advanced location-broadcasting technology in the Washington area, endangering flyers.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-17T18:58:50-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Jack Smith makes his case against Trump in closed-door deposition</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-deposition-congress-00694730</link>
      <description>The former special counsel said the president is responsible for his own actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2cfe-dc54-a3df-6cfefaff0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 11:10:45 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/43/1e/1f6ecd2a42e29b145902174481b0/u-s-congress-01331.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Department of Justice Special Counsel Jack Smith arrives for a closed deposition before the House Judiciary Committee on Capitol Hill, on Dec. 17, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/43/1e/1f6ecd2a42e29b145902174481b0/u-s-congress-01331.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former special counsel Jack Smith, who led the federal criminal cases against President Donald Trump during the Biden administration, defended his investigations in a closed-door deposition Wednesday with members of the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>His testimony — stretching over eight hours, with breaks — was the culmination of a months-long congressional effort to investigate Smith and compel the former Justice Department official to appear on the Hill. It was also wrought with potential legal risks after Trump has openly and repeatedly called for Smith's prosecution.</p> 
<p>In his opening statement to lawmakers, portions of which were obtained by POLITICO, Smith defended his findings of allegations that Trump mishandled classified documents and sought to overturn the results of the 2020 presidential election.</p> 
<p>“The decision to bring charges against President Trump was mine, but the basis for those charges rests entirely with President Trump and his actions, as alleged in the indictments returned by grand juries in two different districts,” said Smith, according to a copy of portions of that statement.</p> 
<p>He maintained that this team found evidence to prove “beyond a reasonable doubt that President Trump engaged in a criminal scheme to overturn the results of the 2020 presidential election and to prevent the lawful transfer of power.”</p> 
<p>Smith also said his team found "powerful evidence” in the classified documents case and alleged that the president “repeatedly tried to obstruct justice.”</p> 
<p>“I made my decisions in the investigation without regard to President Trump’s political association, activities, beliefs, or candidacy in the 2024 presidential election,” Smith said in his statement. “We took actions based on what the facts and the law required — the very lesson I learned early in my career as a prosecutor.”</p> 
<p>He added that he would have made the same decision if Trump had been a Democrat or a Republican — a nod to the GOP members of the committee who believe Smith was pursuing a partisan witch hunt against the president. Their fury has only intensified in the wake of recent revelations Smith secretly obtained phone records of at least eight Republican senators in his election interference probe.</p> 
<p>Smith also defended that decision to request lawmakers’ phone data, for which Smith’s team did not receive the content of the calls.</p> 
<p>“Exploiting that violence, President Trump and his associates tried to call Members of Congress in furtherance of their criminal scheme, urging them to further delay certification of the 2020 election,” Smith said. “I didn’t choose those Members; President Trump did.”</p> 
<p>Abigail Jackson, a White House spokesperson, in a statement said that “Jack Smith is a lying hack who willingly weaponized the justice system against President Trump to try and benefit his Democrat cronies.” </p> 
<p>In the wake of repeated calls for his prosecution from Republicans and Trump himself, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-congress-investigations-00693884" target="_blank"><u>Smith faces unique political and legal dangers</u></a>. His testimony is hamstrung by grand jury secrecy rules and Justice Department policy — as well as an order from a federal judge in Florida that the second volume of his report surrounding the classified documents case remain under seal.</p> 
<p>Smith, however, defended his record as a career prosecutor from Republican allegations that he shepherded a weaponization of the Justice Department against conservatives — to the extent he could.</p> 
<p>Walking into the deposition room, Smith did not answer shouted questions from reporters.</p> 
<p>“The hunters become the hunted, huh?” someone shouted from the rowdy crowd swarming the former prosecutor.</p> 
<p>Smith is represented by the big law giant Covington &amp; Burling, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/25/donald-trump-jack-smith-covington-lawyers-022770" target="_blank"><u>which was sanctioned</u></a> by the Trump administration earlier this year after revelations that it was providing free legal services to Smith. The move suspended security clearances for lawyers at the firm.</p> 
<p>“In today testifying before this committee, Jack is showing tremendous courage in light of the remarkable and unprecedented retribution campaign against him by this administration and this White House,” one of Smith’s attorneys, Lanny Breuer, told reporters. “Let's be clear: Jack Smith, a career prosecutor, conducted this investigation based on the facts and based on the law and nothing more.”</p> 
<p>Breuer said his client “looks forward” to answering questions surrounding both of the cases he oversaw: the classified documents case and the case surrounding Trump’s efforts to subvert the results of the 2020 election. Smith was forced to drop both cases after Trump’s electoral victory in 2024, citing Justice Department policy against prosecuting a sitting president.</p> 
<p>A number of lawmakers filed into the deposition room Wednesday morning to watch the questioning — among them Reps. Scott Fitzgerald (R-Wis.), Ben Cline (R-Va.), Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) and Hank Johnson (D-Ga.). House Judiciary Committee chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) and ranking member Jamie Raskin (D-Md.) are also attending.</p> 
<p>"Jack Smith has just spent several hours schooling the Judiciary Committee on the professional responsibilities of a prosecutor and the ethical duties of a prosecutor," Raskin told reporters Wednesday afternoon, while declining to provide details on Smith's remarks. </p> 
<p>"He didn't come with any particular message," Raskin continued, "but I'll just say that he's answered every single question to the satisfaction of any reasonable-minded person in that room."</p> 
<p>Smith had been requesting a public forum for his testimony to set the record straight about the scope of his work and the cases he would have pursued against Trump.</p> 
<p>Jordan, however, declined that request, instead opting for a deposition behind closed doors. After the conclusion of the deposition, however, Jordan told reporters that he had not ruled out the possibility of Smith appearing in a public venue.</p> 
<p>Democrats agreed that Smith should be given a chance to speak in an open hearing. Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) noted that previous special counsels have been given their own hearings.</p> 
<p>“We're having a deposition behind closed doors because this chairman, this administration, this president — these Republicans want to hide from the American people the results of this investigation,” she said. “There's also no reason to keep Jack Smith from testifying … to the American people about what was in his investigation and why he came to the conclusions that he did.”</p> 
<p>After the hearing, Breuer told reporters that "[a] person who listened today to the deposition would know without any doubt that Jack Smith's investigation was based purely on the facts and the law and the evidence, nothing more and nothing less."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-17T11:08:24-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Frustrated GOP moderates join Democrats to force Obamacare extension vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2cbf-dc54-a3df-6cff63b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 09:40:32 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Four House Republicans joined Democrats Wednesday to force a House vote on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_1834" target="_blank">straight three-year extension</a> of the enhanced Obamacare tax credits that will expire Dec. 31, delivering a sharp rebuke to Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and other GOP leaders.</p> 
<p>Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick </a>of Pennsylvania, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> of New York, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/478639" data-person-id="478639">Rob Bresnahan</a> of Pennsylvania and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/194184" data-person-id="194184">Ryan Mackenzie</a> of Pennsylvania signed the discharge petition filed by House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries </a>— hours after House GOP leaders rejected attempts by Fitzpatrick and other Republican moderates to seek a floor vote on extending the subsidies used by more than 20 million Americans.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick said in a late-night House Rules Committee meeting Tuesday that "the only thing worse than a clean extension ... would be expiration, and I would make that decision." Lawler added that "the only feasible path forward is a discharge petition" if GOP leader reject a floor vote.</p> 
<p>Under House rules, a completed discharge petition is subject to a waiting period, meaning no vote could happen until next month. Johnson could choose to move sooner, but there are no plans to call up the three-year extension bill early, according to two people granted anonymity to describe internal GOP leadership conversations.</p> 
<p>“We have worked for months to craft a two-party solution to address these expiring healthcare credits," Fitzpatrick said in a statement Wednesday. "Our only request was a Floor vote on this compromise, so that the American People’s voice could be heard on this issue. That request was rejected. ... Unfortunately, it is House leadership themselves that have forced this outcome.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries told reporters Wednesday his discharge petition is "the most straightforward path to ensuring that tens of millions of Americans don't have their health care ripped away from them because of the expiration of the Affordable Care Act tax credits."</p> 
<p>The bill, however, unlikely to advance in the Senate. While four GOP senators voted to advance a three-year extension alongside Democrats last week, the proposal fell short of the necessary 60 votes to proceed. Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> was dismissive when asked Monday if he would take up a similar bill if the House sent one over.</p> 
<p>"If they just did what they did over here, which is a straight-up three-year extension, then no," he said. Asked the same question Wednesday, he said, "We'll cross that bridge when we come to it."</p> 
<p>Even if the Senate does not take up a House-passed extension, it could build pressure on Thune and Johnson to take action on some sort of extension when lawmakers return to Washington next month. Fitzpatrick is hosting some rank-and-file senators who have been exploring a health deal at a Problem Solvers Caucus meeting Wednesday in the Capitol.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Jack Smith jumps into a Judiciary minefield</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/jack-smith-deposition-house-judiciary-testimony-trump-00694588</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2ab2-d716-abfb-fafbce910000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jack Smith wants to make his case against Donald Trump to Congress — but he’s walking into a political and legal minefield.</p> 
<p>The Biden-era special counsel who brought the first and only federal criminal charges ever leveled against a former president is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-congress-investigations-00693884" target="_blank">set to testify Wednesday morning</a> to members of House Judiciary.</p> 
<p>The stakes are high.</p> 
<p>Republicans are looking to portray Smith as a tool of a weaponized Justice Department — an allegation Republicans have brandished amid recent revelations Smith obtained phone records of <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/29/congress/senate-gop-blasts-jack-smith-00629073" target="_blank">at least eight GOP senators</a> as part of his probe into Trump’s efforts to subvert the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>“What they did all along, everything was wrong … a lot of things that were just not normal course of investigation or prosecution,” Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) told POLITICO. “If he comes in and doesn’t answer questions, that’s going to be a problem.”</p> 
<p>Judiciary Republican Troy Nehls of Texas, when asked about his ideal outcome for Smith’s deposition, didn’t hold back.</p> 
<p>“Jack Smith should be in jail — if not prison,” he said. “He’s a crook … and he needs to be held accountable for all his games that he played.”</p> 
<p>Democrats, meanwhile, are eager for more information about the investigations Smith had to abandon after Trump won reelection in 2024, bowing to the fact that sitting presidents cannot face federal charges while in office. Smith was investigating Trump for election subversion attempts and mishandling classified documents.</p> 
<p>“We want to hear exactly what he found, and what he did,” said Jamie Raskin (D-Md.), the top House Judiciary Democrat.</p> 
<p>Peter Koski, a former top DOJ official and a member of Smith’s legal team, said in a statement his client is “looking forward to answering the committee’s questions, sharing the legal basis for his investigative steps, and discussing the evidence of President Trump’s alleged efforts to overturn the 2020 election and his unlawful possession of classified documents at Mar-a-Lago.”</p> 
<p>But Smith is bound by complex secrecy rules that limit what he is able to share with lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Raskin maintains Smith’s task Wednesday is simple: “He just needs to come and tell the truth.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Decision day for health care: </b>The House will vote Wednesday on the GOP health care package without an Affordable Care Act subsidy extension — and without any of the amendments moderates were seeking. Members are set to vote on the rule Wednesday morning, with the final vote on the bill expected Wednesday afternoon (assuming the rule is adopted). </p> 
<p>The Problem Solvers will also huddle with rank-and-file senators Wednesday to discuss a framework that includes an ACA extension and other health policy items for January.</p> 
<p><b>— Carr in the hot seat:</b> FCC Chair Brendan Carr’s appearance before Senate Commerce Wednesday will be a <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/inside-brendan-carrs-tightrope-with-republicans-00693611" target="_blank">telling moment for Republicans</a> as GOP committee members balance concerns over free speech with their reluctance to criticize the administration. </p> 
<p>Commerce Chair Ted Cruz (R-Texas) told reporters Tuesday he plans to use the FCC oversight hearing to explore free speech concerns, though it’s unclear how far most Republicans on the committee will go in relitigating Carr’s threats against TV show host Jimmy Kimmel earlier this year. </p> 
<p><i>Kyle Cheney, Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and John Hendel contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jack Smith wants to tell Congress about his Trump investigations. That comes with risks.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-congress-investigations-00693884</link>
      <description>The House Judiciary Committee will question the former special counsel behind closed doors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2929-d716-abfb-f9eb85840000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/53/30/72e9a6514f3d853a6f5c6f17f001/biden-democracy-analysis-37581.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jacquelyn Martin/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Special counsel Jack Smith arrives to speak about an indictment of Donald Trump, Aug. 1, 2023, at a Department of Justice office in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/53/30/72e9a6514f3d853a6f5c6f17f001/biden-democracy-analysis-37581.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Kyle Cheney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Kyle Cheney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jack Smith wants to make his case against Donald Trump to Congress — but he’s walking into a political and legal minefield.</p> 
<p>The Biden-era special counsel who brought the first and only federal criminal charges ever leveled against a former president is set to testify behind closed doors Wednesday to the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>To do so, he must navigate Byzantine secrecy laws and rules that limit what he can disclose to lawmakers. All the while, Republicans are looking to trip him up and incriminate him, to portray him as a tool of a weaponized Justice Department — an allegation they’ve brandished amid recent revelations that Smith obtained phone records of at least eight GOP senators as part of his probe into Trump’s efforts to subvert the 2020 election results.</p> 
<p>“What they did all along, everything was wrong … a lot of things that were just not normal course of investigation or prosecution,” House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan said in an interview. “If he comes in and doesn’t answer questions, that’s going to be a problem.”</p> 
<p>At the same time, Democrats are eager for further details about the investigations Smith had to abandon after Trump won reelection in 2024, bowing to the reality that sitting presidents cannot face federal charges while in office. Smith was investigating Trump for election subversion attempts and mishandling classified documents.</p> 
<p>“We want to hear exactly what he found, and what he did,” Rep. Jamie Raskin, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, said in an interview. “He just needs to come and tell the truth.”</p> 
<p>It’s all forcing Smith into a delicate, high-stakes dance with members of both parties. Democrats want to exploit any opportunity to discredit Trump, but Republicans are hoping to back Smith into a corner and portray him as a politically motivated activist.</p> 
<p>“Jack Smith should be in jail — if not prison,” said Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Texas), a member of the Judiciary Committee, when asked about his ideal outcome for Smith’s deposition. “He’s a crook. Jack Smith is a crook, and he needs to be held accountable for all his games that he played.”</p> 
<p>Peter Koski, the former deputy chief of the DOJ Public Integrity Section and a member of Smith’s legal team at Covington &amp; Burling, said in a statement Tuesday his client is “looking forward to answering the committee’s questions, sharing the legal basis for his investigative steps, and discussing the evidence of President Trump’s alleged efforts to overturn the 2020 election and his unlawful possession of classified documents at Mar-a-Lago.”</p> 
<p>Ultimately, though, there are restrictions for what Smith can and cannot tell members. He remains bound by grand jury rules that bar prosecutors from disclosing evidence that was never made public, at least without the permission of a court.</p> 
<p>And in his capacity as a former Justice Department employee, he’s also limited in what he can share about his prosecutorial work. DOJ has provided an authorization letter to facilitate Smith’s testimony, according to a person granted anonymity to share details of private correspondence; however, the scope of the waiver is not clear.</p> 
<p>A federal judge in Florida has also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/trump-jack-smith-classified-docs-report-00673178" target="_blank"><u>maintained an 11-month prohibition</u></a> on the release of any details of Smith’s final report in the classified documents probe — a restriction Trump has urged her to maintain indefinitely — further narrowing what Smith is legally permitted to share about that investigation.</p> 
<p>Complicating matters further is that Trump has called repeatedly for Smith’s prosecution, fueling the GOP appetite for incriminating Smith. That’s forcing Smith to weigh potential risks of criminal accusations against his desire to share information about his work with lawmakers.</p> 
<p>Jordan has already sent out a criminal referral for Thomas Windom, a top Smith deputy, after the former senior assistant special counsel repeatedly declined to answer questions during his September deposition before investigators with the Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>“They are trying to get him on the fast road to one of their ridiculous prosecutions,” Raskin said, of Smith.</p> 
<p>House Judiciary Democrats are simultaneously pressing for the public release of Smith’s report detailing the results of his investigation into Trump’s alleged mishandling of classified documents.</p> 
<p>Earlier this month, committee Democrats filed an amicus brief to a federal court in Florida urging Judge Aileen Cannon to allow its release, citing the ongoing panel’s investigations and the need to balance out what is currently a “one-sided public record.”</p> 
<p>“Neither the Committee nor the public can meaningfully evaluate Mr. Smith’s conduct, or assess the Committee’s accusations, without access to the report that memorializes what the Special Counsel actually did and why,” stated the amicus brief, submitted by the Democrats’ lawyers.</p> 
<p>Cannon, a Trump appointee who once ruled Smith was put into the special counsel role unconstitutionally, has so far maintained that the report will not be released. This decision could further complicate Smith’s testimony before Congressional investigators, adding limitations to what he can share.</p> 
<p>“Every other special counsel committee report has been released, and I believe every other special counsel or independent counsel has appeared before Congress publicly,” Raskin said, “so our Republican colleagues seem to fear the strength of Jack Smith's advocacy and presentation.”</p> 
<p>Jordan said he intends to ask Smith about the classified documents case, including the FBI’s search of Trump’s Mar-a-Lago home in 2022. He also wants Smith to answer for DOJ’s efforts to obtain phone data from former Speaker Kevin McCarthy as part of his probe.</p> 
<p>Smith preferred that all this take place in a public setting, with his legal team pressing Congressional Republicans hard to let the testimony proceed in an open hearing. Jordan declined that request. The GOP-led Senate Judiciary Committee, in contrast, has expressed an openness to facilitating such a hearing as it pursues its own Smith investigation, and Sen. Ron Johnson (R-Wis.) said he believed the House deposition will lay the groundwork for the Senate’s questioning.</p> 
<p>"Before you interview somebody, before you hold a hearing — you need information, otherwise they run circles around you. You get nothing fruitful out of them," said Johnson, who is co-leading the Senate's probe into Smith's investigations in his role as chair of the Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations.</p> 
<p>Johnson said he expected Jordan would eventually produce a transcript of Smith’s House deposition. “Those would be the documents we’ll use when we interview him,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fitzpatrick declines to turn off ACA discharge petition as amendment talks drag on</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/fitzpatrick-declines-to-turn-off-aca-discharge-petition-as-amendment-talks-drag-on-00694065</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2985-dffa-a7db-6fb7861d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 18:36:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Vulnerable Republican Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick told Speaker Mike Johnson on the House floor Tuesday he would not withdraw his <a href="https://clerk.house.gov/DischargePetition/2025121012?Page=2" target="_blank">discharge petition</a> that would force a floor vote on <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_3001" target="_blank">extending expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies</a> — amid Johnson’s attempt to find a potential agreement to allow a vote on an amendment instead that would be similar in substance.</p> 
<p>The standoff, described by three people granted anonymity to divulge private conversations, shows the pressure GOP leadership is under to defuse a politically challenging dynamic around the future of the enhanced Obamacare subsidies that have divided Johnson’s conference.</p> 
<p>At the same time, the speaker’s allies argue it shows that the GOP moderates themselves are still refusing to reach a deal ahead of a Wednesday vote on a health care bill Republicans want to pass to show they are serious about preventing a looming spike in insurance premiums.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and Rep. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.), in private conversations with Johnson and other Republicans, have both so far declined to turn off their respective discharge petitions in the absence of an agreement they can vote on this week alongside the GOP health care bill.</p> 
<p>Johnson in recent days told GOP moderates who want a vote on an ACA subsidies extension he would agree to such a vote if they in turn agreed to turn off their various discharge petitions and make sure the amendment was paid for with a satisfactory offset. Johnson also wanted to use Fitzpatrick’s two-year ACA extension bill as the base for a compromise amendment, according to two people with direct knowledge of the matter. But those talks never produced a deal.</p> 
<p>The speaker told reporters after talking to Fitzpatrick Tuesday afternoon that they're still “working” on various ACA amendment options. But, he said, “I thought there was an agreement on the Fitzpatrick amendment and then they made different decisions.” </p> 
<p>The speaker added later he thought “there’s a real possibility they get a vote on it” and noted he “certainly tried my best to provide for that.”</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.) huddled with Johnson on the floor Tuesday evening, along with Kiggans and a larger group of moderates and Johnson’s top floor and policy staff, but the group still disbanded without an agreement, according to two people involved in the conversation.</p> 
<p>The House Rules Committee, meanwhile, is meeting to pave the way for floor consideration of the narrow health package endorsed by House Republican leaders, as centrists have submitted more than five proposed amendments to either extend the subsidies or provide new tax deductions for health insurance premiums.</p> 
<p>If no ACA extension amendment makes it to the floor Wednesday, there are several House Republicans who are considering signing onto Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries three-year clean extension of the ACA subsidies he is also pushing through a discharge petition, according to three people granted anonymity to share their direct knowledge of the matter.</p> 
<p>Fitzpatrick and his bipartisan Problem Solvers Caucus will also meet with a bipartisan group of rank and file senators Wednesday to discuss a possible framework they could agree on for a health care deal.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP pushes major permitting bill through key vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/hardline-republicans-arrest-the-speed-act-00693199</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-290a-dffa-a7db-6f3b96800006</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 16:22:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans succeeded Tuesday in advancing a bipartisan bill aimed at speeding up the federal permitting process, fending off a late challenge from hard-liners who wanted more power to kill offshore wind projects.</p> 
<p>The House adopted the rule governing floor debate on several bills in a 215-209 vote. Among those bills that will now be considered on the chamber floor later this week is the so-called SPEED Act, which would overhaul the National Environmental Policy Act to remove regulatory roadblocks around building and completing energy projects.</p> 
<p>But in order to secure the support of holdouts — led by GOP Reps. Andy Harris of Maryland and Jeff Van Drew of New Jersey — Republican leaders will have to alter a provision of the bipartisan legislation in the Rules Committee to ensure the Trump administration can continue to block offshore wind developments in these two states specifically.</p> 
<p>This adjustment will be made as part of a separate rule paving the way for floor consideration of a health care package the Rules Committee is debating Tuesday afternoon and that the full House is expected to vote on Wednesday.</p> 
<p>A floor vote on the SPEED Act, with the new change, is still on track for Thursday. Van Drew said it would include “really important language so we can go back and show these wind projects were rushed through and that the permitting wasn’t proper.”</p> 
<p>Natural Resources Chair Bruce Westerman had included the original provision in the SPEED Act during the panel markup that would make it harder for presidents to cancel permits for any energy project. <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/11/natural-resources-committee-approves-measure-to-stop-executive-branch-revoking-energy-permits-00662581" target="_blank">It was added</a> to address concerns from Democrats that President Donald Trump was prepared to attack wind and solar projects — and assuage anxieties across all energy industries that their project approvals could get arbitrarily yanked depending on the party in power.</p> 
<p>But Harris, Van Drew and others argued the provision would <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/conservative-lawmakers-warn-trump-against-gop-led-nepa-overhaul-00684686" target="_blank">undermine Trump’s anti-offshore wind agenda</a>, with which the two Republicans align.</p> 
<p>Alongside Van Drew and Harris, the rule initially had GOP defections from Reps. Scott Perry of Pennsylvania, Chris Smith of New Jersey, Tim Burchett of Tennessee and Anna Paulina Luna of Florida. Leaders were able to flip all the “no” votes with the exceptions of Luna and Smith.</p> 
<p>Other Republicans, including Reps. Chip Roy of Texas, Kat Cammack of Florida, Andrew Clyde of Georgia and Andy Biggs of Arizona initially withheld their votes.</p> 
<p>Most of these members were seen huddling in long conversations on the House floor with Speaker Mike Johnson, Majority Leader Steve Scalise and Majority Whip Tom Emmer.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson confronted by GOP moderates over Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-johnson-confronted-gop-moderates-00693242</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2882-da7a-a9bf-bcd373cc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 13:54:48 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A group of vulnerable House Republicans confronted Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> inside a closed-door meeting Tuesday about expiring Obamacare health insurance subsidies — and Johnson’s refusal to allow a vote on extending them.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) could be heard yelling outside the room where the centrist Republican Governance Group was meeting with Johnson in attendance, sounding off about GOP leaders’ opposition to a vote this week and mocking the assurance from some that Republicans could work on a party-line health care bill next year.</p> 
<p>Lawler — who earlier in the day <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-lawler-obamacare-lapse-00692577" target="_blank">publicly accused GOP leaders</a> of “political malpractice” — shot back that Republicans would “never” get a second reconciliation bill passed, despite the wishful thinking.</p> 
<p>A stern Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/348387" data-person-id="348387">Jen Kiggans</a> (R-Va.) also pressed Johnson, according to three people in the room granted anonymity to describe the private meeting, asking why he and other leaders didn’t act sooner on the expiring subsides and health care generally.</p> 
<p>The venting session was a remarkable climax to a monthslong debate within the GOP over how to address spiking insurance premiums for millions of Americans starting next year. In the view of many GOP moderates, the Obamacare subsidies are poised to lapse without any comprehensive plan over how to manage the inevitable political fallout ahead of the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>The moderates are nonetheless making some last-minute moves to try to force the issue.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) <a href="https://amendments-rules.house.gov/amendments/FITZBR_092_xml251216113645604.pdf" target="_blank">submitted an amendment</a> Tuesday to a narrow GOP health package set to hit the House floor this week that would extend the expiring tax credits for two years with anti-fraud and income eligibility restrictions. Kiggans is also expected to file an amendment that would extend the subsidies while cracking down on fraud, and there are efforts to craft a third amendment that Johnson told reporters might be amendable to a wider group of Republicans.</p> 
<p>As Johnson left the meeting with the moderates, he brushed off the intraparty barbs, saying they were “trying to solve the equation” for everyone and the group had some ideas worth considering.</p> 
<p>House Democrats are championing an alternative — a straight three-year extension of the expiring subsidies — and are urging a handful of Republicans to join a discharge petition that would force a floor vote on it.</p> 
<p>The GOP moderates have previously rejected the Democrats’ proposal, arguing the subsidies need new guardrails. But Lawler said Tuesday morning, “All options are on the table,” while Fitzpatrick said after the Tuesday meeting, “Ask me after today.”</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misstated the day of the Republican Governance Group. It was on Tuesday.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House permitting vote at risk over offshore wind backlash</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/house-permitting-rule-vote-00692850</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2837-dffa-a7db-6f378ca10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 12:33:19 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An intraparty war over the House GOP’s flagship legislation to speed up the federal permitting process for energy projects is threatening to freeze the chamber’s floor before lawmakers leave for the holidays.</p> 
<p>Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151768" data-person-id="151768">Andy Harris</a> (R-Md.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew </a>(R-N.J.) said in interviews that they plan to vote against the procedural measure setting up debate on the bipartisan <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_4776" target="_blank">SPEED Act</a> and believe they have enough allied Republicans to kill it. The two lawmakers are among those arguing that language in the bill making it harder for presidents to cancel permits would <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/conservative-lawmakers-warn-trump-against-gop-led-nepa-overhaul-00684686" target="_blank">undermine Donald Trump’s assault on offshore wind</a>.</p> 
<p>Despite the threat, GOP leaders are moving forward with the rule vote as they track a handful of Republican holdouts, according to four people granted anonymity to describe internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>’s leadership circle privately acknowledges that success on the procedural vote will likely depend on attendance and a final push to convince Republicans to support the measure.</p> 
<p>Republicans cannot afford even modest defections given their razor-thin majority, since the minority party rarely votes with the majority on rule votes.</p> 
<p>“We’ll see — it always depends on attendance,” said Natural Resources Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189075" data-person-id="189075">Bruce Westerman</a> (R-Ark.), the architect of the SPEED Act, in a Tuesday interview. “I still have faith we can get somewhere because this is so important to the country in so many ways. I am not going to give up on it.”</p> 
<p>Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said Tuesday he’s “talked to those members” threatening to oppose the rule and told them “this is just the first step” to enact permitting reform as House and Senate leaders negotiate a broader package.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/republicans-make-concessions-to-conservatives-on-permitting-bill-00692343" target="_blank">already made some concessions to hard-liners</a>, with the House Rules Committee agreeing Monday to allow votes on amendments they demanded — including one stripping the contentious offshore wind language from the bill.</p> 
<p>Westerman said Tuesday he would plan to oppose that amendment if the rule is adopted and the bill moves to the floor.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-16T11:24:33-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘Absolute bulls--t’: Endangered House Republican blasts leaders over impending Obamacare lapse</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/mike-lawler-obamacare-lapse-00692577</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-27c0-d653-afff-67c009d90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 10:22:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An infuriated Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> left a closed-door House Republican meeting Tuesday and sounded off on GOP leaders who are planning to allow key Obamacare subsidies to expire in two weeks.</p> 
<p>"This is absolute bullshit," the New York Republican said.</p> 
<p>“I think it's idiotic not to have an up-or-down vote on this issue,” he told reporters of leaders’ refusal to hold a vote on a modified version of the expiring subsidies. “It is political malpractice.”</p> 
<p>Lawler also laid into House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>, arguing that Democrats don’t actually want to compromise on the issue and instead want to use health care as a political cudgel against the GOP in the midterms.</p> 
<p>“They want to kill it. They want the issue,” said Lawler. “That's why [Minority Leader] <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> put a nonsensical three-year vote on the floor of the Senate when given an opportunity.”</p> 
<p>At the same time, Lawler did not rule out joining a Democratic-led discharge petition that would force a vote on a three-year extension to send a message to GOP leaders.</p> 
<p>“All options are on the table,” he said.</p> 
<p>Lawler’s outburst came after Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> told his members in the closed-door meeting that he’s moving forward with a Wednesday vote on a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/whats-in-the-gop-health-bill-00689950" target="_blank">GOP health care bill</a> that would not extend the expiring Obamacare subsidies, according to four people in the room who were granted anonymity to describe the closed-door comments.</p> 
<p>Lawler stood up in the meeting, two of the people said, to call Republican leaders' decision to allow the expiration “a mistake.”</p> 
<p>Johnson pushed back on the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/house-gop-moderates-signal-theyll-fall-in-line-with-johnsons-health-plan-00692138" target="_blank">criticism from Lawler and allies</a> such as Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> (R-Pa.) at a Tuesday news conference. </p> 
<p>"Fitzpatrick and Lawler and the others are fighting tooth-an-nail for their constituents — I understand that as well as anyone, because I'm the one in their districts campaigning with them," Johnson told reporters, adding that "the solution that is being sought by Democrats would further harm the system."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Parallel pushes for an 11th-hour health deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/16/congress/health-care-deal-moderates-obamacare-subsidies-00692374</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-259b-da9a-a7db-3dbf9bec0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rank-and-file dealmakers in both chambers are making last-ditch attempts to extend key Obamacare subsidies this week, even as it becomes crystal clear the subsidies will expire first.</p> 
<p>House GOP moderates are hashing out what sort of extension to offer as an amendment at Tuesday afternoon’s Rules meeting — even as they signal they will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/house-gop-moderates-signal-theyll-fall-in-line-with-johnsons-health-plan-00692138" target="_blank">fall in line</a> with Speaker Mike Johnson’s health care plan whether they get a vote or not. A bipartisan Senate group is working simultaneously toward an extension framework that they hope to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/15/congress/senators-obamacare-extension-talks-00692316" target="_blank">announce by the end of the week</a>, while acknowledging it won’t get a vote till next year.</p> 
<p>Here’s where the mod movement in each chamber stands.</p> 
<p><b>— In the House: </b>Majority Leader Steve Scalise said Monday night there’s no “final decision” on putting a subsidy extension amendment on the floor. Tuesday morning’s GOP Conference meeting could get heated as frustrated moderates — who call a subsidy extension omission “a huge mistake” — make their last plea for a vote.</p> 
<p>But they face a huge obstacle at the 2 p.m. Rules meeting Tuesday, where Rep. Brian Fitzpatrick (R-Pa.) and other moderates are unlikely to get a warm welcome from the panel’s conservative hard-liners, who are firmly against extending Obamacare in any form.</p> 
<p>The moderates could pull a page out of the Freedom Caucus playbook and threaten to tank the rule or the underlying bill in return, but that does not appear to be in the cards: “I wouldn’t vote against it in protest,” Fitzpatrick said.</p> 
<p><b>— In the Senate:&nbsp;</b>Meanwhile, nearly two dozen senators convened by Sens. Susan Collins (R-Maine) and Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) discussed issuing a roadmap this week toward a bipartisan deal.</p> 
<p>The rough framework under discussion would pair a two-year subsidy extension with a new income eligibility cap and fraud prevention language. A potential extension of open enrollment for Obamacare exchanges and possible restrictions on abortion funding also remain under consideration.</p> 
<p>That’s similar to Fitzpatrick’s proposal in the House, but the two efforts so far are entirely parallel. There is some hope they might eventually converge: Rank-and-file senators are invited to join a Problem Solvers Caucus meeting Fitzpatrick is hosting Wednesday to discuss a joint effort.</p> 
<p>But this much is clear: The Dec. 31 deadline for the subsidies is certain to come and go.</p> 
<p>“The calendar precludes getting something done this week,” Sen. Bill Cassidy (R-La.) told reporters. “But, still, a commitment to work together is a lot of progress.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Boat strikes oversight:</b> The Pentagon will make video of the Sept. 2 strikes on an alleged drug boat leaving Venezuela available to all members of the House and Senate Armed Services committees later this week, a White House official said. It’s only been shown thus far to the Gang of Eight leaders as well as top members of the Armed Services and Defense Appropriations panels.</p> 
<p><b>— Approps movement in the Senate: </b>Senate Republicans are getting close to reaching agreement within their own ranks to move a five-bill spending package before they leave for the holiday recess. Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.) said that he and Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah) are in discussions with GOP leaders to get a vote stripping earmarks out of the package and potentially also an amendment related to balancing the budget.</p> 
<p><b>— SPEED Act speeds through: </b>The House GOP’s flagship legislation to speed up federal permitting for energy projects is on track for the chamber floor after House Rules agreed to allow amendment votes demanded by conservative hard-liners — including three from foes of offshore wind, who had otherwise threatened to oppose the measure. One of those amendments would strip language that would limit the president's power to revoke approved permits for energy projects.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Jennifer Scholtes and Josh Siegel contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
