<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:33:48 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T21:33:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Ilhan Omar sprayed with liquid at Minneapolis town hall</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540</link>
      <description>The attack on the progressive lawmaker briefly interrupted her remarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0258-d1ea-a5de-32dc80180000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:29:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/2b/64/9fac20b44870aed536fea3bfcd0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2257991042">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Octavio Jones/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Ilhan Omar reacts after being sprayed with an unknown substance by a man as she hosted a town hall in Minneapolis, Minnesota, on Jan. 27.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2b/64/9fac20b44870aed536fea3bfcd0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2257991042" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Minnesota Rep. Ilhan Omar was attacked by a man who sprayed a liquid while lunging at her before being detained at a town hall in Minneapolis on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Omar was speaking to constituents in her district, which includes much of Minneapolis, about the turmoil in the city in the wake of federal immigration agents shooting Alex Pretti, the second U.S. citizen killed by federal agents in the city in less than a month.</p> 
<p>As she spoke, a man charged at Omar and sprayed her with an unknown substance before being detained by security. She did not appear to be injured and, after a pause, continued the town hall despite a security officer’s advice to halt the event, asking him to “please not let them have the show.”</p> 
<p>“Here’s the reality that people like this ugly man don’t understand,” Omar said. “We are Minnesota strong and we will stay resilient in the face of whatever they might throw at us.”</p> 
<p>The lawmaker's office later said <a href="https://x.com/ilhan/status/2016334654949777714?s=46" target="_blank">on social media</a> that the man who threw the liquid is in custody. "The Congresswoman is okay," it said. "She continued with her town hall because she doesn’t let bullies win.” </p> 
<p>Omar has been the subject of frequent rhetorical attacks from Republicans, including President Donald Trump, who have sought to tie the lawmaker to investigations into public benefits fraud linked with Minnesota’s Somali community. On Tuesday, Trump said the Department of Justice is investigating her personal finances while suggesting she illegally profited from her service in Congress.</p> 
<p>The incident heightens the tensions in Minneapolis, where anti-Trump protests continue to embroil the city in response to a surge of federal immigration enforcement. Two Minneapolis residents, Pretti and Renee Good, were killed by immigration officers, sparking further backlash to the Trump administration’s immigration policies from protesters around the city.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The DHS crisis is squeezing Susan Collins</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/susan-collins-dhs-ice-shutdown-00751545</link>
      <description>The Maine Republican is under immense pressure as a huge funding package hangs by a thread and federal agents swarm her state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0268-dabb-ad9c-3fed275e0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:24:04 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fc/66/b90a782b4c13ad7fd81507163c69/2026-0127-congress-francis-44-2-50610.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) is seen at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 27, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fc/66/b90a782b4c13ad7fd81507163c69/2026-0127-congress-francis-44-2-50610.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> is stuck in the middle of an ICE storm.</p> 
<p>The Maine Republican and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/16/susan-collins-reelection-appropriations-00455206" target="_blank">Senate Appropriations Committee chair</a> is working overtime to salvage a package of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">six funding bills hanging by a thread</a> after the Saturday killing of a Minnesota man by federal agents. The scramble follows months of work to put the appropriations process back on track in the wake of a record government shutdown.</p> 
<p>How Collins navigates the fight will have reverberations far beyond whether or not Congress manages to avoid falling over the shutdown cliff for the second time in four months. The 73-year-old — who intends to seek a sixth term this November — is already under a microscope from Democrats back home after the Trump administration launched an immigration enforcement operation in her state.</p> 
<p>Collins, who said earlier this month she didn’t “see the rationale for a large number of ICE agents” in Maine, spoke with Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem on Monday, later telling reporters Tuesday <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/susan-collins-speaks-with-noem-about-immigration-enforcement-00747915" target="_blank">she urged Noem</a> to pause “this surge of enforcement” in Minnesota and Maine “until we can get far better focus.”</p> 
<p>On Capitol Hill, she’s part of a group of senators who are trying to defuse the shutdown fight, including by exploring actions President Donald Trump could have his agencies take without needing to strip DHS funding out of the pending spending package as Democrats are demanding.</p> 
<p>“We are having conversations with all the parties,” Collins said in an interview Tuesday, referring to the White House and Democrats.</p> 
<p>As to whether or not a shutdown is inevitable, she separately told reporters “it depends on whether people look at the consequences.”</p> 
<p>She pointed to Trump’s decision to send <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis</a> as a sign that the administration is willing to make policy changes in the wake of Saturday’s shooting. But just sending in Homan won’t be enough to appease Democrats.</p> 
<p>Republicans, including Collins, are loath to do that because any changes to the six-bill package would virtually guarantee a partial shutdown starting 12:01 a.m. Saturday. The House would need to approve any changes to the package, and the chamber is in recess until Monday.</p> 
<p>Republican leaders are also wary of an internal backlash to any revised bill, with the ultra-conservative Freedom Caucus warning Monday that they would oppose any measure that did not include money for DHS.</p> 
<p>Democrats say the deployment of DHS agents in Collins’ home state is justification enough for pulling apart the funding package she’s trying to salvage this week.</p> 
<p>“All you have to do is look at what's happening in Minnesota, look at what's happening in Maine,” Maryland Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51658" data-person-id="51658">Chris Van Hollen</a>, a senior Democratic appropriator, told reporters. “And I think that this is why everyone's got to vote to rein in Trump's ICE operation.”</p> 
<p>Collins acknowledged on the Senate floor Monday that the killing of Alex Pretti in Minnesota Saturday refocused attention on Homeland Security funding and whether more guardrails are needed for the immigration agencies under its purview.</p> 
<p>“I recognize that and share the concerns,” she said.</p> 
<p>But she noted that the funding package includes “many safeguards” on DHS funding and that the majority of the department’s budget covers work unrelated to immigration enforcement, including TSA, the Coast Guard and FEMA.</p> 
<p>The political backdrop could hardly be more fraught for Collins. She was already dealing with a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/09/susan-collins-trump-reelection-00719283" target="_blank">complicated relationship with Trump</a>, with the president attacking her and several other GOP senators just this month for supporting an effort to rein in military action in Venezuela. They “should never be elected to office again,” Trump announced — with Collins the only in-cycle Republican among those targeted.</p> 
<p>Collins also voted against the Trump-backed “Big, Beautiful Bill” last year and a separate $9 billion funding clawback pushed by the White House. Still, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and other GOP colleagues have publicly defended Collins as essential to keeping the Maine seat in Republican hands.</p> 
<p>But her well-documented willingness to break from her party has done little to stop Democrats back home from linking her to Trump’s immigration enforcement policies. The Maine Democratic Party <a href="https://www.mainedems.org/media/susan-collins-slammed-refusing-hold-trump-accountable-ice" target="_blank">accused Collins</a> of “choosing Donald Trump over the people of Maine” and “<a href="https://www.mainedems.org/media/collins-call-out-collins-pushing-bill-fund-ice-no-reforms-or-accountability" target="_blank">leading the charge</a> to pass more funding for ICE.”</p> 
<p>One of her aspiring Democratic challengers, Gov. Janet Mills, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/janet-mills-ice-raids-state-address-00751216" target="_blank">leaned into the immigration fight</a> during her State of the State speech Tuesday night — the latest indication of how it is potentially reorienting midterm politics.</p> 
<p>“Tonight, I say to the people of Maine: We will not be intimidated. We will not be silenced,” Mills said.</p> 
<p>Back in Washington, Collins is speaking with Democrats on the Appropriations Committee and members of the Trump administration, as well as fellow Republicans including Thune and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a>, the top Homeland Security appropriator.</p> 
<p>Whether Collins can hold the funding package together and avoid a partial shutdown, most Hill Republicans believe, will ultimately come down to what Trump and congressional Democrats can agree to.</p> 
<p>Thune cited “good conversations” involving Collins and Britt, before adding: “The other thing too is making sure that they’re engaged in the White House.”</p> 
<p>Democrats believe Republicans are open to immigration enforcement changes — and are speaking out about Saturday’s shooting — in large part because of the potential electoral ramifications coming in November.</p> 
<p>Oregon Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66836" data-person-id="66836">Jeff Merkley</a>, another Democratic appropriator, said Republicans are only concerned about the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement actions “in the context of elections right now.”</p> 
<p>“So they talk about Maine — there's a reason that there's extra attention to Maine,” Merkley said in an interview. “I'd like to see some actual principles exhorted by the Republican leadership in both houses — to stand up.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alex Pretti was shot by 2 CBP agents, not just 1, report finds</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/pretti-shot-by-two-cbp-agents-00751207</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01f7-d9a8-a7be-87f78d8a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:34:43 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Authorities believe two federal officers fired their weapons in the shooting that killed Alex Pretti as he was wrestled to the ground in Minneapolis, according to a preliminary Homeland Security report to Congress.</p> 
<p>The report obtained by POLITICO provides the government’s most detailed account yet of the killing of the 37-year-old Pretti, whose death has sparked widespread outrage and prompted the government to modify its immigration enforcement campaign in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>U.S. Customs and Border Protection’s Office of Professional Responsibility said in the report that two of its officers fired after another officer on the scene yelled “He’s got a gun” while restraining Pretti on the snowy street.</p> 
<p>Video from bystanders showed officers had already taken the gun from Pretti, an ICU nurse with a permit to carry a concealed weapon, when he was shot. He appeared to be attempting to intercede in a confrontation between agents and a woman who was protesting immigration operations when the officers grabbed him and forced him to the ground.</p> 
<p>The new details come as the Trump administration scrambles to respond to intense blowback over the killings of Pretti and Renee Good, a Minneapolis woman who was killed by a federal immigration officer earlier in January. Some Republican lawmakers have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/john-thune-kristi-noem-minnesota-00750451" target="_blank">declined to offer their support</a> for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem’s handling of the shootings.</p> 
<p>Earlier on Tuesday, President Donald Trump suggested Pretti shouldn’t have been armed when confronting immigration agents. Other administration officials have indicated that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/trump-pretti-shouldnt-have-been-carrying-a-gun-00750241" target="_blank">Pretti risked provoking the officers</a> by carrying a weapon.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tillis, Murkowski say Noem should be fired</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/thom-tillis-kristi-noem-fired-00750580</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01bd-d9a8-a7be-87bfe06d0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:16:44 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican Sens. Thom Tillis and Lisa Murkowski said Tuesday that Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem should be fired given her response to the killing of a 37-year-old Minneapolis man by DHS agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>Tillis, of North Carolina, said Noem should be "out of a job." Murkowski, of Alaska, said separately that "she should go."</p> 
<p>“I think what she’s done in Minnesota should be disqualifying,” Tillis told reporters. “It’s just amateurish. It’s terrible. It’s making the president look bad.”</p> 
<p>Tillis and Murkowski are the first two Republican lawmakers to say outright that Noem should lose her Cabinet job. Trump is facing intense pressure to fire Noem in the wake of Saturday’s shooting, as well as calls from Democrats for her to be impeached.</p> 
<p>In addition to Noem, Tillis faulted deputy White House chief of staff Stephen Miller for castigating victim Alex Pretti in the immediate aftermath of his shooting: “Those two people told the president before they even had any incident report whatsoever that the person who died was a terrorist. I mean that is amateur hour at its worst.”</p> 
<p>Tillis also signaled he is open to operational changes at DHS in the wake of the shooting, including requiring an independent investigation. And he said he would be OK with a Democratic demand to split off DHS funding from a six-bill package up for debate in the Senate this week, with a stopgap measure in place while funding for the department is renegotiated. </p> 
<p>“I wouldn’t have a problem with its absence,” Tillis said about the DHS bill.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Thune declines chance to back Noem after Minnesota killing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/john-thune-kristi-noem-minnesota-00750451</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-019c-dabb-ad9c-3ffde9330000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:40:47 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> declined to say Tuesday whether he had confidence in Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem as President Donald Trump faces calls to fire her and Democrats push for her impeachment.</p> 
<p>“That's the president's judgment call,” Thune told reporters when asked about Noem, a fellow South Dakota native who previously served with him in the state’s congressional delegation.</p> 
<p>Noem has been at the center of intense scrutiny over the administration’s immigration enforcement tactics after federal agents killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti during a street skirmish on Minneapolis Saturday. Trump said Tuesday he was standing by the embattled secretary.</p> 
<p>While Thune’s comments fell well short of an endorsement of Noem’s performance, he has similarly withheld comment on other embattled Trump officials in recent months, including Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth in December.</p> 
<p>Thune said Tuesday he backs an impartial investigation of the Pretti killing, including probes by state and local officials, as well as a federal investigation outside of DHS.</p> 
<p>“Clearly, there a lot of questions that have to be answered,” he said, adding that investigations are “necessary … any time there's a shooting like that and lives lost.”</p> 
<p>He doubled down on praise for Trump’s decision to send White House border czar Tom Homan to Minnesota to oversee immigration enforcement operations there, calling him “an experienced pro” and calling the moment an “opportunity to evaluate and to really assess the policies and the procedure.”</p> 
<p>Thune’s GOP counterpart across the Capitol, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, has been silent since the shooting, with the House out of session for a one-week break.</p> 
<p>The fallout from Pretti’s killing has upended the Senate’s plan to pass a six-bill spending package by the Friday midnight deadline to avoid a partial government shutdown. Democrats want DHS funding stripped out of the bill and renegotiated, but Republicans are hoping that they can appease Democrats with other actions.</p> 
<p>Thune said Democrats should make their policy demands “clear and known and see to what degree the administration will be able to address that,” adding that he “would prefer that there be a way that we keep the package together.”</p> 
<p>If Democrats block the six-bill package, as they have vowed to do, Thune said the Senate would move to “Plan B,” which is “to be determined.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Henry Cuellar warns against shutdown, handing DHS ‘blank check’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/cuellar-dhs-blank-check-00749995</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0125-d1ea-a5de-31a5a4f50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:30:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a>, who helped craft and backed the Homeland Security funding bill now fueling a standoff in the Senate, said in an interview Tuesday that he supports putting more guardrails on federal immigration enforcement agencies but urged senators to pass the legislation the House approved last week.</p> 
<p>The partial government shutdown senators are barreling toward after Saturday’s DHS-involved killing of a Minneapolis man, he warned, would be “the worst situation,” leaving the controversial agencies operating with “a blank check.”</p> 
<p>“If you have a government shutdown, what really happens? ICE got $75 billion in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/26/trump-megabills-name-not-good-for-explaining-what-it-does-00527379" target="_blank">big-beautiful-slash-ugly bill</a>. [But] you shut down FEMA, you shut down TSA, you shut down the Coast Guard, you shut down CISA,” the moderate Texas lawmaker said. “I don't think that's a good alternative.”</p> 
<p>Cuellar, the ranking Democrat on the Homeland Security Appropriations Subcommittee, said he supports many strictures that got left on the cutting room floor in the House, including banning agents from wearing masks and requiring identification, codifying parts of the agency’s use of force policy and notifying Congress about large surges in ICE activity.</p> 
<p>But he suggested those could be revisited in the next yearly funding cycle if Democrats are unable to secure commitments from Republicans before the shutdown deadline. And he said there are steps the Trump administration could take now to defuse tensions, such as increasing training and enforcing ICE’s internal use-of-force policy.</p> 
<p>“I sense an opening where I think we can get more Republicans to work with us,” Cuellar said.</p> 
<p>Amid <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707'" target="_blank">bipartisan backlash</a> to Alex Pretti’s killing, Senate Democrats are seeking to strip the DHS funding bill from a larger six-bill appropriations package and renegotiate it. They’re seeking a raft of new provisions, including requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, mandating federal agents identify themselves and compelling DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations.</p> 
<p>But Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">scrambling to avoid making changes</a> to the massive bill as the Friday midnight deadline for a partial government shutdown approaches. With the House out till next week, passing the funding package intact is the only viable path to avoiding a shutdown.</p> 
<p>Cuellar joined his fellow Democrats and many Republicans in calling for independent investigations into the shootings of both Pretti and Renee Good, who was also killed in a confrontation with a DHS officer. And he didn’t rule out joining House Democrats’ push to impeach DHS Secretary Kristi Noem if President Donald Trump doesn’t fire her first.</p> 
<p>“I’ll wait until a later time” to weigh in, Cuellar said. “But I’m certainly looking at everything that’s going on, and [Trump and his team] definitely need to change course on it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ICE, Border Patrol leaders to testify in House, Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/ice-border-officials-hearing-00749840</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00f3-d1ea-a5de-30f760b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:53:36 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Top officials from ICE and U.S. Customs and Border Protection will testify before the House and Senate Homeland Security committees next month, as lawmakers ramp up scrutiny of the Trump administration's immigration crackdown after the killing of Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p>ICE acting director Todd Lyons, Customs and Border Protection Commissioner Rodney Scott and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services Director Joseph Edlow have agreed to appear in the House on Feb. 10 and in the Senate on Feb. 12.</p> 
<p>House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) and Senate Homeland Security Chair Rand Paul (R-Ky.) called for the oversight hearings after federal agents shot and killed Pretti in Minneapolis Saturday.</p> 
<p>“Transparency and communication are needed to turn the temperature down,” Garbarino said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem, who has overseen the Minneapolis operation, isn't set to testify on Capitol Hill until March 3. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freedom Caucus pushes to fund DHS amid funding fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/freedom-caucus-dhs-ultimatum-00749816</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00f3-d1ea-a5de-30f774530000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:36:10 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Freedom Caucus leaders are warning they will oppose a proposal favored by Senate Democrats to send an amended spending package back across the Capitol without Department of Homeland Security funding.</p> 
<p>The ultimatum from the hard-right group comes as top leaders try to find a way to avoid a partial government shutdown late this week after Saturday's DHS-involved shooting in Minneapolis threw the massive funding package passed by the House last week into jeopardy. Members of the group could potentially tank procedural votes required to advance any alternative funding package.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://x.com/freedomcaucus/status/2016223256445956146" target="_blank">letter to President Donald Trump</a> sent Tuesday, senior members of the group said they would "not allow Democrats to strip [DHS] funding out to pass other appropriations separately."</p> 
<p>"We cannot support giving Democrats the ability to control the funding of our Department of Homeland Security," they added.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats want to break up the six-bill package sent over from the House, stripping out the DHS funding to renegotiate terms following the killing of 37-year-old Alex Pretti. But House GOP leaders privately believe that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">would open a new "hellscape"</a> in the funding talks within the divided House Republican conference.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T15:41:18-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democratic House leaders join push to impeach Kristi Noem</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/democratic-house-leaders-kristi-noem-impeachment-00749643</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00c1-d1ea-a5de-30c5adef0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:02:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The leaders of the House Democratic caucus vowed on Tuesday to impeach Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem if President Donald Trump does not fire her, citing a “DHS killing spree unleashed in Minnesota.”</p> 
<p>The threat comes as Noem <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/kristi-noem-scrutiny-minneapolis-shootings-00748618?can_id=bb0274a7e273dbe000778c447d392e4c&amp;email_referrer=email_3071138&amp;email_subject=tuesday-minnesota-update-add-your-name-if-you-agree-impeach-secretary-of-homeland-security-kristi-noem&amp;link_id=8&amp;source=email-tuesday-minnesota-update-add-your-name-if-you-agree-impeach-secretary-of-homeland-security-kristi-noem" target="_blank">faces heightened scrutiny</a> over her response to the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by Customs and Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis on Saturday, the second killing by federal immigration agents in the city this month.</p> 
<p>Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, whip Katherine Clark (D-Mass.) and caucus Chair Pete Aguilar (D-Calif.) in a joint statement called for “dramatic changes” at DHS and criminal prosecution of federal agents who have broken the law.</p> 
<p>“Taxpayer dollars are being weaponized by the Trump administration to kill American citizens, brutalize communities and violently target law-abiding immigrant families,” the leaders wrote. “The country is disgusted by what the Department of Homeland Security has done.”</p> 
<p>More than 140 House Democrats have signed on to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865" target="_blank">an impeachment resolution</a> against Noem, who is <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610" target="_blank">set to testify</a> before the Senate Judiciary Committee in March. GOP lawmakers and influential MAGA commentators have also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/john-curtis-kristi-noem-minnesota-investigation-00747397" target="_blank">publicly rebuked the Homeland Security secretary</a> in recent days, saying her department’s aggressive immigration operation in Minnesota has overstepped.</p> 
<p>“If Democrats cared this much about deporting violent, criminal illegal aliens, the American people would be much safer," White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson said in response to the statement. </p> 
<p>DHS spokesperson Tricia McLaughlin said in a statement that Democrats should "focus on protecting the American people," which the DHS does "every day under Secretary Noem's leadership."</p> 
<p>"DHS enforces the laws Congress passes, period. If certain members don’t like those laws, changing them is literally their job," McLaughlin said.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration signaled a possible shift in strategy on Monday, with the president sending border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis and announcing that Homan “will report directly to me.” The White House also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">pulled Border Patrol Commander Gregory Bovino</a>, a close ally of Noem’s whose response to the shooting also drew backlash, from his assignment in the city.</p> 
<p>Still, White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Monday that Noem retains “the utmost confidence and trust of the president of the United States,” and Trump told reporters Tuesday that “she's done a very good job” and will not step down.</p> 
<p>The Democratic leaders wrote in their statement that “the violence unleashed on the American people by the Department of Homeland Security must end forthwith,” adding: “We can do this the easy way or the hard way.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eleanor Holmes Norton confirms her retirement as DC delegate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-statement-00749099</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-003d-dabb-ad9c-3ffdeff70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:32:11 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Eleanor Holmes Norton, Washington's nonvoting House delegate for 35 years, confirmed Tuesday she is retiring from office — more than 48 hours after a public filing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/eleanor-holmes-norton-retires-dc-delegate-00731986" target="_blank">terminating her reelection campaign</a>.</p> 
<p>“With pride in our accomplishments, gratitude to DC, and confidence in the next generation, I announced I'll retire at the end of this term,” she said in a statement. </p> 
<p>Norton, who is 88 and has faced serious questions about her fitness for office, said she would complete her 18th term.</p> 
<p>“Although I’ve decided not to seek reelection, I will never falter in my commitment to the residents I have long championed,” she said, touting her success in securing the transfer of federal lands to local government control and the establishment of a federally funded college tuition assistance program for D.C. residents.</p> 
<p>Norton stayed silent for days after her campaign filed termination paperwork Sunday morning — even as local politicians and dignitaries paid public tribute to Norton and her service to the city.</p> 
<p>Norton has made limited public appearances in the past year, even as President Donald Trump targeted the city for a police takeover and immigration enforcement surge. She insisted for months she would run for reelection but raised barely any campaign cash as pressure to retire mounted and challengers began to line up against her. </p> 
<p>Among the Democrats already vying to succeed her are D.C. Council members Brooke Pinto and Robert White, political strategist Kinney Zalesne and former Norton aide Trent Holbrook. The June 16 primary is all but certain to decide the next delegate in a city that hasn’t given a Republican presidential nominee more than 10 percent of the vote since 1988.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T17:08:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Florida Republican Vern Buchanan won’t seek reelection</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/vern-buchanan-florida-retirement-00748961</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0016-d9a8-a7be-869687cf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:35:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Florida Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51853" data-person-id="51853">Vern Buchanan</a> announced Tuesday that he will be retiring from Congress after 20 years in office, the latest Republican to forgo seeking reelection amid a challenging midterm environment for the party.</p> 
<p>Buchanan, who represents the red 16th District that includes some of Tampa’s suburbs along the Gulf Coast, is a longtime member of the House Ways and Means Committee.</p> 
<p>“Serving the people of Southwest Florida has been the honor of my lifetime,” Buchanan said in a statement. “After 20 years of service, I believe it’s the right time to pass the torch and begin a new chapter in my life.”</p> 
<p>First elected in 2006, Buchanan became a key player on tax, trade and health care policy.</p> 
<p>His decision to step aside has sparked chatter among Republicans over potential successors. Shortly after news of Buchanan’s retirement broke, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260192" data-person-id="260192">Randy Fine</a> (R-Fla.) voiced support for Republican National Committee Chair Joe Gruters, writing <a href="https://x.com/VoteRandyFine/status/2016170411755462822?s=20" target="_blank"><u>“Run, Joe, run!” in a post on X</u></a>.</p> 
<p>But Gruters is not interested in running to replace Buchanan in the Florida district, according to two people with direct knowledge of the matter granted anonymity to discuss his thinking, and is instead interested in remaining the RNC chair. </p> 
<p>But another person close to Gruters, similarly granted anonymity, said he “wouldn’t shut any doors just yet” over whether Gruters might run, despite him being elected to lead the RNC in August. The person added that Gruters would be a “significant frontrunner should he do it.”</p> 
<p>Christian Ziegler, a former Florida GOP chair, floated other possible names for the seat, including Buchanan’s son, Florida state Rep. James Buchanan, who is running for the state Senate; Manatee County Commissioner Mike Rahn; former state Senate President Bill Galvano; state Rep. Fiona McFarland; and former state Rep. Tommy Gregory.</p> 
<p>Ziegler added there was “always a chance” wealthy self-funders could also enter the race.</p> 
<p>Buchanan’s early years in Congress drew scrutiny after he was <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2011/10/report-doj-investigating-buchanan-066301" target="_blank"><u>investigated by the Justice Department in 2011</u></a> over allegations that he asked a former associate in the auto industry to improperly reimburse his employees for their contributions to his campaign. Buchanan denied any wrongdoing, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2012/09/doj-drops-case-against-rep-buchanan-081069" target="_blank"><u>the case was dropped in 2012</u></a>.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Kimberly Leonard contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: No shutdown deal in sight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/shutdown-dhs-ice-funding-minnesota-shooting-00748768</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fda2-d1ea-a5df-fda680270000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senators are scrambling to avoid a partial government shutdown later this week after Saturday’s fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by a federal agent has members of both parties debating what guardrails they can place on President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p>There’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">no deal</a> in sight.</p> 
<p>The Homeland Security appropriations measure is a part of a multi-bill funding package the House sent over to the Senate last Thursday before leaving town for recess, and which the Senate now must clear before 12:01 a.m. Saturday, Jan. 31 — or spark funding lapses across multiple agencies. Making changes to any portion of that package at this point would jeopardize its chances for being signed into law in time.</p> 
<p>But recent developments in Minnesota have Democrats calling for changes to the DHS measure. Among their list of demands are requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, mandating federal agents identify themselves, requiring DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations and limiting the “mission creep of federal agencies.”</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer wants the DHS bill stripped out of the larger funding package entirely and renegotiated.</p> 
<p>Republicans are reluctant to engage, taking the first step Monday to set up an initial vote on the package Thursday. Instead, GOP senators are dangling alternatives that would let them avoid having to tweak the package at the eleventh hour, floating new potential executive actions or a commitment to passing a separate piece of legislation that would address shared priorities.</p> 
<p>Democrats aren’t biting. Many believe they have leverage as Americans recoil at the administration’s immigration enforcement tactics in Minnesota and elsewhere. Plenty of Democrats are also skeptical the administration can be trusted to bring accountability to DHS operations or that standalone legislation reining in the department would ever make it through the House.</p> 
<p>“My options are to do nothing or to recognize that two U.S. citizens were recently … executed by federal agents,” Sen. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.) told reporters Monday. “We need to at least bring some level of pressure on DHS or on our Republican colleagues to explain to the American public why we are going to continue funding this without any changes.”</p> 
<p>Democrats are also increasingly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865" target="_blank">calling for DHS Secretary&nbsp;Kristi Noem’s impeachment</a> amid the fallout. Noem will testify March 3 for an oversight hearing <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610" target="_blank">before Senate Judiciary</a>, according to an aide for Chair Chuck Grassley (R-Iowa), where questions about her leadership are sure to arise.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans could still have the upper hand. A group of conservatives, including Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah), is vowing to oppose any effort to strip out DHS funding. And due to the time crunch ahead of Friday’s shutdown deadline, a single senator can block an attempt to quickly amend the legislation.</p> 
<p>Privately, many Republicans believe any off-ramp will need to come from the White House, anyway, according to two people granted anonymity to disclose private thinking — and the administration said Monday it wants to see the funding package passed as written.</p> 
<p>Over in the House, Speaker Mike Johnson’s leadership circle is still weighing its options but there are no plans to bring the chamber back early from recess, according to three people granted anonymity to comment on private planning.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No off-ramp in sight for DHS-fueled shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628</link>
      <description>Republicans are dangling options that would avoid having to change a massive spending bill. Democrats aren’t biting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fcf0-d1ea-a5df-fcf431d30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:55:52 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c9/02/7b3ffafc4e3ea5110a323ac21399/u-s-congress-53267.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Katie Britt (R-Ala.), who leads the Appropriations subcommittee dealing with DHS, said actions “within the purview of the administration” could address Democrats’ concerns.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c9/02/7b3ffafc4e3ea5110a323ac21399/u-s-congress-53267.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Washington is charging toward a partial government shutdown over President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda even as senators and the White House scramble to find an elusive off-ramp.</p> 
<p>Democrats, Republicans and the White House each say they want to avoid another costly lapse in government funding. But Saturday’s killing of a 37-year-old Minnesota man by federal agents has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">badly complicated the approach pattern</a> for a massive six-bill appropriations package that the Senate planned to approve this week.</p> 
<p>In the wake of the Minnesota shooting, Democrats want Republicans to join them in stripping out funding for the Department of Homeland Security from the sprawling package. Yet any changes would require further action in the House, which is out of town until Monday — after a shutdown would start at 12:01 a.m. Saturday.</p> 
<p>Republicans are dangling alternatives that would avoid having to change the massive bill, including potential executive actions or an agreement to pass a separate piece of legislation. But Democrats believe they have leverage as Americans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">recoil at Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement tactics</a> in Minnesota and elsewhere.</p> 
<p>The captured-on-video killing of Alex Pretti has sparked public unease even from Trump allies in Congress and fueled new questions about how the administration is enacting its agenda, putting intense pressure on Democrats to dig in and fight.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said Monday that the “responsibility to prevent a partial government shutdown” lies in the hands of Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and his fellow Senate Republicans. He called on them to agree to strip out and renegotiate the DHS bill while allowing the rest of the package — which would fund nearly three-quarters of annual agency spending — to be passed into law.</p> 
<p>As recently as Friday, enough senators were expected to help pass the full set of funding bills, which was negotiated over the course of months by bipartisan appropriators. Now, according to a person granted anonymity to disclose private discussions, Democrats are quickly “coalescing” around a number of changes they want to the DHS bill, which won only seven Democratic votes in the House.</p> 
<p>Those include requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, overruling a recently disclosed ICE memo asserting they are not required. Other potential Democratic amendments would mandate federal agents identify themselves, require DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations and limit the “mission creep of federal agencies.”</p> 
<p>Despite the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">concern that has emerged within the GOP ranks</a> after Saturday’s shooting, Republicans are moving forward with the six-bill package as currently drafted, taking a first step Monday to put it on the floor. Senators are expected to take an initial vote Thursday, when at least eight Democrats will be needed to leap a 60-vote hurdle.</p> 
<p>Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) told reporters Monday that she did not favor removing the DHS bill from the six-bill package but that there are ongoing discussions about “further reforms or procedural protections.”</p> 
<p>“My hope is that we’re not going to get to that point, that everyone would recognize that a government shutdown is extremely harmful and should be avoided,” Collins said when asked about the prospects for a partial shutdown.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a> (R-Ala.), who leads the Appropriations subcommittee dealing with DHS and met with Collins Monday, also told reporters the Senate should pass the funding package as is but that there could be actions taken “within the purview of the administration” to address Democrats’ concerns.</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers and aides held out hope that some of Trump’s moves Monday, which included sending border czar Tom Homan to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">oversee the Minnesota enforcement surge</a>, would soften the ground for a possible deal. Others were encouraged that lines of communications remained open between the parties early in the week.</p> 
<p>Republicans are facing their own internal pressures as they seek to avoid a shutdown. A group of conservatives, including Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah), is vowing to oppose any effort to strip out DHS funding. And because the Senate is locked in a time crunch with the Friday midnight deadline looming, any one senator can block an attempt to quickly amend the legislation.</p> 
<p>At the same time, there are some Democratic qualms about pushing agencies to the brink less than three months after ending a record 43-day shutdown fought over health care. Some are noting that ICE and Border Patrol will continue to be funded in any case through the GOP megabill enacted last year while other DHS agencies such as FEMA and TSA would be subject to the shutdown.</p> 
<p>But so far Democrats are insisting that Republicans agree to rewrite the bill. Democrats are skeptical that the administration can be trusted to take executive action or that standalone legislation reining in DHS would ever make it through the House.</p> 
<p>“My options are to do nothing or to recognize that two U.S. citizens were recently … executed by federal agents,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189136" data-person-id="189136">Ruben Gallego</a> (D-Ariz.) told reporters Monday. “We need to at least bring some level of pressure on DHS or on our Republican colleagues to explain to the American public why we are going to continue funding this without any changes.”</p> 
<p>Even sending an amended bill back to the House would carry the risk of an extended standoff. One senior House Republican granted anonymity said that would open a new "hellscape" in the funding talks, with the fractious GOP conference divided over the way forward.</p> 
<p>“Democrats already had a say in DHS funding during the bipartisan negotiations that occurred on each and every individual appropriations bill," said a House GOP aide granted anonymity to speak candidly about the dynamics. “If they renege on the agreement on any of these bipartisan bills, then it would open a bigger can of worms.”</p> 
<p>Privately, many Republicans on Capitol Hill believe that any off-ramp to be found before Friday night’s deadline will need to come from the White House, according to two people granted anonymity to disclose private thinking.</p> 
<p>But <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/white-house-backs-appropriations-package-with-dhs-funding-00746971" target="_blank">the administration said Monday</a> it wants to see the six-bill package passed as written — without the DHS funding separated out.</p> 
<p>“Policy discussions on immigration in Minnesota are happening,” White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said, adding that those talks “should not be at the expense of government funding for the American people.”</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson's leadership circle is still weighing options as the partial shutdown looms. While some Senate Democrats are calling on the House to cut its one-week break short and reconvene, there are no plans to bring the chamber back early, according to three people granted anonymity to comment on private planning.</p> 
<p>While GOP leaders plan for now to bring the House back next Monday as scheduled, some rank-and-file Republicans are wary that Johnson might re-run his strategy from the last shutdown and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/09/mike-johnson-shutdown-no-show-00601215" target="_blank">keep the House out even longer</a> in a bid to jam the Senate.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Susan Collins speaks with Noem about immigration enforcement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/susan-collins-speaks-with-noem-about-immigration-enforcement-00747915</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc6c-d452-a99b-fdfe0abf0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:28:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>GOP Sen. Susan Collins said she spoke Monday to embattled Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem after the administration launched an immigration enforcement campaign in her home state.</p> 
<p>Collins declined to divulge details of her conversation with Noem to reporters — though her office indicated earlier this month that the senator had reached out to DHS about ICE’s activities in Maine.</p> 
<p>Regarding the ICE presence there, Collins said in a statement last week that “people who are in this country legally should not be targets of ICE investigations,” while those who have “entered this country illegally and who have engaged in criminal activity …. could be subject to arrest and deportation.” </p> 
<p>She added, “People who are exercising the right to peacefully gather and protest their government should be careful not to interfere with law enforcement efforts while doing so.</p> 
<p>But the conversation comes at a critical moment. Federal agents shot and killed a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis over the weekend, prompting public outrage and sparking criticism from a growing number of Senate Republicans about the Trump administration’s handling of the situation. It’s the second such shooting to occur in the city since January began.</p> 
<p>Collins is also the chair of the Senate Appropriations Committee who helped negotiate legislation to fund several agencies — including DHS — through the end of September. That bipartisan package is now imperiled as Democrats now say they won’t vote to support any bill that funds DHS without significant guardrails in place to rein in immigration enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>DHS is among several agencies that would shut down after Jan. 30 unless lawmakers can reach some sort of compromise.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kristi Noem to testify before Senate Judiciary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc32-dabb-ad9f-fffff7b80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:35:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem will testify March 3 before the Senate Judiciary Committee, according to an aide for Chair Chuck Grassley.</p> 
<p>Grassley has been haggling for weeks to schedule Noem’s testimony as part of his panel’s regular oversight of DHS. But her high-profile appearance will likely be dominated by senators’ questions regarding the agency’s immigration enforcement tactics following two fatal shootings by federal agents in Minneapolis in the past month.</p> 
<p>Some GOP senators — including Sen. Thom Tillis of North Carolina, who is a member on the committee — have called for an independent investigation into the latest shooting over the weekend, while others have criticized initial comments from top administration officials that suggested the victim bore responsibility and not the officers involved.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rand Paul summons Trump immigration officials to testify after Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/rand-paul-dhs-hearing-minneapolis-00747012</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbef-d1ea-a5df-fbefeffb0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:14:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151828" data-person-id="151828">Rand Paul</a>, chair of the Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee, called on three top immigration enforcement officials to testify before his panel in the wake of Saturday’s killing of a Minneapolis man by federal agents.</p> 
<p>The Kentucky Republican <a href="https://x.com/SenRandPaul/status/2015868311825785113/photo/1" target="_blank">sent letters Monday</a> to Rodney Scott, the commissioner of Customs and Border Protection; Joseph Edlow, director of U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services; and Todd Lyons, who is serving as acting director of ICE, requesting that the three men testify at a Feb. 12 hearing.</p> 
<p>“As you know, the Department of Homeland Security has been provided an exceptional amount of funding to secure our borders and enforce our immigration laws,” Paul said in the letters to the administration officials. “Congress has an obligation to conduct oversight of those tax dollars and ensure the funding is used to accomplish the mission, provide proper support for our law enforcement, and, most importantly, protect the American people.”</p> 
<p>Paul’s letters don’t mention this weekend’s killing of 37-year-old Alex Pretti, which has sparked a wave of new scrutiny of the immigration enforcement actions in Minnesota ordered by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>But the hearing would be the first chance senators will have to question Trump administration officials’ over the shooting and the president’s broader immigration and Homeland Security agenda.</p> 
<p>Separately, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/52983" data-person-id="52983">Todd Young</a> (R-Ind.) joined the growing ranks of Republicans raising questions about the shooting, saying he supports a “full and transparent investigation into the tragic event in Minneapolis.”</p> 
<p>“Congress has requested testimony from ICE, CBP, and USCIS leaders in an open hearing, and they should testify soon,” said Young, who is not a member of Paul’s committee, in a statement to POLITICO. “Providing the American people with the full facts is an important part of maintaining public trust. We also need state and local officials to better cooperate with federal enforcement efforts.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House backs appropriations package with DHS funding</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/white-house-backs-appropriations-package-with-dhs-funding-00746971</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbe1-d452-a99b-fbff7a170000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:58:58 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House on Monday urged the Senate to pass the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill appropriations package</a> to avert a partial government shutdown and signaled it doesn’t want <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">Department of Homeland Security money</a> separated out.</p> 
<p>“At this point, the White House supports the bipartisan work that was done to advance the bipartisan appropriations package and we want to see that passed,” press secretary Karoline Leavitt said at a White House briefing when asked if the administration would be willing to separate DHS funding.</p> 
<p>Leavitt said that “policy discussions on immigration in Minnesota are happening,” pointing to President Donald Trump’s call with Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz earlier Monday. She said the discussions “should not be at the expense of government funding for the American people.”</p> 
<p>The press secretary also pointed to the winter storms across the country and the effect a lapse in FEMA funding could have on the response effort.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer has pressed Republicans to rewrite the DHS funding legislation in the wake of the killing of Alex Pretti in Minnesota and signaled that the other five appropriations bills could move forward without it. Senate Republican leadership want to move forward all six bills, including DHS funding, and the first votes are expected Thursday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Hill Democrats want Kristi Noem out as DHS secretary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbb8-dabb-ad9f-fffde7210000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:37:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A growing number of Hill Democrats are calling for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem to step aside or be impeached following the shooting of a Minneapolis man by DHS agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>A House impeachment resolution targeting Noem now has <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HRES_996?q=H.Res.996" target="_blank">140 cosponsors</a>, nearly two-thirds of the Democratic Caucus, according to a spokesperson for Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/204795" data-person-id="204795">Robin Kelly</a> (D-Ill.), who authored the legislation. Dozens signed on over the weekend, including after a private caucus call Sunday in which a number of House Democrats spoke out for impeachment.</p> 
<p>Although impeaching President Donald Trump remains a highly divisive issue among Democrats, calling for Noem’s impeachment or resignation is fast becoming a mainstream position in the party.</p> 
<p>On the cosponsor list for Kelly's resolution are purple-district lawmakers such as Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422300" data-person-id="422300">Laura Gillen</a> (D-N.Y.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422519" data-person-id="422519">Greg Landsman</a> (D-Ohio), as well as members of the party leadership team including Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/152934" data-person-id="152934">Debbie Dingell</a> (D-Mich.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198811" data-person-id="198811">Suzan DelBene</a> (D-Wash.). </p> 
<p>Others in the party are calling for Noem's removal without mentioning the prospect of impeachment. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a>, for instance, declared in a Monday <a href="https://x.com/SenSchumer/status/2015840890112057442?s=20" target="_blank">social media post</a> that Noem "must be fired.” </p> 
<p>In a statement provided first to POLITICO, 15 House Democrats who are veterans said Noem should resign.</p> 
<p>“We call for an immediate stand down of ICE and CBP interior enforcement operations and demand the resignation of the Secretary of Homeland Security,” said the lawmakers, including California Democratic Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189606" data-person-id="189606">Ted Lieu</a>, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259485" data-person-id="259485">Salud Carbajal</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307601" data-person-id="307601">Gil Cisneros</a>. “Current leadership has failed to protect civil liberties, ensure accountability, or maintain the public trust.”</p> 
<p>With Republicans in control of the House floor, it could be difficult for Democrats to force the issue anytime soon. Absent a GOP groundswell, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> will be able to bottle up the measure indefinitely though Kelly could try to call up her impeachment legislation as a privileged matter, allowing it to bypass committees and move to a quick House vote.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suozzi: ‘I failed’ when voting to pass DHS funding bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-suozzi-dhs-funding-vote-00746598</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb59-d452-a99b-fbffc8740006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:29:47 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Tom Suozzi (D-N.Y.) on Monday said he regretted his vote last week for a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">funding bill for the Department of Homeland Security</a>, amid intense backlash surrounding the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“I failed to view the DHS funding vote as a referendum on the illegal and immoral conduct of ICE in Minneapolis,” <a href="https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=1428888331927735&amp;id=100044197461606&amp;mibextid=wwXIfr&amp;rdid=39dD6MhX9Elb42eK#" target="_blank">he said in a statement</a>. “I hear the anger from my constituents, and I take responsibility for that. I have long been critical of ICE’s unlawful behavior and I must do a better job demonstrating that.”</p> 
<p>Suozzi was one of seven Democrats who crossed party lines to join Republicans in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402" target="_blank">narrowly passing the DHS funding bill</a> in a 220-207 vote. The bill funded agencies including FEMA and the Coast Guard — and ICE, keeping it funded at $10 billion for the fiscal year.</p> 
<p>Suozzi expressed his regret amid mounting tensions following federal immigration operations in Minnesota and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">killing of a second U.S. citizen protester</a>, 37-year-old ICU nurse Alex Pretti, on Saturday.</p> 
<p>“The senseless and tragic murder of Alex Pretti underscores what happens when untrained federal agents operate without accountability,” Suozzi said. “President Trump must immediately end ‘Operation Metro Surge’ and ICE’s occupation of Minneapolis that has sown chaos, led to tragedy, and undermined experienced local law enforcement.”</p> 
<p>Before the weekend killing, the DHS funding was slated to be part of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill package</a> that seemed likely to pass in the Senate. But Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said over the weekend that Democrats would not help <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">advance the current package</a> if it included the DHS funding — significantly raising the risk of a partial government shutdown at the end of the week.</p> 
<p>Rep. Laura Gillen (D-N.Y.), another one of the seven House Democrats who voted for the DHS package, called for DHS Secretary Kristi Noem’s impeachment following Pretti’s killing.</p> 
<p>“Another U.S. citizen has been killed at the hands of ICE and there must be accountability, which is why Secretary Noem must be impeached immediately,” Gillen <a href="https://gillen.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-gillen-urges-accountability-following-events-minnesota" target="_blank">said in a statement Sunday</a>. “Under her leadership, ICE has targeted U.S. citizens and children and killed Americans.”</p> 
<p>But Vicente Gonzalez (D-Texas), another member of the group of breakaway House Democrats, <a href="https://x.com/RepGonzalez/status/2015795510762787001" target="_blank">defended his vote in a video message Monday</a>, calling the footage out of Minnesota "appalling” but defending voting for the DHS funding.</p> 
<p>“ICE has all the resources they need that they got from that big ugly bill Republicans passed last year, that I voted against,” he said, adding he voted for funding for agencies like FEMA and the TSA.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T13:59:49-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans offer early support for Trump’s Minnesota pivot</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-homan-gop-support-00746206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb00-d1ea-a5df-fb8404090005</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:52:21 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Republicans on Capitol Hill expressed relief after President Donald Trump announced Monday he would send border czar Tom Homan to handle immigration enforcement in Minnesota after Department of Homeland Security agents shot and killed a second U.S. citizen there.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) said in an interview that the move was "a positive step to get the situation under control" while calling for a "full and transparent investigation" into the two Minneapolis shootings.</p> 
<p>"There needs to be greater coordination and cooperation between federal, state, and local officials — which is why sanctuary policies need to end and local officials must work with ICE so they can do their jobs without interference," he said. "It is paramount that we work to keep the public and law enforcement safe, while respecting the rights of everyone involved, including the right to peacefully protest."</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> <a href="https://x.com/LeaderJohnThune/status/2015841218182152505" target="_blank">called the move</a> a "positive development," while Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) also offered praise Monday, saying on X “we need a new set of eyes and someone with his experience to help turn around the problems of the moment and the future."</p> 
<p>“Tom is the right man to find a way to de-escalate the situation,” Graham added.</p> 
<p>A growing number of Hill Republicans have been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">pushing publicly and privately</a> for a lowering of the temperature, including from the federal government, after DHS agents shot and killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Saturday.</p> 
<p>GOP lawmakers largely view Homan as a more practical enforcer of Trump’s mass deportation plans as some grow increasingly wary of how Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem and Border Patrol commander Gregory Bovino are handling the campaign, according to six GOP lawmakers granted anonymity to discuss internal conversations.</p> 
<p>“There needed to be a change,” said one of the GOP lawmakers. But other at-risk Republicans have been wary to publicly embrace Homan, who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/16/tom-homan-50k-sting-operation-00611219" target="_blank">denied reports</a> that he took a $50,000 bribe from federal agents.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T13:25:07-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump says Justice Department is investigating Ilhan Omar</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/trump-justice-department-ilhan-omar-00746103</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fac6-d9a8-a7bf-fec66b6c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:30:55 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Monday said the Justice Department is investigating Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.).</p> 
<p>Trump made the <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115961647505369753" target="_blank">announcement on Truth Social</a>, writing: “the DOJ and Congress are looking at ‘Congresswoman’ Illhan Omar, who left Somalia with NOTHING, and is now reportedly worth more than 44 Million Dollars. Time will tell all.”</p> 
<p>It is the latest attack the president has levied at Omar, and the most recent instance of the president directing an investigation into his political rivals.</p> 
<p>Trump has previously said Omar <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/01/trump-ilhan-omar-somalia-00632599" target="_blank">should be jailed or deported to Somalia</a>, where she was born, though Omar has been a U.S. citizen since 2000. He has also linked Omar to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/29/us/fraud-minnesota-somali.html" target="_blank">government services fraud</a> investigations in Minnesota, accusing her of being “one of many scammers,” despite no clear evidence linking her to the cases.</p> 
<p>Tensions have only grown between the two as immigration officials continue to patrol the city of Minneapolis, which Omar represents.</p> 
<p>Omar on Monday appeared unperturbed by Trump's announcement. <a href="https://x.com/IlhanMN/status/2015818278728257569?s=20" target="_blank">In her own post on X</a>, Omar said Trump was "deflecting."</p> 
<p>"Sorry, Trump, your support is collapsing and you’re panicking," she wrote. "Right on cue, you’re deflecting from your failures with lies and conspiracy theories about me. Years of 'investigations' have found nothing. Get your goons out of Minnesota."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Omar's office said she has not received anything from DOJ about an investigation.</p> 
<p>Omar’s net worth skyrocketed in the last year, and House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) <a href="https://nypost.com/2026/01/24/us-news/house-gop-prepares-for-court-to-establish-how-ilhan-omar-her-husband-are-worth-up-to-30m/" target="_blank">recently told the New York Post</a> that he plans to launch an investigation into what caused the dramatic spike.</p> 
<p>According to <a href="https://disclosures-clerk.house.gov/public_disc/financial-pdfs/2024/10068415.pdf" target="_blank">financial disclosures filed last year</a>, Omar’s net worth principally increased due to her spouse — and not her work with the government. She disclosed her spouse having stakes worth collectively between $6 million and $30 million in a venture capital firm and a winery.</p> 
<p>Members of Congress’ and their spouses’ sources of income and assets are traditionally disclosed in broad ranges, not as a specific dollar amount.</p> 
<p>Omar has previously denied the allegations of anything untoward and has said Trump has <a href="https://x.com/ilhanmn/status/1995957774510162165?s=46" target="_blank">a “creepy” obsession</a> with her.</p> 
<p>Trump also announced Monday that he is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">sending border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis</a>. Residents have flooded the streets of the city this month, protesting the shootings of Renee Good, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/woman-killed-by-ice-agent-in-minneapolis-was-a-mother-of-3-poet-and-new-to-the-city-00715809" target="_blank">who was killed by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement officer</a> Jan. 7, and Alex Pretti, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">who was killed by a Border Patrol</a> agent Saturday.</p> 
<p>The Department of Justice did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: Due to an editing error, an earlier version of this report misstated the value of Omar's spouse's business partnerships.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Shutdown odds spike after Minnesota killing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/what-were-watching-00745892</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f841-dabb-ad9f-ffede4950000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The killing of Alex Pretti at the hands of federal agents is hitting hard on Capitol Hill, ratcheting up the odds of a partial government shutdown and spurring Republican lawmakers to make another break with the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Here’s the latest on how the fallout from the Minnesota shooting is playing out in Congress:</p> 
<p><b>— Shutdown looks likely: </b>The Senate is set to take its first vote on the last tranche of government funding bills Thursday, and things aren’t looking good.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer is insisting that Republicans work across the aisle to rewrite DHS funding legislation but also signaling that Democrats would be willing to help advance the other five pending appropriations bills in the meantime. Several Democrats who helped end the previous shutdown say they plan to vote against the funding bills unless there are changes to the ICE operation in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>At this stage, Senate GOP leadership expects to move forward as planned on the six-bill package including DHS. Republicans and the White House have reached out to Senate Democrats about how to proceed, but one Senate Democratic leadership aide granted anonymity said they haven’t raised “realistic solutions.” A number of rank-and-file Senate Republicans are speaking out against any attempt to “defund” DHS — and leadership would need buy-in from all 100 senators to quickly strip out the DHS bill. President Donald Trump is <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115958123338296139" target="_blank">now pushing Republicans</a> to pass a bill to “END Sanctuary Cities.”</p> 
<p>A couple key reminders: The pending funding bills include money for the departments of Defense, Health and Human Services and State, and account for more than 75 percent of federal discretionary spending.</p> 
<p>And don’t forget the House is out this week and wouldn’t be around to pass any revamped funding bills before Friday. The Senate won’t hold its first vote of the week until Tuesday afternoon because of the snow storm.</p> 
<p><b>— Trump faces nervous GOP: </b>A growing number of House and Senate Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">voicing public concerns</a> about the incident and calling for an investigation, as top administration officials defend the agents involved.</p> 
<p>Even close Trump allies are beginning to speak out. Sen. David McCormick (R-Pa.) <a href="https://x.com/SenMcCormickPA/status/2015562528114520255" target="_blank">said on X Sunday night</a> that he supports the Border Patrol and ICE but that he agrees <a href="https://x.com/NRA/status/2015227627464728661?s=20" target="_blank">with the NRA</a> about the need for a “full investigation.”</p> 
<p>House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) is calling for DHS officials to testify. House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) suggested to Fox News that Trump would want to “maybe go to another city” as Minnesota officials push back.</p> 
<p>Some Republicans have been privately warning administration officials and GOP leaders for months that Trump’s immigration crackdown is not going over well in some pockets of the country.</p> 
<p>“Many of us wonder if the administration has any clue as to how much this will hurt us legislatively and electorally this year,” said one House Republican.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How $16B in earmarks evaded conservative ire — and helped clinch a funding deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/earmarks-conservatives-government-funding-00745730</link>
      <description>Republican leaders have agreed to earmarks for thousands of pet projects in specific congressional districts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f6cd-d1ea-a5df-f6cda3d30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/dd/d3/c37e10b84e35b500d42b7d2e2afe/u-s-congress-22286.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Reps. Ralph Norman and Chip Roy confer during a House Rules Committee meeting at the U.S. Capitol on July 1, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/dd/d3/c37e10b84e35b500d42b7d2e2afe/u-s-congress-22286.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fiscal conservatives in Congress threatened for months to block government funding if GOP leaders didn’t shun earmarks. They succeeded in scrapping just one; the rest, almost $16 billion worth, are slated in the package the Senate needs to clear by Friday to avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p>Republican hard-liners on both sides of the Capitol have made things difficult this winter for their leadership, which has been scrambling to fund the government before cash runs out Friday for the vast majority of federal agencies. But they failed to significantly curtail the practice of directing federal dollars to specific projects back home.</p> 
<p>Republicans swore off earmarks for more than a decade in 2010 amid corruption scandals and demands from conservatives empowered by the rise of the Tea Party movement that has since receded. Then in 2021, Democrats brought back the practice after the party swept control of the White House and Congress, softening the return with a rebrand as “community project funding,” new rules to prevent abuse and a cap at 1 percent of funding.</p> 
<p>Now Republicans run Washington once again, and they’re overwhelmingly embracing the renaissance. As the Senate considers a nearly <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">$1.3 trillion funding package</a> this week loaded with thousands of earmarks for projects in specific congressional districts, fiscal hawks are acknowledging defeat.</p> 
<p>“When a majority of the United States House and a large chunk of the Senate seemingly want to advance earmarks, there's only so much you can do,” Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas), a member of the House Freedom Caucus, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>“I've long stated I think it's the currency of corruption, and we shouldn't do it,” he added. “But, you know, members like to do it.”</p> 
<p>Capitol Hill’s most vocal earmark proponents argue that, if not for the revival of earmarks, congressional leaders would not have succeeded in clinching bipartisan deals to fund the Pentagon and nondefense agencies with new budgets for the first time in almost two years.</p> 
<p>The multibill funding package has yet to reach President Donald Trump’s desk and is now <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank"><u>complicated by Democratic outrage</u></a> over ICE funding after a federal immigration enforcement agent fatally shot another U.S. citizen in Minnesota over the weekend. But lawmakers in both parties are already touting the cash they secured for local projects as they campaign for reelection nine months out from the midterms.</p> 
<p>“It's not worth being in Congress if you can't find ways to help your district,” Rep. Mike Flood said in an interview.</p> 
<p>The Nebraska Republican secured almost $30 million in projects for his district in the current slate of funding bills, including millions of dollars to repave roads, about $750,000 for police cruisers and $500,000 for improvements to a shelter for minors who would otherwise be in juvenile detention.</p> 
<p>Flood argues the inclusion of earmarks ultimately helped Republicans negotiate funding bills that keep federal spending mostly steady — a top priority of congressional fiscal hawks. “For all the things that people say are wrong with Congress, this process is working. And it's working well,” he said. “And we are bringing this in under budget.”</p> 
<p>This month members of the House Freedom Caucus threatened to tank a preliminary vote on spending bills if GOP leaders didn’t knock out at least some earmarks. They were able to kill only one: a $1 million earmark Democratic Rep. Ilhan Omar secured for a community organization in her Minnesota district, in part because the address listed for the group was that of a restaurant.</p> 
<p>House fiscal hawks made a final stand last week when they demanded, and received, a vote to nix hundreds of earmarks senators had worked to secure. That vote failed overwhelmingly, right before the House passed a funding package with a price tag of more than $1 trillion, with every earmark intact.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman, a member of the Freedom Caucus, said it was a “sad day” and called it “irredeemable” for a GOP-led Congress and White House to support the earmark-filled package. Norman said he now has no hope Republicans will ever do anything to get rid of earmarks.</p> 
<p>“I wish it was different,” he said.</p> 
<p>More than 70 House Republicans voted against killing the Senate earmarks. However, some hard-liners argue that it’s really the minority party driving the resurgence in a narrowly divided Congress.</p> 
<p>“You need Democratic votes, right? So let's not forget that,” said Rep. Scott Perry (R-Pa.), a former chair of the House Freedom Caucus. “I'm not here to apologize for, or validate, a bunch of garbage Republican earmarks. But we’d have a much better time at making sure those didn't prevail if we didn't need the Democrat votes.”</p> 
<p>In the Senate, where Democratic buy-in is necessary to overcome the filibuster, fiscal conservatives <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/senate-gop-conservatives-lee-johnson-scott-00703034" target="_blank">delayed action on funding bills</a> for more than a month following the end of the record-breaking government shutdown in November — in part due to their earmark concerns. Now that the final slate of funding bills is before the Senate, those same lawmakers are again demanding a vote to eliminate the pet projects.</p> 
<p>Last week Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.), a leader of that charge, noted that in 2021 the Senate Republican Conference voted unanimously to maintain their rule against earmarks, a nonbinding prohibition many <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/05/05/senate-republicans-earmarks-485373" target="_blank"><u>GOP senators were quick to flout</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“It’s time for Senate Republicans to follow our own rules. END ALL EARMARKS NOW!” <a href="https://x.com/SenRickScott/status/2014799358047216093?s=20" target="_blank"><u>Scott posted on social media</u></a>.</p> 
<p>The earmarks Congress has inserted in the new funding bills are the first of Trump’s presidency, since federal agencies have been running on stopgap funding patches for almost two years. Lawmakers in both parties see them as a way to protect their authority to dictate how federal money is spent as the Trump administration continues to shift and cancel billions of dollars in contravention of their wishes.</p> 
<p>“It restores the institutional faith in Congress' ability — albeit in a very small and minor way — to direct congressional spending and gets power back from any executive branch,” Tennessee Rep. Chuck Fleischmann, a senior Republican appropriator, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Many Republican lawmakers have been privately pressing GOP leaders to bring back earmarks for years, including as far back as 2016, when then-Speaker Paul Ryan <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2016/11/gop-lift-earmark-ban-231500" target="_blank"><u>halted a closed-door vote</u></a> on restoring the practice.</p> 
<p>At least under the old rules, earmarks were entwined with corruption. In the early 2000s, several lawmakers pled guilty to money laundering and bribery charges for abusing the practice. In the most high-profile of those cases, the late Rep. Randy “Duke” Cunningham (R-Calif.) admitted to accepting $2.4 million in bribes to secure earmarks.</p> 
<p>Now Congress has much tighter rules governing the process, including a prohibition on steering money to for-profit organizations. Senior members of the Appropriations Committees who want to avoid a repeat of infamous earmarks scandals also closely vet the requests, said House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.).</p> 
<p>“We scrub them pretty hard, and honestly the Democrats do, too,” he said.</p> 
<p>In a sign House Republicans are growing more comfortable with the practice, they are now discussing whether to expand earmarks in future funding bills to include education, health and labor projects, according to Rep. Robert Aderholt (R-Ala.), who chairs the panel in charge of that money. Only senators are currently allowed to specify projects for funding within those jurisdictions.</p> 
<p>“There's interest on both sides, as long as it's done in a way that doesn't make both sides feel uncomfortable,” Aderholt said. “Members want to have a little bit of say-so, because we do have the power of the purse.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-25T16:14:29-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans start raising concerns about Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707</link>
      <description>Most in the GOP are silent or backing the Trump administration, but a conspicuous few are speaking out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f675-dabb-ad9f-fffd94780000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 13:44:59 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f5/bb/3089e2184b72b2a7d1e4df2758d0/u-s-congress-33546.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“ICE agents do not have carte blanche in carrying out their duties," Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said Sunday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f5/bb/3089e2184b72b2a7d1e4df2758d0/u-s-congress-33546.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A small but growing number of Republicans are raising public concerns about the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">killing Saturday of a 37-year-old Minnesota man</a> by federal agents.</p> 
<p>Hours after the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti on a Minneapolis street, one House GOP chair called for the top Immigration and Customs Enforcement leader and other Trump administration officials to publicly answer lawmakers’ questions. GOP Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66858" data-person-id="66858">Bill Cassidy</a> of Louisiana, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51218" data-person-id="51218">Lisa Murkowski</a> of Alaska and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> of North Carolina called for independent probes into the shooting, with <a href="https://x.com/SenBillCassidy/status/2015247523003162922" target="_blank">Cassidy arguing</a> the integrity of ICE and the Department of Homeland Security are “at stake.”</p> 
<p>Another House GOP chair appeared to suggest President Donald Trump should withdraw from Minneapolis and send the agents there to another city.</p> 
<p>"If I were President Trump, I would almost think about, OK, if the mayor and governor are going put our ICE officials in harm's way and there's a chance of losing more innocent lives, or whatever, then maybe go to another city and let the people of Minneapolis decide: Do we want to continue to have all of these illegals?” Oversight Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260072" data-person-id="260072">James Comer</a> (R-Ky.) said Sunday on Fox News, adding that he expected Minnesotans to “rebel against their leadership.”</p> 
<p>However gentle and equivocal the pushback might be, it is growing increasingly conspicuous as congressional Republicans privately discuss how to respond to Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement campaign ahead of the midterm elections. Some Republicans have been privately warning administration officials and GOP leaders for months that the operation is not going over well in some pockets of the country.</p> 
<p>“Many of us wonder if the administration has any clue as to how much this will hurt us legislatively and electorally this year,” said one House Republican granted anonymity to candidly discuss private reactions.</p> 
<p>Murkowski said Sunday “ICE agents do not have carte blanche in carrying out their duties.”</p> 
<p>“Lawfully carrying a firearm does not justify federal agents killing an American — especially, as video footage appears to show, after the victim had been disarmed,” she said.</p> 
<p>While some of those speaking out are retiring, <a href="https://x.com/SenThomTillis/status/2015435983316189686?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">like Tillis</a>, or known to be at odds with Trump, like Murkowski, not all fit that bill. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/306838" data-person-id="306838">Dusty Johnson</a>, who called Sunday for all parties to “deescalate,” is running in a June GOP primary to be South Dakota’s governor.</p> 
<p>"As with any officer-involved shooting, this demands a thorough investigation," <a href="https://x.com/RepDustyJohnson/status/2015468366773858419" target="_blank">he wrote on X</a>.</p> 
<p>After House Homeland Security Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/240947" data-person-id="240947">Andrew Garbarino</a> (R-N.Y.) called Saturday for ICE, Border Patrol and other DHS officials to <a href="https://homeland.house.gov/2026/01/24/chairman-garbarino-requests-ice-cbp-uscis-testimony-for-upcoming-oversight-hearing/" target="_blank">testify before his panel</a>, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/195413" data-person-id="195413">Michael Baumgartner</a> (R-Wash.) praised the move, saying it was important “the American people and Congress be given a better understanding of how immigration enforcement is being handled.”</p> 
<p>Still, most Hill Republicans have not weighed in publicly or are backing the Trump administration, which was quick to argue Pretti was a “domestic terrorist” intent on massacring federal agents. Eyewitness video shows no evidence he drew his weapon or otherwise threatened agents with deadly force before he was shot.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> said in an interview with CBS’ “Face the Nation” Sunday that people are not allowed to carry a gun while committing another crime. "And interfering with law enforcement is a felony,” he added.</p> 
<p>"Peaceful protesters don’t have 9mm weapons with two extra magazines,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196450" data-person-id="196450">Jeff Van Drew</a> (R-N.J.) said on Fox News, referring to the concealed handgun Pretti had a permit to carry.</p> 
<p>The shooting and backlash from Democrats has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">upended a crucial government funding package</a> that the Senate was expected to pass this week. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said Saturday that Democrats won’t vote to advance <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">the legislation</a> so long as DHS funding is included, raising the likelihood of a partial shutdown at midnight Friday.</p> 
<p>He called on Republicans Sunday to pass the parts of the package funding other agencies while working with Democrats on "overhauling ICE and CBP to protect the public."</p> 
<p>"People should be safe from abuse by their own government," he said.</p> 
<p>Amid the uncertainty, some Republicans have privately fretted about the lack of guidance coming from the Trump administration about the shooting. Four GOP lawmakers and several GOP aides noted they had received many more updates from the administration about the weekend’s major winter storm than the situation in Minneapolis or immigration enforcement operations generally.</p> 
<p>Compounding the confusion, a DHS official sent an email alert with incorrect and contradictory information to congressional Republicans about three hours after the shooting Saturday, according to three people with direct knowledge of the message, which POLITICO obtained.</p> 
<p>The email described “the incident this morning between US Border Patrol officers and an illegal alien with a 9 mm semi-automatic handgun, who was wanted for violent assault.” But it linked to a DHS social media post that said federal agents were pursuing “an illegal alien wanted for violent assault” and then an “individual approached US Border Patrol officers with a 9 mm semi-automatic handgun,” referring to Pretti, who was a U.S. citizen.</p> 
<p>As Republicans wrangle with the shooting, Democrats are discussing internally how to mount a response — with senators strategizing over the funding bill and House leaders considering options including targeting Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem with sanctions.</p> 
<p>There’s a growing demand in the caucus to impeach Noem, with one purple-district Democrat who voted for DHS funding last week, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422300" data-person-id="422300">Laura Gillen</a> of New York, <a href="https://x.com/RepLauraGillen/status/2015460034537247216?s=20" target="_blank">publicly backing</a> the move shortly after a Sunday morning caucus call.</p> 
<p>Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz and state Attorney General Keith Ellison, both former House Democrats, briefed the lawmakers on the private call.</p> 
<p>Walz “sounded the alarm” over the “illegal” DHS activity in Minnesota, “and he urged everyone to unite and defend the integrity of the victims who are being smeared by the Trump administration,” said one House Democrat on the call who was granted anonymity because participants were encouraged not to leak its contents.</p> 
<p>“This is dark, unthinkable stuff, but I've never seen Democrats more militantly united,” the lawmaker added.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu and Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eleanor Holmes Norton won’t seek reelection as DC delegate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/eleanor-holmes-norton-retires-dc-delegate-00731986</link>
      <description>The 88-year-old Democrat had been facing mounting calls to step down.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c336-d22e-a1db-df37d7660000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 10:28:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a7/7c/46c635804d1e99e63f5fc2eab258/u-s-congress-06956.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Eleanor Holmes Norton's campaign on Sunday filed a termination notice with the Federal Election Commission.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a7/7c/46c635804d1e99e63f5fc2eab258/u-s-congress-06956.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Eleanor Holmes Norton, Washington’s nonvoting delegate to the House for more than three decades, will not seek a 19th term in office.</p> 
<p>Norton's campaign on Sunday <a href="https://docquery.fec.gov/cgi-bin/forms/C00244335/1935124/" target="_blank">filed a termination notice</a> with the Federal Election Commission, essentially signaling an end to her campaign. She can still file for reelection in the future. </p> 
<p>Norton's spokesperson did not respond to a request for comment. <a href="https://www.notus.org/2026-election/eleanor-holmes-norton-reelection-campaign-termination" target="_blank">NOTUS first reported</a> on the termination filing. </p> 
<p>Norton, 88, has faced mounting questions about her ability to serve in office as she retreated from most public appearances and showed unmistakable signs of frailty when she did speak.</p> 
<p>Her fitness came under particular scrutiny last summer when <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/13/eleanor-holmes-norton-trump-dc-00506273" target="_blank">she remained largely out of sight</a> as President Donald Trump announced a move to surge National Guard and federal law enforcement into Washington and take over its police department against the will of city leaders.</p> 
<p>While Norton insisted for months afterward she would in fact run again, reelection appeared increasingly untenable. Prominent Democratic strategist Donna Brazile, her former top aide, publicly called on her to retire, and Norton <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/08/congress/eleanor-holmes-norton-reelection-fundraising-00598060" target="_blank">raised scant funds</a> for her campaign.</p> 
<p>What is already a crowded field of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/18/robert-white-eleanor-holmes-norton-challenge-00571433" target="_blank">challengers to the longtime delegate</a> could balloon even further. The election is likely to be decided in the Democratic primary election in a city that hasn’t given a Republican presidential nominee more than 10 percent of the vote since 1988.</p> 
<p>Among the Democrats already vying to succeed her are D.C. Council members Brooke Pinto and Robert White, political strategist Kinney Zalesne and former Norton aide Trent Holbrook.</p> 
<p>One of only two people who have represented D.C. in Congress since the delegate position was established in 1970, Norton made her reputation as a civil rights activist and pioneering attorney for women’s rights. Elected to succeed Walter Fauntroy in 1990, she became known on Capitol Hill as a fierce defender of the city’s self-rule, helping to orchestrate a financial rescue for the city in the 1990s while fending off efforts by congressional Republicans to assert more control over the city.</p> 
<p>In the later decades of her career, she worked to build support for more autonomy for the city government and to secure congressional voting rights for D.C. residents. A bipartisan bid to secure D.C. a full House vote evaporated in 2009, and Norton turned to pushing statehood efforts.</p> 
<p>The House voted to support D.C. statehood in 2020 and 2021, but the effort has not otherwise advanced.</p> 
<p>Decades of improving conditions in the city had led to an increasingly hands-off approach from federal overseers. But that changed in recent years after a post-pandemic surge in crime and Trump’s reelection in 2024 — posing the greatest threat to the city’s autonomy since it was granted partial home rule in 1973.</p> 
<p>Norton was largely absent from the public eye during Trump’s takeover, issuing statements and news releases but not granting interviews or appearing alongside municipal leaders who railed against the Trump administration. When she has made speeches on Capitol Hill, she has read from prepared remarks with halting delivery and with aides close beside her.</p> 
<p>In an episode that raised further questions about her fitness for reelection, Norton was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/24/eleanor-holmes-norton-police-report-00622757" target="_blank">scammed out of thousands of dollars</a> by fraudsters last year. She was described as having “early stages of dementia” in an internal police report that also described a longtime aide as her caretaker with power of attorney.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump’s return supercharges lobbying revenues</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/trump-lobbying-revenues-00744357</link>
      <description>Firms with ties to the administration reaped windfalls, including one that saw a 350 percent revenue bump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f1d6-d1ea-a5df-f1d6d47d0009</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fc/36/936360274e5d827d807a87a23129/k-street-02405.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">J. Scott Applewhite/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>The K Street corridor is seen in northwest Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fc/36/936360274e5d827d807a87a23129/k-street-02405.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Caitlin Oprysko</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Caitlin Oprysko</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump’s second term is already delivering a massive payday for Washington’s top lobbying shops — especially those with close ties to the administration.</p> 
<p>According to disclosures filed this week, Trump's wide-ranging policy upheavals across trade, tax, health care, tech, defense and energy boosted the bottom lines of almost every one of K Street's biggest lobbying firms.</p> 
<p>Thirteen of the largest 20 firms by revenue reported growth of 10 percent or more compared to 2024. In total, they brought in nearly $824 million, up from $595 million during the final year of the Biden administration.</p> 
<p>Several reported their highest-ever annual revenues, including Ballard Partners, Brownstein Hyatt Farber Schreck, BGR Group, Akin Gump Strauss Hauer &amp; Feld and Holland &amp; Knight.</p> 
<p>"The real driver was that it's the most activity that we've seen from a first year of a new administration in a long time," said Holland &amp; Knight partner Paul Stimers, whose firm brought in $54.6 million in lobbying revenues last year.</p> 
<p>While federal lobbying spending <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/news/2025/02/federal-lobbying-set-new-record-in-2024/" target="_blank">has been climbing steadily</a> for the past decade — and the typical Year 1 of an administration also juices revenue — Trump's aggressive use of executive power and influence is supercharging the trend.</p> 
<p>“Every quarter it seems that there are more challenges and opportunities from the administration and Congress,” said Brownstein policy director Nadeam Elshami.</p> 
<p>Some of the firms that saw the most dramatic windfalls were those with close ties to Trump and top administration officials.</p> 
<p>Ballard Partners, which counts Attorney General Pam Bondi and White House chief of staff Susie Wiles among its alumni, signed more than 200 new clients after Trump's election. It led K Street last year with more than $88.3 million in lobbying fees — a 350 percent increase from 2024. </p> 
<p>In the fourth quarter alone, Ballard brought in more revenue than it did in all of 2024. (POLITICO’s parent company, Axel Springer, was a Ballard Partners client for less than two months last year.)</p> 
<p>Ballard contends that it's focused on long-term success, beyond its sharp rise last year and close ties to the current administration.</p> 
<p>“We remain doggedly committed to growing a fiercely bipartisan firm that is built to thrive in Washington’s dynamic political environment for decades to come,” said the firm's founder and president Brian Ballard, who credited his employees for the firm's growth.</p> 
<p>Brownstein, K Street's previous top earner and No. 2 for 2025, brought in $73.9 million in lobbying revenues last year, up from $67.9 million in 2024.</p> 
<p>Coming in third last year was BGR Group, which employed former Wisconsin Republican Rep. Sean Duffy before he became Trump's Secretary of Transportation. It also counts former Trump campaign adviser David Urban as a managing director. BGR reported $71.5 million in lobbying revenues last year, a 58 percent increase from 2024.</p> 
<p>Among the upstart lobbying firms that cashed in on Trump’s second term were Continental Strategy, which was launched in 2021 by former Trump diplomat and adviser Carlos Trujillo. Continental, which also employs a top former aide to Secretary of State Marco Rubio and one of Wiles’ daughters, saw its lobbying revenues skyrocket from $1.8 million in 2024 to more than $27 million in 2025. </p> 
<p>Checkmate Government Relations, which is led by Ches McDowell, a friend of Donald Trump Jr., reported receiving $70,000 from a single client at the end of 2024 but signed 80 clients and brought in more than $21 million in 2025.</p> 
<p>Looking ahead, lobbyists expect trade to continue driving client interest in 2026, especially as businesses await the Supreme Court’s decision on the legality of Trump’s so-called reciprocal tariffs. </p> 
<p>Even as they forecast a slowdown in legislation ahead of the midterm elections, lobbyists say they’ll also remain busy with congressional oversight, the government funding process as well as the administration's latest foreign policy moves.</p> 
<p>“Frankly, the lesson learned going forward is, Don't be surprised,” Elshami said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats are shying away from climate messaging. One of their own is fighting back.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-climate-affordability-trump-00745597</link>
      <description>There’s a schism within the Democratic Party about whether talking about climate change is the right message to win back control of Washington.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f1f4-dabb-ad9f-fffda3950000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/23/8e/20cab1e04de9922f36d8f44fe764/u-s-congress-10611.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse (D-R.I.) walks to a meeting at the U.S. Capitol on Dec. 8, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/23/8e/20cab1e04de9922f36d8f44fe764/u-s-congress-10611.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Amelia Davidson and Kelsey Brugger</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Amelia Davidson and Kelsey Brugger</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of Congress’ loudest climate hawks is trying to fend off a push within his party to abandon calls to combat climate change as left-leaning agenda-setters are plotting to reclaim both chambers of Congress in the midterms.</p> 
<p>"There’s a thing out there called a ‘climate husher,'” Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse, the top Democrat on the Environment and Public Works Committee, posted as part of a long social media thread last week.</p> 
<p>“Anyone who cares about what fossil fuel pollution is doing to Earth’s natural systems needs to ignore these so-called ‘climate hushers’ — people who think Dems should stop talking about climate,” he said.</p> 
<p>In a later interview about his posts, Whitehouse warned these “climate hushers” have also made their way into strategy conversations on Capitol Hill. He noted he’s been present for some of them, which he described as “polling presentations made to the Senate Democratic Caucus in a so-called strategy retreat that didn’t ask about climate change … There’s this massive blind spot.”</p> 
<p>In recent years, Democrats have been handwringing over the best messaging on environmental issues to reach an electorate that cares about “kitchen table” matters – and doesn’t uniformly consider the rapidly warming planet to be one of them. Environmentalists made a strong argument during the 2024 presidential campaign that the climate crisis should be a motivator in electing Kamala Harris — but the contest went to Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Now Democrats are increasingly showing they have decided it’s a losing message to tout the ways in which they’d curb fossil fuel production to thwart the most dire effects of climate change. Instead, they’re choosing to focus on policies that would lower energy costs and lean hard into affordability talking points embraced by Trump and congressional Republicans.</p> 
<p>Whitehouse understands the importance of talking about affordability — for years he’s spoken about the climate crisis as a threat to the global economy.</p> 
<p>His social media thread notes that people are feeling the economic burdens of climate change throughout the country, from home insurance hikes to drops in property values.</p> 
<p>That's the message Democrats should lean into, he said, rather than shy away from.</p> 
<p>“When leaders don’t talk about something, enthusiasm falls among voters,” Whitehouse wrote in his post. “In politics, you can often make your own wind, or you can make your own doldrums.”</p> 
<p>This is something Democrats are grappling with on Capitol Hill. Interviews with a half dozen House and Senate Democrats revealed how many are still struggling with how to discuss climate change, a problem they consider existential but that doesn’t register among voters’ top immediate concerns.</p> 
<p>Some are talking nearly exclusively about competitive prices for clean energy — largely in hopes of beating Republicans at their own messaging game.</p> 
<p>“My theory of the case is that the argument that I’ve been making for 30 years is finally breaking through,” said Rep. Sean Casten (D-Ill.), a former clean energy professional.</p> 
<p>“The urgency of climate change means that we have to focus on it especially when it’s not as salient with the American people, if we are to be the leaders we claim to be,” he added. “But I think that’s largely a separable conversation from what is the best way to talk about it in any given moment, that has the most ability to move public opinion.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Brian Schatz of Hawaii, who is on track to be the next Senate Democratic whip, has a similar perspective.</p> 
<p>Last year, he removed “climate hawk,” along with other self-descriptions, from his bio on X. And during an event this fall affiliated with New York Climate Week, he said that “those of us in the climate community who are used to making a more broad argument about where we are in the sweep of history have to get comfortable making a more immediate argument that says the reason prices are going up is a deliberate policy choice of the Republican Party.”</p> 
<p>Schatz said in a statement last week that he and Whitehouse were united in their ideas around “climate action,” but he also doubled down on the importance of affordability messaging at this time.</p> 
<p>“There are think tanks and advocacy organizations that are dedicated to the proposition that climate action is incompatible with affordable energy, but those factional rivalries have been overtaken by events,” Schatz said. “Cheap is clean, and clean is cheap.”</p> 
<p>Recent actions from the Democrats’ Sustainable Energy and Environment Coalition, or SEEC — of which Casten is vice-chair — have also focused squarely on energy costs and the ability of clean energy to lower Americans’ bills.</p> 
<p>At a SEEC press conference earlier this month meant to respond to the last year of energy and environment policy under President Donald Trump, a roster of climate-focused Democrats spoke nearly exclusively about energy prices. “Trump lied; Energy costs are up,” read the main sign at the presser.</p> 
<p>Rep. Melanie Stansbury (D-N.M.), a member of the House Natural Resources Committee, said in an interview that Democrats need to focus on energy prices because Trump has used that as a justification for executive actions that bolster oil and gas.</p> 
<p>“People, when they see the ways in which the energy policies that are serving big oil are hurting their pocketbooks, it makes it more tangible for why folks should care, in addition to the welfare of the planet,” Stansbury said.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Republicans have picked up on the Democrats’ shift in talking points and have used it to their advantage.</p> 
<p>“You actually see on the left, this debate going on right now, where a lot of people within the Democratic Party, they are talking about how they’ve lost the narrative, or the culture war, on climate,” EPA Administrator Lee Zeldin said on Fox Business this month.</p> 
<p>Left-leaning thinkers and independent analysts have also argued that Democrats may have gone too far in following the lead of environmental groups they say were out of touch with most Americans.</p> 
<p>Columnist Matt Yglesias argued in a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/18/opinion/democrats-liberals-oil-gas-industry.html" target="_blank"><i><u>New York Times</u></i><u> op-ed</u></a> that Democrats should not be hostile to oil and gas. Longtime energy expert Daniel Yergin wrote in <i>Foreign Affairs</i> about the “<a href="https://www.foreignaffairs.com/united-states/troubled-energy-transition-yergin-orszag-arya" target="_blank"><u>troubled energy transition</u></a>” and the need for a “pragmatic path” forward. And Veteran Democratic operative Adam Jentleson started the think tank <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/03/dems-are-quietly-forming-a-think-tank-to-help-them-win-again-00381601" target="_blank"><u>the Searchlight Institute</u></a> to curb the influence of the “groups” on party positions, including climate.</p> 
<p>Rep. Kathy Castor of Florida, the top Democrat on the Energy and Commerce’s Energy Subcommittee, downplayed the notion that congressional Democrats were at odds over how to message on climate change. Talking about affordability need not negate the focus on the impact of climate change, she said.</p> 
<p>“I think they are one in the same,” Castor said. “Take my community in Florida. We’re still recovering from Hurricane Helen and Milton and people understand that those storms were supercharged because the Gulf was very, very hot, very warm. And the rain was unlike anything we’ve ever seen. So they are trying to afford rebuilding their homes and paying their property insurance and also suffering higher rate increases.”</p> 
<p>Whitehouse in an interview acknowledged some shortcomings to Democrats’ past depictions of climate change “as sort of a moral imperative, as an intangible thing floating out there, something that will affect polar bears,” but said the solution wasn’t to be silent in calling out the harmful impacts of fossil fuel emissions and the influence of oil and gas companies on Trump administration policy.</p> 
<p>Ultimately, there's only so much he can do to press his case. In recent months he has organized forums on climate change as the senior Democrat on the Environment and Public Works panel, toured red states to talk about rising insurance rates related to natural disasters spurred by global warming and said he has commissioned his own polling on the issue.</p> 
<p>Those activities, plus delivering speeches and crafting social media posts, are among the limits of what he can achieve with his party in the minority and his colleagues making their own messaging choices.</p> 
<p>He isn't giving up.</p> 
<p>“Democrats and environmental groups’ climate messaging for years has been crap, and so if you go back to that crap messaging, obviously it’s not going to succeed,” Whitehouse said. “But that doesn’t mean that the alternative is to throw in the towel.”</p> 
<p><i>Andres Picon and Timothy Cama contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-24T19:20:28-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Shutdown risk grows as Democrats revolt after Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642</link>
      <description>Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said "Senate Democrats will not provide the votes" to fund immigration enforcement, part of a six-bill package set for action next week.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f25d-d452-a99b-fbffdaf10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 18:39:15 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/47/26/1beb046d49468116fc0a3e55f93f/u-s-congress-30162.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Catherine Cortez Masto of Nevada is among the Democrats who previously supported funding bills who are now opposing DHS appropriations.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/47/26/1beb046d49468116fc0a3e55f93f/u-s-congress-30162.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress is on a path toward a partial government shutdown next week after Senate Democrats vowed to oppose Department of Homeland Security funding following the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">killing of a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident</a> by federal agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said in a statement Saturday night that Democrats would not help advance the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill spending package</a> set for consideration next week as long as it includes DHS funding. Republicans will need Democratic support in order to clear a 60-vote hurdle to advance the funding bill.</p> 
<p>“Senate Democrats will not provide the votes to proceed to the appropriations bill if the DHS funding bill is included,” Schumer said, adding that he would personally vote “no.”</p> 
<p>Congress has already passed full-year funding for some agencies — including the departments of Agriculture, Commerce, Interior and Justice — but not for several of the largest, including the Pentagon. Temporary funding for those departments, representing more than 75 percent of federal discretionary spending, expires midnight Friday.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats will hold a conference call Sunday evening, according to a Democratic aide granted anonymity to discuss the private meeting. The call will give them a chance to discuss next steps with the Senate stuck out of town <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/senate-vote-shutdown-snow-00745282" target="_blank">until at least Tuesday</a> because of the massive winter storm affecting much of the country. </p> 
<p>Earlier in the day, as news of the Minneapolis shooting spread, several Democratic senators who had previously voted to advance government funding measures under President Donald Trump vowed to oppose DHS funding this time. Funding for ICE and Border Patrol, the agencies involved in the Minnesota operation, is included in the pending Senate bill.</p> 
<p>“I am voting against any funding for DHS until and unless more controls are put in place to hold ICE accountable,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/201768" data-person-id="201768">Brian Schatz</a> (D-Hawaii) <a href="https://x.com/brianschatz/status/2015171159164096863?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">in a statement Saturday</a>. “These repeated incidents of violence across the country are unlawful, needlessly escalatory, and making all of us less safe.”</p> 
<p>Schatz helped advance a funding bill in March, and Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259552" data-person-id="259552">Catherine Cortez Masto</a> (D-Nev.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259494" data-person-id="259494">Jacky Rosen</a> (D-Nev.), who voted to end the 43-day shutdown in November, also both said Saturday that they will oppose the DHS funding bill.</p> 
<p>“I have the responsibility to hold the Trump Administration accountable when I see abuses of power — like we are seeing from ICE right now,” <a href="https://x.com/SenJackyRosen/status/2015172486392857019?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">Rosen said on X</a>. “That is why I’ll be voting against any government funding package that contains the bill that funds this agency, until we have guardrails in place to curtail these abuses of power and ensure more accountability and transparency.”</p> 
<p>The DHS bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402" target="_blank">passed the House Thursday 220-207</a>, with only seven Democrats voting for it. But Republican House leaders merged it with five other bills funding the departments of Defense, Health and Human Services and State, among others, sending it to the Senate as one package.</p> 
<p>More than half of the 47-member Democratic caucus has already vowed to oppose the package, many before Saturday’s shooting. And that number is growing as Democrats’ re-evaluate the legislation in the wake of the shooting and as they face pressure from House Democrats and their Senate colleagues, not to mention outside voices close to the party base.</p> 
<p>Abdul El-Sayed, a Democratic candidate seeking a Senate seat in Michigan, said in an interview Saturday he saw no way for any Democrat to justify a vote for DHS funding.</p> 
<p>“How many more people do they need to shoot?” he asked.</p> 
<p>A group of senators, including <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a> (D-Conn.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189610" data-person-id="189610">Alex Padilla</a> (D-Calif.), have been whipping colleagues for days to oppose the DHS bill, according to two aides granted anonymity to discuss their private effort. And two people familiar with the plans said House Democrats are scheduled to hold a private caucus call Sunday morning to discuss a response to the shooting.</p> 
<p>Cortez Masto, in a statement, suggested dropping the Department of Homeland Security bill from the larger package, noting there is a “bipartisan agreement on 96% of the budget.”</p> 
<p>“Let’s pass the remaining five bipartisan bills and fund essential agencies while we continue to fight for a Department of Homeland Security that respects Americans’ constitutional rights and preserves federal law enforcement’s essential role to keep us safe,” she said.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51223" data-person-id="51223">Jack Reed</a> (D-R.I.) said he would agree to “immediately pass” the other five bills while providing “short term funding for DHS so the Senate can fully debate and vote on common sense reforms to ICE that bolster the rule of law.”</p> 
<p>But stripping out the DHS bill before the Friday deadline would require every senator to agree — something Republicans aren’t likely to be able to get. Any changes to the package, meanwhile, will require sending it back to the House, which has already left town until after the shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>Instead, Republicans believe it's up to Democrats to decide whether or not to vote against the funding package and avoid a partial shutdown. GOP leaders aren’t currently expected to bring the House back early from its break, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy.</p> 
<p>Democratic aides, meanwhile, privately acknowledged Saturday that the odds of a shutdown were rising, though some questioned what alternatives are available if Democrats block the pending six-bill package.</p> 
<p>Heading into the weekend, some Democrats acknowledged they were conflicted — including Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151823" data-person-id="151823">Chris Coons</a> (D-Del.), a senior appropriator who has championed Congress’ ability to use the spending bills to reverse many of Trump’s foreign aid cuts.</p> 
<p>“I don't know the details of exactly what the language is in the Homeland Security bills in terms of trying to hold ICE accountable and trying to minimize their misconduct, and I don’t know whether it is worse to have a continuing resolution and how that might be misused,” Coons told reporters Friday.</p> 
<p><i>Adam Wren, Meredith Lee Hill and Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate cancels Monday vote as shutdown deadline looms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/senate-vote-shutdown-snow-00745282</link>
      <description>The Senate will instead hold its first vote of the week on Tuesday as Washington prepares for a weekend snowstorm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ecd0-d9a8-a7bf-eed233ce0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:45:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/3f/03/238e7b8b486fa398bb4c53a73464/u-s-congress-90876.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune speaks with reporters as he walks into his office at the U.S. Capitol on Jan. 12.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/3f/03/238e7b8b486fa398bb4c53a73464/u-s-congress-90876.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate is canceling its scheduled Monday night vote as the District of Columbia braces for a winter storm that will dump snow and ice on a significant swath of the country — with just days left for the chamber to avert a partial government shutdown.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/f340f334-a33f-49d3-a476-6eb321780d94" target="_blank">John Thune</a>’s office announced the scheduling change Friday, following days of private speculation among senators who have already received warnings of travel delays from airlines and wondered how and when they would get back to Washington.</p> 
<p>The Senate had been expected to vote Monday at 5:30 p.m. Instead, that vote is being moved to Tuesday at 5:30 p.m. “due to the impending weather event that is expected to impact a significant portion of the country,” Thune spokesperson Ryan Wrasse <a href="https://x.com/RWrasse/status/2014801309715538174?s=20" target="_blank">announced on X</a>.</p> 
<p>Monday’s vote isn’t related to the looming Jan. 30 government funding cliff, and Wrasse added that “the importance of funding the remaining portions of the government by Friday remains the same.”</p> 
<p>But the scheduling change will give senators a truncated timeline for haggling out a deal in person to avoid a shutdown of multiple federal agencies at the end of next week.</p> 
<p>The Senate is due to take up six funding bills already advanced by the House, which has left town for its previously-scheduled recess. Even though the six bills have been merged into <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">one package</a>, Senate leaders already needed all 100 members to cut a deal to speed up the process for moving the funding bills through the system in order to meet the Jan. 30 deadline.</p> 
<p>If the Senate fails to meet that deadline, a significant portion of the federal government would shutter, including the Pentagon, the Department of Homeland Security and the State Department, among others.</p> 
<p>Republicans and Democrats privately expect the package to pass the Senate in time to avoid a partial shutdown. That will require it to get support from at least eight Democratic votes, and potentially more, in order to clear a 60-vote hurdle to advance the bill. A growing number of Senate Democrats, however, have vowed to oppose the legislation because it includes <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">funding for the Department of Homeland Security</a> amid increasing unease over the administration’s immigration enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>“We are not living in normal times. The President is acting chaotically and unlawfully and we shouldn’t give his deranged decisions the imprimatur of congressional approval by passing this legislation without significant amendment,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175490" target="_blank" data-person-id="175490">Tim Kaine</a> (D-Va.), who was one of the eight members of the Democratic caucus who helped end last year’s prolonged shutdown, said in a statement Friday.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151823" target="_blank" data-person-id="151823">Chris Coons</a> (D-Del.), a member of the Appropriations Committee, separately told reporters Friday he was undecided on how he would vote for the six-bill spending package.</p> 
<p>Republicans will also need to reach an agreement with their own members to move forward expeditiously. According to two people granted anonymity to disclose private conversations, a band of conservatives — which includes Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" target="_blank" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.) — is pushing leadership for a vote to remove earmarks from the spending package.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wesley Hunt dodges questions on spotty voting record</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/wesley-hunt-voting-record-00742874</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e7e5-d9a8-a7bf-e7e7dba30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 18:04:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Wesley Hunt refused to answer repeated questions about his spotty voting record Thursday after he appeared in the Capitol for the first time in two weeks.</p> 
<p>The Texas Republican has missed dozens of votes this Congress as he seeks the Senate seat now held by fellow Republican John Cornyn. His last recorded vote before providing the decisive vote Thursday to kill a measure constraining President Donald Trump’s war powers in Venezuela was on Jan. 7.</p> 
<p>“Y’all be safe, y’all be safe — the storm is coming,” he said, referring to the upcoming winter weather, as reporters peppered him with questions about why he has missed so many House votes.</p> 
<p>Earlier in the day a Hunt spokesperson said he was on his way back to Washington at Speaker Mike Johnson’s request after being told by another, unnamed GOP leader “that his presence in D.C. was not needed this week.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
