<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/politics-news.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:47:29 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>RNC pushed Bovino’s false claims as talking points hours before his removal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/rnc-bovino-ice-talking-points-memo-00751117</link>
      <description>A new memo from the RNC reveals how the party wanted to frame the fallout over a second fatal shooting in Minnesota — but shows how quickly the messaging is changing in real time</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01e7-d1ea-a5de-31e71acc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:47:29 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/23/69/5c83203d48a4a561ee35d2e77a82/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-95123.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Angelina Katsanis/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>U.S. Border Patrol Cmdr. Gregory Bovino walks with federal agents outside a convenience store on Jan. 21, 2026, in Minneapolis.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/23/69/5c83203d48a4a561ee35d2e77a82/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-95123.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The RNC distributed talking points highlighting Border Patrol commander Greg Bovino’s false statements about the killing of Alex Pretti just hours before he was sidelined by President Donald Trump — a sign of how quickly the party’s messaging has shifted on the events in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-01f7-d9a8-a7be-87f729550001" target="_blank">The memo</a>, sent to party surrogates midday on Monday and obtained by POLITICO, encouraged Republicans to cast blame for the shooting on Democrats for “inciting protestors to attack and aggressively confront law enforcement in Minneapolis.” The talking points also delve into administration officials’ account of how the shooting took place, including Bovino’s Saturday comments that the U.S. citizen killed by immigration agents “wanted to do maximum damage and massacre law enforcement." The government’s initial account has been called into question by videos shot by witnesses as well as analyses conducted by The <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-federal-agents-video.html" target="_blank">New York Times</a>, The <a href="https://www.wsj.com/livecoverage/minneapolis-shooting-alex-pretti/card/wsj-visual-investigation-videos-contradict-u-s-account-of-minneapolis-shooting-lrNpSm80hhnrxVxEy7kO?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqeMfXHa-r5f_coUtyWU2TDX_pUwGzct7ciQYXf_QuPsBeDX-5YqhaQBv69a5x8%3D&amp;gaa_ts=69793983&amp;gaa_sig=DSspyLz-8HCs-CWTnsRr3TjzrIBrFPt1TzRmBugZwzesss81GIE8xUHvg0x1nkczT8b97u7hD1yc8-EZ9pRSsg%3D%3D" target="_blank">Wall Street Journal</a>, and others.</p> 
<p>The memo includes the talking point that “Agents attempted to disarm the individual as he violently resisted. Fearing for his life and the lives and safety of fellow officers, a Border Patrol agent fired defensive shots.” Video from the scene appears to contradict that statement.</p> 
<p>The whiplash between the RNC’s promotion of Bovino’s comments and his sudden removal shortly afterward from the federal operation in Minneapolis shows how the administration and other Republicans scrambled to contain the fallout from the shooting. A significant number of elected GOP officials have called for an official investigation into the matter, a rare and notable break with the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Immediately following the shooting on Saturday, high-profile administration officials like Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem publicly described Pretti, a 37-year-old nurse, as a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/leavitt-briefing-minneapolis-trump-walz-alex-pretti-00747495" target="_blank">“domestic terrorist.”</a></p> 
<p>By that evening, however, Trump was already more cautious in his description of what had transpired. <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/policy/trump-says-administration-is-reviewing-everything-about-minneapolis-shooting-a501f48e?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqcZVoLjAgLS_LENGeVH-NWCqZFB9zgFqjGu85ixp9xYdgMDpDSXuPw2gtxFkd8%3D&amp;gaa_ts=69792383&amp;gaa_sig=nUi-HJXipOVQ2Rgqh7-IB_Dhu-dAq4sY2s6SwobYlLst1e3NtzUYThMdV4gHRtW4R2uldBGkMhRutTfX9moJxA%3D%3D" target="_blank">In an interview that day with The Wall Street Journal</a>, the president did not answer directly when asked whether the officer involved in the shooting did the right thing and said his administration is “reviewing everything.”</p> 
<p>Speaking at a restaurant in Iowa on Tuesday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/trump-pretti-shouldnt-have-been-carrying-a-gun-00750241" target="_blank">Trump said that he hadn’t heard the assessment</a> from Noem and others in his administration, such as deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller, that Pretti was a “domestic terrorist” or assassin, but said that “certainly he shouldn’t have been carrying a gun.” Pretti had a permit to carry a firearm, according to Minnesota officials.</p> 
<p>Monday’s talking points memo notably omits reference to any comments made by Noem since the shooting took place. While the White House has publicly stood behind Noem, administration allies have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/kristi-noem-scrutiny-minneapolis-shootings-00748618" target="_blank">increasingly placed blame on the secretary’s handling of the chaotic crackdown in Minnesota</a> as calls among Democrats for her impeachment have grown. <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/thom-tillis-kristi-noem-fired-00750580" target="_blank">On Tuesday evening</a>, Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said Noem should be “out of a job,” while Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said she “should go.”</p> 
<p>Trump announced on Monday morning that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">border czar Tom Homan would go to Minneapolis</a> to oversee the administration’s immigration operation there, a move seen as an acknowledgement that DHS’s leadership had mishandled the situation. Hours later, Bovino had been removed from his post as commander at large, <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/2026/01/greg-bovino-demoted-minneapolis-border-patrol/685770/" target="_blank">according to The Atlantic</a>.</p> 
<p>Kiersten Pels, a spokesperson for the RNC, would not confirm the authenticity of the memo but echoed its overall sentiment in a written statement. “Democrats incited this violence by encouraging protesters to confront law enforcement,” she wrote. “Democrats are demonizing ICE and threatening to defund DHS instead of condemning attacks on officers – while President Trump and Republicans stand with law enforcement and public safety.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s approval rating on immigration has dropped significantly since he first came into office, with only 39% of Americans now approving of the president’s handling of immigration, according to a <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/trumps-immigration-approval-drops-record-low-reutersipsos-poll-finds-2026-01-26/" target="_blank">recent Reuters/Ipsos poll</a>. The high-profile shooting in Minneapolis, following the fatal shooting earlier this month of Renée Good in the city, has only brought more attention to the administration’s goal of a mass deportation.</p> 
<p>Democrats in the Senate have pledged to vote against funding DHS in a crucial vote later this week unless the bill is amended to add guardrails for the agency — and the RNC’s talking points seize on the potential for a partial government shutdown as well.</p> 
<p>“Now, Democrats are threatening to defund law enforcement later this week by refusing to pass a DHS funding bill,” the memo concludes.</p> 
<p>“While Democrats will stand in the way of ICE and law enforcement to defend terrorists and criminal aliens, President Trump and Republicans are working to keep our communities safe.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T20:48:09-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Janet Mills: Maine ‘will not be intimidated’ amid ongoing ICE surge</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/janet-mills-ice-raids-state-address-00751216</link>
      <description>The Maine governor delivered her annual address as immigrant enforcement surges in the state and she gears up for a Senate run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01fa-dabb-ad9c-3fffe7d00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:28:03 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d4/04/c7bfa20b481c83eedd260ece2fbf/20260127-janet-mills-sots.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jessica Piper/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Maine Gov. Janet Mills speaks during her State of the State address at the State House in Augusta, Maine, on Jan. 27, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d4/04/c7bfa20b481c83eedd260ece2fbf/20260127-janet-mills-sots.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AUGUSTA, Maine — Gov. Janet Mills issued a dire warning in her annual address to state lawmakers Tuesday night: The federal immigration raids sweeping the state are part of an ongoing nationwide attack on democracy.</p> 
<p>The speech from Mills, who is a leading Democratic challenger to Republican Sen. Susan Collins, marks perhaps the most prominent example of how the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration raids have upended communities — and potentially electoral politics — around the country. The crackdown has become a political crisis for the White House in recent days following two fatal shootings by federal officers in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“Today, I say to the people of Maine: We will not be intimidated. We will not be silenced,” Mills said, to cheers from the Democratic side of the chamber. “And to anyone outside these halls, including any federal officials, I say: If you seek to harm Maine people, you will have to go through me first.”</p> 
<p>The Democratic governor’s defiant State of the State address on Tuesday came as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/ice-maine-dhs-trump-00740138" target="_blank">a sweeping ICE operation in Maine</a> has prompted widespread protests throughout the state since it began last week. The killing of a protester in Minneapolis by federal immigration officers this weekend has amplified those pressures — and the political stakes.</p> 
<p>Mills addressed the ICE operation directly in the opening of her speech, commending the “moral clarity” of Mainers who had risen to “protect their neighbors and their communities against federal agents who seek to intimidate and silence us.”</p> 
<p>Federal officials indicated Monday that <a href="https://www.mainepublic.org/immigration/2026-01-26/ice-says-its-arrested-more-than-200-people-since-last-week-in-maine-operation" target="_blank">more than 200 people had been arrested</a> in the immigrant enforcement action in Maine they’re calling Operation Catch of the Day. That effort has followed a pattern of surges in other localities under President Donald Trump’s aggressive revamped enforcement operations.</p> 
<p>Mills, who has made opposition to Trump a centerpiece of her Senate campaign, cast the immigration enforcement operation as part of a broader federal overreach that threatens American democracy in Tuesday’s speech — warning “the very idea of America is in peril.” She accused federal officials of arresting people not on “public safety grounds but based on quotas, on skin color, on accents, and religion and ethnic origin.”</p> 
<p>“For those who may be unconcerned by the federal government’s abuses of today, affecting our state, I only ask you to consider this — what happens when the federal government finds you to be the problem tomorrow?” Mills said, her voice rising and cracking with emotion in a departure from the more soft-spoken tone she had adopted while ticking through the policy points of her speech.</p> 
<p>Much of Mills’ speech was met with partisan reaction in the House chamber in Augusta, with some Republican lawmakers audibly pushing back at Mills’ notion that ICE activities amounted to an abuse of power. Earlier in her speech, Republican state Rep. Jim Thorne interrupted Mills’ call for the federal government to enact universal health care, suggesting it was out of place for a State of the State speech.</p> 
<p>Mills’ address to the legislature came days after <a href="https://www.maine.gov/governor/mills/news/governor-janet-mills-statement-following-another-killing-minnesota-hands-federal-agents-2026" target="_blank">she asked for a meeting with Trump</a> to call for a withdrawal of ICE agents from Maine. The Maine governor famously confronted Trump at the Oval Office last year over his administration’s intent to withhold federal funding from Maine over the state’s allowance of transgender students’ participation in youth sports.</p> 
<p>The politics of Trump’s deportation campaign have rapidly evolved in the wake of two shootings in Minnesota, putting ICE at the forefront of both the Democratic primary between Mills and political newcomer Graham Platner, and their efforts to unseat Collins.</p> 
<p>Collins — who has conflicted with the Trump administration more than most Republicans — <a href="https://www.mainepublic.org/politics/2026-01-27/susan-collins-asks-dhs-to-pause-immigration-enforcement-surge-in-maine-and-minnesota" target="_blank">told Maine Public</a> on Tuesday that she had asked Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem to pause the immigration enforcement surge in both Maine and Minnesota, calling it sweeping and indiscriminate. Those detained in Maine have included a corrections officer trainee who the Cumberland County sheriff <a href="https://www.mainepublic.org/courts-and-crime/2026-01-22/cumberland-county-sheriff-kevin-joyce-denounces-actions-by-ice-agents-in-maine" target="_blank">said had a legal work permit</a>.</p> 
<p>Mills has called on Collins to join with Democrats in holding up DHS funding until ICE changes course. Minutes before her speech, she <a href="https://x.com/JanetMillsforME/status/2016278711759253867?s=20" target="_blank">castigated Collins</a> on social media for <a href="https://x.com/JanetMillsforME/status/2016299356584890596?s=20" target="_blank">not calling for Noem’s ouster</a> and for “pushing to give the agency more funding without any accountability.” Collins oversees ICE’s purse strings as the Senate’s top appropriator, and she has advocated for passing the DHS funding bill as a Saturday shutdown deadline looms, saying it includes new guardrails for ICE such as body cameras and training and would fund other key agencies such as FEMA and the Coast Guard.</p> 
<p>The Democratic governor has also faced criticism from her left, with Platner attacking her Monday for her handling of a bill last year that sought to limit law enforcement cooperation with federal immigration authorities.</p> 
<p>Platner blasted Mills in an interview Monday for letting the bill idle, saying the governor “stymied the state’s ability to prepare” for the surge of federal immigration agents that “many in the immigrant rights community and the immigrant community knew … was coming” by preventing the law from taking effect sooner.</p> 
<p>Mills allowed the bill to become law without her signature in December, which means it does not officially take effect until after the end of this year’s legislative session. However, the Portland Press Herald <a href="https://www.pressherald.com/2026/01/21/a-new-anti-ice-law-isnt-in-effect-yet-maine-state-police-are-already-following-it/" target="_blank">reported earlier this month</a> that Maine’s public safety commissioner had implemented a directive to immediately comply with the law’s provisions.</p> 
<p>Platner dismissed her escalating rhetoric against ICE as politically convenient.</p> 
<p>“For the governor now to kind of just read the tea leaves and realize that people are actually really angry about this and want to see action, and then suddenly be like ‘I’m fighting this tooth and nail’ while not even fighting tooth and nail … yeah, that’s going to be a pretty clear distinction for the voters of Maine,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T18:32:33-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Virginia state court blocks Democrats’ redistricting push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/virginia-redistricting-blocked-court-ruling-00750060</link>
      <description>The ruling is a major setback for Democrats’ efforts to redraw the lines in the state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0152-d452-a99e-69fea57c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:19:44 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b1/27/17417f2b4032af94d8236dd2b98a/election-2019-redistricting-45464.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Matthew Barakat/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>A mobile billboard urges voters to cast ballots for Democrats outside Centreville High School in Clifton, Va. on Nov. 5, 2019.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b1/27/17417f2b4032af94d8236dd2b98a/election-2019-redistricting-45464.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard and Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard and Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A Virginia state court blocked Democrats’ plans to redistrict this year, a blow to the party’s hopes of redrawing the state’s congressional lines ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>Jack Hurley Jr., a judge on the Tazewell County circuit court, ruled that Democrats did <a href="https://www.virginiascope.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/CL25001582-00-PO-95_Certified.pdf?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email" target="_blank"><u>not follow the right procedure</u></a> to approve the proposed constitutional amendment that would allow for the last-minute redraw of the state’s lines.</p> 
<p>Democrats are expected to appeal the decision. But the ruling is still a major loss for the party in the ongoing mid-decade redistricting fight, and one that could — if ultimately upheld — block the party from picking up as many as four seats in next year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>Democrats in the Legislature first passed a measure to take up redistricting <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2025/10/31/virginia-senate-approves-mid-decade-redistricting-amendment-in-party-line-vote/" target="_blank"><u>in October of last year</u></a>, utilizing a special session left open by then-Gov. Glenn Youngkin. Lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/virginia-redistricting-legislature-00733644" target="_blank"><u>took up the issue again in January</u></a>, finalizing the plan to put the issue before voters ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>But Hurley said using the still-open special session was not allowed because early voting in last year’s elections had already begun, and state law requires the Legislature to pass proposed constitutional amendments both before and after an election. Hurley also ruled that the proposed constitutional amendment was not properly noticed in state courts.</p> 
<p>The judge also noted that lawmakers in the special session passed a procedural resolution along party lines, with the Democrat-controlled legislature delivering the decisive votes for the resolution’s passage. Because lawmakers did not vote unanimously, as is required under the Legislature’s own rules, and did not pass it by a two-thirds Senate majority, it was a violation of the rules governing a special session.</p> 
<p>“Certinaly, both houses of the Commonwealth’s legislature are required to follow their own rules and resolutions,” Hurley wrote.</p> 
<p>The Republican plaintiffs in the suit issued a statement praising the court’s ruling, calling it a “decisive victory for the rule of law” but also noting this legal challenge was not about partisanship, rather the process the majority used in attempting to rewrite Virginia’s Constitution.</p> 
<p>"The court confirmed that Democrat legislative leaders unlawfully expanded a Special Session, violated their own rules, and attempted to force through a redistricting constitutional amendment while Virginians were already voting,” said Del. Terry Kilgore, the top Republican in the Virginia House, state Sen. Minority Leader Ryan McDougle and former Rep. Eric Cantor (R-Va.) said in a joint statement Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Virginia had been seen as the crown jewel in Democrats' redistricting fight, especially as state Republicans in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/desantis-florida-redistricting-special-session-00713882" target="_blank"><u>GOP-led Florida eye midcycle redistricting</u></a> later this year. Currently in Virginia, Democrats control six congressional seats and Republicans hold five. Virginia Democrats, had been forging ahead with their plans to unveil a proposed map by their self-imposed deadline of Jan. 31, with the goal of holding a special election to approve the maps in spring.</p> 
<p>Democrats strongly criticized Hurley’s ruling.</p> 
<p>“This is a clear attempt to confuse voters and block them from having a say,” said Karen Charles Dongo, who is heading Virginians for Fair Elections, the Democrat-affiliated group that launched this month to urge the state's voters to pass a pending ballot measure. “We’re prepared for what comes next, and Virginians deserve both the right to vote and the chance to level the playing field.”</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for the top Democrats in the Virginia legislature, state Sen. Majority Leader Scott Surovell and state House Speaker Don Scott, did not respond to requests for comment on whether the ruling will impact the release of their proposed maps.</p> 
<p>But in a joint statement along with other top Virginia Democrats on Tuesday, the group struck a defiant tone and promised to continue with plans to redraw maps, suggesting the ruling was but a minor blip in their quest to deliver what could be a 10-1 map that favors their party.</p> 
<p>“Nothing that happened today will dissuade us from continuing to move forward and put this matter directly to the voters,” the Democratic lawmakers said. “We will be appealing this ruling immediately and we expect to prevail.”</p> 
<p>Julie Merz, who heads up the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, suggested the court overreached. </p> 
<p>"This rogue decision is a disappointing, but temporary setback issued by a lower court that will be immediately appealed — where we're confident it will be overturned," Merz said in a statement. "The order issued today has no constitutional basis, but is instead a desperate attempt to keep electoral power out of the hands of Virginia voters."<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T13:35:55-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Philip Glass pulls new symphony from Kennedy Center</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/philip-glass-symphony-kennedy-center-00749464</link>
      <description>He joins a growing list of artists who have canceled performances at the beleaguered institution this year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-008d-d452-a99e-69ff067f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:15:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/47/2d/49940ec34b348b47795ef035ec08/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2041954554">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ilya S. Savenok/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Bowen Yang, left, and Philip Glass are seen backstage during the 37th Annual Tibet House US Benefit Concert at Carnegie Hall on Feb. 26, 2024, in New York City.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/47/2d/49940ec34b348b47795ef035ec08/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2041954554" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Famed American composer Philip Glass on Tuesday announced he is pulling the premiere of his newest symphony, titled “Lincoln,” from the Kennedy Center, becoming the latest performer to cut ties with the beleaguered institution since its takeover by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>“Symphony No. 15 is a portrait of Abraham Lincoln, and the values of the Kennedy Center today are in direct conflict with the message of the Symphony,” Glass said <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DUBSBMejT_5/?igsh=MTM5NGVmcXh4YnYzZg==" target="_blank">in a post on social media</a>. “Therefore, I feel an obligation to withdraw this Symphony premiere from the Kennedy Center under its current leadership.”</p> 
<p>He joins a growing list of artists who have canceled performances at the Kennedy Center since Trump’s overhaul of Washington’s premier arts center. Grammy winner Renee Fleming canceled performances set for May, <a href="https://www.kennedy-center.org/nso/home/2025-2026/gaffigan/" target="_blank">the institution announced on its website</a>. More performers, including banjo player Béla Fleck and singer Sonia De Los Santos, as well as groups such as the Martha Graham Dance Company and the Seattle Children’s Theater, have also canceled planned shows.</p> 
<p>Trump has made rebranding the Kennedy Center a priority since returning to the White House early last year. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/07/donald-trump-kennedy-center-014498" target="_blank">axed several members from the center’s board</a> and installed himself as chair in February 2025, later bringing on longtime ally Richard <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/10/trump-ric-grenell-kennedy-center-00203484" target="_blank">Grenell to serve as interim executive director</a>.</p> 
<p>In December, the newly reformed Kennedy Center’s board voted to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/trump-kennedy-center-00698140" target="_blank">add the president’s name</a> to the building. One lawmaker, Rep. Joyce Beatty (D-Ohio), an ex officio member of the board, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/kennedy-center-lawsuit-trump-00704327" target="_blank">sued in protest</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump has also taken a personal interest in a refurbishment of the Center, including overseeing details <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115787817857959030" target="_blank">down to the theater’s armrests</a>.</p> 
<p>Glass, 88, is one of the country’s most celebrated living composers, <a href="https://www.eno.org/discover-opera/articles/the-beginners-guide-to-philip-glass/" target="_blank">an early pioneer of minimalism</a> in classical music and famous in part for scores in films such as 2002’s "The Hours" and "The Truman Show," starring Jim Carrey.</p> 
<p>“We have no place for politics in the arts, and those calling for boycotts based on politics are making the wrong decision," Roma Daravi, the institution's vice president of public relations, said in a statement. "We have not cancelled a single show. Leftist activists are pushing artists to cancel but the public wants artists to perform and create—not cancel under pressure from political insiders that benefit from creating division.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How a Democratic heavyweight is using AI in the midterms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/american-bridge-opposition-research-ai-00747243</link>
      <description>American Bridge 21st Century is publishing its research for everyone to see ahead of the midterms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc04-d452-a99b-fdfea31b0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/da/1f/59b5d43848958d4f1d12f634434c/gettyimages-1230110704-1.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Al Drago/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>American Bridge released opposition research on President Donald Trump online in 2020. They have bigger plans for the midterms.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/da/1f/59b5d43848958d4f1d12f634434c/gettyimages-1230110704-1.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A Democratic opposition research powerhouse is putting massive troves of its work product online ahead of the midterms. And it’s using artificial intelligence to help everyone from campaigns to podcasters figure out how to navigate it.</p> 
<p>The project from American Bridge 21st Century, shared first with POLITICO, reflects an expansion of its efforts ahead of the 2026 midterms — as well as the evolving nature of political campaigning, including oppo research, in an increasingly fragmented media environment.</p> 
<p>“Swing voters are generally speaking getting their information very ambiently,” American Bridge President Pat Dennis said in an interview. </p> 
<p>A challenge in recent election cycles, he said, has not been a lack of opposition research, but rather how to best convey it when more voters are getting political news from podcasts, social media influencers or group chats. “If people can’t find it or read it, it’s no good,” Dennis said.</p> 
<p>The new tool, <a href="https://research-books.com/" target="_blank">titled Research Books</a>, is a public-facing website featuring opposition research on dozens of Republican candidates in races that American Bridge has identified as crucial to deciding control of Congress. It also includes select statewide candidates.</p> 
<p>Pages for each candidate feature messaging around key votes, candidate-specific research and — in some races — videos from Democratic trackers and sample media based on the oppo that closely resemble campaign ads.</p> 
<p>It also includes an AI-powered search tool that aims to bring together different sources about a candidate into cohesive messaging. (The AI agent only probes the super PAC’s internal database, not external sources or the wider internet.) </p> 
<p>Results from the search link back to original sources, which include news articles, videos and public records. The tool also integrates with other external large language model platforms such as ChatGPT.</p> 
<p>The notion of publishing opposition research files online, rather than keeping them closely held by party operatives for strategic deployment, is not entirely new for American Bridge. Ahead of the 2020 election, the group <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/08/07/american-bridge-trump-oppo-book-392536" target="_blank">posted 1,043 pages of opposition research</a> about President Donald Trump online for use by other Democratic groups. </p> 
<p>Sharing such research publicly is a way for super PACs to avoid running afoul of campaign finance laws that prohibit direction coordination.</p> 
<p>Because the new research tool is publicly available online, it could similarly be used by Democratic campaigns or other outside groups — though American Bridge hopes the uptake is broader than that, including among influencers and voters.</p> 
<p>For its initial public rollout, Research Books includes 15 GOP House incumbents in seats Democrats are hoping to flip this year, along with Republican Senate candidates in four seats Democrats are trying to flip, as well as Georgia, where Democratic Sen. Jon Ossoff is seeking reelection.</p> 
<p>The initial list also includes 15 candidates for governor or attorney general in key states like Arizona, Michigan, Nevada, Pennsylvania, Georgia, New Hampshire and Iowa.</p> 
<p>The inclusion of attorney general candidates, newer territory for American Bridge, reflects in part the greater role that they have played in suing the Trump administration, Dennis said. He expects the tool to include more races and candidates as the midterms near, with the super PAC seeking to help Democrats cast a broad net.</p> 
<p>“There are times where opposition research can fundamentally reshape a race, so we prefer to take an expansive view on this,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klobuchar delays governor campaign launch as Border Patrol killing upends Minnesota</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/klobuchar-delays-governor-campaign-launch-as-border-patrol-killing-upends-minnesota-00748621</link>
      <description>Before Alex Pretti’s death, Sen. Amy Klobuchar had planned to launch her gubernatorial campaign Monday, two people tell POLITICO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fcd5-d452-a99b-fdff189d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:40:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e2/4c/fc15baf64402b42605584a2ec926/u-s-congress-36790.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Amy Klobuchar (D-Minn.) speaks during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol on Dec. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e2/4c/fc15baf64402b42605584a2ec926/u-s-congress-36790.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Amy Klobuchar planned to officially launch her gubernatorial campaign on Monday, but has delayed it in the wake of the fatal shooting of a protester by immigration agents in Minneapolis over the weekend, according to two people familiar with the Minnesota Democrat’s plans.</p> 
<p>The senator instead spent Monday morning speaking to White House officials, urging deescalation and pushing to get the administration to end its immigration crackdown in her state, according to a third person, who is close to the senator and, like the others, was granted anonymity to describe private conversations.</p> 
<p>Her decision to wait on her campaign launch comes amid weeks of turmoil in Minnesota that further escalated over the weekend when Border Patrol agents on Saturday fatally shot Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old intensive care unit nurse and American citizen.</p> 
<p>Over the last two days, Klobuchar has been meeting with city and state leaders, strategizing with Senate colleagues over Department of Homeland Security funding and calling Trump administration officials, according to the third person, who said Klobuchar’s “focus is on de-escalating the situation and getting ICE out of Minnesota. There's not time for politics today.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar’s nascent gubernatorial campaign has run headlong into a national crisis, another twist for a campaign that started under unusual circumstances. Earlier this month, Democratic Gov. Tim Walz unexpectedly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/tim-walz-out-minnesota-00710541" target="_blank"><u>dropped his reelection bid</u></a> for a third term, as a swirling fraud scandal threatened to engulf his campaign, and met with Klobuchar about running for the office herself. Since then, two American citizens have been killed by federal immigration agents, thrusting Klobuchar into the center of a battle on an issue for which she’s traditionally cut a moderate profile.</p> 
<p>“Regardless of what [campaign] Klobuchar is considering, this is what I’d expect from her, she’s been the leader in this state,” said Democratic Minnesota state Sen. Grant Hauschild. “We’re facing unprecedented circumstances of federal overreach and harm to our communities, and she’s stepped up, being present on the ground and fighting in Congress.”</p> 
<p>The two people who described her changed launch plans said they expect the senator to formally launch before next Tuesday, when the state’s party precinct caucus kicks off. Klobuchar <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/klobuchar-files-paperwork-minnesota-governor-00741649" target="_blank"><u>already filed paperwork with the state’s campaign finance board</u></a> last week, allowing her to begin raising funds ahead of an expected bid.</p> 
<p>Pretti’s killing also shook up the GOP side of the Minnesota governors’ race. Chris Madel, an attorney who launched his campaign as a Republican late last year, announced on Monday he would be dropping out, calling the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement tactics “wrong” and “an unmitigated disaster.”</p> 
<p>“I cannot support the national Republican-stated retribution on the citizens of our state, nor can I count myself a member of a party that would do so,” he said <a href="https://x.com/CWMadel/status/2015783448091283559?s=20" target="_blank"><u>in a video posted to social media</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Klobuchar is not expected to face a serious Democratic opponent when she enters the gubernatorial race, giving her some breathing room on both her announcement timeline and on her stance on immigration. Minnesota Attorney General Keith Ellison, a well-known progressive who was considered a potential candidate, confirmed he would not be running for the job last week.</p> 
<p>“What you hear from Klobuchar is, ‘ICE needs to get out of here,’ and I don’t think she needs to say more than that [because] without a primary challenger, I don’t think she’ll have to change her position on it,” said a Minnesota Democratic strategist, granted anonymity to discuss the issue candidly. “She’s smart, she’s careful and she’s cautious, and she knows how to win suburban and independent voters.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar has always cut a moderate profile. She rose up in Hennepin County as its prosecutor before running for Senate. During her presidential campaign in 2020, Klobuchar rejected calls for “abolishing ICE,” drawing fire from immigration rights advocates groups in that race, and instead called for reforms of the agency.</p> 
<p>When asked during <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/video/amy-klobuchar-says-ice-is-making-us-less-safe-after-another-fatal-mn-shooting-full-interview-256544325570" target="_blank"><u>an interview on NBC’s “Meet the Press”</u></a> on Sunday whether she supported abolishing ICE, Klobuchar said “we’re always going to have some immigration enforcement in this country, and border control.” But she called for the ICE operation to leave the state because “this agency has been functioning is completely against every tenet of law enforcement.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar ticked through several reforms she supports: “New leadership. Stopping these surges across the country, not just in my state. Training them like they were supposed to be trained. ... Mandatory body cameras. Stopping ramming into people's houses without a judicial warrant.”</p> 
<p>Those specifics could become part of Senate Democrats’ demands to give enough votes to pass a bill to fund the Department of Homeland Security and other parts of the government.</p> 
<p>Other Democrats have called for more aggressive policies, including abolishing ICE altogether. Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn) <a href="https://x.com/IlhanMN/status/2015544841405350257" target="_blank"><u>posted on X</u></a> that “voting NO on the DHS funding bill is the bare minimum,” adding that ICE is “beyond reform” and to “abolish it.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar’s approach is once again drawing criticism from some immigrant-rights advocates. “I do not believe that's far enough,” said George Escobar, executive director of CASA, an immigration advocacy organization. “Unless we deal with the cancer that is causing this, which is ICE itself, and unless we have a comprehensive reform of that agency, which to us, means abolishing it, then honestly, this cycle is just going to repeat over and over again.”One Democratic consultant who has worked on Minnesota races warned that Klobuchar’s deliberative approach could hurt her. “She’s incredibly cautious, and this is not a cautious moment,” they said. “So far, she has not put her foot in it by being too moderate, but she’s also not been under a huge spotlight — and that will change with the gubernatorial run.”</p> 
<p>Nonetheless, Klobuchar’s messaging earned her praise from even some progressives. "I think she’s spot on,” said Mark Longabaugh, a former adviser to Sen Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.). “If you're going to step up and say that this organization needs to be restructured, or shut down and restructured, you also have to tie that to, ‘Listen, there is a legitimate law enforcement need here, both for customs and for border control.’”</p> 
<p>Most Minnesota Democrats don’t think Klobuchar will suddenly center anti-ICE messaging in her gubernatorial campaign. Interviews with a half dozen operatives and elected officials found they still expected the campaign to largely revolve around the economy. “Affordability is still going to be central to her work, along with protecting her state,” said the person close to Klobuchar. “She will always stand up for Minnesota on both.”</p> 
<p>“Who knows if, in 10 months, it will specifically be a part of the narrative or messaging,” said a Minnesota Democratic donor adviser. “But this isn’t going to go away any time soon … because we’re traumatized here.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T19:27:31-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Former Trail Blazer Chris Dudley to run again for governor of Oregon</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/chris-dudley-oregon-governor-00747694</link>
      <description>He came within 2 points when he ran in 2010.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc31-d1ea-a5df-fcb566ec0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:02:30 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/64/fa/df60895a4d47ab770da0232758e1/oregon-governor.JPEG">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Greg Wahl-Stephens/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Oregon Republican gubernatorial candidate Chris Dudley, center, thanks supporters as his family, from left, Charles Dudley, Emma Dudley, Sam Dudley, and his wife, Chris Love Dudley, listen at his election night gathering in Portland, Oregon, on Nov. 2, 2010.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/64/fa/df60895a4d47ab770da0232758e1/oregon-governor.JPEG" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Natalie Fertig</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Natalie Fertig</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Portland Trail Blazer center Chris Dudley has launched a second attempt to run for governor of Oregon as a Republican, a long-shot bid in a blue state even as the incumbent has struggled in polls.</p> 
<p>Dudley, who played six seasons for the Trail Blazers and 16 for the NBA overall, said in an announcement video Monday that he would ease divisiveness and focus on public safety, affordability and education in a state where support for Democratic Gov. Tina Kotek has been low for her entire tenure.</p> 
<p>“The empty promises, the name calling, the finger pointing and fear mongering that has solved nothing must stop,” said in <a href="https://www.dudley4oregon.com/" target="_blank">his election announcement</a>. “There are real solutions, and I have a plan.”</p> 
<p>Dudley is one of the most successful Republicans of the last 25 years in Oregon, coming within 2 points of defeating Democratic Gov. John Kitzhaber in 2010.</p> 
<p>“I think it’s imperative that we get somebody from outside of Salem who’s away from the partisan politics, away from the name calling, the finger pointing,” Dudley <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2026/01/former-blazer-chris-dudley-will-run-for-oregon-governor-setting-up-heated-republican-primary.html" target="_blank">told The Oregonian</a>. “Who has the expertise and background and the ability to bring people together to solve these issues.”</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://www.dudley4oregon.com/" target="_blank">his election announcement,</a> Dudley spoke about his love of the state and frustration people have with the current state of politics. He mentioned education, safety and affordability as key issues he plans to address but did not give any key policy specifics.</p> 
<p>Dudley is a Yale graduate who worked in finance after leaving the NBA. A diabetic, he also founded a foundation focused on children with Type 1 diabetes.</p> 
<p>In the GOP primary, Dudley faces a field that includes state Sen. Christine Drazan, who lost to Kotek by nearly 4 percentage points in 2022.</p> 
<p>Other candidates include another state lawmaker, a county commissioner and <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2026/01/this-jan-6-rioter-who-was-pardoned-by-trump-is-now-running-for-oregon-governor.html" target="_blank">a conservative influencer</a> who was pardoned by President Donald Trump for his involvement in the Jan. 6, 2021, riot at the U.S. Capitol.</p> 
<p>Kotek is a relatively unpopular governor. Her approval rating has consistently remained under 50 percent her entire term in office, <a href="https://pro.morningconsult.com/trackers/governor-approval-ratings" target="_blank">according to polling analysis by Morning Consult</a>. In December, she announced her intention to seek reelection.</p> 
<p>Despite expectations that Democrats will do well in the midterms, a number of Oregon Republicans have become more involved in state politics since the last election. Phil Knight, a co-founder of Nike, donated $3 million to an Oregon Republican PAC focused on gaining seats in the state Legislature in October. It was his largest political donation to date, <a href="https://www.wweek.com/news/state/2025/11/24/phil-knight-writes-record-check-to-republican-legislative-pac/?utm_source=chatgpt.com" target="_blank">according to the Willamette Week</a>.</p> 
<p>Dudley received <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2025/11/former-blazer-and-republican-is-testing-the-waters-for-a-2026-run-for-oregon-governor.html" target="_blank">significant backing from Knight</a> in his 2010 race, but it’s unclear if he will get the same level of support this time around.</p> 
<p>Any Republican faces an uphill battle for governor in Oregon, where a GOP candidate has not won since 1982 and where Democrats have a registration edge of about 8 percentage points.</p>CORRECTION: A previous version incorrectly reported that Gov. Kotek had not announced plans to seek reelection.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pence calls images of Minnesota shooting ‘deeply troubling’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/mike-pence-minnesota-shooting-00746688</link>
      <description>The former vice president called for a “transparent” investigation into the deadly incident.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb35-d9a8-a7bf-ffb74c3d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 13:26:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/97/9b/a6bd161946a6a6450d588cfd6cb6/cheney-funeral-04016.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>“The American people deserve to have safe streets, our laws enforced and our constitutional rights of Freedom of Speech, peaceable assembly and the right to keep and bear Arms respected and preserved all at the same time,” former Vice President Mike Pence said.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/97/9b/a6bd161946a6a6450d588cfd6cb6/cheney-funeral-04016.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Vice President Mike Pence on Monday called video footage of the shooting of Alex Pretti in Minnesota “deeply troubling” as he urged a full investigation into the deadly incident.</p> 
<p>“In the wake of the tragic shooting that claimed the life of Alex Pretti this weekend, our prayers are with his family, the citizens of Minneapolis and local, state and federal law enforcement officers serving there,” <a href="https://x.com/Mike_Pence/status/2015813964605636760?s=20" target="_blank">Pence said in a post on X</a>. “The images of this incident are deeply troubling and a full and transparent investigation of this officer involved shooting must take place immediately.”</p> 
<p>Pretti, a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident, was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">shot and killed</a> by Border Patrol agents on Saturday. The incident, which occurred about 2 miles from where Renee Good was shot and killed by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement officer on Jan. 7, has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-trump-administration-dueling-accounts-minneapolis-shooting-00745811" target="_blank">ignited a heated debate</a> between the Trump administration and Minnesota officials amid intense scrutiny of the tactics of the president's immigration crackdown. </p> 
<p>Protesters have flooded the streets of Minnesota in the aftermath of Pretti’s killing.</p> 
<p>State leaders have <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/state-watch/5705051-alex-pretti-federal-shooting-investigation/" target="_blank">alleged federal officials have blocked them</a> from being involved in an investigation into the shooting. Administration officials have accused Minnesota authorities of refusing to collaborate with immigration authorities on deportations.</p> 
<p>But Pence on Monday called for law enforcement at all levels to work together on investigating the latest shooting.</p> 
<p>“The focus now should be to bring together law enforcement at every level to address the concerns in the community even while ensuring that dangerous illegal aliens are apprehended and no longer a threat to families in Minneapolis,” Pence said.</p> 
<p>The former vice president is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">the latest high-profile Republican to express concerns</a> over the events unfolding in Minnesota. Like Pence, some of the party’s top voices have called for a full investigation into the shooting. </p> 
<p>Others have disputed the administration's justification that Pretti’s carrying of a gun was legal justification for his killing, which Pence echoed on Monday.</p> 
<p>“The American people deserve to have safe streets, our laws enforced and our constitutional rights of Freedom of Speech, peaceable assembly and the right to keep and bear Arms respected and preserved all at the same time,” said Pence. “That’s how Law and Order and Freedom work together in America.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T16:28:20-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans go all-in on 'Sharia law' attacks ahead of Texas primary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/republicans-go-all-in-on-sharia-law-attacks-ahead-of-texas-primary-00745647</link>
      <description>From the Senate primary to local races, Republicans are pledging to fight the supposed spread of radical Islam</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f583-dabb-ad9f-ffefb6820001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:08:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/81/4b/29b73c1f4abb994bc07a4ac543ab/u-s-congress-21753.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. John Cornyn (R-Texas) walks to a Senate Republican Conference luncheon at the U.S. Capitol in Washington, on Dec. 3, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/81/4b/29b73c1f4abb994bc07a4ac543ab/u-s-congress-21753.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton and Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton and Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Anti-Muslim rhetoric has emerged as a potent ingredient in the looming Texas Republican primary while candidates compete to raise fears about the spread of Sharia law in the state and portray themselves as the toughest option to stand against it.</p> 
<p>From the state’s white-hot GOP Senate primary down to local races, Republican candidates are pledging to fight the hardest against a proposed residential development of 1,000 homes centered around a Mosque north of Dallas, while issuing dire warnings about the supposed threat of Islam and questioning their opponents’ commitment to the cause.</p> 
<p>Sen. John Cornyn (R-Texas) and his top primary opponent, Texas Attorney General Ken Paxton, have sparred in attack ads and on the trail over that project and Afghan refugee resettlement program, at times veering into inflammatory anti-Islamic rhetoric. Cornyn called for a federal investigation into the project; Paxton launched several probes and in December sued the development over alleged securities fraud.</p> 
<p>Texas is a heavily diverse state, with non-Hispanic whites representing less than two fifths of its total population — a flashpoint for years on the right. The state’s relatively small but fast-growing Muslim population has become a charged issue for Republicans seeking to distinguish themselves in competitive races. This year’s GOP ads – which vary from condemning terror attacks to burning the Quran – represent an escalation of rhetoric the party has long used to rally its voters.</p> 
<p>“The Muslim community is the boogeyman for this cycle,” said Texas GOP consultant Vinny Minchillo. “One hundred percent this message works — there's no question about it. This has been polled up one side and down the other, and with Texas Republican primary voters, it works. It is a thing they are legitimately scared of.”</p> 
<p>Muslim advocacy organizations and Democrats decry the ads as racist and grossly inaccurate characterizations of those communities.</p> 
<p>“The Texas GOP has declared war on Islam in Texas, claiming that Islamic leaders in the state are implementing Sharia law and using it in court,” said Joel Montfort, a north Texas-based Democratic strategist. “None of it is true, it is just fearmongering and racism to stir up the GOP base and get them to vote.”</p> 
<p>A POLITICO review identified ads in half a dozen races since the start of 2025 that highlighted “Sharia law,” according to data from AdImpact, which tracks political advertising. All were from or backing Republican candidates touting their fights against it, and most were common in Texas.</p> 
<p>Last week, Cornyn launched a seven-figure <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0vD6gujdRfE" target="_blank"><u>ad</u></a> buy titled “Evil Face” that declares “radical Islam is a bloodthirsty ideology,” referencing the Oct. 7 Hamas attack against Israel and December Bondi Beach shooting in Australia. The ad also references his bill to revoke the tax-exempt status of Council on American-Islamic Relations, a Muslim advocacy organization.</p> 
<p>Paxton has <a href="https://x.com/KenPaxtonTX/status/2014344216508498073?s=20" target="_blank"><u>gone after</u></a> Cornyn’s past support of an Afghan refugee resettlement program. And in his capacity as attorney general, Paxton <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2025/12/05/texas-ken-paxton-epic-city-lawsuit/" target="_blank"><u>said</u></a> the project is an “illegal land development scheme” and its leaders are “engaged in a radical plot to destroy hundreds of acres of beautiful Texas land and line their own pockets.”</p> 
<p>In the four-way GOP race for Texas attorney general, candidate Aaron Reitz says in an <a href="https://x.com/bwaltens/status/2013978366030864753" target="_blank"><u>ad</u></a> out this week that “Islam is not compatible with Western civilization” and vows to “stop the invasion” of Muslims. Reitz served less than a year in the Justice Department before launching his bid for attorney general. His opponent, state Sen. Mayes Middleton, also has an <a href="https://pdfweb.s3.amazonaws.com/scraped-ads/CR17061108716880789505.mp4" target="_blank"><u>ad</u></a> boasting that he’s running to “stop Sharia law” in Texas.</p> 
<p>And, most provocatively, Valentina Gomez <a href="https://www.fox26houston.com/isiah-factor-uncensored/texas-congressional-candidate-sparks-controversy-quran-burning-video" target="_blank"><u>launched</u></a> her candidacy in Texas’ 31st Congressional District last year with a video showing her burning a Quran and declaring that “your daughters will be raped and your sons beheaded, unless we stop Islam once and for all.” Gomez, who is challenging President Donald Trump-endorsed Rep. John Carter (R-Texas), is a known conservative activist and provocateur who won just 8 percent of the primary vote when she ran for Missouri secretary of state last year.</p> 
<p>Anti-muslim sentiment in the U.S. grew out of the 9/11 terror attacks, which some Republicans used to rally their base for political gain. False rumors on the right that Barack Hussein Obama was a secret Muslim persisted <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2007/10/untraceable-e-mails-spread-obama-rumor-006314" target="_blank"><u>from his rise to the White House </u></a>and for years after. The planned construction of a mosque blocks from Ground Zero became a right-wing cause celebre early in his presidency, with multiple national Republican figures rallying against it.</p> 
<p>Trump intensified those feelings, first by elevating conspiracy theories that Obama wasn’t born in the U.S., then by repeatedly disparaging Muslims, pledging in his 2016 campaign to ban Muslims from entering the country and once he became president implementing travel bans against majority-Muslim countries. On Tuesday, Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115928297468422986" target="_blank"><u>reposted</u></a> a comment calling Islam a “cult.”</p> 
<p>But in recent years Islam hasn’t been as much of a focus within GOP campaigns — until now.</p> 
<p>The Texas ads come as Republicans nationwide have placed heightened scrutiny on CAIR, the largest Muslim advocacy group in the U.S. Sameeha Rizvi, CAIR Action Texas Policy and Advocacy Coordinator, called Cornyn’s ad “defamatory and despicable” and borne out of “desperation to compete with Ken Paxton’s anti-Muslim bigotry.”</p> 
<p>“CAIR is not going anywhere, American Muslims are not going anywhere, and our community will show its strength at the ballot box, God willing,” Rizvi said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Cornyn has introduced legislation seeking to revoke CAIR’s tax-exempt status. U.S. Rep Chip Roy, who is also in the Texas attorney general race, introduced a similar bill last year.</p> 
<p>When a super PAC on behalf of Cornyn launched an <a href="https://x.com/bradj_TX/status/2014319896671199443" target="_blank"><u>attack</u></a> against Paxton on Thursday, calling him “weird” and highlighting his divorce and alleged extramarital affairs, Paxton <a href="https://x.com/KenPaxtonTX/status/2014344216508498073" target="_blank"><u>shot back</u></a> on X : “This desperate hail mary can't erase the fact that he [Cornyn] helped radical Islamic Afghans invade Texas and that his family's making a fortune securing visas for foreigners.”</p> 
<p>Paxton was referencing Cornyn’s past support for increasing the number of Special Immigrant Visas available to Afghans following the Taliban’s 2021 takeover of the country. Cornyn, who had once been supportive of the program,<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/republicans-drop-support-afghans-asylum-00697430" target="_blank"><u> reversed course</u></a> along with other Republicans late last year following the shooting of two National Guard members by an Afghan who’d been granted asylum in the U.S., on the basis that the vetting of applicants was inadequate.</p> 
<p>Cornyn has responded to Paxton’s attacks with a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xZSeyNhSbPY" target="_blank"><u>digital ad</u></a> stating that Paxton talks tough but he’s actually “soft on radical Islam,” claiming that Paxton directed $2.5 million to resettle Afghan refugees in Texas, and his former attorney who defended him during impeachment proceedings now represents the East Plano Islamic Center.</p> 
<p>Several ads from different candidates in Texas use footage of the project from the East Plano Islamic Center, which would also feature a K-12 school and retail. Texas leaders, including Gov. Greg Abbott, have said that the presence of the planned Muslim community raises national security concerns. The East Plano Islamic Center did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>“Texans overwhelmingly care about this – they're looking at their communities transform in radical ways,” said Reitz, the attorney general candidate.</p> 
<p>“You look at the number of mosques that have been built in Texas in just the last 10 to 20 years, and it's explosive,” he said. “It’s alarming for good reason, and I think that Republican voters in particular are looking for their public office holders to address it, and so it's such a pressing issue that I chose to really lean into this.”</p> 
<p>Cornyn’s ad declares that “Sharia law has no place in American courts or communities,” a reference to the development. Trump’s Justice Department also launched a civil rights investigation into the project last year after Cornyn requested the federal government to investigate “religious discrimination.”</p> 
<p>The project was already on the radar of Paxton, who had opened his first of several probes into its construction. In December, Paxton — whose candidacy is boosted by his reputation as an aggressive attorney general who frequently files lawsuits on behalf of MAGA causes — <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2025/12/05/texas-ken-paxton-epic-city-lawsuit/" target="_blank"><u>sued</u></a> the development for alleged securities fraud.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department quietly <a href="https://www.keranews.org/news/2025-06-25/department-justice-ends-federal-probe-epic-city-mosque" target="_blank"><u>closed</u></a> its investigation last summer without filing any charges. But Abbott still went forward and signed multiple laws last year that banned “Sharia compounds” and designating CAIR and Muslim Brotherhood as terrorist organizations. CAIR sued Texas in response, arguing the action was unconstitutional and defamatory.</p> 
<p>Paxton, in his official capacity as attorney general, <a href="https://x.com/KenPaxtonTX/status/2015160530848121149" target="_blank"><u>said</u></a> last week that the state comptroller can exclude private schools from the school voucher program if they violate the recently signed anti-terror laws, declaring that “Texans’ tax dollars should never fund Islamic terrorists or America’s enemies.”</p> 
<p><i>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misstated John Cornyn's level of involvement in legislation to revoke CAIR's tax-exempt status. He introduced it.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A battle over the truth erupts after deadly Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-trump-administration-dueling-accounts-minneapolis-shooting-00745811</link>
      <description>Federal and local leaders are sharply divided over what happened and who is to blame.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f77a-d9a8-a7bf-f7faaf830000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 19:29:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/50/46/b239cb1548d0be8872d389b3e16f/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-40005.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Adam Gray/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A makeshift memorial is placed where Alex Pretti was fatally shot by a U.S. Border Patrol agent the previous day, in Minneapolis, on Jan. 25, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/50/46/b239cb1548d0be8872d389b3e16f/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-40005.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels and Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels and Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of another fatal shooting involving immigration agents, Trump administration and Minnesota officials are locked in a heated dispute over what exactly transpired and who’s to blame for the death of 37-year-old Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p>And they don’t just disagree in their interpretation of the events — they fundamentally differ on what exactly took place and what triggered it.</p> 
<p>Border Patrol agents <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">shot and killed</a> Pretti on Saturday during a tense encounter between observers and federal agents, a dynamic that has led to several violent interactions as the Trump administration escalates its nationwide immigration crackdown. His death comes less than a month after an Immigration and Customs Enforcement officer <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/minneapolis-immigration-crackdown-shooting-00714034" target="_blank">fatally shot 37-year-old Renee Good</a>. The scenes of the shootings were roughly two miles apart, and protesters flooded the streets after both.</p> 
<p>Amid conflicting accounts over the incident — including whether Pretti’s hand at any point during the incident was near his gun — video verified and analyzed by several media outlets, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-federal-agents-video.html" target="_blank">including The New York Times</a>, show the item Pretti appeared to be holding was a phone he was using to film the scene before he attempted to help a woman who had been pushed to the ground by Border Patrol agents. According to a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/investigations/2026/01/25/minneapolis-shooting-video-gun/" target="_blank">Washington Post analysis</a> of video footage, federal agents appear to have secured Pretti's gun just moments before an agent shot him.</p> 
<p>“What you see is someone brandishing a cellphone who is simply there with a cellphone helping someone up, a woman up, as his parents point out, when she had slipped,” Sen. Amy Klobuchar (D-Minn.) <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/video/amy-klobuchar-says-ice-is-making-us-less-safe-after-another-fatal-mn-shooting-full-interview-256544325570" target="_blank">told NBC’s “Meet the Press.”</a> “And so when I hear these officials from the Trump administration describe this video in ways that simply aren’t true, I just keep thinking, ‘Your eyes don’t lie.’”</p> 
<p>Border Patrol commander Gregory Bovino on Sunday <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/bovino-border-patrol-agents-minneapolis-victims-00745702" target="_blank">accused Pretti of having “injected” himself</a> into a law enforcement investigation. Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said Pretti had committed a “felony” by impeding law enforcement. And Deputy Attorney General Todd Blanche blamed local state officials for what he called an “entirely avoidable” event.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/1f/1a/db0193cf4a55a6c5a4e24bf5d77b/ap26024812004514-edit.jpg" alt="People gather at the intersection of 27th Street and Nicollet Avenue, a block from the shooting." data-portal-copyright="Ben Hovland/Minnesota Public Radio via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26024812004514" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="People gather at the intersection of 27th Street and Nicollet Avenue, a block from the shooting."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/5d/ef/38ac589b42c58a09cdf599421d97/gettyimages-2258037569-edit.jpg" alt="A person is tackled by a federal agent amid protests following the shooting." data-portal-copyright="Brandon Bell/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2258037569" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="A person is tackled by a federal agent amid protests following the shooting."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/26/92/d47baebe4fc3a3966708e045f536/ap26024793513012-edit.jpg" alt="Protesters react in the street along Nicollet Avenue on Jan 24." data-portal-copyright="Aaron Lavinsky/Minneapolis Star Tribune via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26024793513012" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Protesters react in the street along Nicollet Avenue on Jan 24."/><p>But Minnesota officials see a different story in the footage. Minneapolis Police Chief Brian O’Hara said Pretti was lawfully armed and exercising his constitutional rights, and Klobuchar told NBC’s “Meet the Press” that the video shows him holding a cellphone and helping a woman up, not acting aggressively toward agents.</p> 
<p>Shortly after Saturday’s shooting, Noem offered one account of the incident: She said Pretti “approached U.S. Border Patrol officers with a 9mm semi-automatic handgun” and that he “violently resisted” when the officers attempted to disarm him.</p> 
<p>Noem then <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=91s4Iwa3K6Q" target="_blank">told Fox News on Sunday</a> that agents on Saturday “clearly feared for their lives” before shooting Pretti. She and other federal officials have claimed that Pretti was approaching agents with a gun.</p> 
<p>“We do know that he came to that scene and impeded a law enforcement operation, which is against federal law. It's a felony. When he did that, interacting with those agents when they tried to get him to disengage, he became aggressive and resisted them throughout that process,” Noem said. “These officers used their training, followed their protocols and were in fear of their lives and the people around them.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/a6/b1/0e9ee652414ebde1e7edfc87edda/gettyimages-2258012002-edit.jpg" alt="Shortly after Saturday’s shooting, Kristi Noem offered one account of the incident: She said Pretti “approached U.S. Border Patrol officers with a 9mm semi-automatic handgun” and that he “violently resisted” when the officers attempted to disarm him." data-portal-copyright="Al Drago/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2258012002" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Shortly after Saturday’s shooting, Kristi Noem offered one account of the incident: She said Pretti “approached U.S. Border Patrol officers with a 9mm semi-automatic handgun” and that he “violently resisted” when the officers attempted to disarm him."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/77/a1/33171be6435c9da3fae973e1d3e3/ap26010606785601-edit.jpg" alt="Minneapolis Police Chief Brian O’Hara said Pretti was lawfully armed and exercising his constitutional rights." data-portal-copyright="Jen Golbeck/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26010606785601" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Minneapolis Police Chief Brian O’Hara said Pretti was lawfully armed and exercising his constitutional rights."/><p>Despite Noem’s claim that the agents feared for their lives, O’Hara, <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/video/minneapolis-police-chief-brian-ohara-says-people-have-had-enough-after-border-patrol-shooting/" target="_blank">speaking on CBS’ “Face the Nation”</a> on Sunday morning, said he had seen no evidence Pretti brandished a weapon during the encounter.</p> 
<p>“You have a Second Amendment right in the United States to possess a firearm,” O’Hara said during an interview with host Margaret Brennan. “And there are some restrictions around that in Minnesota, and everything that we see that we are aware of shows that he did not violate any of those restrictions.”</p> 
<p>But in an interview with CNN’s “State of the Union” on Sunday, Bovino said a person’s Second Amendment rights “don’t count when you riot and assault, delay, obstruct and impede law enforcement officers.”</p> 
<p>Noem seemingly suggested the fact that Pretti possessed “a gun and ammunition, rather than a sign” meant the scene was a “violent riot.”</p> 
<p>“We have someone showing up with weapons and are using them to assault law enforcement officers,” she said Saturday of the situation.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/c8/10/53fe7d5b41e899cafe21b2fa719e/ap26025601602125-edit.jpg" alt="Bureau of Criminal Apprehension officers stand over a memorial at the scene where Pretti was fatally shot." data-portal-copyright="Adam Gray/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26025601602125" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Bureau of Criminal Apprehension officers stand over a memorial at the scene where Pretti was fatally shot."/><p><a href="https://x.com/kylegriffin1/status/2015481050248470580" target="_blank">Former President Barack Obama also said</a> the Trump administration’s explanations “appear to be directly contradicted by video evidence.” And Pretti’s family members have accused the White House of <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/01/24/us/alex-pretti-minneapolis-ice-shooting-invs" target="_blank">spreading “sickening lies.”</a></p> 
<p>Just as in the aftermath of Good’s shooting, federal and state officials disagree about who bears responsibility — and how to manage the fallout.</p> 
<p>Blanche on Sunday told NBC’s “Meet the Press” that Pretti’s shooting was a “tragedy” but added that “this was entirely avoidable if we had a governor, if we had a mayor, if we had leadership in Washington and over in Minnesota that actually cared about their citizens.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/e6/6c/85fae6f54bde8e3ef57befd2ed87/gettyimages-2257466650-edit.jpg" alt="A person carries an American flag on Nicollet Avenue in Minneapolis on Jan. 24." data-portal-copyright="Stephen Maturen/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2257466650" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="A person carries an American flag on Nicollet Avenue in Minneapolis on Jan. 24."/><p>But Gov. Tim Walz and local officials say it’s the Trump administration that has sown chaos. Walz deployed the state’s National Guard to Minneapolis in the aftermath of Pretti’s killing, which he called “sickening.”</p> 
<p>“I just spoke with the White House after another horrific shooting by federal agents this morning. Minnesota has had it. This is sickening,” <a href="https://x.com/GovTimWalz/status/2015093164999119352?s=20" target="_blank">Walz posted on X</a>. “The President must end this operation. Pull the thousands of violent, untrained officers out of Minnesota. Now.”</p> 
<p>“This administration and everyone involved in this operation should be reflecting. They should be reflecting right now and asking themselves, what exactly are you accomplishing?” Minneapolis Mayor Jacob Frey, a Democrat, said at a Saturday press conference. “If the goal was to achieve peace and safety, this is doing exactly the opposite. If the goal was to achieve calm and prosperity, this is doing exactly the opposite.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rift over generational change roils the Congressional Black Caucus</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/congressional-black-caucus-2026-midterms-00741618</link>
      <description>“You cannot be a part of the system for 40 years and also be the one who's going to change it for the next 40,” said Tennessee state Rep. Justin Pearson.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ec66-d452-a99b-edfecbd70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/e5/5a/a5d72a90427bad4a6421fcb980e0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2241490328">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jan Sonnenmair/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tennessee state Rep. Justin Pearson takes a selfie with rallygoers at the "No Kings" protest on Oct. 18, 2025 in Memphis, Tennessee.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e5/5a/a5d72a90427bad4a6421fcb980e0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2241490328" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A new generation of Black Democrats is running in the midterms, aiming to inject a younger vision into an aging Congressional Black Caucus. And in some cases, that means primarying incumbents.</p> 
<p>The wave of new candidates comes amid an identity crisis for the Democratic Party, which has splintered along generational and ideological lines as the party searches for new leaders in the second Trump era, both for this November and the open presidential race in two years.</p> 
<p>“This is a new moment that requires different ideas, requires new energy and new perspectives and you cannot be a part of the system for 40 years and also be the one who's going to change it for the next 40,” said Tennessee state Rep. Justin Pearson, 31, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/justin-j-pearson-to-challenge-tennessee-rep-steve-cohen-in-dem-primary-00597567" target="_blank">who launched his primary challenge</a> to 76-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51856" data-person-id="51856">Steve Cohen</a> (D-Tenn.) last year. “You've done the best that you could, and it's time for other folks to be able to do the best that they can for the present and for the future.”</p> 
<p>Young Black candidates say they’re motivated to run due to rising racial tensions, redistricting and the possibility of <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-nightly/2025/08/08/its-been-60-years-since-the-voting-rights-act-was-signed-will-it-make-it-to-61-00500390" target="_blank">an end to the Voting Rights Act</a> — and what they describe as an inadequate response from older generations that are fighting past battles.</p> 
<p>“Our generation recognizes the fierce urgency of now,” Pearson said.</p> 
<p>The CBC has grown exponentially since its establishment in 1971, currently boasting a historic 62 members — the largest of any of the affinity caucuses. But the average age of CBC members is 60 years old, and some of the oldest House Democrats are members.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51325" data-person-id="51325">Jim Clyburn</a>, 85, has represented South Carolina for more than 30 years and plans on running again. At 88 years old, D.C. Del. Eleanor Holmes Norton has not ruled out running for reelection, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/10/congress/eleanor-holmes-norton-reelection-00397248" target="_blank">despite growing concerns about her age</a>. And 87-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51664" data-person-id="51664">Maxine Waters</a> (D-Calif.), who was first elected in 1990, said she <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/05/15/house-democrats-age-members-reelection-biden" target="_blank">also plans on running for reelection</a> this year.</p> 
<p>These long tenures have started to worry some new candidates, they said in interviews.</p> 
<p>“When I was born in 1992, this was the poorest district in the poorest state in the country,” said Evan Turnage, who is primarying 77-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51647" data-person-id="51647">Bennie Thompson</a> (D-Miss.). “Congressman Thompson was elected in ’93 and now today, I'm 33, and this is still the poorest district in the poorest state in the country.”</p> 
<p>Turnage — a former senior staffer to Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> of New York and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> of Massachusetts — said these long-serving members have “failed” younger generations for too long.</p> 
<p>“Just because you've been around the block for 30 years doesn't mean you're delivering results for the district, doesn't mean you're delivering results for your constituents,” Turnage said.</p> 
<p>In a statement, Thompson said he has spent his entire career encouraging young people “to make a difference in the world.”</p> 
<p>“If this is how Mr. Turnage chooses to make a difference in Mississippi’s 2nd Congressional District, that's his choice," Thompson said.</p> 
<p>The younger Black candidates — and current lawmakers — have generally pushed more progressive policies in their campaigns than CBC members who have served for decades. They've had a heavy focus on issues they say are of most concern to those in their generations, such as the cost of living and education.</p> 
<p>"The Democratic Party has to adapt in order to survive. That work starts right now," said Pearson, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/04/12/second-tennessee-state-lawmaker-reinstated-00091715" target="_blank">gained nationwide fame in 2023 as a member of the "Tennessee Three”</a> after he was expelled from, and then reelected to, the state Legislature for leading a gun safety protest on the state House floor.</p> 
<p>"Black folks in this country are still suffering disproportionately in every single category, and without leadership to elevate those concerns, those worries, those issues in a meaningful way, we're never going to see that change," Pearson added.</p> 
<p>He is challenging Cohen, who is white, in a majority-Black district based in Memphis that Cohen has represented for decades. During his 2007 campaign, Cohen expressed interest in joining the CBC, <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2007/01/black-caucus-whites-not-allowed-002389" target="_blank">but caucus members quickly shut that down</a>.</p> 
<p>Cohen said in an interview that his tenure in Congress is actually a strength.</p> 
<p>“I know the issues and I know the problems, I know the people,” said Cohen. “The way you get legislation passed hasn't changed, really, in the 40 years I've been here. Some people think it's about getting a megaphone and hollering or making some kind of a fuss, and I've done some of that in my younger days, and I still like to occasionally … but it's a matter of having friends, having relationships, and being able to get the majority of votes to pass the bills. And I've done that all my life.”</p> 
<p>The CBC has begun to see younger legislators enter their ranks in recent years. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/461974" data-person-id="461974">Gabe Amo</a>, 38, made history in 2023 when he was elected as Rhode Island’s first Black representative. And in 2022, at the age of 25, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/411928" data-person-id="411928">Maxwell Frost </a>became the first Gen Z CBC member elected to Congress.</p> 
<p>“Our movement — from the civil rights era to the birth of the CBC itself — was born from the energy and courage of young people to stand up and do the right thing,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51521" data-person-id="51521">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.), chair of the CBC’s political arm, in a statement. “Our caucus today represents the breadth and depth of our community — from every corner of America — and folks whose families have been here for generations, those who are immigrants, queer, disabled, and more women and young people than ever before.”</p> 
<p>The CBC PAC has already endorsed some young candidates this cycle, including California’s Lauren Babb and Arkansas’ Chris Jones. It’s likely the PAC will also endorse Adrian Boafo, 31, according to a person familiar with the matter who was granted anonymity to discuss private matters, who is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/steny-hoyer-retirement-00715790" target="_blank">running to succeed</a> 86-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51438" data-person-id="51438">Steny Hoyer</a>. </p> 
<p>But the PAC this year also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/congressional-black-caucus-espaillat-primary-00728543?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter" target="_blank">endorsed 71-year-old incumbent</a> Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/193043" data-person-id="193043">Adriano Espaillat </a>(D-N.Y.) — who identifies as Afro Latino, currently chairs the Congressional Hispanic Caucus and has had a bumpy relationship with the CBC — over his 32-year-old primary challenger, Darializa Avila Chevalier.</p> 
<p>As the age gap between caucus members and voters grows, an influx of fresh faces will be vital to regaining voters’ support for Democrats ahead of the 2026 midterms, said 25-year-old Courtney McClain, who is running for a red House seat in South Carolina.</p> 
<p>“Within the party in general, we've had an issue of connecting with younger voters, and especially with young men,” said McClain, referring to the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2025/06/26/behind-trumps-2024-victory-a-more-racially-and-ethnically-diverse-voter-coalition/" target="_blank">15 percent of Black men</a> who supported President Donald Trump in the 2024 presidential election. “I really think a lot of people are more apt to vote if they can see themselves in the candidate as opposed to someone who has been there for many years.”</p> 
<p>But these young Black candidates still hold a deep appreciation for the caucus, despite their concerns around age.</p> 
<p>Turnage said he’d “love” to be a member of the CBC. Pearson called the caucus an "extraordinary institution.” And McClain — a onetime CBC Foundation intern and a fellow with the CBC Institute last year — said she would “definitely” like to be a member.</p> 
<p>Ultimately, McClain said, the CBC needs young members if they hope to actually address the challenges facing the next generation.</p> 
<p>“The legislation that's being passed, a lot of the people that are currently in office won't even be impacted by it, say, in the next 20 years,” McClain said. “But my generation will.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-23T14:01:14-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>RNC takes steps toward a 2026 GOP midterm convention</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/republicans-take-steps-towards-midterm-convention-00744673</link>
      <description>The Republican National Committee voted Friday to allow for an off-cycle national convention this summer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ec26-d452-a99b-edfe7b3f0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:50:59 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b4/64/0e964bda4a499a2063d6a439ffb6/election-2024-rnc-photo-gallery-68296.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Nam Y. Huh/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Republican presidential nominee Donald Trump and Republican vice-presidential nominee Sen. J.D. Vance watch with their families as the balloons fall during the final day of the Republican National Convention in Milwaukee on July 18, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b4/64/0e964bda4a499a2063d6a439ffb6/election-2024-rnc-photo-gallery-68296.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Melanie Mason and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Melanie Mason and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>SANTA BARBARA, Calif. — Republicans are one step closer to finalizing plans for a midterm convention later this year.</p> 
<p>The Republican National Committee approved a rule change during its winter meeting on Friday that would allow the party to hold a convention during a midterm election year.</p> 
<p>"I'm incredibly excited about the possibility of hosting midterm convention to highlight what President Trump and Republicans have been able to accomplish this year," RNC Chairman Joe Gruters said after the rule change was adopted. "If the president wants us to host a convention to highlight the great work this administration has done for the American people, we are doing the work now and will be ready to act when that time comes."</p> 
<p>The amendment was approved at the RNC’s winter meeting with no objections. An unusually high number of RNC members had already left the meeting to catch early flights ahead of winter storms bearing down on much of the country by the time the vote was brought up.</p> 
<p>The rule authorizes the RNC to “conduct a special ceremonial convention between presidential conventions, such as a midterm convention,” said Bill O’Brien, the national committeeman from New Hampshire.</p> 
<p>National party conventions have typically been held only during presidential elections in the modern era. But President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/16/trump-says-the-gop-will-hold-a-midterm-convention-00566778" target="_blank"><u>announced in September</u></a> that the party would be holding a “Midterm Convention,” leaving the party scrambling to execute.</p> 
<p>The event would give Republicans an opportunity to message the administration’s wins and platform candidates in battleground races across the country as they fight to hold onto congressional control.</p> 
<p>Democrats, who held a series of midterm-year national conventions in the 1970s, are also flirting with the possibility. At the Democratic National Committee’s winter meetings in Los Angeles last month, officials from Nebraska and Utah were <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/13/dnc-democratic-national-committee-hope-00689938" target="_blank"><u>among those jockeying to host the potential event</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Republicans have not yet announced where their convention will be held or when, though Nevada GOP leaders are <a href="https://nevadanewsandviews.com/a-solid-bet-bring-gop-midterm-convention-to-vegas-baby/" target="_blank"><u>pushing for Las Vegas to host</u></a>.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mark Kelly’s money bomb</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/mark-kelly-fundraising-midterms-00743357</link>
      <description>The Arizona senator's moves thus far have positioned him to be a key fundraiser in 2026 and offer him a platform to build out a 2028 base.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ea8e-dabb-ad9f-ffef5e640000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 06:42:24 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/41/d7/cbd6083c4144a8f3b60b6bf95cf3/u-s-congress-42936.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.) speaks during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol Dec. 1, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/41/d7/cbd6083c4144a8f3b60b6bf95cf3/u-s-congress-42936.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Adam Wren</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Adam Wren</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As he increasingly flirts with a <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/01/21/politics/mark-kelly-pentagon-profile" target="_blank">2028 presidential run</a>, Mark Kelly is winning friends up and down the ballot — if not influencing his Trump administration enemies.</p> 
<p>In an effort to help flip the House and Senate in 2026, Kelly has strategically used his star turn as President Donald Trump and Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth’s Public Enemy No. 1 to ramp up his giving and fundraising to competitive candidates, party committees and state parties to the tune of nearly $5 million last year, according to figures shared exclusively with POLITICO.</p> 
<p>Since Trump in late November attacked the Arizona senator and other national security Democrats with a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115582703277798715" target="_blank">Truth Social post</a> accusing them of “SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR, punishable by DEATH,” one of the biggest questions in political circles has been just how much Kelly would benefit from Trump fashioning him into a foil. That post has raised Kelly’s profile, boosted further by Hegseth announcing an <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/mark-kelly-pete-hegseth-lawsuit-00722382" target="_blank">investigation into Kelly</a>.</p> 
<p>While Kelly’s total fundraising numbers aren't yet available, what he raised and gave away will likely only be a fraction. His moves thus far — and the spotlight that Trump has shone on him — have positioned him to be a key fundraiser for Democrats in 2026, and offer him a platform to build out a 2028 base.</p> 
<p>Kelly made more than $1 million in direct contributions and transfers to Democrats across the country, bringing his total direct contributions to more than $1.4 million for 2025. That includes $100,000 each to the DCCC and the DSCC and more than $280,000 to the DNC and state parties combined. As for the Senate, the DSCC vice chair has raised or contributed more than $2.3 million for the committee since the start of last year. He also raised $1 million for other Democrats in the fourth quarter alone by signing emails, text messages and ads.</p> 
<p>Kelly also made direct contributions to approximately 30 state parties, including in potential early nominating 2028 states like Iowa, Michigan, South Carolina and New Hampshire. He also made two trips to South Carolina and one trip to Michigan, along with travel to Nevada.</p> 
<p>“There’s definitely a message there that resonates with Nevada voters across the board,” Nevada Democrats Chair Daniele Monroe-Moreno told POLITICO, adding that Kelly drew a diverse crowd to the event he attended and praising his contribution to the state party. “So yes, I know there'll be a number of people that will probably throw their hat in the ring, but he has definitely sparked the interest of some Nevada voters.”</p> 
<p>That's not to mention off-year election trips for Democrats in North Carolina, New Jersey and Virginia. “Senator Kelly is working overtime to support Democrats running in tough races because he knows that taking back the House and Senate is critical to holding Trump accountable and delivering relief from rising costs for American families,” said Jacob Peters, a Kelly spokesperson.</p> 
<p>Kelly’s chits make it clear that attention from Trump can be a major boon for a potential 2028 presidential candidate. But more than anything, Kelly’s rising national profile, much like that of California Gov. Gavin Newsom's last year, shows Trump has a unique ability to elevate foils. Trump has a great deal of power to pare the Democratic field.</p> 
<p>“I’m sure that will be something we want him to do” as the 2028 presidential race gets closer, one Republican close to the White House told Playbook, though they noted that it’s still early.</p> 
<p>But do Republicans who want to keep the White House think he's making smart bets by elevating the Newsoms and Kellys of the opposition?</p> 
<p>“Newsom is a perfect foil because his record is so horrendous,” said Dave Carney, the veteran New Hampshire GOP political consultant. “He will tell you whatever he thinks you want to hear.” One minute, Carney said, “he sounds like Arnold Schwarzenegger — a moderate Republican. But then he gets beat up from the left, and he, you know, scurries back there.” As for Kelly? “Kelly's a press thing,” Carney said. “He's not a real thing.”</p> 
<p>There’s at least one candidate who Carney does <i>not</i> want to see Trump elevate: Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro.</p> 
<p>“He's the first candidate in the history of America that I'm aware of where his vice presidential search in not being picked has helped him,” Carney said, citing Shapiro’s fundraising ability. “There’s a lot of assets he has.”</p> 
<p>The drawback for Democrats vying for the nomination: Trump’s ire and retribution could lead to a rolling and unpredictable flavor of the month for some time leading up to 2028. Or, as Carney put it: “The president has the capacity — demonstrated over time — that he can beat the shit out of more than one person at a time.”</p> 
<p><i>Like this content? Consider signing up for POLITICO's </i><a href="https://www.politico.com/playbook" target="_blank"><i>Playbook newsletter</i></a><i>. </i><br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>These Gen-Z Trump voters don’t want JD Vance in 2028</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/gen-z-trump-voter-jd-vance-2028-00742811</link>
      <description>A recent focus group of 18- to 24-year-old Trump voters suggests weaknesses for Vance among young Republicans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e7ce-d9a8-a7bf-e7ceeac90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/20/0e/58685d13415e96ef1d56e4d5401d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2255448042">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Wong/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I don’t think Vance can win, because I think he's too connected to the current political establishment in Washington, which I think has a very negative approval rating right now,” said Sam Z., a voter in Minnesota.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/20/0e/58685d13415e96ef1d56e4d5401d/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2255448042" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Vice President JD Vance is the Trump administration’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/21/vance-maga-infighting-turning-point-usa-00702396" target="_blank">unofficial envoy to Gen Z</a>. But young Trump supporters may not be all that enamored with him as they weigh their 2028 options.</p> 
<p>In a focus group of nine young men who supported Trump in 2024, conducted Monday by Longwell Partners and shared with POLITICO, they showed tepid enthusiasm about the vice president and suggested he is too bridled by the baggage of Trump's second term.</p> 
<p>“I feel like it's just time for someone new, especially for the Republican Party,” said Alexandre M., a voter in Maryland, who raised concerns about Trumps’s handling of the Epstein files, “because JD Vance was also pushing that as well.”</p> 
<p>When the 18- to 24-year-olds were asked who else they would like to see as potential candidates in 2028, they named Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis, Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Ohio gubernatorial candidate Vivek Ramaswamy, Sen. Tom Cotton (R-Ark.) and Florida gubernatorial candidate James Fishback. When the moderator asked who wants to see Vance as the GOP nominee, just one of the nine raised their hand — and even he later signaled he is still unsure of his support.</p> 
<p>Others in the group raised concerns about electability as well as Vance’s changing views.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think Vance can win, because I think he's too connected to the current political establishment in Washington, which I think has a very negative approval rating right now,” said Sam Z., a voter in Minnesota. “If you look at what he was about in 2018, 2019, 2020, and you look at what he's about now, it's very, very different. … Somebody younger running in office would be awesome. So that's the one thing I wouldn't mind for Vance. But overall, I just don't think [he] can win. I think he's kind of flip-flopped on a lot of issues.”</p> 
<p>The one voter who said he’d be open to Vance in 2028 said he liked Vance’s experience. “I think because he already is a VP, like he has more experience than most people will, which puts him at an advantage,” said Ruben T., a voter in Georgia.</p> 
<p>Vance wasn’t the only topic where these voters split from the traditional party line.</p> 
<p>Asked about U.S. support for Israel, five said they felt the U.S. supports Israel too much and four said the right amount. None said too little.</p> 
<p>Some mentioned conspiracy theories — like Candace Owens’ <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2025/12/16/candace-owens-maga-conspiracy-charlie-kirk/" target="_blank">assertion that Charlie Kirk was assassinated by the Israeli government</a> — for steering their belief that the U.S. should support Israel less.</p> 
<p>“I don't know how factual some of this stuff is, but after seeing a lot of things after Charlie Kirk's death and with Candace Owens’ private investigation, I kind of started to notice of, like, Israel was kind of always a big talking point with the Republicans,” said Richard B., a voter in Pennsylvania. “I personally have an issue with it.”</p> 
<p>Some of them spoke in free-speech terms, through a humanitarian lens or from an America First perspective. “I just don't believe that death is justifiable in any way, and of course, Israel is responsible for many deaths,” Matteo R. in Illinois said.</p> 
<p>“I think we should be more focused on eliminating problems that we have in our own country, versus one that's pretty far across the world,” said Sam M., a voter in New Mexico.</p> 
<p>That domestic-first approach applied to Trump’s flirtations with Greenland. When asked, “Who would like to see the U.S. buy Greenland?” none raised their hands.</p> 
<p>“No other president has ever said that,” said Mukeesh S., in California. “It's been part of Denmark. I think we should just respect it and leave it, and focus on what's actually happening inside the nation.”</p> 
<p>Dillon, a voter from Rhode Island, added: “I think it's kind of an unnecessary thing to do right now, and it's not what our resources could best be used on.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists on the week in politics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2026/01/23/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00743233</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's an offering of the best of this week's crop, picked fresh off the Toonosphere. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e87f-d9a8-a7bf-eeffa93c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Brain the size of a walnut’: Bessent goes off on Newsom</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/scott-bessent-gavin-newsom-the-conversation-00742777</link>
      <description>The Treasury Secretary pushed back the California governor’s criticisms of the Trump administration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e7c3-d1ea-a5df-f7c7c0f60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b4/01/623505c048d5ad098a92009607b4/switzerland-davos-52355.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Markus Schreiber/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I actually think he knows less about economics than Kamala Harris, which is a terrible place to be in,” Scott Bessent said of Gavin Newsom.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b4/01/623505c048d5ad098a92009607b4/switzerland-davos-52355.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>California Gov. Gavin Newsom has been one of the most vocal critics of President Donald Trump since his return to office last year. Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent argues it’s a sign of Newsom’s weakness.</p> 
<p>“I think Gavin Newsom may be cracking up, some of these things he’s saying. I think he may be in over his hairdo,” Bessent said in an interview Thursday with POLITICO’s Dasha Burns for “The Conversation."</p> 
<p>Trump’s top economic adviser said that Newsom, a potential 2028 presidential candidate and longstanding Trump foe, has a “brain the size of a walnut” and that he knows “less about economics than” former Vice President Kamala Harris, which he clarified is “a terrible place to be in.”</p> 
<p>The attacks are the latest in a simmering feud between Trump and Newsom, which escalated over the course of the week at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. Newsom was scheduled to speak at USA House on Wednesday as part of the conference, but his appearance was cancelled at the last minute. Newsom <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/newsom-administration-alleges-state-department-pressure-in-davos-cancellation-00738966" target="_blank">blamed the Trump administration</a>, but an organizer said they decided to focus on programming with business leaders.</p> 
<p>At Davos, Newsom met with world leaders, as did Bessent and Trump.</p> 
<p>Upon arriving, Newsom urged European leaders not to cave to Trump’s demands over a wide-range of foreign policy issues. In a panel at the conference, the California governor brandished a pair of kneepads bearing Trump’s signature to mock world leaders he feels have been overly accommodating of the president.</p> 
<p>Bessent dismissed the “strange things” Newsom has said to attack Trump, including the knee pad stunt and a comment in which <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/gavin-newsom-world-leaders-pathetic-donald-trump/" target="_blank">Newsom analogized Trump to a dinosaur</a>.</p> 
<p>“To say strange things like President Trump is a tyrannosaurus rex, what the hell does that mean? I can say Gavin Newsom is a brontosaurus with a brain the size of a walnut,” Bessent said. “And, if you brought the knee pads, maybe that was for his meeting with Alex Soros.”</p> 
<p>Bessent also defended the Trump administration from criticisms that they’re out of touch with the economic concerns of Americans. During a panel in Davos, Bessent said the administration wants to protect the investments of “mom and pop” retirees who may have purchased “5, 10, 12 homes.”</p> 
<p>In his defense, Bessent took another opportunity to swipe at Newsom, who he labeled “Patrick Bateman meets Sparkle Beach Ken” during a speech earlier at the conference.</p> 
<p>“I think it was a Dem governor, Newsom, who made the comment of being out of touch. What does he know? Like, his father worked for the Getty family,” Bessent said. “I actually think he knows less about economics than Kamala Harris, which is a terrible place to be in.”</p> 
<p>The full interview with Bessent will <a href="https://www.politico.com/podcasts/the-conversation" target="_blank">air on "The Conversation."</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scott Bessent at Davos on Greenland, affordability, and the Fed | The Conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/01/22/scott-bessent-at-davos-on-greenland-affordability-and-the-fed-the-conversation-1901907</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e86b-d452-a99b-e9ff15460000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 23:59:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">Scott Bessent at Davos on Greenland, affordability, and the Fed | The Conversation</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6388113445112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/fe2f6064-0eff-4f74-92a0-ea0a86b5354b/4e50ffab-3f64-4136-86cd-574e2d6df58b/main.mp4" src="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/fe2f6064-0eff-4f74-92a0-ea0a86b5354b/74aa1945-1192-4df5-98fa-96d8c2a0857c/1280x720/match/image.jpg">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Dems rally against ICE funding just one year after dozens broke ranks on immigration</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/dems-reject-ice-funding-immigration-00743033</link>
      <description>Only seven Democrats voted to give ICE more money on Thursday, a stark contrast from the 42 who backed the Laken Riley Act.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e7fe-d9a8-a7bf-e7feaa7c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 18:41:01 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e9/817d9db74eea9daab6d97ba473b0/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-47669.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tear gas is deployed amid protesters near the scene where Renee Good was fatally shot by an ICE officer last week, Tuesday, Jan. 13, 2026, in Minneapolis.(AP Photo/Adam Gray)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e9/817d9db74eea9daab6d97ba473b0/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-47669.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Democrats voted overwhelmingly Thursday to block additional funding for ICE, a remarkable shift from when dozens of them voted to expand the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement authority just one year ago — and a sign of how quickly the political ground has moved since President Donald Trump returned to the White House.</p> 
<p>Just seven Democrats voted for the Homeland Security spending bill that included billions for Immigration and Customs Enforcement: Reps. Henry Cuellar and Vicente Gonzalez of Texas, Jared Golden of Maine, Laura Gillen and Tom Suozzi of New York, Marie Gluesenkamp Perez of Washington and Don Davis of North Carolina. All represent tough terrain — Trump carried all of their districts but Gillen’s, which he lost by just over one point.</p> 
<p>Other Democrats, incensed by an ICE agent’s shooting of Renee Good in Minneapolis, voted against the bill — including many who voted exactly one year ago to pass the Laken Riley Act that allows for the detention of undocumented immigrants accused of certain crimes.</p> 
<p>One of them, Rep. Susie Lee (D-Nev.), a top GOP target in the midterms from a district Trump narrowly carried in 2024, argued this vote was different.</p> 
<p>“What we have seen time and again is ICE has blatantly violated our Constitution and our law, whether you’re talking about the shooting of a young mother to sending a five year old thousands of miles away to entice his father to turn himself in — this type of shit is not American,” Lee said in an interview Thursday. “ICE has plenty of money … I can’t in good conscience give them any more money until we get some type of guardrails.”</p> 
<p>Even the Democrats who voted for the funding were sharply critical of ICE.</p> 
<p>“I hate what ICE is doing in my district and across the country. It's atrocious. It's appalling. We should find ways to defund those operations in a surgical way,” Gonzalez said in a brief interview, adding that he supported the bill because it also included funding for Coast Guard and FEMA operations. “But voting no, just to make a statement, could have its own repercussions.”</p> 
<p>The House passed the DHS funding bill 220 to 207.</p> 
<p>Democrats’ near-united stand against the bill comes amid building opposition to Trump’s mass deportation campaign. A 49 percent plurality of voters in a new POLITICO poll conducted Jan. 16 to 19 said the effort — including Trump’s widespread deployment of ICE agents across the U.S. — is too aggressive.</p> 
<p>“The shift is dramatic. And I think the reason for the shift is: Last year the debate in the country was about getting control of the borders and out-of-control immigration. Now the entire situation is about ICE itself and its behavior,” Mark Longabaugh, a veteran Democratic strategist, said of the party’s recalibration on immigration.</p> 
<p>Amid the growing public furor over ICE’s hardline tactics, congressional Democrats had demanded that any new Homeland Security funding come with more guardrails.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/congress-clinches-funding-deal-for-dhs-pentagon-domestic-agencies-00735698" target="_blank"><u>bill most of them voted against Thursday funds ICE at $10 billion through the rest of the fiscal year</u></a> that ends in September, while cutting funding for removal and enforcement operations by $115 million and <a href="https://democrats-appropriations.house.gov/news/press-releases/appropriations-committees-release-homeland-security-funding-bill" target="_blank"><u>Border Patrol funding by $1.8 billion</u></a>. It also included some Democratic demands: decreasing the number of detention beds by 5,500, providing $20 million each for body cameras for agents and independent oversight of DHS detention facilities, and directing the department to give officers more training on diffusing conflict while interacting with the public.</p> 
<p>It does not include other items Democrats pushed for, however, such as banning agents from wearing masks during operations, requiring judicial warrants, preventing DHS from detaining and deporting U.S. citizens and blocking the department from using other agencies’ personnel for immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>The Democrats who voted in favor of the funding bill argued it was preferable to the alternative — giving Trump what Cuellar described as a “blank check” to carry out his hardline immigration agenda “virtually unchecked.”</p> 
<p>And some expressed concerns about ramifications for their districts if other agencies who receive their funding through DHS were cut off. Davis warned of the potential consequences of lapsed FEMA and Coast Guard funding in his home state of North Carolina that has been battered by storms and floods in recent years.</p> 
<p>“Obviously we should have the honest conversations about warrants. We should have the honest conversations about taking off the masks,” Davis said Thursday. But “if we can't consistently predict when disasters are coming our way, then we're leaving populations of people vulnerable.”</p> 
<p><i>Erin Doherty and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rahm Emanuel calls for mandatory retirement age for public officials — including him</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/rahm-emanuel-calls-for-mandatory-retirement-age-for-public-officials-including-him-00739398</link>
      <description>The potential 2028 White House hopeful called for a mandatory retirement age of 75 for government officials, which would keep him from serving a second presidential term if elected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e209-dabb-ad9f-ffedf73c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:27:30 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/15/c0/4a6ffe8d4754a97280b5d81c8e24/congress-us-china-87456.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former U.S. ambassador to Japan Rahm Emanuel testifies during a House Select Committee on China hearing on Capitol Hill, Wednesday, July 23, 2025, in Washington. (AP Photo/Mariam Zuhaib)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/15/c0/4a6ffe8d4754a97280b5d81c8e24/congress-us-china-87456.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rahm Emanuel said Wednesday he wants to institute a mandatory retirement age of 75 for the president and across branches of government, a pipe dream of a call from the potential White House hopeful that would bar him from serving a second term as president.</p> 
<p>“You’re 75 years old: done,” the former Chicago mayor and ambassador to Japan said Wednesday at a Center for American Progress event. “And that would be in the legislative branch, it’d be in the executive branch — including the Cabinet — and it’d be also in the Supreme Court, and all the federal courts.”</p> 
<p>Emanuel, who is 66, would be 69 when sworn into office if he runs for and wins the 2028 presidential contest. He would be 73 at the start of his second term, and would, by his own standard, be unable to serve all four years. He acknowledged this when pressed by POLITICO at a Christian Science Monitor roundtable Wednesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>“I know where I am in my age. Of course it would apply to me,” Emanuel said. “You can’t say ‘here’s what I want to do to change Washington, one of the things I want to do’ — but I get an exemption because I bought it beforehand.’”</p> 
<p>His standard would make Donald Trump, 79, ineligible to continue serving as president. And it would have barred Joe Biden, under whom Emanuel served as ambassador to Japan, from serving his single term. It would also impact the 17 senators and 45 members of the House who are currently 75 or older.</p> 
<p>“You can’t serve in the armed forces, you can’t serve in private sector jobs” at 75, Emanuel said. “Go work on your golf swing, it’s not that good to begin with.”</p> 
<p>Emanuel is reigniting a debate that raged throughout the last presidential election as Biden, then 81, and Trump, then 78, each sought a second term — and as questions about Biden’s mental and physical stamina crescendoed. And it’s simmered for years on Capitol Hill as lawmakers confront mental decline and even death within their ranks.</p> 
<p>Age limits are popular with voters who have balked in recent years at the advancing ages of the nation’s presidential contenders, lawmakers and Supreme Court justices. Roughly <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2023/10/04/most-americans-favor-maximum-age-limits-for-federal-elected-officials-supreme-court-justices/" target="_blank"><u>two-thirds of Americans support age limits</u></a> for federal elected officials and the Supreme Court, <a href="https://www.axios.com/2023/09/10/politicians-age-limits-joe-biden-mitch-mcconnell" target="_blank"><u>polls show</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Emanuel, a former representative, said he would push for legislation to set the limit rather than attempt a constitutional amendment. (The Constitution sets a minimum age for members of Congress but not a maximum, and establishes no limits for the Supreme Court.) It’s not clear whether that legislation itself would be constitutional — and could be a tough sell in a Congress where the median age for senators is 64.</p> 
<p>Emanuel framed the age limit as part of a broader call for “comprehensive ethics, lobbying [and] anti-corruption reform” across the federal government that he said should include a crackdown on lawmakers and judges <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/06/06/supreme-court-justices-millions-dollars-gifts-clarence-thomas.html" target="_blank"><u>taking gifts</u></a> and stock trading. The veteran Democratic strategist said his party should be hammering that message as part of a midterms platform that also includes raising the minimum wage and instituting a bill of rights for ratepayers.</p> 
<p>“You have a president of the United States, in my view, that has expanded, deepened the swamp. Our job is to drain the swamp as Democrats,” Emanuel said, turning Trump’s trademark phrase against him. “There’s not a day that goes by that you don’t read a story about either his family, [Commerce Secretary Howard] Lutnick’s family or [Special Envoy Steve] Witkoff’s family making money.”</p> 
<p>Emanuel’s choice of 75 may have been influenced by his brother, Ezekiel Emanuel, a former White House adviser and oncologist who <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2014/10/why-i-hope-to-die-at-75/379329/" target="_blank"><u>wrote in 2014</u></a> that he did not want to live past 75. In that piece, he wrote that his view “drives my brothers crazy.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-20T13:22:24-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Letlow launches Trump-backed Senate bid against Cassidy</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/letlow-senate-cassidy-trump-00736200</link>
      <description>While Sen. Bill Cassidy has maintained he will win, Trump’s endorsement of Letlow is a particular blow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-db8f-dcbd-afbb-dbff8ac00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:19:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7b/da/c8d472c24d3bb5b3a9213e62777e/election-2026-senate-louisiana-85307.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Brett Duke/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Julia Letlow speaks to reporters on Jan. 21, 2021, in Baton Rouge,Louisiana, after signing up to run for the 5th Congressional District.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7b/da/c8d472c24d3bb5b3a9213e62777e/election-2026-senate-louisiana-85307.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard, Erin Doherty and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard, Erin Doherty and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Julia Letlow announced her primary challenge to Sen. Bill Cassidy on Tuesday, just days after President Donald Trump lent his endorsement in the race.</p> 
<p>The entrance of Letlow, a Louisiana Republican who has served in Congress since 2021, is a major blow to Cassidy, who was already fending off another MAGA-aligned challenger in a state Trump carried by 22 points in 2024.</p> 
<p>“My parents taught me well. They taught me that when the Lord opens a door, you don’t walk through it — you run. It's an honor to share with you today that I’m officially announcing my candidacy for the United States Senate,” Letlow said at an annual business event with other state leaders in Baton Rouge, Louisiana, according to two people who attended the event. </p> 
<p>Cassidy said in a statement Letlow had called him beforehand.</p> 
<p>"She said she respected me and that I had done a good job," he said. "I will continue to do a good job when I win re-election."</p> 
<p>Trump upended the primary in the Republican state over the weekend when he preemptively endorsed Letlow. “Should she decide to enter this Race, Julia Letlow has my Complete and Total Endorsement. RUN, JULIA, RUN!!!” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115913724519885202" target="_blank">Trump wrote on Truth Social</a>.</p> 
<p>Letlow said that she was “honored to have President Trump’s endorsement and trust,” but did not immediately launch her bid after receiving the president’s public backing.</p> 
<p>Cassidy, seeking a third term in the Senate, has drawn criticism from Trump after voting to convict Trump in his 2021 impeachment trial over his role in the Jan. 6, 2021, Capitol riot. He has also clashed with the administration at times on health care, though he was a key vote to confirm Health and Human Services Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr. last year.</p> 
<p>While Cassidy has maintained he will win, Trump’s endorsement of Letlow is a serious blow to his chances. Cassidy has told fellow GOP senators that top White House officials promised him they would stay neutral in the race, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/04/bill-cassidy-trump-rfk-jr-louisiana-endorsement-00543192" target="_blank">as POLITICO reported in September</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump’s endorsement — and Letlow’s entrance into the race — also adds a new complication for Senate GOP leadership, which has backed Cassidy. </p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune campaigned with Cassidy in Lousiana late last week and privately encouraged Trump to support him during a call Friday. And Sen. John Barrasso of Wyoming, the No. 2 GOP leader, said Tuesday he has been supporting Cassidy "from the beginning."</p> 
<p>"We’re going to do everything we can to build the majority," Barrasso said when asked how much of a "headache" Trump's endorsement is for Republicans.</p> 
<p>Letlow first entered Congress after her husband, Rep.-elect Luke Letlow (R-La.), died of COVID before entering office, and in her Tuesday speech compared her career trajectory to that of former Rep. Lindy Boggs (D-La.), who won her House seat after her husband, Rep. Hale Boggs (D-La.), died in office.</p> 
<p>In office, Letlow has been a strong ally of both Speaker Mike Johnson and Majority Leader Steve Scalise, Louisiana's most powerful House members.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misreported Cassidy's whereabouts Tuesday. He did not attend the event where Letlow made her announcement, according to a spokesperson.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The states fighting to be at the front of Democrats’ 2028 presidential primary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/2028-democratic-presidential-primary-calendar-00731826</link>
      <description>States have until Friday to apply to be an early primary contest in 2028.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c318-dcbd-afbb-cb7bb3f00001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5f/4d/e2a747284baab1db2822c66345c7/election-2024-voting-calendar-23418.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Andrew Harnik/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>A woman takes a Democratic ballot to vote in the New Hampshire Primary at Parker-Varney Elementary School, Feb. 11, 2020, in Manchester, N.H.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5f/4d/e2a747284baab1db2822c66345c7/election-2024-voting-calendar-23418.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At least a half-dozen states applied to be in the early nominating window for 2028’s Democratic presidential campaign, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/25/dnc-2028-primary-states-iowa-new-hampshire-00521488" target="_blank"><u>kicking off a contentious battle</u></a> for securing an influential perch inside the primary calendar.</p> 
<p>The usual suspects — New Hampshire, Nevada, South Carolina and Michigan, who made up the early states in Democrats’ 2024 primary calendar, though not in the order set out by the Democratic National Committee — are all back, per their state parties. So is Iowa, hoping to reinsert itself into the process after it was bounced four years ago. Georgia also applied.</p> 
<p>Virginia and North Carolina are both seriously considering applying, according to three people familiar with the state’s thinking and granted anonymity to describe private conversations, ahead of the deadline later Friday. Other wild-card states may also still apply before the cutoff, and the DNC declined to comment on which states have applied so far.</p> 
<p>The presidential nominating calendar — which states are in it and in what order — will affect how Democratic presidential candidates tailor their strategies heading into a wide-open 2028 primary. It would inform which states to prioritize, where to place staff, how much money each state will cost a campaign — all calculations that have shaped previous presidential primaries. Unsurprisingly, Democrats have a lot of opinions on how that should go.</p> 
<p>“The day after the 2026 midterms, people are going to launch into action, so the window needs to be set,” said Jay Parmley, executive director of the South Carolina Democratic Party. “It’s possible they not only start coming, but they could start putting staff on the ground the earliest we’ve ever seen.”</p> 
<p>The process to set the process could stretch deep into 2026. Members of the DNC’s Rules and Bylaws Committee charged with setting the calendar are expected to winnow the field of applicants at their Jan. 31 meeting, according to three DNC members involved in the process and granted anonymity to discuss private conversations.</p> 
<p>States will then be invited to make presentations to the committee later that spring. One DNC member said they expected the calendar to be set over the summer and voted on by the full DNC at its August meeting, but the timeline could easily shift later into 2026.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/12/02/democrats-biden-2024-primaries-00071943" target="_blank"><u>Shaking up the presidential nominating calendar started back in 2022</u></a>, after Iowa’s disastrous 2020 caucuses and accusations that the early states didn’t reflect the party’s racial diversity. Then-President Joe Biden — ahead of what was at the time expected to be a staid primary process — elevated South Carolina even earlier in the order, cut Iowa and added Michigan to the calendar.</p> 
<p>Now, DNC officials have pledged to start the process from scratch. They’ve said they want all four regions of the country represented, as well as a potential extra state, to vote ahead of Super Tuesday. DNC members have also emphasized whether states represent racial and geographic diversity, the cost effectiveness for smaller presidential candidates and the general election competitiveness of the states.</p> 
<p>“The early states should be swing states,” said Curtis Hertel, chair of the Michigan Democratic Party. “The investments we’re making on the ground [in the primary] are beneficial to the general.”</p> 
<p>That’s led to two fights resurfacing: For some states, it’s about just getting into the window; others want to be first. Think Iowa, Michigan and Georgia for those hoping to be invited to the early window party. All three are vying to either return or get into it for the first time.</p> 
<p>For Georgia, the path is more complicated. Democrats don’t currently hold the governor’s mansion or the Legislature and almost assuredly won’t have a trifecta after the midterms, meaning they’d need GOP cooperation to move up their primary should the state be selected. But Georgia Democrats are confident they could adjust their date.</p> 
<p>“Even if there is a Republican [governor],” after the 2026 election, “Republicans in the past have very much wanted theirs to be earlier as well,” said Charlie Bailey, the Georgia Democratic Party’s chair. “All the logic in the world points to Republicans wanting to move up in their process for their own reasons.”</p> 
<p>The second group — including Nevada, New Hampshire and South Carolina — are all pushing for the influential first-place slot. Nevada, in particular, has been aggressive in their lobbying push of DNC members. New Hampshire released a memo last fall, emphasizing they wouldn’t just rely on a “tradition” argument to maintain their first-in-the-nation status.</p> 
<p>South Carolina, too, said it wants to keep its spot, after Biden elevated them to the coveted first official spot. (New Hampshire, however, still held its primary first in 2024 despite threats from the DNC, as required under state law.)</p> 
<p>“Our hope is that we maintain the position, but, of course, we’ll fully respect the decision and wishes of the RBC, even if we are unhappy,” said Parmley, the South Carolinian.</p> 
<p>In a statement, RBC Co-chairs Jim Roosevelt and Minyon Moore said: “The Rules and Bylaws Committee is committed to running a rigorous, efficient, and fair process that will deliver the strongest presidential nominee for our party. We look forward to continuing that work later this month when the committee begins consideration of state applications to hold their contest in the early window of the 2028 Democratic presidential nominating process.”</p> 
<p><i>Samuel Benson contributed to this report. A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists on the week in politics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2026/01/16/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00733019</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's an offering of the best of this week's crop, picked fresh off the Toonosphere. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c488-dd3c-a5df-eefae1920000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Talarico leads Crockett in Texas Senate primary, according to new poll</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/talarico-crockett-texas-senate-primary-poll-00730929</link>
      <description>An Emerson College poll finds state Rep. James Talarico with a 9-point lead in the Democratic primary and Sen. John Cornyn neck and neck with Attorney General Ken Paxton on the GOP side.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-c27f-dcbd-afbb-ca7f11980001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:00:25 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4a/66/a8634cea4c6eb620fd1f31f3aafd/texas-legislature-54637.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Eric Gay/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Texas state Rep. James Talarico speaks during a rally to protest against redistricting hearings at the Texas Capitol on July 24, 2025, in Austin.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4a/66/a8634cea4c6eb620fd1f31f3aafd/texas-legislature-54637.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>James Talarico has leapt ahead in the Texas Senate Democratic primary with a 9-point lead over Rep. Jasmine Crockett, according to <a href="https://emersoncollegepolling.com/texas-2026-poll/" target="_blank">new polling</a> from Emerson College released Thursday.</p> 
<p>The data shows Talarico, a state representative from Austin, leading the Dallas Congress member by 47 percent to 38 percent ahead of their March 3 primary.</p> 
<p>When Crockett <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/08/crockett-announces-texas-senate-bid-00680505" target="_blank">jumped into the race</a> in December, her national prominence and fundraising strength had some expecting her to take the lead in the primary. But Talarico has poured money into his campaign and built a large online following.</p> 
<p>On the GOP side, the poll shows a tight race: Attorney General Ken Paxton leads Sen. John Cornyn by 1 point, at 27 to 26 percent, with Rep. Wesley Hunt sitting at 16 percent support. The race is widely expected to head to a May 26 runoff since no candidate is close to 50 percent support, which would extend the brutal GOP primary.</p> 
<p>Democrats have long pined for winning statewide in Texas yet repeatedly fallen short. The party believes it can ride an anticipated electoral wave fueled by opposition to Trump to finally achieve that goal. Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/schumer-thinks-these-four-states-will-deliver-for-dems-in-november-00727181" target="_blank">told POLITICO</a> earlier this week that he views Texas as a “very possible” pickup opportunity but didn’t list it among the party’s top four offensive opportunities.</p> 
<p>There’s a stark racial split between Talarico's and Crockett's blocs of support. Talarico brings in majority support from Hispanic and white voters, while the large majority of Black voters back Crockett, according to the poll’s findings. Men support Talarico 52 percent to 30 percent, while women are evenly divided between the two, at 44 and 43 percent respectively.</p> 
<p>Many Republican voters remain outraged at Cornyn for supporting a bipartisan gun control bill during the Biden administration and have threatened to vote him out of office as punishment. Paxton, Texas’ top attorney for a decade, has strong support from the MAGA base, despite facing multiple state and federal investigations.</p> 
<p>Democrats are hoping that Paxton will win the GOP primary, believing his political baggage would turn off voters in the general election. The poll shows both Talarico and Crockett tied with Paxton at 46 percent in a hypothetical matchup. Cornyn would fare better: He would lead Talarico 47 to 44 percent, and Crockett 48 to 43 percent.</p> 
<p>The economy stands as the top issue for Texas voters, followed by immigration and threats to democracy.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bill Cassidy raises $1.65 million for reelection fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/cassidy-raises-1-65m-00730420</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-beee-d22e-a1db-bfff1a880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:02:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Bill Cassidy raised $1.65 million in the latest fundraising quarter and has $11 million in cash on hand, his team told POLITICO, as he seeks to ward off a right-wing primary challenge.</p> 
<p>The Louisiana Republican is facing several primary challengers on the right fueled by his past criticism of President Donald Trump. Cassidy voted to impeach Trump following the Jan. 6, 2021, attack against the Capitol, a stance that angered the GOP base in Louisiana.</p> 
<p>Cassidy has consistently posted slightly higher fundraising numbers than his opponents, John Fleming, the state treasurer and a former congressman, and state Sen. Blake Miguez, but has a significantly larger war chest. Cassidy has raised more than $17 million this cycle to date. Fleming and Miguez haven’t released their latest numbers; they had just over $2 million and $2.5 million in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/15/congress/bill-cassidy-fec-deadline-primary-challengers-00610818" target="_blank">the bank</a> respectively as of the end of September. Rep. Julia Letlow (R-La.) has also flirted with a bid, though <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">sources told POLITICO</a> she is not expected to run; she had $2.3 million in the bank as of the end of September.</p> 
<p>The senator will have some help. A pair of super PACs supporting Cassidy’s reelection will show they had $5 million in cash on hand at the end of 2025 and received an additional $2 million in the first two weeks of January, according to a person close to those efforts. The PACs expect to spend between $13 million and $15 million on his behalf.</p> 
<p>Cassidy is one of a trio of GOP senators facing tough reelection fights where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">Trump is declining to endorse a candidate</a>, along with Texas Sen. John Cornyn and Maine Sen. Susan Collins.</p> 
<p>Cassidy’s Senate GOP colleagues are backing his reelection. On Thursday, Majority Leader John Thune will host a fundraiser for Cassidy in Baton Rouge that’s expected to bring in $600,000.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-15T18:22:39-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Latino voters powered Trump’s comeback. Now they’re turning on his economy.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/latino-voters-powered-trumps-comeback-now-theyre-turning-on-his-economy-00726548</link>
      <description>Hispanic small business owners are souring on the Trump economy, a warning sign to Republicans ahead of this year’s midterms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b982-da56-afff-bd9225610001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/11/74/1b0726414d549e42ba7e117b7668/201101-trump-az-ap-773.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Andrew Harnik/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump arrives for a Latinos for Trump Coalition roundtable at Arizona Grand Resort &amp;amp; Spa in Phoenix on Sept. 14, 2020.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/11/74/1b0726414d549e42ba7e117b7668/201101-trump-az-ap-773.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson and Alec Hernandez</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson and Alec Hernandez</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 2024, economic anxiety and immigration concerns drove Latino voters to President Donald Trump. Those same issues are beginning to push them away.</p> 
<p>Across the country, the cost-of-living woes and immigration enforcement overshadowing Trump’s first year back in office are souring Hispanic businesspeople, a key constituency that helped propel him to the White House. In <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1jOEqWhlc-vU_3pxtKLRxojF8wzVCkd5-cjZz4GZU2RI/edit?gid=0#gid=0" target="_blank"><u>a recent survey of Hispanic business owners</u></a> conducted by the U.S. Hispanic Business Council and shared exclusively with POLITICO, 42 percent said their economic situation is getting worse, while only 24 said it was getting better. Seventy percent of respondents ranked the cost of living as a top-three issue facing the country, more than double the number that selected any other issue.</p> 
<p>That’s a particularly striking number from this group: nearly two-thirds of respondents in the organization’s final survey before the 2024 election said they trusted Trump more than then-Vice President Kamala Harris to handle the economy.</p> 
<p>“The broader Hispanic community certainly feels let down,” said Javier Palomarez, the organization’s president and CEO. “It would be different if immigration and the economy had not been principal talking points for [Trump]. On both fronts, we didn't get what we thought we were going to get.”</p> 
<p>The combination of ongoing economic uncertainty and stubbornly high prices driven by Trump’s tariffs — coupled with the economic impact of the Trump administration’s ongoing raids in immigrant-heavy communities — makes the situation increasingly dire for some Hispanic business owners.</p> 
<p>Trump and his allies argue that they're just cleaning up the mess left by the previous president.</p> 
<p>"Republicans are putting in the work to fix the Bidenflation mess we inherited. From lowering inflation to creating a housing plan, President Trump is fighting for the working families Democrats left behind," said Republican National Committee spokeswoman Delanie Bomar.</p> 
<p>Monica Villalobos, president and CEO of the Arizona Hispanic Chamber of Commerce, told POLITICO about a South Phoenix restaurant hit hard by tariffs and labor shortages. Then, a series of ICE raids in the parking lot in front of the restaurant caused customers and workers to stop showing up and forced the owners to shut it down for several days. She predicted this kind of situation will blow back on Republicans in the next election.</p> 
<p>“We certainly do sense that our members — our clients in Arizona and across the country — feel a sense of betrayal by this administration, given its excessive overreach,” Villalobos said. “Now that we've had a taste of [the Trump administration], I think you're going to see a big shift [in the vote].”</p> 
<p>In 2024, Trump won <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2025/06/26/behind-trumps-2024-victory-a-more-racially-and-ethnically-diverse-voter-coalition/" target="_blank"><u>48 percent of self-described Hispanic or Latino voters</u></a>, the highest mark for a Republican presidential candidate <a href="https://search.issuelab.org/resource/the-exit-polls-a-history-and-trends-over-time-1972-2020.html" target="_blank"><u>in at least a half-century</u></a>, driven largely by economic anxiety. But polling shows Trump’s approval among Latino voters cratering as their satisfaction with the economy and immigration enforcement plummet.</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/poll-americans-trump-voters-affordability-crisis-00674747" target="_blank"><u>a November POLITICO Poll</u></a>, a plurality — 48 percent — of Hispanic respondents said the cost of living in the U.S. is “the worst I can ever remember it being,” and a majority (67 percent) said responsibility lies with the president to fix it.</p> 
<p>According to <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/race-and-ethnicity/2025/11/24/majorities-of-latinos-disapprove-of-trump-and-his-policies-on-immigration-economy/" target="_blank"><u>a November Pew Research poll</u></a>, about two-thirds (68 percent) of U.S. Hispanics say their situation today is worse than it was a year ago, and just nine percent say it is better; 65 percent of Latinos disagree with this administration’s approach to immigration, and a majority (52 percent) said they worried they, a family member or a close friend could be deported, a ten-point increase since March.</p> 
<p>Trump’s favorability rating among Hispanics is now at 28 percent, per <a href="https://d3nkl3psvxxpe9.cloudfront.net/documents/econTabReport_qsNv5iE.pdf" target="_blank"><u>a recent The Economist/YouGov poll</u></a>, 13 points lower than it was <a href="https://d3nkl3psvxxpe9.cloudfront.net/documents/econTabReport_1q7T4HA.pdf" target="_blank"><u>in February of last year</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“Small business owners are becoming a swing constituency, when you think about the midterms coming up,” said Tayde Aburto, president and CEO of the Hispanic Chamber of E-Commerce. “And not because their values have changed—it's just because their costs did.”</p> 
<p>Latino voters have swung hard back toward Democrats in recent elections as well. In Passaic County, New Jersey, Latinos voted narrowly for Trump in 2024 but in November <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/11/latino-voters-trump-democrats-00646300" target="_blank"><u>backed Democratic Governor-elect Mikie Sherrill by double digits</u></a>. And in Miami, where over 70 percent of residents are Hispanic, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/miami-elects-first-woman-mayor-ends-gops-28-year-control-of-city-hall-00683878" target="_blank"><u>a Democratic mayor was elected last month</u></a> for the first time in 28 years last month.</p> 
<p>Those elections are a referendum on Trump’s economy, said Christian Ulvert, a Democratic strategist and adviser to newly-elected Miami Mayor Eileen Higgins’ campaign.</p> 
<p>“[Trump’s] agenda literally does little to nothing to help Hispanic families,” Ulvert said. “Worse, it preys on Hispanic families. And what we heard on the campaign trail most pointedly is the old adage: is my life better today than it was yesterday under new leaders? And resoundingly, not only verbally, but through the ballot box throughout the year, Hispanic families are saying, ‘no, my life is actually worse.’”</p> 
<p>Joe Vichot, the Republican Party chair in Lehigh County, Pennsylvania, said he knows many Hispanic Republicans in Allentown who are supportive of curbing illegal immigration and fighting crime. “But there's also stories of people who have been here for 10 years or more with their family, but they've never been legal, that are now caught up into the [deportation] system,” he said.</p> 
<p>“There should be a way to find some type of common ground where that won't happen.”</p> 
<p>The White House has tried to ease the ailing economic sentiment by sending Trump and Vice President JD Vance on the road, delivering <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/never-going-to-be-pitch-perfect-trump-loyalists-see-an-imperfect-messenger-00685649" target="_blank"><u>a series of stump speeches</u></a> on affordability in working-class areas, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/16/vance-tries-to-thread-affordability-needle-in-rust-belt-00693642" target="_blank"><u>Vance’s Dec. 16 stop in Lehigh County, Pennsylvania</u></a>, which includes the Hispanic-majority city of Allentown. They insist the economy deserves an “A+++” grade, and are now buoyed by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/inflation-report-trump-economy-00724227" target="_blank"><u>a December consumer price index report released Tuesday</u></a> that showed inflation rising at a slower pace than expected.</p> 
<p>“Joe Biden gave us a colossal catastrophe, but my administration has rapidly and very decisively ended that,” Trump said during a speech in Detroit Tuesday. “We have quickly achieved the exact opposite of stagflation — almost no inflation and super high growth.”</p> 
<p>But cooling inflation rates just mean prices aren’t rising as fast as they had been — prices still remain much higher on many goods than they had been in recent years. And improving macroeconomic trends are not yet being felt by consumers, said Massey Villarreal, a business executive in Houston.</p> 
<p>“I'm like most Americans. I hear the inflation number and I don’t translate it to my going to the grocery store, when I look at the cost of hamburger meat,” said Villarreal, a former chair of the Republican National Hispanic Assembly.</p> 
<p>Palomarez, the U.S. Hispanic Business Council president, compared it to the Biden administration’s insistence that the post-Covid economy was healthy, even as consumer sentiment plunged. “While we were talking about GDP and unemployment and jobs growth rates, people were worried about the rent and the price of gas and the price of eggs. And we've got kind of the same thing here," he said.</p> 
<p>In Chicago, where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/28/bovino-federal-judge-chicago-immigration-00625519" target="_blank"><u>some of the most-publicized immigration enforcement occurred</u></a> last year, Hispanic-run businesses have been hit hard. Sam Sanchez, CEO of Third Coast Hospitality, said 2025 was the hardest period for business of his four decades in restauranteering, aside from the COVID pandemic.</p> 
<p>“It sends a really negative message to the 48 percent of Hispanic voters that voted for President Trump,” Sanchez said. “Everything’s just starting to fall apart.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-14T11:23:57-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Virginia Democrats look to decimate GOP seats in redistricting effort</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/virginia-redistricting-democrats-republicans-seats-00723660</link>
      <description>But some Democrats warn that the effort may be more difficult than it looks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b48d-da56-afff-bc9f92b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 19:23:38 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/13/6b/858d53be4d40b5d435c5a742dcf9/virginia-legislature-64340.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Steve Helber/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Chairman of the Virginia State Senate Finance Committee, Sen. Louise Lucas, D-Portsmouth, applauds after the Senate passed it's version of the state budget at the Capitol, in Richmond, Virginia, May. 13, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/13/6b/858d53be4d40b5d435c5a742dcf9/virginia-legislature-64340.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Virginia Democrats are launching their last big campaign in the redistricting wars this week — but big questions loom about whether they can agree on how to maximize benefits to their party and whether they can convince voters to support their power grab.</p> 
<p>On Wednesday, the Virginia Legislature kicks off its first session since Democrats won unified control of the commonwealth in last November’s elections. A persistent divide has emerged however, between Democrats who hope to draw an aggressive gerrymander that could deliver them 10 of the state’s 11 congressional seats — a four-seat grab for their side that would wipe out all but one GOP congressional district — and those who want to take a more subtle approach to offsetting GOP gerrymanders elsewhere.</p> 
<p>“It will be a real debate. I mean, we want to get as much as we can, but we also want the referendum to pass,” Rep. Don Beyer (D-Va.) told POLITICO Tuesday afternoon, adding that an expected Supreme Court decision this year on the Voting Rights Act could ultimately give Republicans more seats.</p> 
<p>“[Democrats] basically have voting rights act seats in South Carolina, Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi and Louisiana,” he said. “They could all be gone, right? So that's a great concern. So it's essential in Virginia that we look at the fairness argument from a national perspective, not just the Commonwealth.”</p> 
<p>Virginia’s current congressional delegation has six Democrats and five Republicans, so under the new maps Democrats would likely pick up three or four seats.</p> 
<p>Democrats are worried that some of their members won’t be as eager to take on so much in such a truncated period of time. The party will need to be unified if they stand any chance of selling voters on the urgency of empowering legislators to draw new Congressional lines within a matter of weeks.</p> 
<p>“I haven’t heard a lot of people talking about how much work it’s going to be to pass it,” said one Virginia Democrat granted anonymity to discuss internal party discussions. The person added that some in the party are underestimating the amount of time and political capital it will take to prop up a statewide campaign for what is expected to be a special election in April.</p> 
<p>The National Democratic Redistricting Committee, the party’s group leading the charge on redistricting, confirmed to POLITICO it has presented two new maps to Virginia lawmakers. One remakes the map into a 9-2 configuration that only provides cover for districts held by Republican Reps. Ben Cline and Morgan Griffith from being eliminated. Another proposed map largely leaves intact Griffiths’ seat and, if approved, could deliver a 10-1 map, a development <a href="https://punchbowl.news/article/the-daily-punch/gop-stumble-2026/" target="_blank">first reported by Punchbowl News</a>.</p> 
<p>John Bisognano, the NDRC president, argues that aggressive changes to the current Virginia congressional maps are necessary to respond to brazen gerrymanders Republicans drew in other states under pressure from President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>“Not for one second has Donald Trump laid down arms in this redistricting manufactured war that he created,” he said, adding that Democrats have so far fought him nearly to a draw after states like Indiana rebuffed Trump’s pressure campaign to take up recasting the state’s congressional lines.</p> 
<p>Emboldened by their better-than-expected wins in statewide elections last year, Virginia’s legislative leaders say they want to eliminate as many GOP seats as possible.</p> 
<p>“I said in August of 2025 that the maps will be 10-1 and I’m sticking with that today,” Virginia state Senate President Pro Tem L. Louise Lucas <a href="https://x.com/SenLouiseLucas/status/2009676762871967947?s=20" target="_blank">recently posted on social media</a>. “Anyone in the congressional delegation who wants a seat needs to campaign for it and not expect a safe seat.”</p> 
<p>Virginia’s Democratic House Speaker Don Scott also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/virginia-house-speaker-optimism-supreme-court-00684139" target="_blank">previously said he’s open to a 10-1 map</a> that favors his party. Scott and Lucas did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>State Sen. Ryan McDougle, the top Republican in Virginia’s upper chamber, criticized Democrats’ redistricting push just five years after voters passed a constitutional amendment that gave the authority to draw legislative and congressional lines to a bipartisan commission of state lawmakers and citizens. And he argued it would mark the permanent end of independent redistricting in the state.</p> 
<p>“If this goes through, I find it hard to believe that we will not return to a path of gerrymandering in the future, because if [Democrats] can do it … I'm sure somebody will come up with a situation in the future that is just as egregious and do it back.”</p> 
<p>McDougle is a plaintiff in a lawsuit seeking to block Democrats from what it says is “an unconstitutional redistricting amendment.”</p> 
<p>“It's an illegal and unconstitutionally passed measure,” said Michael Young, a Virginia-based Republican consultant working to block Democrats’ redistricting push in the state. Previous conservative-led <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2025/11/07/judges-cool-to-legal-challenges-as-democrats-move-to-redraw-virginias-maps/" target="_blank">legal challenges</a> to the current redistricting battles in Virginia have so far been unsuccessful.</p> 
<p>Virginia’s redistricting effort comes days after Florida GOP Gov. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/desantis-florida-redistricting-special-session-00713882?can_id=c21e952e3462b1deb7503e90924b70ce&amp;email_referrer=email_3043804&amp;email_subject=progress-florida-daily-clips-1-8-26&amp;link_id=0" target="_blank">Ron DeSantis called for a special legislative session in April</a> focused on mid-cycle redistricting that some predict could net Republicans between three to five seats. DeSantis said he wants to wait until April so he can get “guidance” from the Supreme Court since the justices are expected to rule later this year in a landmark voting rights case that could prohibit states from considering race when drawing new districts and give Republicans a freer hand to erase minority-majority districts. Some predict that, depending on the ruling, the high court’s decision <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/republicans-scotus-vra-00597212" target="_blank">could help Republicans gain upwards of 19 seats</a> across several states.</p> 
<p>“We know we have work to do, and I think we understand the assignment,” said state Sen. Lamont Bagby, who also serves as the chair of the Virginia Democratic Party.</p> 
<p>Bagby said his party needs other Democratic-led states to join California, which passed a ballot initiative in November to help thwart Trump’s push to eliminate seats currently held by Democrats in red-leaning states. Already, Texas, North Carolina, and Missouri have changed their maps, though some GOP-led states like Indiana have bucked the president. Bagby said if Democrats stand any chance of taking back the House, they need to fight using new rules of engagement that Republicans are utilizing.</p> 
<p>“They've already done enough to force us to put this to voters,” Bagby said. “I don't think anything's changed.”</p> 
<p>An unanswered question is how big of a role the incoming Democratic Gov. Abigail Spanberger, who will be sworn in on Saturday, will play in the redistricting fight. She bested her GOP gubernatorial challenger Winsome Earle-Sears by 15 points and Republicans lost at least 13 seats in the House of Delegates. A week before those elections, Democrats approved the first step of a multi-step process to amend the state’s constitution to redraw congressional lines before the next Census in 2030.</p> 
<p>In an appearance on “<a href="https://www.cbs.com/shows/video/AWcw74QxrNR_7FeF4S_akN9DKCqyxd4v/" target="_blank">The Late Show with Stephen Colbert</a>” on Monday she expressed a desire to make good on campaign promises of making life more affordable for Virginians, but made no mention of redistricting. During a POLITICO forum in Richmond last month, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/spanberger-redistricting-00683066" target="_blank">she stopped short of embracing a redistricting overhaul</a> that other governors have championed, including Gavin Newsom of California.</p> 
<p>After the Legislature gavels in on Wednesday, lawmakers are expected to pass another amendment that will pave the way for Spanberger to call a special election in the spring. That election will allow voters to decide whether to give state lawmakers authority to amend the state constitution and approve new congressional maps.</p> 
<p>“In light of what Texas, Missouri and now, Florida seem to be doing, it seems like we have a right to be in a position where we can take action if … Virginia voters allow us to do so,” Virginia Senate Majority Leader Scott Surovell, a Democrat, said in an interview.</p> 
<p>Surovell said he does not foresee any major hurdles to a new map passage, though he anticipates there will need to be some reworking of the elections calendar to accommodate new candidate filing deadlines for federal House races once new maps are approved. The current deadline for House candidates is April 2, <a href="https://www.elections.virginia.gov/media/candidatesandpacs/2026-candidate-bulletins/2026-06-16_US_House_Prim_One_Pager_(12-29-25).pdf" target="_blank">according to the Virginia Department of Elections</a>.</p>CORRECTION: This story has been updated to correct the name of the National Democratic Redistricting Committee.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scott Adams, whose comic strip ‘Dilbert’ ridiculed white-collar office life, dies at 68</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/scott-adams-dead-at-68-00724995</link>
      <description>His first ex-wife, Shelly Miles, announced the death on a livestream posted on Adams’ social media accounts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b846-da56-afff-bcd6f6ce0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:02:12 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7d/70/66da483d4d849ebd68a325aaf598/obit-scott-adams-61370.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>FILE - Scott Adams, creator of the comic strip Dilbert, talks about his work at his studio in Dublin, Calif., on Oct. 26, 2006. (AP Photo/Marcio Jose Sanchez, File)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7d/70/66da483d4d849ebd68a325aaf598/obit-scott-adams-61370.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Associated Press</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Associated Press</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Scott Adams, whose popular comic strip “Dilbert” captured the frustration of beleaguered, white-collar cubicle workers and satirized the ridiculousness of modern office culture until he was abruptly dropped from syndication in 2023 for racist remarks, has died. He was 68.</p> 
<p>His first ex-wife, Shelly Miles, announced the death Tuesday on a livestream posted on Adams’ social media accounts. “He’s not with us right anymore,” she said. Adams revealed in 2025 that he had prostate cancer that had spread to his bones. Miles had said he was in hospice care in his Northern California home on Monday.</p> 
<p>“I had an amazing life,” the statement said in part. “I gave it everything I had.”</p> 
<p>At its height, “Dilbert,” with its mouthless, bespectacled hero in a white short-sleeved shirt and a perpetually curled red tie, appeared in 2,000 newspapers worldwide in at least 70 countries and 25 languages.</p> 
<p>Adams was the 1997 recipient of the National Cartoonist Society’s Reuben Award, considered one of the most prestigious awards for cartoonists. That same year, “Dilbert” became the first fictional character to make Time magazine’s list of the most influential Americans.</p> 
<p>“We are rooting for him because he is our mouthpiece for the lessons we have accumulated — but are too afraid to express — in our effort to avoid cubicular homicide,” the magazine said.</p> 
<p>“Dilbert” strips were routinely photocopied, pinned up, emailed and posted online, a popularity that would spawn bestselling books, merchandise, commercials for Office Depot and an animated TV series, with Daniel Stern voicing Dilbert.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">The collapse of ‘Dilbert’ empire</h4> 
<p>It all collapsed quickly in 2023 when Adams, who was white, repeatedly referred to Black people as members of a “hate group” and said he would no longer “help Black Americans.” He later said he was being hyperbolic, yet continued to defend his stance.</p> 
<p>Almost immediately, newspapers dropped “Dilbert” and his distributor, Andrews McMeel Universal, severed ties with the cartoonist. The Sun Chronicle in Attleboro, Massachusetts, decided to keep the “Dilbert” space blank for a while “as a reminder of the racism that pervades our society.” A planned book was scrapped.</p> 
<p>“He’s not being canceled. He’s experiencing the consequences of expressing his views,” Bill Holbrook, the creator of the strip “On the Fastrack,” told The Associated Press at the time. “I am in full support with him saying anything he wants to, but then he has to own the consequences of saying them.”</p> 
<p>Adams relaunched the same daily comic strip under the name Dilbert Reborn via the video platform Rumble, popular with conservatives and far-right groups. He also hosted a podcast, “Real Coffee,” where talked about various political and social issues.</p> 
<p>After Jimmy Kimmel’s late-night show on ABC was suspended in September in the wake of the host’s comments on the murder of conservative activist Charlie Kirk, Adams stood for free speech.</p> 
<p>“Would I like some revenge?” Adams said. “Yes. Yes, I would enjoy that. But that doesn’t mean I get it. That doesn’t mean I should pursue it. Doesn’t mean the world’s a better place if it happens.”</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">How ‘Dilbert’ got its start</h4> 
<p>Adams, who earned a bachelor’s degree from Hartwick College and an MBA from the University of California, Berkeley, was working a corporate job at the Pacific Bell telephone company in the 1980s, sharing his cartoons to amuse co-workers. He drew Dilbert as a computer programmer and engineer for a high-tech company and mailed a batch to cartoon syndicators.</p> 
<p>“The take on office life was new and on target and insightful,” Sarah Gillespie, who helped discover “Dilbert” in the 1980s at United Media, told The Washington Post. “I looked first for humor and only secondarily for art, which with ‘Dilbert’ was a good thing, as the art is universally acknowledged to be… not great.”</p> 
<p>The first “Dilbert” comic strip officially appeared April 16, 1989, long before such workplace comedies as “Office Space” and “The Office.” It portrayed corporate culture as a “Severance”-like, Kafkaesque world of heavy bureaucracy and pointless benchmarks, where employee effort and skill were underappreciated.</p> 
<p>The strip would introduce the “Dilbert Principle”: The most ineffective workers will be systematically moved to the place where they can do the least damage — management.</p> 
<p>“Throughout history, there have always been times when it’s very clear that the managers have all the power and the workers have none,” Adams told Time. “Through ‘Dilbert,’ I would think the balance of power has slightly changed.”</p> 
<p>Other strip characters included Dilbert’s pointy-haired boss; Asok, a young, naive intern; Wally, a middle-aged slacker; and Alice, a worker so frustrated that she was prone to frequent outbursts of rage. Then there was Dilbert’s pet, Dogbert, a megalomaniac.</p> 
<p>“There’s a certain amount of anger you need to draw ‘Dilbert’ comics,” Adams told the Contra Costa Times in 2009.</p> 
<p>In 1993, Adams became the first syndicated cartoonist to include his email address in his strip. That triggered a dialogue between the artist and his fans, giving Adams a fountain of ideas for the strip.</p> 
<p>“Dilbert” was also known for generating aphorisms, like “All rumors are true — especially if your boss denies them” and “OK, let’s get this preliminary pre-meeting going.”</p> 
<p>“If you can come to peace with the fact that you’re surrounded by idiots, you’ll realize that resistance is futile, your tension will dissipate, and you can sit back and have a good laugh at the expense of others,” Adams wrote in his 1996 book “The Dilbert Principle.”</p> 
<p>In one real-life case, an Iowa worker was fired from the Catfish Bend Casino in 2007 for posting a “Dilbert” comic strip on the office bulletin board. In the strip, Adams wrote: “Why does it seem as if most of the decisions in my workplace are made by drunken lemurs?” A judge later sided with the worker; Adams helped find him a new job.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">A gradual darkening</h4> 
<p>While Adams’ career fall seemed swift, careful readers of “Dilbert” saw a gradual darkening of the strip’s tone and its creator’s descent into misogyny, anti-immigration and racism.</p> 
<p>He attracted attention for controversial comments, including saying in 2011 that women are treated differently by society for the same reason as children and the mentally disabled — “it’s just easier this way for everyone.” In a blog post from 2006, he questioned the death toll of the Holocaust.</p> 
<p>In June 2020, Adams tweeted that when the “Dilbert” TV show ended in 2000 after just two seasons, it was “the third job I lost for being white.” But, at the time, he blamed it on lower viewership and time slot changes.</p> 
<p>Adams’ beliefs began bleeding into his strips. In one in 2022, a boss says that traditional performance reviews would be replaced by a “wokeness” score. When an employee complains that could be subjective, the boss said, “That’ll cost you two points off your wokeness score, bigot.”</p> 
<p>Adams put a brave face on his fall from grace, tweeting in 2023: “Only the dying leftist Fake News industry canceled me (for out-of-context news of course). Social media and banking unaffected. Personal life improved. Never been more popular in my life. Zero pushback in person. Black and White conservatives solidly supporting me.”</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, President Donald Trump remembered Adams as a “Great Influencer.”</p> 
<p>“He was a fantastic guy, who liked and respected me when it wasn’t fashionable to do so. He bravely fought a long battle against a terrible disease,” the president posted on his social media platform Truth Social.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-12T10:43:53-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Former Rep. Mary Peltola jumps into Alaska Senate race</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/peltola-alaska-senate-2026-midterms-00721596</link>
      <description>The former Alaska congressmember will likely face off against Sen. Dan Sullivan (R-Alaska), and is a recruitment coup for national Democrats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-aeb1-dca0-ad9b-ffb947aa0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/26/67/e4509106407d966985b9b1af2e0e/elections-2024-house-71701.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Becky Bohrerm/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Mary Peltola speaks to reporters after giving an address to state lawmakers on Feb. 17, 2023, in Juneau, Alaska.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/26/67/e4509106407d966985b9b1af2e0e/elections-2024-house-71701.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Rep. Mary Peltola entered the Alaska Senate race on Monday, giving Democrats a major candidate recruitment win and the chance to expand the 2026 Senate map as they look for a route to the majority.</p> 
<p>The Alaska Democrat’s decision is a victory for Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/06/democrats-senate-house-races-2025-wins-00639344" target="_blank">recruited Peltola</a> to run against Sen. Dan Sullivan (R-Alaska). Peltola’s brand as a moderate problem-solver and the state’s ranked-choice voting system open the door for Democrats, but it’s still a steep climb in a state President Donald Trump won by 13 percentage points in 2024.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mdgs-jID4T4" target="_blank">In her announcement video</a>, Peltola pledged to focus on “fish, family and freedom,” while also calling for term limits and putting “Alaska first.”</p> 
<p>“Systemic change is the only way to bring down grocery costs, save our fisheries, lower energy prices and build new housing Alaskans can afford,” Peltola said. “It’s about time Alaskans teach the rest of the country what Alaska First and, really, America First looks like.”</p> 
<p>Peltola’s campaign creates another offensive opportunity in play for Democrats, who must flip four seats in order to retake the majority next fall. The odds are long, but Democrats have become increasingly bullish about their chances since their victories in last year’s elections. Peltola <a href="https://alaskapublic.org/news/2024-03-28/peltolas-votes-show-shes-one-of-the-least-loyal-democrats-in-the-u-s-house" target="_blank">carved a moderate profile</a> during her time in Congress, occasionally voting with Republicans on energy and immigration-related legislation.</p> 
<p>Even so, Peltola’s decision to run Alaska presents tough sledding for any Democrat. Peltola’s 2022 wins came in large part because of a bitterly divided GOP field, and besides her victories that year, Democrats have won just one other federal race in Alaska in the last half-century.</p> 
<p>Peltola was first elected in a September 2022 special election to replace Rep. Don Young, who served 49 years in the House and died while in office. She cited Young and former Sen. Ted Stevens, both Republicans, in her Senate announcement, who Peltola said “ignored Lower 48 partisanship to fight for things like public media and disaster relief because Alaska depends on them.”</p> 
<p>In November 2022, Peltola won a full term, beating a divided Republican field that featured former Alaska Gov. Sarah Palin and Nick Begich. But in 2024, Peltola narrowly lost in a rematch with Begich, when the Republican Party consolidated behind him. She had also been mulling a run for governor this year, making her decision to go for the Senate a big win for Washington Democrats.</p> 
<p>Democrats have an easier time winning if Republicans fracture between candidates in a state where ranked-choice voting means every candidate faces off against each other in the first round of voting, and Sullivan has not drawn any serious GOP challengers.</p> 
<p>Peltola will also be without a crucial bipartisan supporter from her past races. Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) immediately endorsed Sullivan on Monday, after crossing party lines to endorse Peltola in both 2022 and 2024.“We've had a pretty solid team here in the Senate for the past 12 years, so we want to figure out how we're going to keep in the majority,” she <a href="https://alaskapublic.org/news/politics/washington-d-c/2026-01-12/mary-peltola-enters-alaska-u-s-senate-race" target="_blank">told Alaska Public Media</a>. “And Dan delivers that.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski and Peltola go way back—they served together in the Alaska legislature starting in the late 1990s, and Peltola backed Murkowski in her 2010 write-in election general victory after she lost the GOP primary. But Murkowski and Sullivan have had a strong working relationship—she worked hard to help elect him in 2014, and he backed her in her race against a Trump-backed GOP challenger in 2022.</p> 
<p>The National Republican Senatorial Committee jumped on Peltola's decision immediately, popping a digital ad accusing her of wanting to "make Alaska last again" by allowing "men in women's sports" and "open borders." It also attacked her for her support of former President Joe Biden and former Vice President Kamala Harris."After voters rejected Mary Peltola's record pushing radical transgender policies and protecting Joe Biden's relentless attacks on Alaska energy, she immediately cashed out to lobby for special interests," NRSC spokesman Nick Puglia said in a statement. "Voters trust Dan Sullivan to keep fighting for the Alaskan comeback and will reject Peltola again."</p> 
<p>Peltola was the first Alaska Native to serve in Congress, and should she win this race would be the first to serve in the Senate.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cornyn rakes in record fundraising ahead of Texas primary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/cornyn-rakes-in-record-fundraising-ahead-of-texas-primary-00721699</link>
      <description>The Republican senator is fighting to survive a competitive reelection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-b001-dca0-ad9b-f98946800001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/36/89/2b377c794347b9a16d5ddf1b3567/u-s-congress-56522.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. John Cornyn (R-Texas) speaks with a reporter outside the U.S. Capitol, on  July 21, 2025. | Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/36/89/2b377c794347b9a16d5ddf1b3567/u-s-congress-56522.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. John Cornyn raised $7 million during the fourth quarter of his reelection campaign — the highest total of his career as the Republican fights a bitter primary challenge.</p> 
<p>The fundraising report, shared first with POLITICO, shows Cornyn has more than $15 million in cash on hand, including money raised through his two joint fundraising committees. It represents more than twice as much as he raised in the third quarter of 2025.</p> 
<p>The four-term incumbent is up against Texas Attorney General Ken Paxton and Rep. Wesley Hunt. Polls show a tight race between Paxton and Cornyn, with Hunt in third, ahead of the early March primary.</p> 
<p>Cornyn has poured money into attacking Paxton, a conservative firebrand who has wide backing from the MAGA base in Texas but has significant political and personal baggage. Paxton has faced multiple state and federal investigations and his wife filed for divorce last summer.</p> 
<p>“Texans understand that President Trump’s legislative agenda and the Senate Republican majority are at risk unless Sen. Cornyn is the nominee,” said Andy Hemming, Cornyn’s campaign manager, in a statement. “We are executing our plan to win this race, and we will win.”</p> 
<p>Paxton and Hunt have not yet released their own latest fundraising hauls. The race is expected to go to a runoff in late May.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP talk of Rubio 2028 heats up in wake of Venezuela op</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/10/marco-rubio-venezuela-2028-future-00718902</link>
      <description>The secretary of State has signaled he may not run for president in 2028, but he’s changed his mind on such matters before.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a383-d65c-affb-ab83f2be0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 16:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/bb/33/6369f0794b39a3774769e157b4cd/main-bensontoosi-rubio2028-v2.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Bill Kuchman/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.BensonToosi.Rubio2028 V2.jpg</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bb/33/6369f0794b39a3774769e157b4cd/main-bensontoosi-rubio2028-v2.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson and Nahal Toosi</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson and Nahal Toosi</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump has handed Marco Rubio the keys to Venezuela. It could make or break the secretary of State should he run for president in 2028.</p> 
<p>Rubio has quickly emerged as the administration’s point person on Venezuela, the man standing behind the president as he declared “we’re going to run the country.” Rubio plastered his face across the Sunday news shows to explain the operation that captured Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro, then went on in the days after to defend it in briefings to Congress.</p> 
<p>Photoshopped memes are now circulating of Rubio sporting a sash with the national colors of Venezuela, like those the country’s presidents wear. Rubio is in on the joke, <a href="https://x.com/marcorubio/status/2009297348799942872?s=46" target="_blank">taking to X on Thursday</a> to humorously knock down “rumors” that he was “a candidate for the currently vacant HC and GM positions with the Miami Dolphins.”</p> 
<p>But it’s the American presidency that could be at stake.</p> 
<p>“Venezuela could make him president — or ensure that he never is,” said Mark McKinnon, a longtime political adviser and former aide to President George W. Bush.</p> 
<p>POLITICO <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/07/rubio-vance-2028-republican-nominee-00640908" target="_blank">reported in November</a> that Rubio privately had said that he’d back JD Vance for president if he runs in 2028, which Rubio publicly confirmed to Vanity Fair.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/36/e6/f784a50a49ebbd0556d8234d55eb/gettyimages-2254501783-edit.jpg" alt="Secretary of State Marco Rubio speaks during a press conference President Donald Trump and other officials listen at Mar-a-Lago club in Palm Beach, Florida, on Jan. 3." data-portal-copyright="Joe Raedle/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2254501783" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Secretary of State Marco Rubio speaks during a press conference President Donald Trump and other officials listen at Mar-a-Lago club in Palm Beach, Florida, on Jan. 3."/><p><br>“If JD Vance runs for president, he’s going to be our nominee, and I’ll be one of the first people to support him,” <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/story/trump-susie-wiles-interview-exclusive-part-2" target="_blank">Rubio told Vanity Fair</a>, a line his aides pointed POLITICO to when asked for comment for this story.</p> 
<p>Few political strategists, however, are buying that line, and Rubio <a href="https://www.npr.org/2016/06/22/483075248/marco-rubio-reverses-course-will-run-for-re-election-to-senate" target="_blank">has changed his mind on not running</a> for office before.</p> 
<p>“He’s quietly stacking internal GOP capital, from what I hear from people in my circles within the Republican Party,” said Buzz Jacobs, senior adviser on Rubio’s 2016 presidential campaign. “As of today, could Marco Rubio enter the presidential race and be very competitive, even against the vice president? I think the answer is undeniably yes.”</p> 
<p>Rubio has spent much of his career railing against Venezuela’s socialist dictatorship, a close ally of the regime in Cuba, his parents’ homeland.</p> 
<p>“Their experience with the evils of socialism and communism is in his DNA,” said Cesar Conda, Rubio’s first Senate chief of staff. “It guides his world view.”</p> 
<p>Rubio ran against Trump for the presidency in 2016; <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-35674780" target="_blank">he called Trump a “con artist.”</a> But since Trump won and effectively commandeered the Republican Party, Rubio has adjusted many of his policy positions and his rhetoric. He has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/15/the-man-in-rubios-ear-00653051" target="_blank">surrounded himself with America First staffers and advisers</a> who help push forward the Trump administration's muscular foreign policy.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ad/eb/0c267e874af0815342f5c339a6d8/venezuela-us-39506.jpg" alt="Smoke rises from Fort Tiuna, the main military garrison in Caracas, Venezuela, on Jan. 3, after the U.S. strikes." data-portal-copyright="Matias Delacroix/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26003793039506" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Smoke rises from Fort Tiuna, the main military garrison in Caracas, Venezuela, on Jan. 3, after the U.S. strikes."/><p><br>Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/07/15/rnc-live-updates-coverage/trump-vp-pick-marco-rubio-00168314" target="_blank">shortlisted him for the vice presidency in 2024</a>, but Rubio ended up at the State Department instead. To the surprise of many political observers, Rubio fell into lockstep with Trump on issues many thought would be a red line for him. He enthusiastically <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/01/29/congress/dems-press-rubio-on-refugee-assistance-pause-00201225" target="_blank">shut down pathways for refugees</a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/29/rubio-human-rights-state-00374606" target="_blank">ended funding for democracy and human rights programs</a>, causes he once championed. Taking such steps helped him stay in Trump’s good graces, enough so that the president named him acting national security adviser as well.</p> 
<p>Trump has often cozied up to autocrats, but he has never liked Maduro. In recent days, he made it clear he sees Venezuela as a source of oil and other natural resources for the U.S. to exploit. Rubio has long painted Maduro as a thug who thwarted democracy.</p> 
<p>For much of this year, both men pushed the idea that Maduro had to be dealt with, alleging he led a drug cartel killing Americans with its products. They got their wish: Maduro is now in U.S. custody in New York.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/d6/7d/066a03cc4dc589e5ea660a5754ce/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/512761052" alt="Rubio, then a presidential candidate, greets guests at a campaign rally in Alabama in 2016." data-portal-copyright=" Scott Olson/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="512761052" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Rubio, then a presidential candidate, greets guests at a campaign rally in Alabama in 2016."/><p>But the South American country’s fate is far from clear. Many of Maduro’s cronies remain in power, even though Trump insists that they will do what the U.S. demands. Trump <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/08/us/politics/trump-interview-venezuela.html" target="_blank">told the New York Times</a> this week that the U.S. could be running Venezuela for years.</p> 
<p>“I understand that in this cycle and society we now live in, everyone wants instant outcomes. They want it to happen overnight,” Rubio told reporters after briefing the Senate Wednesday. “It's not going to work that way.”</p> 
<p>Members of Congress were not notified of the Maduro operation in advance, and many are fuming about what they say is a continued lack of transparency.</p> 
<p>Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.) said Rubio’s briefing “raised more questions than it answered.”</p> 
<p>“It's time to let the public in on this, and let the public see what's at stake,” said Kaine, a member of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.<br></p><p>Venezuela is unlikely to be a quick or easy fix. The country is roughly twice the size of California, with a shattered economy, a varied landscape, and many armed groups in a population of 30 million. The Maduro cronies left behind have their own internal rivalries, and some control military forces.</p> 
<p>Despite Trump and Rubio’s warnings to the remaining members of the regime to fall in line and capitulate to U.S. demands, it’s possible the Venezuelan state could collapse.</p> 
<p>And it may not end with Venezuela: Rubio and Trump are warning other countries to get in line with what the U.S. wants from them, including Colombia, Mexico and Venezuela.</p> 
<p>“If I lived in Havana and I was in the government, I would be concerned, at least a little bit,” Rubio said in a Saturday press conference just hours after the Venezuela operation.</p> 
<p>The potential chaos ahead could leave Rubio on the outs with key GOP voting blocs. Those include anti-interventionist conservatives, who remain wary of Rubio’s neoconservative instincts, and Republican Latino voters, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/22/rubios-political-future-could-hinge-on-venezuela-campaign-00665419" target="_blank">especially in Florida,</a> some who desperately want regime change in the nations their families fled and others who are frustrated by the region’s instability.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/04/c2/9f7a86d343d9934b27360e571595/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2253911776" alt="People react to the news of the capture of Venezuelan President Nicolas Maduro in Doral, Florida, on Jan. 3." data-portal-copyright="Giorgio Viera/AFP via Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2253911776" data-licensor-name="AFP via Getty Images" data-title="People react to the news of the capture of Venezuelan President Nicolas Maduro in Doral, Florida, on Jan. 3."/><p>Then, of course, there’s the general public, a good chunk of whom want the U.S. to avoid another repeat of Iraq and Afghanistan. According to <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/americas/only-33-americans-approve-us-strike-venezuela-reutersipsos-poll-finds-2026-01-05/" target="_blank">a Reuters/Ipsos poll conducted after the raid,</a> 72 percent of Americans are concerned the U.S. will get “too involved” in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>As Rubio has become the face of the effort, Vance, a potential rival in 2028, has largely kept away from it. He was not at the makeshift Mar-a-Lago situation room while the raid unfolded on Saturday, a fact <a href="https://x.com/JacquiHeinrich/status/2007562295568937269" target="_blank">his spokesperson attributed</a> to concern “a late-night motorcade movement … may tip off the Venezuelans.” Vance was “deeply integrated in the process and planning of the Venezuela strikes and Maduro’s arrest,” the spokesperson said.</p> 
<p>Rubio also has to consider some practical matters: If he wants to run for president, he will need to raise money, build a campaign infrastructure and take all the other steps needed before the GOP primary kicks into full gear.</p> 
<p>That's especially difficult to do while secretary of State, a position that traditionally has stayed away from the partisan domestic scene. Former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton had been out of the Obama administration for more than a year before she publicly moved toward a presidential campaign.</p> 
<p>Rubio would likely have to leave the administration after another year or so to have time for all the logistics, as jostling for the 2028 presidential campaign will kick off by early next year.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/d2/b6/5d82a7834478bad22ffb2b7f8c92/ap26006068644299-edit.jpg" alt="Rubio arrives to brief members of Congress on Capitol Hill, on Jan. 5." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26006068644299" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Rubio arrives to brief members of Congress on Capitol Hill, on Jan. 5."/><p>Most U.S. presidential elections don’t hinge on foreign policy, though candidates from John McCain back to Hubert Humphrey have been damaged by their party’s foreign adventurism. Still, the first year of Trump’s second term has been surprisingly heavy on foreign policy — and any Republican running in 2028 will likely have to grapple with the results of Trump’s bold international moves.</p> 
<p>“The MAGA base is very loyal to Trump. It will watch if people are disrespectful to him,” said Alex Gray, a former National Security Council official during the first Trump administration.</p> 
<p>There are also factions of the GOP — including members of the Cuban and Venezuelan diasporas — who will stand by hardline moves against the regimes there no matter what the cost. Mike Madrid, a GOP strategist, said he has heard from many Latino Republicans who are impressed by how much Trump relies on Rubio. Whenever Trump needs “an adult in the room, he seems to look towards Marco’s leadership,” Madrid said.</p> 
<p>But Madrid and other party strategists aren’t about to start taking bets on the GOP primary yet. After all, the situation in Venezuela is just one of multiple Trump foreign policy adventures that could turn into quagmires.</p> 
<p>For Rubio in particular, “what may look like the president knighting him as a sort of competent successor may actually, in fact, be him carrying all the weight of the unpopular actions of the president in a couple of years,” Madrid said. “There's a greater likelihood of that than not.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
