<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/politics-news.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:45:00 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-19T17:45:58-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Bowser requests Trump’s help on Potomac sewage spill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/bowser-requests-trumps-help-on-potomac-sewage-spill-00788896</link>
      <description>The request from D.C. Mayor Muriel Bowser comes days after the president blamed the spill on Democrats and said local officials should call and ask for help “politely.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-775c-d0f8-adde-ff5e23f20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 14:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c1/ac/e7db13044d7db4014ff2631c409f/potomac-river-sewage-24511.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Cliff Owen/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A warning sign is seen at the sight of a massive pipe rupture, as sewage flows into the Potomac River in Glen Echo, Maryland, on Jan. 23.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c1/ac/e7db13044d7db4014ff2631c409f/potomac-river-sewage-24511.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Miranda Willson and Thomas Frank</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Miranda Willson and Thomas Frank</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Washington, D.C., Mayor Muriel Bowser on Wednesday accepted President Donald Trump’s offer to help fix the massive sewage spill outside the city, making an unusual request for Trump to declare the area a disaster and pay for repairs.</p> 
<p>Bowser’s request came days after Trump tried to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-fixates-on-sewage-a-favored-talking-point-in-fight-with-wes-moore-00786490?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=bluesky" target="_blank">blame the spill</a> on her and other Democrats and said that if they want federal help “they have to call me and ask, politely.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://mayor.dc.gov/sites/default/files/dc/sites/mayormb/page_content/attachments/DC%20Request%20for%20Presidential%20Emergency%20Disaster%20Decleration%202.18.26.pdf" target="_blank">Bowser signed her letter</a> “Respectfully” in asking for the Federal Emergency Management Agency to offset all "costs incurred" by the city and regional sewer authorities following the Jan. 19 collapse of a sewer line in Montgomery County, Maryland. FEMA usually pays 75 percent of disaster repairs unless damage is extreme.</p> 
<p>Bowser told reporters Thursday that she made the request now because Trump expressed interest in helping and to minimize costs to D.C. residents. In addition to seeking assistance, the three-term mayor — who is not seeking reelection — <a href="https://mayor.dc.gov/sites/default/files/dc/sites/mayormb/page_content/attachments/Mayor%27s%20Order%202026-028%20Declaration%20of%20Public%20Emergency%20%E2%80%93%20Potomac%20Interceptor%20Collapse%20and%20Impacts.pdf" target="_blank">declared a local public emergency</a> and asked the federal government to support several other water quality and flood protection projects in the city.</p> 
<p>“I have had outreach from the president's team,” Bowser said during a press conference. “That would indicate to me that they're supportive of the request."</p> 
<p>No president has approved a disaster declaration for a sewage spill, according to an analysis by POLITICO's E&amp;E News of FEMA records dating to 1953.</p> 
<p>President Barack Obama approved <a href="https://www.fema.gov/disaster/3375" target="_blank">an emergency declaration</a> in 2016 for water contamination in Flint, Michigan, that began in 2014. FEMA provides limited aid for emergencies.</p> 
<p>But presidents have authority to approve disasters for a wide range of events. In his first term, Trump approved disaster requests for every state to cover their costs of handling the Covid-19 pandemic. FEMA has given states roughly $140 billion for pandemic costs.</p> 
<p>Bowser’s letter contains no cost estimates — which governors routinely include in their multipage disaster requests — and acknowledges aid would help residents outside her jurisdiction, in Maryland and Virginia.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/COMPS-2977/pdf/COMPS-2977.pdf" target="_blank">Federal law says</a> that disaster requests “shall be made by the Governor of the affected State” — or by a government leader such as a tribal chief, territorial governor or the mayor of Washington, and that a disaster request must be based on a finding that a jurisdiction cannot handle an event by itself. Bowser’s letter to Trump makes no such claim.</p> 
<p>Neither Govs. Wes Moore of Maryland nor Abigail Spanberger of Virginia, both Democrats, have requested disaster aid from Trump. DC Water, the sewer authority, operates the sewer line that extends from as far as Dulles International Airport to a treatment plant in the city and did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>“Maryland will not be seeking an emergency declaration because the responsibility for the repair and subsequent clean up does not fall to Maryland,” said Rhylan Lake, a spokesperson for Moore, in an email. “Since Maryland owns neither the infrastructure nor the land, Maryland does not anticipate needing supplemental resources at this time.”</p> 
<p>Neither the White House nor FEMA responded to questions Thursday about whether they planned to grant D.C.'s assistance request.</p> 
<p>Considered the largest raw sewage spill of its kind in U.S. history, the broken sewer line has released over 250 million gallons of raw sewage in the Potomac River. Environmentalists have been raising concerns for weeks about the spill, which could render the river unsafe for fishing and boating and undermine longstanding efforts to repair the Chesapeake Bay.</p> 
<p>Local environmentalists said they would welcome federal funding to help with the cleanup, but that the priority should be to increase water quality monitoring and better notify the public about whether it’s safe to use the river. </p> 
<p>“Going directly from zero comments on it to an emergency declaration after the fact seems like an unusual pathway,” said Betsy Nicholas, president of Potomac Riverkeeper Network. “We haven’t heard anything from the mayor or the mayor’s office on this for an entire month, which in and of itself was a little surprising and frustrating.”</p> 
<p>Representatives for the utility have previously noted that they are working to accelerate a previously planned rehabilitation project to fix the sewer line. The line dates to the early 1960s. </p> 
<p>Trump administration officials and local authorities have traded jabs in recent days over who is responsible for the spill, with the exact cause still undetermined. </p> 
<p>Trump has primarily cast blame on Moore, with the White House describing the state as responsible for protecting water quality in the Potomac. But both Moore’s office and Bowser say that EPA is the primary regulator of DC Water.</p> 
<p>A FEMA report Thursday morning says DC Water “is engaged with” EPA, FEMA, environmental agencies in the District, Maryland and Virginia, and the National Park Service, which owns the wooded parkland where the spill occurred next to the Potomac.</p> 
<p>“Since the incident was first reported, DC Water has provided daily updates,” <a href="https://content.govdelivery.com/attachments/USDHSFEMA/2026/02/19/file_attachments/3558713/FEMA%20Daily%20Ops%20Briefing%2002-19-2026.pdf" target="_blank">the FEMA report says.</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ohio’s GOP governor sidesteps defending Kristi Noem</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/ohio-mike-dewine-sidesteps-defending-kristi-noem-00788704</link>
      <description>Mike DeWine did, however, say he supported billionaire Les Wexner despite his ties to disgraced financier Jeffrey Epstein.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-76d6-d0f8-adde-fedeb8250000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 12:04:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content medium="video" type="video/mp4" url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/1f87e96f-2dff-4547-bb2d-7cb6eeb0f05f/ed2ff5ca-238a-4c9e-b96c-810e38f652bf/main.mp4">
        <media:description>Gov. DeWine: 'No indication ICE is coming in'</media:description>
        <media:title>Gov. DeWine: 'No indication ICE is coming in'</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/1f87e96f-2dff-4547-bb2d-7cb6eeb0f05f/737d3ee0-5774-4048-9636-1104c7dc9cb7/1280x720/match/image.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Adam Wren</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Adam Wren</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ohio Gov. Mike DeWine would not immediately endorse his fellow Buckeye, Vice President JD Vance, for his party’s 2028 presidential nomination and would not express confidence in Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem amid reports that ICE could target Springfield.</p> 
<p>Asked whether Vance should be the Republican party’s nominee, DeWine said Thursday that “he’s a favorite son of ours, and we’ll see how this whole thing plays out.”</p> 
<p>At POLITICO’s 2026 Governors Summit, the Ohio Republican said he has not heard further news following reports that Springfield could face <a href="https://signalohio.org/springfield-ohio-prepares-for-an-ice-immigration-raid-it-cant-confirm-you-become-powerless-in-a-situation-like-this" target="_blank">an ICE crackdown on its</a> large population of Haitian immigrants: “We've not been told at all if they're going to come in.” And while DeWine said that state and local law enforcement would work to keep the peace if there was a crackdown, he warned that federal officers also need to perform professionally.</p> 
<p>“Frankly, we expect ICE, if they come in, to follow good police protocols. If they do that, we’re going to be able to work our way through it,” he said.</p> 
<p>DeWine sidestepped multiple opportunities to express confidence in Noem’s handling of DHS’ stepped up interior enforcement.</p> 
<p>“Look, I think that what happened in Minnesota was a signal to a lot of people — they didn’t like what they saw,” DeWine said when asked about Noem.</p> 
<p>DeWine did <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/les-wexner-jeffrey-epstein-files-00786674" target="_blank">defend Les Wexner</a>, the billionaire businessman and former client of Jeffrey Epstein whose name is blazoned across many central Ohio institutions, including the The Ohio State Wexner Medical Center. DeWine said Thursday that no evidence has emerged of his wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>“Barring some new information of something that he has done illegal, I don’t see that as a problem,” said DeWine.</p> 
<p>The governor, who has frequently tangled with Trump and Vance — including over their baseless attacks of Haitian immigrants eating pets in Springfield — would not say whether the president has been a “force for good” for the GOP and country.</p> 
<p>Instead, he praised Trump’s actions on border enforcement.</p> 
<p>“He has done something that has not been done before, and that is he has basically sealed the southern border,” DeWine said. “And you can talk to Democrats, talk to Republicans. I think everybody is happy about that.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Pay for your own power’: Shapiro digs in on data center energy costs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/shapiro-tests-democrats-data-center-strategy-00767682</link>
      <description>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro knows how to make data center-friendly policies. He's still trying to make them good politics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7387-d0f8-adde-fbdf2deb0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/64/7f/56a9cb024588b66412ac38821ad7/gov1.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Pennsylvania Senate Democratic Caucus</media:credit>
        <media:title>Gov. Josh Shapiro shakes hands with state Sen. Steve Santarsiero in Falls Township, Pennsylvania, to tout Amazon's new high-tech data center.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/64/7f/56a9cb024588b66412ac38821ad7/gov1.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Peter Behr, Christa Marshall and Joel Kirkland</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Peter Behr, Christa Marshall and Joel Kirkland</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>PHILADELPHIA — Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro, a bellwether Democrat on AI and data centers, is tempering his message ahead of his reelection campaign.</p> 
<p>Shapiro, a swing-state Democrat and a 2028 presidential prospect, has staked his state’s economic fortunes on the tech industry. He wooed a $20 billion investment from Amazon along with major investments by Microsoft and Google. Shapiro has backed President Donald Trump’s call for more nuclear and natural gas plants to power new tech hubs.</p> 
<p>He's now trying to hedge his bet as data centers absorb a nationwide backlash from voters increasingly concerned about their impact on electricity bills.</p> 
<p>“Pay for your own power, so it's not saddling local businesses or homeowners with higher costs,” Shapiro said in an interview with POLITICO earlier this month from a union hall in Philadelphia.</p> 
<p>It’s an unmistakable pivot by a leading practitioner of data center politics who along with other Democratic governors has been trying to bring under control rising electricity prices that could be political kryptonite for both parties. Household electricity bills are rising at <a href="https://www.bls.gov/news.release/cpi.nr0.htm" target="_blank">twice the rate of inflation</a>. In recent weeks, Shapiro has joined Arizona Gov. Katie Hobbs, New York Gov. Kathy Hochul and other Democrats who are sharpening their tone and putting new policies in place to try to claw back taxpayer expenses, increase pressure on utility companies and address local backlash against development.</p> 
<p>“Too many of these projects have been shrouded in secrecy, with local communities left in the dark about who is coming in and what they’re building,” Shapiro said in his annual address to the Pennsylvania General Assembly earlier this month.</p> 
<p>Shapiro, who is riding high in the polls as he launches his reelection campaign, is pitching the AI and data center boom as a source of union jobs during the yearslong construction phase — but also trying to manage the boom's potential to alienate other voters.</p> 
<p>Christopher Borick, a political science professor at Muhlenberg College in Allentown, said Shapiro’s “get stuff done” political brand runs into trouble if voters tie energy affordability concerns to data center projects.</p> 
<p>“People have started to connect the demand for AI and data centers to pricing,” he said.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/05/07/b3237ce4409da660c685961b2367/gutman-amazondatacenter-45.jpg" alt="Construction of the future Amazon data center site in Fairless Hills, Pennsylvania, on Dec. 17, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Caroline Gutman for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Caroline Gutman" data-title="Construction of the future Amazon data center site in Fairless Hills, Pennsylvania, on Dec. 17, 2025."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Jobs and energy</h4> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium"></h5> 
<p>Few Democrats have anticipated the data center zeitgeist as deftly as Shapiro. Shortly after taking office in 2023, he ordered an analysis of where the state and U.S. economies were headed. AI jumped out as a key opportunity, a top adviser said.</p> 
<p>“Not just because we thought it was cool, but because we have strengths,” said Rick Siger, a former Obama staffer who serves as Shapiro’s secretary of community and economic development.</p> 
<p>Carnegie Mellon University, a top engineering and technology school, was a selling point. So was the state’s manufacturing base, which makes hardware for data centers and boasts tech companies that will deploy advanced AI. Shapiro’s team fixated on what major developers were after. “Speed matters, in particular to companies that are competing in AI,” Siger said.</p> 
<p>In June 2025, Shapiro announced Amazon's $20 billion investment in two data center complexes: one in the Philadelphia suburbs of Bucks County and another south of Wilkes-Barre.</p> 
<p>“The employees will be making, in some cases, double the average wage in that county,” Siger said, “to work in a high-tech job and be able to stay home and raise their kids in their hometown.” The data center piece of the AI juggernaut also works well for Shapiro's union-heavy constituency. He toured Steamfitters Local Union 420’s training center in Philadelphia earlier this month, which is training apprentices to install cooling systems for the computer chips packed in wall-to-wall racks inside the cluster of AI factories being developed in Bucks County.</p> 
<p>Rory Carroll, a 42-year-old steamfitter who was among the trainees greeting Shapiro, said he’s “tried everything” to make a living. “I sold cars, delivered pizza, managed a supermarket.” Now, he says he’s on a rising tide.</p> 
<p>Local officials in Bucks County — which Trump flipped red in 2024, for the first time since 1988 — are wary but welcoming.</p> 
<p>“Do I think the trend of technology replacing jobs will continue with the data centers? Of course I do,” said Erin Mullen, vice chair of the Falls Township Board of Supervisors. But she said the temporary construction jobs were worth pursuing. “This is a blue-collar township,” Mullen said. “So even though the jobs are temporary, a lot of families here survive on temporary jobs, and this is huge for the trades.”</p> 
<p>Data centers' demand for energy also works for Shapiro, who's been touting the state's large natural gas reserves in talks with tech companies. Last summer, he joined Trump and the state’s Republican senator, Dave McCormick, in Pittsburgh to announce multibillion-dollar commitments for restarting aging hydropower and expanding electricity generation from nuclear and natural gas.</p> 
<p>Now, after cuts to federal renewable energy tax credits, he's still touting Pennsylvania energy — with a partisan edge.</p> 
<p>"I'm an 'all-of-the-above' energy governor," Shapiro said in the POLITICO interview. "Unfortunately, the president of the United States has cut hundreds of millions of dollars from clean energy development in this commonwealth, which has cost us 26,000 union trade jobs who were set to work on these projects."</p> 
<p>“I don't think it's an either-or — it's a both-and," he continued. "We need to generate more power. Yes, it will rely in part on Pennsylvania natural gas. We also need to generate more power with renewables."</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Power politics</h4> 
<p>Shapiro's call for data center developers to pay for electricity infrastructure that could drive up utility bills echoes the Trump administration's <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/09/trump-administration-eyes-data-center-agreements-amid-energy-price-spikes-00772024" target="_blank">recent rhetoric</a> exhorting them to "pick up the tab" — but Shapiro’s focus on power bills was a long time coming.</p> 
<p>In July 2024, as Shapiro was chasing Amazon, mid-Atlantic ratepayers were hit with a $14.7 billion, one-year charge from PJM Interconnection, the region's electricity grid manager. The double-digit cost increases in utility bills came as a result of projections that electricity supplies could fall short of demand across the 13-state region stretching from northern Virginia to Chicago.</p> 
<p>Shapiro demanded a price cap in December 2024 on the fastest-rising part of PJM customers’ electricity bills — a headline-grabbing event in Pennsylvania. And he’s threatened to pull Pennsylvania out of the PJM market all together, a major uprooting of the way power is delivered in the region. He’s attacked PJM for its byzantine utility-heavy leadership structure that leads to a sclerotic response to rising power prices.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/22/94/fe042a8c43f3a4ceba9879c879ae/secondary7.jpg" alt="Top: Construction of the future Amazon data center site, in Fairless Hills. Bottom: An industrial facility near the same site, in Morrisville." data-portal-copyright="Caroline Gutman for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Top: Construction of the future Amazon data center site, in Fairless Hills. Bottom: An industrial facility near the same site, in Morrisville."/><p>According to federal data, <a href="https://www.eia.gov/electricity/monthly/update/end-use.php#:~:text=Total%20average%20revenues%20per%20kilowatt,with%20three%20sectors%20seeing%20increases." target="_blank">electricity prices in Pennsylvania</a> rose roughly 20 percent between November 2024 and November 2025 — the highest rate in the country. And PJM has warned that states could face power shortages by the end of the decade if the construction of new data centers race ahead of the energy supply.</p> 
<p>“PJM is broken,” Shapiro said in December. “They’re too damned slow. And the needs we have in this country to produce more energy to support everything from data centers to more manufacturing need to be met. And we are being held captive.”</p> 
<p>The enormously complex market rules that affect power prices in Shapiro’s state are outside average Americans’ conversations. But Shapiro and Trump have tied a rising part of their political parties’ credibility to the outcome of their pledges to make data centers pay their own way.</p> 
<p>In January, Shapiro <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/trump-tame-electricity-prices-00733422" target="_blank">went to the White House</a> alongside other East Coast governors of both parties to call for PJM to control power prices — and for data centers to “bring their own power” through long-term contracts with new generation developers.</p> 
<p>Big tech companies are starting to sign on. Trump used a Truth Social post in early January to announce the White House was working with tech companies to get more agreement on containing the public cost of energy infrastructure. Microsoft then pledged to shoulder more of those costs.</p> 
<p>Shapiro's tack could work for him, according to recent polling.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/power-switch/2026/02/13/data-centers-your-new-neighbor-00780829" target="_blank">POLITICO poll</a> released last week showed an electorate still wrestling with the data center question. Respondents' top concerns surrounding data centers were power prices and the risk of blackouts — yet they were generally willing to support a new data center in their area even<a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/02/13/what-do-people-know-about-data-centers-we-explain-in-5-charts-00769974" target="_blank">if it hikes their power bills</a>.</p> 
<p>In his address to lawmakers, Shapiro proposed a three-pronged strike against rising energy costs — proposing new rules for data center developers, electric utilities and the regional grid PJM. He pledged to “hold data center developers accountable to strict standards if they want our full support.”</p> 
<p>Last week, PJM agreed to extend price controls on future electricity production into 2030.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cox pushes back on Trump over gambling and AI regulation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/spencer-cox-utah-trump-ai-unity-gambling-00788583</link>
      <description>The White House recently warned Utah lawmakers against passing a bill regulating artificial intelligence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7692-d647-addc-ffd7e25d0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 11:01:43 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content medium="video" type="video/mp4" url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/2452e6aa-ddc1-434a-9335-679dcd8a16d9/5525a2a0-0952-49ec-b861-44bb2a4d0e8f/main.mp4">
        <media:description>Gov. Spencer Cox criticizes Trump's CTFC head over gambling regulation</media:description>
        <media:title>Gov. Spencer Cox criticizes Trump's CTFC head over gambling regulation</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/2452e6aa-ddc1-434a-9335-679dcd8a16d9/b358bfdb-52b2-4603-8387-ec11d362eb56/1280x720/match/image.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Utah Gov. Spencer Cox criticized the Trump administration’s approaches to prediction markets and artificial intelligence on Thursday — as well as the president’s lack of interest in unifying the country.</p> 
<p>During an interview at POLITICO’s 2026 Governors Summit, the Republican governor and occasional critic of President Donald Trump pushed back on the Trump administration’s recent efforts to limit states’ abilities to regulate gambling and AI, saying the federal government “coming in and trying to tell us” to back off state-level fixes is “preposterous.”</p> 
<p>“Look, this is a joke, and I can’t believe he tried to say this with a straight face,” Cox said, referring to <a href="https://x.com/ChairmanSelig/status/2023744651216240966" target="_blank">CFTC Chair Mike Selig’s</a> announcement earlier this week that the agency has singular authority to regulate prediction markets.</p> 
<p>“I’m concerned about these new technologies, and what they’re doing to our kids,” Cox added. “It's one thing if we're fighting China, and you're developing your model. But once you start selling sexualized chat bots to kids in my state, now I have a problem with that, and I'm going to get involved there, and the Supreme Court is going to back me up.”</p> 
<p>Last week, the White House <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/02/white-house-opposes-utah-gops-ai-transparency-bill-00782634" target="_blank">sent a letter to the Utah Legislature</a> warning lawmakers that a Republican-led AI regulation bill clashes with federal policy. Trump also signed <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/trump-orders-government-to-fight-state-ai-laws-00687948" target="_blank">a December executive order</a> that warned states of consequences for attempting to regulate the fast-growing industry.</p> 
<p>Cox said his approach does not conflict with his belief that the U.S. should win “the AI arms race with China and Russia,” and thus states and municipalities should support construction of data centers across the country.</p> 
<p>“Let's use this technology to benefit humankind, and let's regulate it to make sure they don't destroy humankind,” Cox said.</p> 
<p>He also made it clear he differs with Trump’s approach toward bringing together Americans from different perspectives. Shortly after Trump’s attempted assassination in Butler, Pennsylvania, in 2024, <a href="https://www.deseret.com/politics/2024/07/19/utah-gov-spencer-cox-donald-trump/" target="_blank">Cox endorsed him</a>, saying he hoped Trump could bring the country together.</p> 
<p>Cox said Thursday that hope had been “aspirational.”</p> 
<p>Trump is “someone who, if he put his mind to it, could unify” the country, Cox said. “He's not putting his mind to it. He has said very clearly that he’s not, and that's okay. That's different than me.”</p> 
<p>Cox also critiqued <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/07/31/heritage-american-jd-vance-online-right-phrase-00481724" target="_blank">the growing “Heritage American” movement</a> within his party, saying the nativist message is a recipe for electoral failure.</p> 
<p>“I worry about it because that's a future where we lose a lot of elections in a very ugly way,” Cox said. “I worry about it because that's not where most Americans are. It's certainly not where I am.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wes Moore: 'I don't answer to the Democratic Party’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/wes-moore-redistricting-democrats-2028-00788517</link>
      <description>The Maryland Governor addressed his clashes with state Democrats and said he's not thinking about 2028 at a POLITICO Summit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7690-d647-addc-ffd7efd90001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 10:48:01 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content medium="video" type="video/mp4" url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/98a943ac-06a3-4adb-9670-8390370ce658/5199c4b2-7a22-4d8c-92a6-fc2349a20e81/main.mp4">
        <media:description>Wes Moore: 'I don't answer to the Democratic Party'</media:description>
        <media:title>Wes Moore: 'I don't answer to the Democratic Party'</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/98a943ac-06a3-4adb-9670-8390370ce658/687353e6-1417-4d4e-9c50-40fc5b3dc862/1280x720/match/image.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore on Thursday defended his recent clashes with state Democrats, denying that he’s in a weak political position with his own legislature that has held up several of his policies and a push to redraw the state’s Congressional maps.</p> 
<p>“There is no political party that made me. In fact, the Democratic Party put millions of dollars to try to stop me from winning. I don’t answer to the Democratic Party. I don’t answer to party bosses,” Moore, a Democrat, said during POLITICO’s 2026 Governors Summit. “I only answer to the people who made me governor of Maryland, which is the people of Maryland.”</p> 
<p>Moore pointed out that he defeated the preferred candidate of many Democratic party bosses when he first ran for governor as a political newcomer in 2022.</p> 
<p><a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/mgawebsite/FloorActions/Agenda/senate-1-?ys=2025S1#Veto2" target="_blank">Maryland Democrats overrode at least 16</a> of the governor’s vetoes in December and the state’s Senate president, Bill Ferguson, is actively blocking Moore’s redistricting effort, saying the bill doesn’t have enough votes to pass on the floor. Moore continues to say Maryland residents are in favor of redistricting in the state, though a poll from December found <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/maryland-residents-bristle-at-wes-moores-redistricting-push-00690336" target="_blank">just 27 percent of residents</a> supported the issue.</p> 
<p>“If Bill Ferguson says, well, the votes aren't there in the Senate, my only point is this: OK, well, you know, the best way to prove that's true? Do a vote,” Moore said.</p> 
<p>Moore — widely considered a 2028 contender though he has repeatedly denied he wants to run — has attempted to position himself as a counterweight to President Donald Trump. But the resistance he’s facing in his own backyard has some national Democrats wondering whether he can successfully mount a White House run.</p> 
<p>On Thursday, Moore again dismissed the idea of running for president, saying he was focused on 2026 and “not even thinking” about 2028. <b>&nbsp;</b></p> 
<p>Oklahoma’s GOP Gov. Kevin Stitt, the current chair of the National Governors Association, defended Moore at the event, saying he had more respect for the Democrat knowing he stood up to lawmakers within his own party.</p> 
<p>“I have more respect for him now, knowing that he vetoed the bills,” Stitt said. “ I have a super majority Republican, and I vetoed 67 bills last year, and I think they overrode probably 45 of them. So it happens to all of us.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pro-Israel group wades into Democratic House primaries</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/pro-israel-dmfi-endorsements-democrats-house-primaries-00787254</link>
      <description>The Democratic Majority for Israel PAC shared its first round of House candidate endorsements in a range of safe-seat and battleground seats exclusively with POLITICO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-72fb-d0f8-adde-fafb72970000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ab/d9/5f73bc234ee6a2571e4b5ec85016/us-israel-hegseth-00814.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>U.S. and Israeli flags are displayed on a table during a meeting at the Pentagon in July 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ab/d9/5f73bc234ee6a2571e4b5ec85016/us-israel-hegseth-00814.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A pro-Israel group is wading into nearly a dozen contentious House primaries as it tries to shape the Democratic Party’s approach to the controversial issue.</p> 
<p>The Democratic Majority for Israel PAC, which backs pro-Israel Democrats, is endorsing 11 House candidates, including several in expensive and crowded primaries the party must win in order to retake the House. The group’s initial endorsement list was shared first with POLITICO.</p> 
<p>DMFI, first launched in 2019, is one of several groups across the political spectrum looking to influence the party’s views on Israel, even as its military operations in Gaza have divided the Democratic Party and become an early litmus test for both 2026 congressional candidates and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/14/2028-democrats-israel-gaza-litmus-test-00508934" target="_blank">2028 presidential hopefuls.</a></p> 
<p>The endorsements include candidates in six battleground races and five more in safe-blue, but crowded, Democratic primaries. They are backing moderate state Rep. Shannon Bird over progressive state Rep. Manny Rutinel for the right to face Rep. Gabe Evans (R-Colo.) in a swingy Colorado district.</p> 
<p>In New York, the group is backing Cait Conley, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/new-york-playbook-pm/2026/02/12/ny-17-primary-poll-cait-conley-beth-davidson-chatzky-drama-00779107" target="_blank">who has entered a crowded primary</a> to take on Rep. Mike Lawler (R-N.Y.) in a district which Kamala Harris won by a one-point margin in 2024. In Texas, DMFI has endorsed police officer Johnny Garcia in a wide-open primary for the newly drawn, red-leaning seat.</p> 
<p>DMFI is backing a pair of candidates in two of the four most competitive seats in Pennsylvania — Scranton Mayor Paige Cognetti, who will face off against Rep. Rob Bresnahan (R-Pa.), and former TV anchor Janelle Stelson, who is also on track to run against Rep. Scott Perry (R-Pa.). And in Virginia, former Rep. Elaine Luria picked up the group’s support as she vies to take on her former opponent, Rep. Jen Kiggans (R-Va.).</p> 
<p>The other candidates who are receiving DMFI’s endorsement are all running in crowded primaries in safe blue seats: Maryland state Del. Adrian Boafo, who is running to replace retiring Rep. Steny Hoyer (D-Md.); Michigan state Sen. Jeremy Moss, who is running to replace Rep. Haley Stevens (D-Mich.), who is running for Senate; and former Obama administration official Maura Sullivan, who is running to replace Rep. Chris Pappas (D-N.H.), who is running for the Senate.</p> 
<p>"The vast majority of Americans support the right of Israel to exist as a Jewish state and understand the importance of the U.S.-Israel relationship,” said former Rep. Kathy Manning, who serves on the DMFI PAC board. “If you're running in a competitive district, you need Democrats, you need independents, you need Republicans.”</p> 
<p>Several groups, including DMFI and the American Israel Public Affairs Committee, known as AIPAC, are boosting pro-Israel candidates with significant outside spending. The two groups have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/02/08/dmfi-democratic-primaries-2024-00140267" target="_blank">often</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/05/20/congress/pro-israel-groups-dem-battleground-endorsements-00158859" target="_blank">overlapped</a> in their endorsements, but AIPAC supports Democrats and Republicans — and has drawn the ire of progressives. DMFI, for its part, is focused on regaining a Democratic congressional majority.</p> 
<p>AIPAC’s super PAC, United Democracy Project, dropped more than $38 million on independent expenditures in 2024, while DMFI spent about $4.3 million. DMFI President Brian Romick said the group expects to be spending “comfortably” in the “seven-figures again” in 2026 but declined to elaborate further on the plans.</p> 
<p>In Illinois, among the first primaries next month, DMFI and AIPAC appear aligned in their preferred candidates. DMFI announced it is backing former Rep. Melissa Bean, who is running to replace Rep. Raja Krishnamoorthi (D-Ill.), who is running for the Senate, and Cook County Commissioner Donna Miller, who is vying to replace Rep. Robin Kelly (D-Ill.), another Senate candidate.</p> 
<p>Bean and Miller have also attracted attention for their connections to AIPAC. Their primary opponents in both races <a href="http://washingtonpost.com/politics/2026/02/18/aipac-democrats-midterms-2026-illinois/?utm_campaign=wp_power_up&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=newsletter&amp;carta-url=https%3A%2F%2Fs2.washingtonpost.com%2Fcar-ln-tr%2F46c7a6a%2F6995a0cda424af764b17c096%2F596c2b4bade4e24119c5ca45%2F16%2F64%2F6995a0cda424af764b17c096" target="_blank">have accused them of benefiting from AIPAC’s spending</a>, concealed by shell super PACs that are boosting them with hundreds of thousands of dollars in positive TV spending. But DMFI has not yet endorsed in Illinois’ 9th District, another contentious primary to replace retiring Rep. Jan Schakowsky that AIPAC appears to have waded into.</p> 
<p>Earlier this month, AIPAC <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/centrist-democrats-are-livid-with-aipac-after-primary-meddling-00769461" target="_blank">triggered a wave of criticism and frustration, even from its own allies,</a> for spending $2 million to sink former Rep. Tom Malinowski in a congressional special election in New Jersey. The group’s spending backfired, eliminating Malinowski, but failing to lift up its preferred candidate. Analilia Mejia, a progressive organizer who <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aQCOQ6R5mok&amp;t=2987s" target="_blank">has said Israel committed genocide in Gaza</a>, ultimately won.</p> 
<p>Romick and Manning declined to comment on AIPAC’s strategy, with the former congresswoman noting DMFI is “a distinctly different and separate organization.”</p> 
<p>In 2024, DMFI and AIPAC targeted former Reps. Cori Bush (D-Mo.) and Jamaal Bowman (D-N.Y.) in 2024, both of whom lost their primaries to pro-Israel candidates. Romick demurred on whether DMFI planned to target any Democratic incumbents in 2026, adding that it is going “to take these primaries as they come and see if things develop.”</p> 
<p><i>Jessica Piper contributed reporting.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In feud with Wes Moore, Trump slings feces</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/19/trump-fixates-on-sewage-a-favored-talking-point-in-fight-with-wes-moore-00786490</link>
      <description>The president returned to his long-running gripes over all things scatological this week in his feud with the rising Democratic star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7271-d647-addc-fbf7e03a0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ba/f2/da3c80a841d4aefd6b49a7f29caa/2026-0217-potomac-francis-1-12.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>The Potomac River is seen near Fletcher's Boathouse in Washington on Tuesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ba/f2/da3c80a841d4aefd6b49a7f29caa/2026-0217-potomac-francis-1-12.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Miranda Willson and Annie Snider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Miranda Willson and Annie Snider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump didn’t just take his feud with Maryland governor and possible 2028 Democratic presidential hopeful Wes Moore into the gutter this week. He turned to the toilet.</p> 
<p><a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116086782319939311" target="_blank">In a series</a> of <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116082091487085093" target="_blank">social media posts</a> Monday and Tuesday, Trump blasted Moore for what he deemed an inept response to a sewage spill that sent hundreds of millions of gallons of raw waste into the Potomac River beginning four weeks ago.</p> 
<p>“There is a massive Ecological Disaster unfolding in the Potomac River as a result of the Gross Mismanagement of Local Democrat Leaders, particularly, Governor Wes Moore, of Maryland,” Trump wrote Tuesday on Truth Social, saying that it’s time <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/02/17/trump-assailed-fema-for-a-year-now-hes-relying-on-it-00784187" target="_blank">for the federal government to step in</a>. “I cannot allow incompetent Local ‘Leadership’ to turn the River in the Heart of Washington into a Disaster Zone.”</p> 
<p>On Wednesday, White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said the president is worried that the Potomac River will carry the stench of excrement during the July 4 celebration of the country’s semiquincentennial that Trump has been planning since returning to office.</p> 
<p>“He is worried about that. Which is why the federal government wants to fix it, and we hope that the local authorities will cooperate with us in doing so,” Leavitt said in response to a reporter’s question during the White House press briefing.</p> 
<p>It’s not the first time Trump has turned poop into a political weapon. In fact, the president who complains regularly about low-flow toilet standards has a long list of scatological gripes that have become one of the few areas where his administration is seeking additional environmental protections as it aggressively rolls back dozens of climate, air and water pollution rules.</p> 
<p>It was on the sewage-fouled beaches of San Diego that EPA Administrator Lee Zeldin marked his first Earth Day as the nation’s top environmental regulator. The administration has put concerted effort into pressuring Mexico to do more to stem the tide of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/20/next-border-fight-stinker-00241886" target="_blank">raw sewage pollution</a> flowing across the border from Tijuana, which for years has dirtied beaches and sickened residents and Navy SEALs who train nearby.</p> 
<p>And during Trump’s first term, it was San Francisco’s long-running sewer overflow problem that EPA targeted for enforcement after the president groused about the city’s large homeless population — a move that <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2019/10/02/us-epa-cites-san-francisco-1-day-after-city-accuses-feds-of-false-statements-1217320" target="_blank">California leaders saw</a> as politically charged.</p> 
<p>Now as Trump feuds with Moore, the nation’s only Black governor, less than two weeks <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/08/wes-moore-race-governors-trump-00770586" target="_blank">after excluding him</a> from a White House dinner for the National Governor’s Association, the image of millions of gallons of raw sewage flowing into the nation’s capital offered another level of political punch altogether. The situation comes as Moore is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/16/trump-fema-coordinating-response-potomac-sewage-spill-00783327" target="_blank">pushing to redraw</a> Maryland’s congressional lines to counter Trump’s red-state redistricting. </p> 
<p>“It’s a great political issue. Nobody wants sewage in the water — that is true of Democrats and Republicans,” said Mae Stevens, a water infrastructure lobbyist who previously served as an environment staffer for Democratic former Maryland Sen. Ben Cardin.</p> 
<p>Asked about the president’s longstanding interest in sewage pollution, White House spokesperson Taylor Rogers said the administration would not allow “the failures of local and state Democrats to diminish the quality of life for millions of Americans.”</p> 
<p>The source of the spill is the Potomac Interceptor sewer line, which partially collapsed Jan. 19 near Cabin John, Maryland, amid frigid winter temperatures, releasing nearly 200 million gallons of untreated wastewater in the first five days. Operating since<i>&nbsp;</i> constructed in 1964, the 54-mile line carries wastewater from D.C. suburbs as far away as Dulles Airport to a treatment plant in southern Washington.</p> 
<p>DC Water, the utility that operates the line, has been making emergency repairs to the broken interceptor, but the effort will take four to six more weeks. After that, crews will need to get to work on an already-planned rehabilitation project, which could take a further nine or 10 months, DC Water spokesperson Sherri Lewis said.</p> 
<p>Though the spill captured the nation’s attention only this week, local environmentalists have been sounding the alarm from the beginning. </p> 
<p>“It’s certainly a big ecological problem and an incredible threat to public health to have raw sewage splashing around and on shorelines,” said Hedrick Belin, president of the Potomac Conservancy, a conservation group. “We don’t need partisan politics getting in the way. This crisis is just too serious.” </p> 
<p>Officials in Maryland, which is technically responsible for the Potomac River, responded “within hours” of the initial spill, said Ammar Moussa, a spokesperson for Moore. But the interceptor falls under EPA’s regulatory purview, according to the governor’s office, accusing the agency that’s <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/01/27/epa-cuts-top-executive-jobs-under-trumps-reorg-00749294" target="_blank">lost thousands of staff</a> under Trump of failing to take action.</p> 
<p>“For the last four weeks, the Trump Administration has failed to act, shirking its responsibility and putting people's health at risk,” Moussa said in a statement. “Notably, the president’s own EPA explicitly refused to participate in the major legislative hearing about the cleanup last Friday.”</p> 
<p>Zeldin shot back at that accusation on Tuesday afternoon. </p> 
<p>“At no point in the lead up to today had DC Water or the state of Maryland requested EPA to take over their responsibilities, and EPA has continued to offer its full support to state and local leaders from the onset,” Zeldin said in a post on X.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Funding woes and ‘really poor infrastructure’</h4> 
<p>Water experts say the sewage spill is a symptom of a larger problem: Aging sewer pipes and water lines nationwide are in desperate need of repairs, but cash-strapped local governments are struggling to pay for them. </p> 
<p>The Trump administration has repeatedly pushed to slash federal funding for water projects. Last year, the White House <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2025/05/02/trump-calls-for-cutting-55-of-epas-budget-00323893" target="_blank">proposed a 90 percent cut</a> to EPA’s State Revolving Funds, the water sector’s largest source of federal dollars. The Senate ultimately rejected the cut in a spending bill that Trump <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/01/16/congress-oks-spending-package-without-protecting-colorado-research-lab-00731555" target="_blank">signed into law</a> last month. </p> 
<p>But extra water funding from the 2021 bipartisan infrastructure law is set to run out this fall, and experts warn of a coming funding cliff at the same time as extreme weather and AI data centers put more pressure on existing pipes, sewers and treatment plants.</p> 
<p>“We’ve got really poor infrastructure. A lot of these pipes, especially on the East Coast, were built decades ago,” said Jon Mueller, a visiting associate law professor at the University of Maryland. “I think it’s unfortunate that it takes a disaster like this to get people to focus on the problem.”</p> 
<p>It’s not yet clear how much the Potomac spill will cost, but the broader rehabilitation project for the interceptor sewer system’s “most vulnerable sections” is $625 million, said DC Water spokesperson Sherri Lewis. The utility has been coordinating with EPA, she added. </p> 
<p>“Just last week, we hosted the Assistant Administrator for Water for a tour of the site and briefing on the project and the progress made to date,” Lewis said in a statement. </p> 
<p>Although officials say the worst of the spill has been contained and that it has not impacted drinking water supplies, 243.5 million gallons of sewage overflows have been reported thus far. </p> 
<p>Environmental advocates are worried about long-term implications for the river, which feeds into the Chesapeake Bay, the nation’s largest estuary and the subject of decades of cleanup efforts. </p> 
<p>Earlier this month, University of Maryland researchers <a href="https://sph.umd.edu/news/umd-team-finds-e-coli-mrsa-potomac-river-after-sewage-spill" target="_blank">recorded extremely high concentrations of bacteria</a>, including a strain that resists antibiotics, tied to the spill. By springtime, that could render parts of the water unsafe for boating, canoeing and fishing. </p> 
<p>Dean Naujoks, who leads the environmental group Potomac Riverkeeper, said he hopes Trump’s involvement could improve what he described as a “botched” cleanup process by DC Water. But he cast blame as well on EPA, describing the agency as essentially missing in action.</p> 
<p>“We can’t get a hold of [EPA]. I have no idea what they’re doing,” Naujoks said. “The squabble between Trump and Gov. Moore has focused more of the attention on accountability, which I think is a good thing.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump looms over Texas attorney general race</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/maga-purity-test-plays-out-in-texas-attorney-general-race-00786750</link>
      <description>Rep. Chip Roy has long sparred with Trump. His breaks with the president have become a flashpoint in his run to be Texas' top lawman.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7246-d3b5-addf-f2c680fc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 16:30:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/97/2c/acf611d84a85b21938197d706eef/u-s-congress-48049.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>It remains unclear whether Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and other fiscal hawks will balk at a new health package with reforms to PBMs and additional community health center funding.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/97/2c/acf611d84a85b21938197d706eef/u-s-congress-48049.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Republican battle to become Texas’ next attorney general has turned into a MAGA purity test, with major implications for the future of the GOP after President Donald Trump leaves office.</p> 
<p>Rep. Chip Roy, a well known Freedom Caucus rabble-rouser and hardline fiscal conservative who has occasionally broken with Trump, is fighting to stay the front-runner for a job that has long been used to aggressively push the conservative agenda and served as a jumping-off point for higher office — like current Attorney General Ken Paxton, who’s running for Senate.</p> 
<p>The next Texas attorney general will help shape the future of the Republican party post-Trump, playing a key role leading the conservative legal movement. But if Roy is going to get there, he’ll first have to get by State Sen. Mayes Middleton and former DOJ attorney Aaron Reitz, who have both carved paths as aggressive foot soldiers for the MAGA movement. The race also includes state Sen. Joan Huffman, who is making a more measured pitch for the job.</p> 
<p>Roy has a lead in the polls, and all three candidates are trying to keep him from earning more than 50 percent of the vote in the March primary to force a runoff in May.</p> 
<p>Their main line of attack: Roy’s past dustups with Trump shows he is inadequately conservative in order to represent Texas in court. Roy, in response, has argued that his reputation as an obstructionist in Congress, deep experience in Washington and independent streak within the party demonstrates he’s well equipped to serve as Texas’ top lawyer.</p> 
<p>The candidates’ eagerness to prove their MAGA credentials were on display in the first few moments of a debate Tuesday night. Middleton bragged that Trump once called him a “MAGA champion.” Reitz said Trump regards him as a “true MAGA attorney.” Huffman said she “led the fight with President Trump on border security” in the state legislature. Roy said he has worked alongside Trump to designate cartels as terrorist organizations.</p> 
<p>But Roy’s rivals have repeatedly hammered him <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/01/24/chip-roy-donald-trump-threats-00200372?fbclid=IwY2xjawP5ifNleHRuA2FlbQIxMQBzcnRjBmFwcF9pZAwzNTA2ODU1MzE3MjgAAR60uqmVC4nhfNyNBfQXXUukkPUOCuIdnJI-gIYsTjGT5vldq-1srH-qcUsZkw_aem_Fd_USs9yKejW3hhPevsP5g" target="_blank"><u>for being at odds</u></a> with Trump and the GOP in the past. The congressman was the first to <a href="https://roy.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-chip-roy-released-following-statement-texas-ag-ken-paxton" target="_blank"><u>call for Paxton to resign</u></a> after he faced charges of bribery and abuse of office in 2020. He bucked Trump to certify the 2020 election and said the president demonstrated “clearly impeachable conduct” on Jan. 6. Roy backed Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis for president in 2024, making him one of just a handful of House Republicans who opposed Trump during that year’s primaries.</p> 
<p>And, his refusal to fall in line with GOP leadership in the House — even holding up numerous funding bills — has <a href="https://rollcall.com/2026/02/05/donald-trump-national-prayer-breakfast-democrats/" target="_blank"><u>occasionally infuriated</u></a> Trump. In late 2024, as Roy led the charge against Trump’s demand that the House raise the debt ceiling without restrictions on future spending, Trump blasted him as “just another ambitious guy, with no talent” and invited primary challengers against him. Roy was a late holdout on Trump’s signature legislative achievement, the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, though he eventually voted for it.</p> 
<p>“This is somebody who has a deep disdain for the MAGA movement … and he's only now singing a different tune now that it's campaign season,” Reitz said of Roy in an interview, while touting his own experience working in the Trump Justice Department’s Office of Legal Policy, a position he held for several months. Reitz has received Paxton’s coveted endorsement and posted strong fundraising numbers.</p> 
<p>Trump has not yet weighed in on who he prefers to take the mantle from Paxton, but his potential endorsement looms over the field. A recent <a href="https://www.uh.edu/news-events/stories/2026/february/02112026-hobby-primary-election-outlook-governor.php" target="_blank"><u>poll</u></a> shows Roy in the lead, with 33 percent of likely Republican voters, followed by Middleton, with 23 percent. Huffman and Reitz trail at 13 percent and 6 percent, respectively. A quarter of voters are undecided.</p> 
<p>Among Texas Republican voters, “the attorney general position is kind of viewed as the police officer of the state,” said Jen French, chair of the Travis County GOP. “Voters like somebody who's going to get in there and what they perceive as ‘fight, fight, fight.’”</p> 
<p>All four GOP candidates are closely aligned on policy, vowing to follow strict interpretations of the Texas and U.S. Constitutions, but Middleton and Reitz have made more bombastic declarations about how they would enforce the law. The differences between the set are mostly stylistic, as they try one to one-up each other on red meat issues like stopping the alleged spread of Sharia law in Texas and halting the flow of abortion pills into the state.</p> 
<p>Middleton has nicknamed himself “MAGA Mayes,” a slogan he’s put on hats his campaign gives away. He’s also leaned into culture war issues that rally the base like banning trans student athletes from competition and allowing the Ten Commandments in schools. The oil and gas businessman from Galveston has largely self-funded his campaign, putting more than $11 million toward the effort.</p> 
<p>Roy, who also leads in fundraising, has been endorsed by well-known conservatives like Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas), who Roy once worked for as his chief of staff, as well as fellow Freedom Caucus Reps. Lauren Boebert of Colorado and Andy Biggs of Arizona. Roy reported $4.2 million in the bank in January, fueled by a $2 million transfer from his congressional campaign account.</p> 
<p>Huffman, one of the longest-serving state senators, highlights her experience prosecuting felony crimes as an assistant district attorney and state district judge in Harris County. In an interview, she said she would treat the job of attorney general as “chief law enforcement officer for Texans,” and work closely with local law enforcement.</p> 
<p>Whoever emerges from the GOP primary will be the heavy favorite in the general election in the Republican-leaning state. On the Democratic side, the race includes State Sen. Nathan Johnson and former Galveston mayor Joe Jaworski, who is making his second shot at the nomination. Jaworski, in an interview, said voters are tired of “a rabid ultra MAGA representation of what government is. It’s all about punishing the vulnerable.”</p> 
<p>The job has long allowed its holder a leading role in the national culture wars — and a springboard to higher office. Republican Gov. Greg Abbott was attorney general before he ran for governor and barraged the Obama administration with lawsuits that made national headlines: He famously quipped in 2013 that his day-to-day was, “I go into the office, I sue the federal government and I go home.” Before he had the job, it was filled by now-Sen. John Cornyn (R-Texas), the man Paxton is currently running against.</p> 
<p>Paxton spent a decade steering the office into the center of the culture wars, pursuing actions in the name of preserving religious liberty and spearheading multistate lawsuits filed by Republican attorneys general against the federal government. The AG role has since become the top destination for young conservative legal talents, a number of whom have gone on to become judges appointed by Trump.</p> 
<p>It is a “choice position,” said Mark Jones, a political science professor at Rice University.</p> 
<p>“There’s this whole playing field within the legal system where the states can have a powerful impact on national policy in a wide range of areas,” he said. “And no state has more successfully – or at least more aggressively – used the power of the courts to try to further a conservative policy agenda than the state of Texas.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Hampshire’s GOP Gov. Kelly Ayotte draws her first major challenger</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/new-hampshire-kelly-ayotte-cinde-warmington-00785878</link>
      <description>Democrat Cinde Warmington launched another bid for the governor’s office after running unsuccessfully in 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-7133-d647-addc-fbf7f2170000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 09:58:12 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/65/31/b6124a7c4fc0952443f459d99e75/election-2024-new-hampshire-governor-82581.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Cinde Warmington during a gubernatorial debate in 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/65/31/b6124a7c4fc0952443f459d99e75/election-2024-new-hampshire-governor-82581.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Cinde Warmington launched a repeat bid for governor of New Hampshire on Wednesday, giving Democrats their first major challenger to GOP Gov. Kelly Ayotte in the purple state.</p> 
<p>Warmington, a former state executive councilor, ran unsuccessfully for governor in 2024, losing the Democratic nomination to former Manchester Mayor Joyce Craig who then went on to lose to Ayotte. She now enters a relatively open Democratic field, with just one other declared candidate.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c_7nRuEu0MY" target="_blank">launch video</a> posted to her campaign website, Warmington attacked Ayotte for “making your life more expensive.” She also accused the Republican of not standing up to President Donald Trump’s attempts to open an ICE detention facility in the state.</p> 
<p>“I’ll stand up to Trump when he jacks up health care costs and tariffs. I’ll say ‘no’ to ICE’s warehouse. I’ll work for our small businesses and I’ll make sure we don’t have a sales or income tax,” Warmington said in the video. <a href="https://url4027.email.politico.com/ss/c/u001.6g0Zd3AyneOViJYBXgbV68q315JmMH5kG-tqpKu2qUAoHQyu3STNAgxPcRVy5UDrIoEl2tLNburyB93d6QTITIZSOu-N17Ly2XnbqmiyU6iqi2Esu7eb9rvfl_W9PV1v/4o9/b1KJ9kx2Q8OKd3sZ95FNEg/h3/h001.vFJbE-rQrzow2egjEotMhktd83eGzjYQRc4D1NozcVE" target="_blank">WMUR</a> first reported her launch.</p> 
<p>Ayotte, for her part, has clashed with Trump. She has criticized <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2026-01-28/ayotte-ice-trump-merrimack-immigration-detention-dhs-kristi-noem-warehouse" target="_blank">the lack of transparency</a> around the ICE warehouse and <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2026-02-09/merrimack-ice-detainee-plans-nh-dncr-stewart-resigns" target="_blank">forced the resignation</a> of a state official who had been communicating with the Trump administration without alerting the governor. Her refusal to redistrict last year led the White House to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/30/redistricting-republican-loyalty-test-trump-00584932" target="_blank">weigh putting up a primary challenger against her</a>.</p> 
<p>Ayotte spokesperson John Corbett blasted Warmington in a statement, saying the former health care lobbyist “chose to make money off big pharmaceutical companies who hurt Granite Staters, and she is absolutely disqualified from serving as our Governor.”</p> 
<p>Democrats are bullish they can block Ayotte from a second term, emboldened by their <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/democrats-2025-win-midterms-virginia-new-jersey-00637057" target="_blank">party’s wins in the off-year elections</a>. But they face an uphill battle in a blue-leaning battleground state that routinely elects Republican governors while sending all-Democratic delegations to Congress. </p> 
<p>Recent history is not on Democrats’ side: The party thrice failed to unseat Ayotte’s predecessor, Republican Gov. Chris Sununu. And prognosticators rate the seat as <a href="https://www.cookpolitical.com/ratings/governor-race-ratings" target="_blank">“likely Republican”</a> this year.</p> 
<p>Democrats may also face another messy primary just two years after Warmington and Craig <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2024-election/new-hampshire-primary-governor-race-battleground-state-rcna169406" target="_blank">waged a bruising battle</a> to be their party’s nominee. For now, just Warmington and Democrat Jon Kiper, who finished a distant third in the 2024 race, have declared their candidacies. But Democratic Portsmouth Mayor Deaglan McEachern has been <a href="https://www.seacoastonline.com/story/news/politics/elections/2026/02/11/portsmouth-mayor-deaglan-mceachern-considers-run-nh-governor-election/88606818007/?gnt-cfr=1&amp;gca-cat=p&amp;gca-uir=true&amp;gca-epti=z11xx11p119550c119550v11xx11d--49--b--49--&amp;gca-ft=262&amp;gca-ds=sophi" target="_blank">publicly weighing a bid for governor</a> as recently as this month.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/survey_center_polls/922/" target="_blank">University of New Hampshire survey from January</a> showed Ayotte leading both men in hypothetical general-election matchups; it did not test her against Warmington. Ayotte notched a 50-percent approval rating in the poll, though 44 percent of likely voters said she did not deserve to be reelected compared to 42 percent who did.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This emerging Democratic star is embroiled in a primary fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/18/texas-house-primary-rio-grande-valley-00784771</link>
      <description>The primary in the Rio Grande Valley mirrors the battle in the state's Senate race.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-6d72-d647-addc-eff78a600001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/86/91/6906c535433d90d55b2c3b6e144c/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2246570182">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Greg Doherty/Getty Images for The Latin Recording Academy</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tejano music star Bobby Pulido, shown last November in Las Vegas, is in a contentious primary that has turned increasingly personal.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/86/91/6906c535433d90d55b2c3b6e144c/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2246570182" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tejano music star Bobby Pulido is a favorite of national Democrats this cycle, as he mounts an uphill battle to flip a deep-red Rio Grande Valley House seat that President Donald Trump won by 18 points in 2024.</p> 
<p>But before he can take on Rep. Monica De La Cruz (R-Texas) in the state's 15th District, he must navigate the politics of a messy primary with emergency room doctor Ada Cuellar in a race that has turned increasingly personal — and mirrors the fight up the ticket for one of the state’s Senate seats.</p> 
<p>The primary has emerged as somewhat of a proxy war in the high-profile Senate primary between Rep. Jasmine Crockett, who has backed Cuellar, and state Rep. James Talarico, who supports Pulido. Both contests have become emblematic of larger divides facing a party that is still going through growing pains after across-the-board losses to Republicans in 2024.</p> 
<p>Pulido is running a race geared toward a general election with a Republican-leaning electorate. In an interview, he said he is “not trying to run a primary race,” but rather a “general campaign.” Cuellar, meanwhile, argues Pulido’s vision for the future of the party is out of touch with what’s on the ground.</p> 
<p>Cuellar herself is facing a tough path to even reach November. Pulido’s name ID alone may be enough to get him through to the general. Even still, she has mounted repeated attacks on Pulido across the airwaves, arguing he is too conservative of a Democrat.</p> 
<p>A few of them have landed. Pulido’s campaign has apologized for a past <a href="https://www.mediaite.com/media/news/exclusive-texas-democrat-bobby-pulido-has-long-history-of-explicit-misogynistic-commentary/" target="_blank">misogynistic comment directed toward Hillary Clinton</a>. His opponents have also focused on past remarks in which <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yAurcCq3vMU&amp;feature=youtu.be" target="_blank">he said he doesn’t live in Texas full time</a> and used his <a href="https://x.com/drcuellartx15/status/2020898021249048773?s=20" target="_blank">friendship with a local judge</a> to get out of a speeding ticket.</p> 
<p>Cuellar said the strategy became necessary because party leaders in both Texas and Washington were putting their thumb on the scale for Pulido.</p> 
<p>“The establishment has been misreading the moment,” she said in an interview. “This district wasn't looking for a conservative Dem. They were looking for someone who is willing to fight someone with experience and someone who can actually solve problems.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Pulido’s campaign says it’s focused on the ground game, pointing to dozens of events Pulido has hosted in the district in recent weeks at taquerias and community centers. They have so far insisted that they don’t want to go negative in the campaign.</p> 
<p>“It’s become personal one way only,” Pulido said. “I haven’t responded. We’ve been really focused on talking to voters.”</p> 
<p>Pulido’s campaign insists he’ll cruise through the primary. An internal poll conducted by GBAO from Jan. 24-27 and shared with POLITICO showed Pulido leading Cuellar by nearly 50 points — 68 percent to 19 percent. Thirteen percent of the 500 likely voters surveyed were undecided, and the poll has a margin of error of plus or minus 4.4 percent.</p> 
<p>While he says he’s not interested in responding publicly, there are still clear signs Pulido is trying to push back on Cuellar’s attacks. In <a href="https://host2.adimpact.com/admo/viewer/927cd4f8-2806-4115-afba-4dc5546d76be" target="_blank">his first campaign ad of the primary</a> released late last week, Cuellar’s face is shown on the screen while Pulido says American politics has become focused on “lies that don’t lower grocery prices.”</p> 
<p>Cuellar has navigated controversy of her own. She fired a consultant who <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2026/02/09/the-big-ads-from-the-big-game-00770981" target="_blank">was previously involved in Republican races</a> as she worked to cast Pulido as too conservative for the district.</p> 
<p>“Would I like for a primary to not be as contentious as it’s been? Yes, I wish it wasn’t,” Pulido said. “But it’s OK. It’s politics. I’m a big boy. But we're trying to advance to face Monica De La Cruz.”</p> 
<p>The sharp-elbowed campaign from Cuellar has worried some Pulido allies who are fearful these same types of attacks could prove potent in a general election. But Cuellar said her tactics are doing national Democrats a favor.</p> 
<p>“We’re actually vetting the candidate,” Cuellar said. “The DCCC clearly didn’t vet him at all.”</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Trump is Remaking America’s Nuclear Regulator</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/18/how-trump-is-remaking-americas-nuclear-regulator-1921561</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-6e89-de8a-a1fc-ffc9dc7c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">How Trump is Remaking America’s Nuclear Regulator</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6389499348112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/35ebde5d-9fff-4792-8adb-527ce18ae726/fb4da6e2-bc9a-4314-8530-7d644f54b739/main.mp4" src="28/92/d6aab046490194242e0c188b5315/ep-5-thumbnail-horizontal-w-title-1.png">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Maryland Democrats are thwarting Wes Moore’s political ambitions</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/16/wes-moore-redistricting-maryland-00783292</link>
      <description>"The operations of his political tentacles are weak," says one Democratic strategist. "His inside political network is weak.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-67fa-de8a-a1fc-fffa27700000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2026 15:40:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/1c/dd/7260ed4549bdadf8f61d2b115c51/trump-baltimore-19131.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Nick Wass/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore speaks during a news conference, Sept. 5, 2025, in Baltimore.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1c/dd/7260ed4549bdadf8f61d2b115c51/trump-baltimore-19131.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore's national political ambitions could be stymied by Democrats in his own backyard.</p> 
<p>The governor’s power play to redraw the state’s congressional lines and snare Democrats a single House seat has earned him accolades from progressive activists and party leaders in Washington, raising his profile as he weighs a 2028 presidential run. But Moore also has been outmaneuvered at times by members of own party, particularly those in the Maryland Senate where his gerrymander blitz is facing an unceremonious death.</p> 
<p>The redistricting gambit is one of the first big political tests Moore has faced that has national implications and could elevate him further within the party — or expose weaknesses as he positions himself as a counterweight to President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Critics say Moore hasn’t been aggressive enough in using bare-knuckle tactics to push through his agenda. Supporters say the first-term governor is focused on redistricting because he sees it as vital to his future national ambitions. Some national Democrats question whether Moore can lead the nation if he fails to bend lawmakers in a solidly blue state with a Democratic-controlled Legislature to enact his policy priorities. POLITICO spoke to almost two dozen state and federal lawmakers and Democratic strategists for this story.</p> 
<p>David Turner, Moore’s senior adviser and communications director, said the governor spearheading Maryland’s redistricting effort is not about furthering his political career.</p> 
<p>“Anyone who thinks this is about national ambitions isn’t paying enough attention to the damage being done in 2026,” he said. “The Governor has been clear: at a time when other states are discussing mid-decade redistricting, Maryland needs to as well.”</p> 
<p>Moore’s inability to convince enough Maryland Democratic senators to go along with redrawing maps has drawn unfavorable comparisons to California Gov. Gavin Newsom, another likely 2028 White House contender who successfully pushed through a major redistricting effort in his state. After California voters approved the state’s redistricting proposal, Newsom urged other states, including Maryland, to “contribute a verse” in the party’s gerrymandering push.</p> 
<p>“If he did kind of match Gavin in terms of that effectiveness, being able to take this issue, win on it and kind of help build his image, I think that would [have been] a great opportunity for him,” said Paul Mitchell of Moore. Mitchell is a redistricting expert and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/15/california-gerrymander-paul-mitchell-00510786" target="_blank">architect of the newly adopted California congressional maps</a>.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/4e/56/3e4b398e4ffabb01c336e4d29d4a/maryland-affordability-26319.jpg" alt="Maryland Gov. Wes Moore speaks during a press conference announcing the Protection from Predatory Pricing Act, in Severna Park, Maryland, Jan. 20, 2026." data-portal-copyright="Stephanie Scarbrough/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26020744326319" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Maryland Gov. Wes Moore speaks during a press conference announcing the Protection from Predatory Pricing Act, in Severna Park, Maryland, Jan. 20, 2026."/><p>While Moore championed bills to raise the state’s minimum wage, worked to reduce <a href="https://www.wbaltv.com/article/2025-crime-data-baltimore-lowest-homicide-rate-decades/69898283" target="_blank">Baltimore's homicide rate</a> to near 50-year lows and helped Marylanders cover soaring energy costs, in December, <a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/mgawebsite/FloorActions/Agenda/senate-1-?ys=2025S1#Veto2" target="_blank">Maryland Democrats overrode at least 16</a> of the governor’s vetoes — tying his predecessor, GOP Gov. Larry Hogan, for the most he had in a single year during his two terms. That included one override veto over an issue that peeved many Black lawmakers months earlier: Moore’s blockage of the formation of a commission to study reparations in the state.</p> 
<p>Weeks after his reparations veto, Moore traveled to an early presidential primary state to deliver the keynote remarks at the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/30/wes-moore-dives-into-2028-race-in-south-carolina-00378647" target="_blank">South Carolina Democrats Blue Palmetto Dinner</a>, where he said: “Gone are the days when we are the party of bureaucracy, multi-year studies, panels and college debate club rules.”</p> 
<p>It is a stark illustration of the criticism that’s followed Moore since he cruised to victory in his first-ever election four years ago: that he’s using the governor’s mansion as a springboard to Washington instead of doing the work of building relationships in Annapolis to get his bills across the finish line.</p> 
<p>“Truly, Wes Moore is a great candidate…He has the pizzazz and the swagger that some folks wish they could have,” a Democratic strategist who has worked on state, local and presidential campaigns said and granted anonymity to offer an unvarnished assessment of Moore. “But the operations of his political tentacles are weak. His inside political network is weak.”</p> 
<p>Moore addressed some of this criticism head on last week, where the tension was palpable during a joint address of the General Assembly.</p> 
<p>“I will not stand here and tell you that I have gotten it all right,” Moore said in his State of the State address Wednesday. “It's taken time to build relationships. It's taken time to learn Annapolis. I am an outsider at heart, and I don't see that changing,” he said before ramping up to a central theme of his remarks – and pressuring Senate Democrats to take up a congressional redistricting bill.</p> 
<p>He characterized his months-long public tussle with Maryland Senate President Bill Ferguson as “a very principled disagreement.”</p> 
<p>Though the Maryland House of Delegates approved legislation Moore backed to redraw the seat of the state’s lone Republican, House Freedom Caucus chair Rep. Andy Harris, Maryland’s gerrymandering effort is still being blocked in the state Senate.</p> 
<p>Ferguson has maintained he will not bring the bill up for a vote, saying there is not enough support for it in his chamber, it’s legally risky and adopting the new maps would jeopardize Maryland’s current 7-1 advantage.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/90/6d/939f90ec49f1a1cf168e845222db/election-2024-maryland-senate-tax-debate-84416.jpg" alt="Maryland State Senate President Bill Ferguson addresses the senate chamber during the opening session of the Maryland General Assembly, at the State Capitol in Annapolis, Maryland, Jan. 10, 2024." data-portal-copyright="Bryan Woolston/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="24093757684416" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Maryland State Senate President Bill Ferguson addresses the senate chamber during the opening session of the Maryland General Assembly, at the State Capitol in Annapolis, Maryland, Jan. 10, 2024."/><p>Many national Democrats have pressured Ferguson and other holdouts, including former Speaker Nancy Pelosi and Democratic Leader Hakeem Jeffries, who in an <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/02/15/politics/jeffries-midterms-gerrymandering-redistricting" target="_blank">interview with CNN on Sunday</a> suggested he would travel to Annapolis to meet with Ferguson.</p> 
<p>Two Moore aides, granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy, also point out that top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, Jamie Raskin (D-Md.), who previously served in the Maryland Senate, <a href="https://jamieraskin.com/md-general-assembly-letter/" target="_blank">penned a letter</a> to state lawmakers this week calling it a “clear and present danger” not to act. Raskin also sought to undercut Ferguson’s legal justification for not acting, pointing to recent decisions by the U.S. Supreme Court allowing both Texas and California to use their redrawn maps ahead of the midterms. But the Senate leader appears unswayed.</p> 
<p>“I think the miscalculation is that a lot of people are being led to believe that it's only Bill who doesn't want the map,” said one Maryland Legislative Black Caucus member granted anonymity to discuss internal party dynamics. </p> 
<p>Maryland’s Feb. 24 <a href="https://elections.maryland.gov/elections/2026/2026_Election_Calendar.pdf" target="_blank">candidate filing deadline</a> is quickly approaching — the date Ferguson and supporters say any changes beyond that date will be too late and overly disruptive to the state elections calendar.</p> 
<p>The two Moore aides argued that it is an arbitrary deadline and pointed to legislation <a href="https://mgaleg.maryland.gov/mgawebsite/Legislation/Details/HB0689?ys=2026rs" target="_blank">working its way through the Maryland House</a> pushing the filing deadline to late March.</p> 
<p>A December poll by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/maryland-residents-bristle-at-wes-moores-redistricting-push-00690336" target="_blank">University of Maryland, Baltimore County</a> found just 27 percent of Maryland residents said redrawing maps was a top issue, signaling affordability and quality education were top of mind.</p> 
<p>Maryland-based Democratic strategist Len Foxwell said Moore’s attempts so far to win over voters in the state have been too focused on cable television and podcast appearances, adding the governor’s redistricting push never gained steam because he and his team “botched the rollout so badly.”</p> 
<p>Instead of engaging in the kind of aggressive public relations campaign that Newsom launched to sell voters on the need to gerrymander, Moore created an advisory commission to solicit public input. Its meetings were held virtually and typically at odd hours, with most proceedings taking place late on Friday afternoons. The outcome of whether the commission was going to recommend new maps was never in doubt.</p> 
<p>“The work of the commission was a rather dreary exercise in muscle-flexing,” Foxwell said. “The clear message was that we are doing this because we can do it. And I don't think that was a message that was satisfying.”</p> 
<p>Moore hasn’t deployed scorched-earth tactics against Ferguson, unlike the kind Trump encouraged where he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/trump-indiana-redistricting-republicans-rodric-bray-00686257" target="_blank">threatened to primary Indiana Republicans</a>who wouldn’t support his attempt to gerrymander in the Hoosier state. Indiana Senate Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/trump-indiana-redistricting-republicans-rodric-bray-00686257" target="_blank">ultimately blocked Trump’s push</a>.</p> 
<p>Jeffries, who could become the nation’s first Black speaker should Democrats take back the U.S. House this fall, said during a hastily arranged press conference in the U.S. Capitol in late January that Marylanders “deserve an up or down vote.” Moore, standing shoulder-to-shoulder with Jeffries, looked on as the Democratic congressional leader directed his disdain toward Ferguson, though he never named him.</p> 
<p>Behind the scenes, Jeffries and other top Democrats backing Moore are working around Ferguson by leaning on the Black Caucus to force a rarely-used state Senate procedure to discharge the redistricting bill out of the chamber’s Rules Committee. If it’s successful it will force a floor vote on the House-passed bill. But <a href="https://www.thebanner.com/politics-power/state-government/arthur-ellis-senate-redistricting-protest-7BHVDQD5JRFJVPGHWVDZXZH3LQ/" target="_blank">just one member</a> of the Black Caucus is openly supporting that tactic and the prevailing thought is the legislation will sit in purgatory until the General Assembly session ends in April.</p> 
<p>The Maryland Legislative Black Caucus member added that while Moore is seen as a rising Democratic star on the national stage, there is work to be done by the governor in Annapolis.</p> 
<p>“I think it's that his folks are trying to insulate him from some things,” the lawmaker continued. “Because if he starts to have those relationships, then he's going to start to hear that some of these ideas that he has are not necessarily the best, and that becomes a problem for some of his national aspirations.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DHS watchdog warns shutdown could imperil immigration enforcement oversight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/15/dhs-watchdog-shutdown-immigration-enforcement-00782758</link>
      <description>The lapse in funding is forcing the department’s inspector general to suspend the majority of its audits and probes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-6353-d647-addc-ebd72ab50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 17:52:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b6/c9/625d6f82417f83004cff90b43180/gettyimages-2258531337.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Patrick T. Fallon/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Protestors clash with police during a protest against Immigration and Customs Enforcement in Los Angeles on January 30, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b6/c9/625d6f82417f83004cff90b43180/gettyimages-2258531337.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The partial government shutdown that went into effect Saturday is throwing the fate of oversight at the Department of Homeland Security into peril, with the department’s independent watchdog warning a lapse in funding could jeopardize several ongoing investigations.</p> 
<p>DHS’s inspector general currently has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/dhs-watchdog-probe-trump-immigration-00768311" target="_blank">eight active probes</a> into the Trump administration’s nationwide immigration crackdown, including reviews of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/dhs-inspector-general-investigates-ice-surveillance-00768778" target="_blank">use of facial recognition</a> and allegations of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents using <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-investigation-use-of-force-ice-00761953" target="_blank">excessive force</a>.</p> 
<p>But with a lapse in funding for DHS, the Office of the Inspector General has been forced to suspend approximately 85 percent of its audits, evaluations and inspections, according to the OIG.</p> 
<p>Congressional Democrats are demanding sweeping reforms to ICE and Customs and Border Patrol before they’ll vote to fund DHS, including requirements that immigration enforcement agents wear body cameras and display their ID numbers and last names. With Senate Republicans and the White House refusing to budge on several key demands — including a proposed prohibition on federal agents wearing masks — the department is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/congress-shutdown-dhs-ice-00779881" target="_blank">likely to remain unfunded</a> for at least 10 days.</p> 
<p>Democrats in Congress first asked Joseph Cuffari, the DHS inspector general President Donald Trump appointed during his first term, to investigate the use of force by ICE agents last June. The lawmakers, including Sens. Elizabeth Warren and Ed Markey of Massachusetts, wrote to Cuffari earlier this month <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-240c-df17-afbf-7d3f17b40000" target="_blank">asking him to expedite the probe</a>, citing the fatal shootings of Renee Good and Alex Pretti by federal agents in Minneapolis as underscoring the “urgent need” for moving quickly.</p> 
<p>Republicans have raised concern about the shutdown’s effect on DHS agencies like TSA and FEMA, although <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499" target="_blank">it will likely take weeks</a> for the public to start feeling the effects of the funding lapse.</p> 
<p>Rep. Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.), who chairs the House Homeland Security Committee, said in a statement that “OIG investigations provide transparency and accountability, and any delay in funding will only disrupt these important efforts,” adding that the DHS appropriations bill passed in the House provided “critical funding” for the office.</p> 
<p>“As we experience yet another DHS shutdown because Senate Democrats refused to pass this legislation, I urge them to negotiate in good faith so we can ensure these resources and the resources for numerous other components, like FEMA and TSA, are not held hostage because of Washington’s dysfunction,” he said.</p> 
<p>ICE, on the other hand, is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/01/trump-protecting-priorities-from-shutdown-00588657" target="_blank">largely insulated</a> from the effects of the shutdown, with GOP lawmakers having appropriated billions of dollars for the agency in the One Big Beautiful Bill Act last year.</p> 
<p>But the lapse in funding raises several potential obstacles to the ability of members of Congress and investigators to conduct oversight of the agency. During the last government shutdown, ICE <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/29/congress/ice-quietly-furloughed-its-congressional-relations-team-during-shutdown-00627355" target="_blank">quietly furloughed</a> most of its congressional relations team and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/27/immigration-congressional-visits-ice-government-shutdown-00624066" target="_blank">blocked lawmakers</a> from visiting immigration detention facilities. (Prior to the shutdown, Democratic lawmakers on several occasions <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/19/new-jersey-congressmember-assault-00357934" target="_blank">clashed with DHS</a> over <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/18/ice-nyc-protest-00572418" target="_blank">their attempts to inspect detention facilities</a>.)</p> 
<p>And with approximately 60 percent of the OIG’s workforce furloughed — including auditors, data scientists and inspectors — only special agents like criminal investigators and personnel whose work is supported by secondary funding sources, like the Disaster Relief Fund, can continue working through the shutdown, per the office.</p> 
<p>The effect of the funding lapse for the inspector general’s work is also slated to affect the office’s reviews of the Secret Service’s handling of the July 2024 assassination attempt against Trump, in addition to probes of DHS’s cybersecurity and counterintelligence operations.</p> 
<p>The Council of the Inspectors General on Integrity and Efficiency — an independent government entity that lays out annual legislative priorities focused on government oversight and accountability — has for years called on Congress to establish authority for IGs to continue oversight during government shutdowns.</p> 
<p>Mark Greenblatt, who served as the Department of the Interior’s inspector general from 2019 until 2025, said while criminal investigations can sometimes continue despite a lapse in funding, IG offices are forced to pause oversight reviews, ceding valuable time on sensitive audits during shutdowns.</p> 
<p>“These situations are raw. They need an independent voice providing facts on what's happening on the ground with respect to these sensitive issues,” said Greenblatt, who was one of several IGs <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/01/25/donald-trump-inspectors-general-firing-00200611" target="_blank">dismissed by Trump</a> last year. “When they push the pause button on these things, they’re not delivering for the American people, and that, to me, is the problem.”</p> 
<p>Democrats have accused DHS Secretary Kristi Noem of deliberately attempting to stymie the OIG’s ongoing probes. In <a href="https://www.politico.com/document/duckworth-noem-letter" target="_blank">a letter sent to Noem</a> earlier this month, Sen. Tammy Duckworth (D-Ill.) cautioned that “repeated tacit threats from your Office of the Secretary to DHS OIG may have already succeeded in weakening DHS OIG’s operational independence.”</p> 
<p>That warning came after Duckworth met with Cuffari to discuss why her request for an independent investigation into use of force by federal agents during ICE’s “Operation Midway Blitz” in Chicago was denied. During the meeting, she wrote in the letter, Duckworth learned that DHS’s general counsel advised the OIG on several occasions that Noem has the power to halt its investigations.</p> 
<p>Cabinet secretaries are empowered by a 1978 law to prevent the OIG from carrying out audits or investigations if they determine the reviews could put national security at risk.</p> 
<p>“This broad authority effectively empowers you to select from a broad range of pretextual options to unilaterally prevent or halt any ‘independent’ DHS OIG investigation, regardless of your true intent,” Duckworth wrote.</p> 
<p>No DHS secretary has ever invoked the provision, Duckworth wrote in the letter.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-16T10:44:56-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>In South Texas, the GOP immigration hard line is now political kryptonite</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/15/south-texas-latino-republicans-immigration-00782129</link>
      <description>Texas Republicans bet on continuing to win over Latino voters. Then Trump began his aggressive deportation campaign.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-593e-de8a-a1fc-f97efab00001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2026 07:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ae/13/ca674b514278859253db6682b2ac/texas-daily-life-10531.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">David Goldman/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A U.S. Army Reserve soldier watches over the Rio Grande river separating Mexico, from the U.S., in Laredo, Texas, Oct. 14, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ae/13/ca674b514278859253db6682b2ac/texas-daily-life-10531.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson and Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson and Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Backlash to President Donald Trump’s immigration crackdown is putting vulnerable Republicans in a tough spot, forcing them to shift their tone to appease frustrated Hispanic voters — or risk losing key battleground seats.</p> 
<p>It’s a delicate pivot for Republicans in South Texas, who spent years taking a hardline approach on immigration and flipped historically blue districts in the process.</p> 
<p>Republican Rep. Monica De La Cruz, representing a majority-Hispanic district, has gone from calling for mass deportations to focusing on the “worst of the worst.” In lieu of expediting removals, she wants to create new visa categories for undocumented workers to fill jobs in construction and agriculture. And instead of slamming the Biden White House for its "border failure," she's setting up private meetings at the Trump White House to plead for temperance in immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>Rep. Tony Gonzales, whose district shares hundreds of miles with Mexico, wants his party to talk more about the border, and said he plans to “continue to advocate that the Republican Party needs to focus on convicted criminal illegal aliens” amid broad outrage over deportations of undocumented people with no proven risk to public safety.</p> 
<p>Like other Republicans, they are trying to slowly distance themselves from the massive immigration crackdown that has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270" target="_blank">quickly become political kryptonite for the GOP</a> — but without being seen as disloyal to the president or undercutting their previous positions.</p> 
<p>“President Trump made a promise, and he's kept that promise by securing the border. That was stage one,” De La Cruz said in an interview. “Now we're at stage two, which is having a conversation of true immigration reform.”</p> 
<p>Republicans’ efforts to change the conversation will test their ability to maintain, or even extend, Trump’s 2024 gains with Hispanic voters — and play a pivotal role in the fight for control of Congress in November. A slew of polls in recent weeks has shown many Hispanic voters across the country, repulsed by the Trump administration’s aggressive deportation campaign, are souring on the Republican president they supported to a historic degree in 2024.</p> 
<p>It’s a warning the White House appears to be taking seriously. In recent weeks, after the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by an immigration enforcement officer in Minneapolis, the White House has signaled openness to paring back its deportation operation. On Thursday, border czar Tom Homan announced the administration’s massive immigration surge in Minneapolis <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/homan-announces-end-to-minnesota-immigration-enforcement-surge-00777990" target="_blank">would come to a close</a>.</p> 
<p>Latino voters’ embrace of Trump was a political earthquake, and South Texas was the epicenter.</p> 
<p>De La Cruz’s district — which sprawls from the Rio Grande Valley on the U.S.-Mexico border up to the San Antonio suburbs — was represented by a Democrat in Congress for 120 years before De La Cruz won her seat in 2022. In 2024, Trump romped to an 18-point victory.</p> 
<p>The 15th Congressional District was among those redrawn by the Texas legislature’s redistricting gambit last year, offering De La Cruz an even more favorable electorate. But that bet relies heavily on Hispanic voters sticking with the GOP: Nearly 80 percent of the district identifies as Hispanic or Latino, and if those voters flip back to the Democratic Party or stay home, it could erase much of the new map’s intended friendliness to Republicans.</p> 
<p>“With the border secure and Latinos responding to ICE raids and government overreach, the districts that Republicans thought were their future a year ago are likely to be their undoing,” said Mike Madrid, a Republican strategist who is a frequent critic of Trump. “Hard to find another situation in the past 50 years where a political party has squandered a generational opportunity like this.”</p> 
<p>Flipping De La Cruz’s district is a top objective for House Democrats this cycle, who are salivating at the prospect of winning back Latino voters. She’ll face either Bobby Pulido, a Tejano music star with widespread name ID recruited by the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, or Ada Cuellar, an ER doctor who has an impressive penchant for fundraising.</p> 
<p>Local Republicans have begun sounding the alarm.</p> 
<p>Daniel Garza, president of the LIBRE Initiative, a grassroots conservative group based in South Texas, said “Biden’s border chaos” was directly responsible for Texas Republicans’ victories in recent election cycles, including De La Cruz’s, but that moving toward the other extreme — a harsh crackdown — could again dissuade Hispanic voters who might otherwise support the GOP.</p> 
<p>“We don't have to be a nation that has to decide between an ‘everybody-in’ or an ‘everybody-out’ approach,” Garza said. “I honestly feel that the counties across the entire Texan border shifted to the right because of the border chaos. … But this sort of everybody-out approach, I think, is also causing some reflection.”</p> 
<p>The immigration crackdown has wreaked havoc for the area’s business community. Greg LaMantia, who runs a major beer wholesaler in the region, said his company’s sales are down as a result of the raids. “You have people that are legal that are scared to death to get caught up in this fiasco and deported,” said LaMantia, who voted for Trump and has donated recently to both Republican and Democratic lawmakers. “It’s caused sales to go down, no doubt about it. It's chaos."</p> 
<p>Daniel Guerrero, CEO of the McAllen-based South Texas Builders Association, said rampant ICE activity has sent a shiver through the construction industry, leading to massive delays. He said ICE is notorious for following concrete trucks to job sites, then apprehending workers as they begin pouring a foundation, leaving half-poured concrete slabs.</p> 
<p>“The sentiment is pretty clear across the table, that nobody really expected this magnitude of enforcement,” said Guerrero, who voted for Trump and De La Cruz in 2024.</p> 
<p>He said the Hispanic Trump supporters he knows are souring on this administration, an observation <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/latino-voters-powered-trumps-comeback-now-theyre-turning-on-his-economy-00726548" target="_blank">supported by recent polling</a>. In the latest warning sign, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/republicans-hispanic-voters-texas-special-00763560" target="_blank">Latino voters helped a Democrat flip a reliably red seat</a> in Fort Worth last month. Taylor Rehmet, who picked up a state Senate seat in a special election, won about 4 out of 5 Hispanic votes <a href="https://votehub.com/2026/02/03/are-hispanic-voters-moving-back-toward-democrats/" target="_blank">across the district</a>, a massive 26-point improvement over Kamala Harris in 2024.</p> 
<p>Many Republicans are trying to steer the discussion around immigration to focus on how border crossings have dropped to historic lows under Trump — which they hope will remind Hispanic voters why they should stick with the GOP.</p> 
<p>“The Hispanic population gives President Trump and Republicans a lot of leeway with just how bad things were before and where they're at now,” said Gonzales, whose sprawling border district is majority Hispanic. “They have a lot of leeway to get a lot of runway, if you will.”</p> 
<p>De La Cruz successfully ran in 2024 on deportations and the “worst border security crisis in our nation's history.” Now she’s proposing <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/immigration-raids-restaurants-construction-visa-expansions-00754051" target="_blank">a new visa category, H-2C,</a> allowing employers like those in construction and hospitality to hire foreign workers. She also <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_4367?q=H.R.4367" target="_blank">introduced legislation</a> which would expand the H-2A visa category for seasonal agricultural workers.</p> 
<p>In recent weeks, De La Cruz said she has taken constituents to meet with the Labor Department, the White House and House Speaker Mike Johnson, pitching them on her bills and encouraging the administration to change its tact on immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>“There's limited resources, period. And we want those limited resources to be focused on the worst of the worst, the criminal immigrants that have come in,” De La Cruz said. “We have legal immigrants in our district who have work visas that they don't want to go out to work because some may have fear about the process that is currently being administered.”</p> 
<p>But De La Cruz’s shift in messaging has simultaneously earned skepticism from some industry leaders and frustration with the base, underscoring the political tightrope she must walk until November.</p> 
<p>Guerrero, the construction nonprofit leader, said he sensed political opportunism in De La Cruz’s newfound interest in helping his industry.</p> 
<p>“People feel abandoned because you never showed face, and now that there's an actual crisis, you want to show face?” Guerrero said. “It's like, dude, it's a little too late, man.”</p> 
<p>The MAGA base, meanwhile, doesn’t love the shift, either. Patricio County GOP Chair Rex Warner thinks De La Cruz has become too soft on deportations. “I align with some of it, but very little,” he said.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misspelled Ada Cuellar’s name.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shapiro grows his donor network ahead of 2028</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/shapiro-donor-network-fundraising-00779879</link>
      <description>The Pennsylvania governor is using his book tour and his reelection bid as a way to expand his donor list.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5494-d3b5-addf-f4d40a100000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e1/c2/08dc2fa545ceaea355d1af9898be/governor-josh-shapiro-in-conversation-at-92ny-14176.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photo by Evan Agostini/Invision/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro is raising campaign cash on the side of his book tour.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e1/c2/08dc2fa545ceaea355d1af9898be/governor-josh-shapiro-in-conversation-at-92ny-14176.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky and Kelly Garrity</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro is using his book tour and 2026 reelection campaign to further build out a national fundraising network that could prove quite useful in a potential 2028 run.</p> 
<p>The governor held a fundraising event over lunch while visiting Massachusetts for his book tour last month, two people familiar with the planning for it confirmed — making it at least the third fundraiser he attended in the last year in the deep-blue state with deep-pocketed donors who have long bankrolled presidential contenders. One of the others was held at the home of Jewish philanthropist and New England Patriots president Jonathan Kraft in April, details of which have not previously been reported. Shapiro attended <a href="https://secure.actblue.com/donate/071925nantucket" target="_blank">another on Nantucket</a>, a summer fundraising mecca, in July, according to an attendee and invitations obtained by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>They add to an extensive list of networking events for the possible White House aspirant who’s long been a prolific fundraiser within and beyond Pennsylvania.</p> 
<p>He amassed $23 million in 2025 with the help of $2.5 million from former New York City Mayor Michael Bloomberg; $1 million from a Soros family PAC, $500,000 from James and Kathryn Murdoch, the left-leaning son and daughter in law of Rupert Murdoch; and over $120,000 from Kraft and his father, New England Patriots owner Robert Kraft. That’s helped him build a $30 million war chest to unleash this year against his likely GOP opponent, state Treasurer Stacy Garrity, who raised nearly $1.5 million last year and had $1 million in the bank to start 2026.</p> 
<p>His book tour side-hustle comes as several of Shapiro’s would-be rivals for the Democratic nomination in 2028 take donor meetings across the country as they navigate their own reelection bids and start laying the groundwork for White House runs.</p> 
<p>Shapiro routinely dismisses talk of 2028 in public, keeping a laser focus on his reelection bid and on his efforts to help Democrats down the ballot.</p> 
<p>“No one should be looking past these midterms,” the governor recently told reporters in Washington, D.C., who were peppering him with hypotheticals.</p> 
<p>Sources say he is just as disciplined behind closed doors: Shapiro has kept his pitch focused on his leadership in purple Pennsylvania and how Democrats should be centering pocketbook issues in the midterms, while declining to engage with questions about his future beyond 2026, according to two people who attended donor events with Shapiro last year.</p> 
<p>“The smartest thing Shapiro and other folks on the ballot in 2026 can do right now is say ‘I’m running for reelection right now and I’m in the middle of the fight.’ [It] makes ‘26 a nice little audition for their eventual 2028 runs,” said Alex Hoffman, a Democratic strategist and donor adviser.</p> 
<p>His out-of-state networking is already paying off. Shapiro raked in over $700,000 from prominent donors in Massachusetts alone in 2025, including $260,000 from construction magnate John Fish and $50,000 from telecommunications tycoon Robert Hale. He also hauled in cash from Hollywood bigwigs and tech titans, including $100,000 from Sony film executive Tom Rothman and $200,000 from Ripple co-founder Chris Larsen.</p> 
<p>But the governor’s expansive donor pool is also drawing scrutiny. Garrity has called on Shapiro to <a href="https://www.pennlive.com/politics/2026/02/garrity-says-shapiro-should-return-over-2m-from-billionaire-mentioned-26k-times-in-epstein-files.html" target="_blank">return over $2 million</a> his campaign has taken over the years from billionaire LinkedIn co-founder Reid Hoffman, who is <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/02/09/tech-leaders-epstein-records-silicon-valley-sergey-brin-thiel-sinofsky-reid-hoffman-musk-gates.html" target="_blank">referenced repeatedly in the Jeffrey Epstein files</a>. Hoffman gave $500,000 to Shapiro last year. Shapiro also received $50,000 from New York Giants co-owner Steve Tisch, who is <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/7040342/2026/02/12/steve-tisch-jeffrey-epstein-new-york-giants/" target="_blank">also mentioned in the Epstein files</a>, as is <a href="https://www.boston.com/news/local-news/2026/02/04/jeffrey-epstein-wanted-robert-kraft-to-hire-his-lawyer-amid-patriots-owners-prostitution-case-documents-show/" target="_blank">Robert Kraft</a>. Both <a href="https://x.com/reidhoffman/status/1989483179716075874?s=20" target="_blank">Hoffman</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/7040342/2026/02/12/steve-tisch-jeffrey-epstein-new-york-giants/" target="_blank">Tisch</a> have issued statements distancing themselves from the late convict.</p> 
<p>“Stacy Garrity should stop playing politics with the Epstein files. Donald Trump is mentioned in the files over 5,000 times. Is she going to ask him to rescind his endorsement?” Shapiro spokesperson Manuel Bonder said in a statement. Bonder declined comment on the governor’s fundraisers.</p> 
<p>He'll need to keep building out that network. Shapiro has benefited from what longtime Pennsylvania Democratic strategist Neil Oxman described as “institutional donors” in the state who’ve given to successive Democratic governors. But of “the thousands of people who raise money nationally, he probably knows a fraction of them. He has some [national] recognition, but he’s not Gavin Newsom. He’s not the Clintons.”</p> 
<p>Shapiro also won’t be able to use the gobs of money he’s raised for his state campaign account to fund a run for federal office, leaving him at an initial disadvantage against other potential 2028ers who are already <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/newsletter/2026/02/democrats-eying-2028-rake-in-the-cash-and-build-their-donor-lists-00763383" target="_blank">squirreling away millions of dollars into federal leadership committees</a>, super PACs and congressional campaign accounts that can be converted when the time comes.</p> 
<p>“That’s why sometimes it’s hard to run for office when you have to run for another office,” Oxman said.</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fetterman on ICE, Israel and identifying as a Democrat | The Conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/13/fetterman-on-ice-israel-and-identifying-as-a-democrat-the-conversation-1910882</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-53df-d3b5-addf-f3df3c310000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 09:56:10 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">Fetterman on ICE, Israel and identifying as a Democrat | The Conversation</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6389143915112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/c56c6757-74eb-4779-a63a-f0a9dc929bbf/d27fb1e8-f674-4644-85ae-6bcf7cb167ea/main.mp4" src="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/c56c6757-74eb-4779-a63a-f0a9dc929bbf/60946689-aa37-4319-8fc2-650a657e4d4b/1280x720/match/image.jpg">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another month, another Rahm Emanuel policy proposal. What’s he up to?</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/13/rahm-emanuel-policy-proposals-2028-00779773</link>
      <description>Many of Emanuel’s would-be 2028 rivals are still in office and can point to concrete governing or legislating proposals. He needs another way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5488-d647-addc-ffcfac2d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/93/8a/a938c0364eb296f9852940e396c8/congress-us-china-14477.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Emanuel's plan to create a skilled-trades apprentice program for departing military service members is his fourth policy proposal in almost as many months.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/93/8a/a938c0364eb296f9852940e396c8/congress-us-china-14477.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Adam Wren</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Adam Wren</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rahm Emanuel is embarking on a three-day swing through the crucial swing-state of Michigan this weekend. But he’s not just dropping in to help boost down-ballot Democratic candidates — he’s also visiting some trade schools to unveil yet another policy proposal.</p> 
<p>The moves raise the question: Is he presenting the planks of a larger platform that he can run on for president? Or is he headfaking a run to build buzz and draw interest to his ideas, redirecting the field to where he thinks the party’s intellectual center of gravity should be?</p> 
<p>“I’m going to continue to lay out changes — reforms — that I think address the challenges Americans are facing today. And that is how to get an education that affords and ensures access to the American dream,” Emanuel said in an interview when asked about his motivations.</p> 
<p>His latest plan is aimed at helping military service members transition back to civilian life through the skilled trades.</p> 
<p>The proposal would give 20,000 departing service members a $10,000 tax-free sign-on bonus to enroll in a registered apprenticeship to become electricians, carpenters, plumbers and construction workers over a five-year period. The $200 million plan would be paid for by <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/emmawhitford/2025/07/05/these-26-rich-private-colleges-just-got-a-tax-cut-from-republicans/" target="_blank">eliminating a tax “giveaway”</a> from President Donald Trump's One Big Beautiful Bill Act for private colleges, Emanuel said.</p> 
<p>“We do a signing bonus of $50,000 to go into ICE and become a lawless mob, yet we have people that have the potential to be a carpenter, electrician, a pipe fitter, an operating engineer, a laborer, and we don't do anything,” said Emanuel.</p> 
<p>His plan is his fourth policy rollout in almost as many months, and months before the midterm election that most Democrats are focused on, as well as years ahead of what could be a crowded 2028 presidential primary. His other proposals include banning children <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/rahm-emanuel-says-u-s-should-follow-australias-youth-social-media-ban-00682185" target="_blank">under 16 from social media</a>; forcing public officials to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/rahm-emanuel-calls-for-mandatory-retirement-age-for-public-officials-including-him-00739398" target="_blank">retire at 75</a>; and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/opinion/the-mississippi-marathon-is-teaching-kids-to-read-765372c4?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqdUSnpWmKtsrM7ci5yEzi1z7JrY-5UPtaaObF99RSOJJhwOCXH9feoKqHqV5Z8%3D&amp;gaa_ts=698df6de&amp;gaa_sig=nirnLL-6GHo6Dgvis4ce3ewj8OkJXSQbzrpZXKReX6YJVqVrgpKt5nku7C-uYbrB80MIYy-BH7xLWQAJerPOuA%3D%3D" target="_blank">boosting literacy</a>. And he has said he is ramping up his 2026<a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook/2026/01/17/the-silver-lining-in-dems-2028-calendar-mess-00735530" target="_blank">travel outside of the coasts</a> to the middle of the country.</p> 
<p>Emanuel’s blizzard of white papers stands in contrast to his potential 2028 foes.</p> 
<p>Many of Emanuel’s would-be rivals are still in office and can point to concrete governing or legislating proposals. Others eyeing a run who are back in private life have sought different paths, like former Democratic nominee Kamala Harris, who has been traveling and promoting her book, and former Transportation Secretary Pete Buttigeig, who recently held a Wisconsin town hall and has been making the rounds on the podcast circuit.</p> 
<p>But Emanuel, the former U.S. ambassador to Japan, Chicago mayor, White House chief of staff and congressman, doesn’t currently have an official day job to leverage to execute policy changes or get himself noticed. He’s instead spent more time on cable TV and podcasts while developing what amounts to an education policy vision.</p> 
<p>“There are some people that want to emphasize the resistance to Donald Trump, and there's a lot to resist. I am about fighting for America as much as about fighting Donald Trump,” Emanuel said.</p> 
<p>He cited several recent moments that have shaped his thinking, including a warning from Michigan-based Ford CEO Jim Farley, who has issued a warning that the U.S. faces a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l94U2aQ5cPg&amp;t=1428s" target="_blank">one-million jobs shortage</a> of skilled workers. He also mentioned a private dinner with Dario Amodei, the CEO of the fast-growing AI startup Anthropic. “No AI can destroy these jobs,” Emanuel told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>At one point in explaining his belief in the “power of ideas” to shape politics, Emanuel seemed to suggest the idea of <i>running </i>before catching himself.</p> 
<p>“If you're going to <i>r— </i>think about public life," he said, redirecting his sentence midstream, “you got to answer these challenges.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists on the week in politics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2026/02/13/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00779548</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's an offering of the best of this week's crop, picked fresh off the Toonosphere. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-53ef-d3b5-addf-f3efbe910000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump continues to lash out at ‘RINO’ GOP Gov. Kevin Stitt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/trump-attack-kevin-stitt-00778506</link>
      <description>The Oklahoma governor has found himself in a protracted dispute with the president over an upcoming event at the White House.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-530c-d0f8-adde-fb5e7f4c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 14:10:30 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/33/89/ad0638fa4a2386df248accb0a775/gettyimages-2151959536.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Brandon Bell/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Oklahoma Gov. Kevin Stitt speaks at a press conference in Barnsdall, Oklahoma, on May 7, 2024. The Republican has drawn Trump's ire over an upcoming meeting of the National Governors Association.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/33/89/ad0638fa4a2386df248accb0a775/gettyimages-2151959536.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Thursday continued to personally attack Oklahoma Gov. Kevin Stitt over a debacle regarding the upcoming annual governors’ weekend in Washington.</p> 
<p>"We will soon have a Governor in Oklahoma who knows how to accurately write a Press Release to the Public, in this case, to state that I invited, not happily, almost all Democrat Governors to the Governor’s Dinner at the White House,” Trump wrote in a Thursday Truth Social post. “Stitt, a wiseguy, knew this, but tried to get some cheap publicity by stating otherwise.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s latest criticism against the Republican comes after Stitt, who serves as chair of the National Governors Association, became embroiled in a back-and-forth over whether Democrats would be invited to the routinely bipartisan governors event. Stitt at one point announced that a bipartisan business meeting with the president would be removed from the NGA’s agenda for the weekend because the White House said <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/white-house-excluding-dems-from-annual-governors-meeting-00769972?fbclid=IwY2xjawP43G5leHRuA2FlbQIxMQBzcnRjBmFwcF9pZAwzNTA2ODU1MzE3MjgAAR45yeVqafX9siEimmvpBx22f673Z5JSoUS9uDHkPWdJiGf9EAiripGjYlKWrQ_aem_h4SdFKk3cIEkWOhmGTEYcA" target="_blank">Democrats would be excluded from the event</a>.</p> 
<p>After a conversation with Trump, Stitt informed governors on Wednesday that all governors would be invited to the meeting, attributing the dispute to a “misunderstanding in scheduling,” according to a letter viewed by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>But that wasn’t enough to salve the president’s displeasure: In a Wednesday afternoon social media post — after Democrats had begun receiving invitations to the meeting — Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/trump-democratic-governors-nga-dispute-00777186" target="_blank">took to Truth Social</a> to lament that “as usual with him, Stitt got it WRONG!”</p> 
<p>All governors were welcome at the event, Trump wrote, except two Democrats: Colorado Gov. Jared Polis and Maryland Gov. Wes Moore — the latter of whom had already received a formal invitation to the meeting at the time of the post, according to a person familiar with the matter.</p> 
<p>In the Thursday morning post, Trump took credit for Stitt’s victory in his last race for governor, writing that the Republican “was massively behind his Opponent in his previous Election for Governor” and “called me to ask for help.”</p> 
<p>Trump added: “I Endorsed him (Barely!), and he won his Race,” but the president eagerly anticipated the arrival of the governor’s successor. Stitt is term-limited and cannot seek another term when his current one expires in 2027.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Stitt’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment, and a spokesperson for the NGA declined to comment on the post.</p> 
<p>Stitt’s position atop the NGA has put him at odds with the president on at least one other occasion, when the Oklahoma Republican <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/09/kevin-stitt-republican-governor-national-guard-00600305" target="_blank">broke with his party</a> to criticize the administration’s cross-state National Guard deployments last year.</p> 
<p>The dispute regarding the upcoming NGA weekend has reignited tensions within the association, with 18 Democratic governors <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/democratic-governors-trump-meeting-00774814" target="_blank">vowing to boycott a bipartisan dinner</a> over the White House’s handling of the invitations.</p> 
<p>With regard to the event, Trump wrote Thursday: “I’ll see whoever shows up at the White House, the fewer the better!”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Virginia’s top court might decide Democrats’ gerrymandering fate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/how-virginias-top-court-might-decide-democrats-gerrymandering-fate-00777364</link>
      <description>The state Supreme Court is likely to determine the fate of redistricting in Virginia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4ef1-d0f8-adde-fefbdb310001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 10:26:27 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/47/56/9a926dcc4fb5b3c128f22a6300d0/spanberger-state-of-commonwealth-01112.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Steve Helber/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Virginia Gov. Abigail Spanberger (D) has signed legislation setting a special election for April 21 for voters to approve new Congressional maps.&lt;br/&gt;</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/47/56/9a926dcc4fb5b3c128f22a6300d0/spanberger-state-of-commonwealth-01112.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Virginia Democrats are moving forward with plans to gerrymander their way to four more congressional seats — but they need help from the state’s top court.</p> 
<p>After a lower court blocked Democrats’ efforts to amend the state Constitution and redraw federal congressional lines ahead of this fall’s midterm elections, the Virginia Court of Appeals <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/04/virginia-supreme-court-will-hear-redistricting-challenge-00765490" target="_blank">requested the Virginia Supreme Court weigh in</a>.</p> 
<p>That puts the fate of the map — and potentially congressional control after the 2026 midterms — in the hands of a group of justices that observers say can be hard to predict.</p> 
<p>Political and legal experts in Virginia agree the state Supreme Court is not overtly ideological, with many describing it as “small-c conservative,” leaning heavily on tradition and precedent rather than handing down ideologically right-wing rulings. And many observers say the court is wary of wading too heavily into political fights. But this time, it’s unavoidable.</p> 
<p>“It's kind of a state Supreme Court tradition to stay away from political matters whenever they can. They like to leave the legislating to the legislature. So this is going to be a really interesting test of that tradition,” said Carolyn Fiddler of the Democratic Attorneys General Association, who attended William &amp; Mary Law School in Virginia and worked in state politics.</p> 
<p>Virginia is one of only two states where the legislature elects Supreme Court justices. Because the state has had divided control for much of the past quarter century, the balance of the court’s justices were appointed by bipartisan compromise. The court’s current seven members include one justice who was elected when Democrats had sole control of the General Assembly, three when Republicans controlled both chambers and three when control of the legislature was split.</p> 
<p>“I voted for all these people – every one of them — and I don’t think any of them are overly political. And they shouldn’t be,” said Virginia House of Delegates Minority Leader Del. Terry Kilgore (R), who said he thinks the court will rule in his side’s favor. “They just should follow the law. If they do, we win.”</p> 
<p>The question before the Virginia Supreme Court is not if, but <i>when,</i> new maps are allowed to go into effect — and whether they’ll be in place for this year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>Gov. Abigail Spanberger (D) signed legislation scheduling a statewide referendum for April 21 last week, asking voters to grant state lawmakers the power to redraw federal Congressional lines immediately. It came a day after Democratic state lawmakers unveiled proposed maps that aim to tilt the congressional map 10-1, potentially handing Democrats four more House seats and leaving just one Republican in the federal delegation.</p> 
<p>But a wrench was thrown in their plans when a circuit court judge in conservative <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/virginia-redistricting-blocked-court-ruling-00750060?utm_campaign=Market+Bullets:+Starbucks+and+ASML+soar+on+earnings,+Amazon+and+UPS+cut+jobs,+consumer+confidence+plummets+-+20522002" target="_blank">Tazewell County ruled</a> late last month that Virginia Democrats did not follow proper procedure when initiating the constitutional amendment.</p> 
<p>To change the Virginia Constitution is a multi-step process, requiring approval by two separate sessions of the General Assembly with a statewide general election for the House of Delegates taking place in between those sessions.</p> 
<p>Judge Jack Hurley ruled that because early voting was already underway when the General Assembly first passed the amendment last October, it should not count as the first step. If the Virginia Supreme Court agrees, the earliest the state could enact new maps is after the next legislative election in 2027 — a blow to Democrats’ hopes of winning back the House this fall.</p> 
<p>It’s a question both sides hope the top court weighs in on – and quickly.</p> 
<p>“If they answer the question that there was not an intervening election, which, that's the big one … then the redistricting is dead,” said former Del. Tim Anderson (R), and who is a practicing attorney. “If they say that there was an intervening election, then the redistricting amendment will go forward.”</p> 
<p>The next opening on the court's docket for a new case is March 2, a tight timeline since that's the same week early voting is scheduled to begin.</p> 
<p>Jay O’Keeffe is a left-leaning appellate attorney based in Roanoke who has argued before the top court. He said it is not uncommon for the justices’ opinions to reference Sir William Blackstone’s “Commentaries on the Laws of England,” the 18th century treatise often cited by those who interpret the law through an originalist, conservative-leaning reading of the law.</p> 
<p>“The justices I've dealt with don't seem to see themselves as political actors,”O’Keeffe said. “But you could imagine a more progressive court … approaching the whole job of judging in a different way.”</p> 
<p>The question both Democrats and Republicans hope the Virginia Supreme Court will answer is whether the April referendum vote can proceed.</p> 
<p>“In matters like this, the Supreme Court is going to try to call it right down the middle, and not on a political basis,” said Steve Emmert, a retired appellate lawyer. “What the parties need now is certainty, and they need it soon.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A tech group is launching a new effort to keep Democrats from falling behind on AI</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/democrats-ai-tech-campaigns-lab-00777286</link>
      <description>Tech for Campaigns plans to partner with Democratic groups to test what works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4ee4-d647-addc-efe728a10001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/fe/15/ab955d3f401aa95abf78dcd418df/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2191540119">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Kirill Kudryavtsev/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tech for Campaigns worries Democrats aren't doing enough to adapt to how AI is shifting the campaigning landscape.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fe/15/ab955d3f401aa95abf78dcd418df/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2191540119" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Voters are already asking artificial intelligence chatbots about candidates, but campaigns don’t yet know what those large language models might say about them or how to shape those answers — one of many AI-fueled campaign challenges a new Democratic-aligned tech group is hoping to solve.</p> 
<p>Tech for Campaigns, a political nonprofit focused on helping Democrats adopt better data and digital marketing techniques, is launching a new initiative called <a href="https://www.techforcampaigns.org/the-lab" target="_blank">The Lab</a>, aiming to conduct experiments on how Democrats can use AI to win. The group says it is prepared to spend millions partnering with Democratic outside groups in key states and battleground races, with the hopes of helping the party make progress in an area they say it has so far neglected.</p> 
<p>“Democrats have shown … they're not willing to try new things. They wait too long and often are at a disadvantage,” said Jessica Alter, board chair at Tech for Campaigns. “With how fast AI is moving, that disadvantage will compound and be very dangerous.”</p> 
<p>Campaigns across the political spectrum are grappling with how to take advantage of the rapidly evolving technology. Major Republican groups have <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/digital-future-daily/2025/10/22/the-partisan-ai-wars-are-looking-unequal-00618161" target="_blank">embraced AI-generated content for ads</a> more than their Democratic counterparts in the past year, although some Democratic campaigns have used AI imagery. AI-generated ads <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/digital-future-daily/2025/11/03/the-case-for-campaign-ai-00633713" target="_blank">tend to be less expensive</a> for campaigns, but strategists are still figuring out how voters feel about them — Rep. Jasmine Crockett’s Senate campaign <a href="https://www.chron.com/politics/article/jasmine-crocklett-super-bowl-ad-21343112.php?taid=698a34ae81a3e3000191b2c0&amp;utm_campaign=trueanthem%2B3985&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter" target="_blank">came under fire this week</a> amid online accusations that her latest ad featured an AI-generated crowd image, although her campaign said it “was created through hundreds of hours of real craft and collaboration between creatives and union labor” without commenting on whether AI was also used.</p> 
<p>And ads are just one piece of the AI campaign blitz. Groups have rolled out AI initiatives on everything from writing fundraising emails to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/american-bridge-opposition-research-ai-00747243?E+-+Content+-+Newsletter=&amp;_hsenc=p2ANqtz-_5zH6v1Tutv5raXsznCLcK08NsMs_2Qm-y8tL-O95gL4KqvxEMp_kP8Ik2e6V67cf8gCLBu_Mj1Mir4XbQf-vTw1bXNO76gmuRuDRDaKMvmUdYJ8E&amp;_hsmi=402435865" target="_blank">searching for opposition research</a>.</p> 
<p>Tech for Campaigns wants to go beyond those uses. Its plan is to partner with outside groups in key races to fund experiments on different uses of AI. Modeled after a Silicon Valley-style startup accelerator, the group plans to pair campaign groups with tech executives and commercial experts from companies including Netflix and Y Combinator..</p> 
<p>Each experiment is expected to take between two weeks and two months and cost between $50,000 and $150,000. Tech for Campaigns is inviting organizations to apply, and is hoping to conduct around 20 experiments this year. The results will be shared among Democrats widely, with the goal of more campaigns replicating tactics that work and avoiding those that don’t.</p> 
<p>Among the challenges the group hopes to tackle: Shaping how candidates show up in output from large language models such as ChatGPT, a practice known as answer engine optimization. Outside researchers have found that <a href="https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2025/12/ai-chatbots-can-effectively-sway-voters-either-direction" target="_blank">AI chatbots can be effective at political persuasion</a>, with voters shifting their opinions on candidates or issues after a short conversation.</p> 
<p>Alter said campaigns need to ensure they are well-represented in chatbot results about them, lest the chatbot basing their response more on an opponent’s research and messaging. While major companies are prioritizing shaping chatbots’ response, she said, campaigns so far have been more hesitant to work on it.</p> 
<p>The group also hopes to study whether AI tools can help with personalized communication and how Democrats can make better use of platforms, such as Reddit, where the party has generally had less of a presence.</p> 
<p>Alter said Republicans have shown an advantage in recent years when it comes to adopting new technologies, from <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/04/democrats-digital-ads-report-tech-for-campaigns-00383869" target="_blank">year-round digital advertising</a> to podcasts. The new initiative aims to make sure that GOP advantage does not extend to AI too.</p> 
<p>“It’s the most powerful technological advancement of our time,” Alter said. “So I don’t think they're gonna eschew it.”</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats are cashing in after DOJ failure to indict them</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/the-doj-failed-to-indict-them-now-theyre-cashing-their-checks-00777562</link>
      <description>Trump wanted to take six Democrats down for telling servicemembers to ignore illegal orders. He might’ve made them more influential instead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4f6d-d3b5-addf-efedbbc90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 21:41:08 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/10/09/75cb5f834cd893e3a2cac26f3fae/congress-video-investigation-81415.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Elissa Slotkin, D-Mich., and Sen. Mark Kelly, D-Ariz., speak during a news conference at Capitol Hill, Wednesday, Feb. 11, 2026, in Washington. (AP Photo/Jose Luis Magana)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/10/09/75cb5f834cd893e3a2cac26f3fae/congress-video-investigation-81415.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez and Erin Doherty</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez and Erin Doherty</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The six Democrats who urged military servicemembers in a video not to comply with illegal orders notched a significant legal win when federal prosecutors <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/lawmakers-military-orders-grand-jury-indictment-00775504" target="_blank"><u>failed to criminally indict them</u></a>. Now they’re looking to gain political momentum and build their campaign war chests.</p> 
<p>“We are not done,” said Pennsylvania Rep. Chrissy Houlahan at a press conference alongside fellow House members.</p> 
<p>“We will continue to push back. The tide is turning and accountability is coming,” Colorado Rep. Jason Crow said in a <a href="https://x.com/RepJasonCrow/status/2021420988727251111" target="_blank"><u>video posted to social media</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Michigan Sen. Elissa Slotkin said in a fundraising email: “They tried to indict me.”</p> 
<p>The group of Democrats, including two senators and four House members with backgrounds in national security, came out swinging against President Donald Trump and the Justice Department Wednesday for what they said was an abuse of power and a threat against all Americans’ right to freedom of speech. In addition to a flurry of social media posts and two afternoon press conferences, several have been making the cable news rounds and scheduled appearances on high-profile late night TV shows — signs that they see political opportunity in Trump’s attacks and are hoping to bottle that clout.</p> 
<p>"Democrats have limited power at the federal level right now and need to leverage every opportunity to capitalize on Trump's overreach and lawlessness to raise the necessary funds to ensure we have a balance of power at the end of the midterms,” said Democratic strategist Adrienne Elrod. “It takes resources to get our message out, hold Trump to account, and win back seats, and I'm glad these members are seizing on this moment and fighting back.”</p> 
<p>As Democrats sharpen their attacks against Trump heading into the midterms, his Justice Department’s unprecedented attempt to prosecute the Democratic lawmakers — most of whom represent crucial battleground states like Michigan, Arizona, and Pennsylvania — has inadvertently elevated their profiles. And the Trump administration, by failing to secure an indictment after months of public sparring with the Democrats and threats from the president, has bolstered their credibility as bare-knuckle fighters who can take on Trump and win.</p> 
<p>In this attention-driven political economy, Trump has given a valuable boost to a group of Democrats that includes some with an eye toward future leadership positions in the party – including for Slotkin and Sen. Mark Kelly of Arizona, who are often discussed as potential future presidential candidates.</p> 
<p>“Trump has elevated them by his baseless attacks and his attempt to weaponize the judicial system against them that has flopped so hard,” said Democratic strategist Ian Russell. “That certainly has given them a platform – an even larger platform – as leaders who are focused on keeping our country safe, serving those who serve us, and so forth.”</p> 
<p>The six members of Congress released a video on social media late last year urging military servicemembers to ignore illegal orders amid questions about the legality of the Trump administration’s strikes on alleged drug boats from Latin America. That quickly drew Trump’s ire and prompted the launch of an investigation into the group that they lambasted as politically motivated.</p> 
<p>The Department of Justice’s failure to indict the Democrats gave them a new opportunity to draw attention.</p> 
<p>“Today wasn’t just an embarrassing day for the Administration. It was another sad day for our country,” Slotkin <a href="https://x.com/SenatorSlotkin/status/2021401432235155834?s=20" target="_blank"><u>posted</u></a> on X Tuesday night, as the first reports circulated that a grand jury had rejected the attempt to indict her and five Democratic colleagues.</p> 
<p>Slotkin has become one of the party’s most prominent voices as it seeks to chart a path out of the political wilderness. Seizing on the new political attention — which can be hard to come by in a Republican-controlled Washington — she sent a fundraising appeal the next morning, held a press conference, went on TV and sent a barrage of posts on X.</p> 
<p>“The investigations kept coming when we were quiet. So, if it's going to be bad when you're quiet, you might as well go on offense and have this conversation publicly,” Slotkin said in an interview on MS Now.</p> 
<p>The strategy reflects a broader dynamic for the Democratic Party: Trump’s actions often serve as their best fundraising tool. A <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/political-donations-trump-fundraising-00774862?utm_medium=bluesky&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank"><u>POLITICO analysis of ActBlue data</u></a> this week found that many of the party’s largest online fundraising spikes last year came after a Democrat stood up to — or was attacked by — Trump.</p> 
<p>“Trump elevating them is the kind of thing that makes Democratic donors, strategists, activists, go, ‘Ah, I like what I see,’” said Russell, the Democratic strategist.</p> 
<p>That dynamic has proven especially true for Kelly, who is also in a protracted public battle with Secretary of Defense Pete Hegseth over the video. Hegseth initiated a review of Kelly’s public comments that <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/12/congress/mark-kelly-pete-hegseth-lawsuit-00722382" target="_blank"><u>could demote the Navy captain’s rank and reduce his retirement pay</u></a>. Kelly has sued to halt the review.</p> 
<p>Kelly has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/23/mark-kelly-fundraising-midterms-00743357" target="_blank"><u>emerged as a top Democratic fundraiser</u></a>, the POLITICO analysis found, dominating online fundraising for weeks after the Pentagon announced the investigation even though he’s not up for reelection this year.</p> 
<p>Shortly before news broke Tuesday night that a grand jury had declined to charge the Democrats, the Arizona senator blasted out another fundraising appeal that nodded to his legal proceedings. “What we need from this team, right now, is the peace of mind that Mark has all the resources he’ll need to stay the course,” said <a href="https://politicalemails.org/messages/2128290" target="_blank"><u>one fundraising email signed by “Team Kelly”</u></a> on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>At least two of the House Democrats investigated by the Justice Department sent similar pleas for cash in recent weeks. Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) – who serves as one of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee’s recruitment co-chairs – <a href="https://politicalemails.org/messages/2124464" target="_blank"><u>asked supporters for $10 </u></a>after detailing the federal inquiry opened into the video, and Rep. Chris Deluzio (D-Pa.) made clear <a href="https://politicalemails.org/messages/2123735" target="_blank"><u>in his own pitch</u></a> that he would not “be intimidated by any harassment campaign.”</p> 
<p>In addition to fundraising appeals and appearances on cable news shows, the House members — which also includes Maggie Goodlander of New Hampshire — presented a unified front at a Wednesday press conference, casting the effort as political retribution.</p> 
<p>“This was about Donald Trump trying to send a message, a message that if you dare step out of line, if you dare dissent and speak up and push back against his agenda, that you will be crushed,” Crow, the Colorado Democrat, said at the press conference.</p> 
<p>Longtime Democratic strategist Jesse Ferguson said the failed indictments — and broader message of retribution — gives lawmakers in his party a potent political argument: Democrats were right when they warned that Trump was going to use the justice system for his personal retribution.</p> 
<p>“He proved they're not the boy who cried wolf,” he said. “They're the meteorologist who predicted the hurricane.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The POLITICO Poll - 2026 February - U.S. Alliance</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-4ef3-d647-addc-eff72c6a0000</link>
      <description>The POLITICO Poll, conducted Feb. 6-Feb. 9, surveying respondents' views of the United States as a partner and ally on the global stage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4ef3-d647-addc-eff72c6a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 18:06:50 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump is Pushing Big Tech on Data Center Energy Costs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/11/trump-is-pushing-big-tech-on-data-center-energy-costs-1908352</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4a98-de8a-a1fc-fbd80c7b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">Trump is Pushing Big Tech on Data Center Energy Costs</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6389060883112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/85ae466b-aa37-469b-bc1d-97dea322291f/5cd30f68-9d5f-4e7d-908f-319f7ae0d307/main.mp4" src="16/c8/b057c148458ca1289b377f96a809/thumbnail-horizontal-w-title-1.png">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democratic governors pledge to boycott White House events after a Trump snub</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/democratic-governors-trump-meeting-00774814</link>
      <description>Press secretary Karoline Leavitt said the president enjoys discretion over whom to invite to events at the White House.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-497d-d647-addc-ebff108a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 16:53:24 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/34/85/eb2f23e94cc2b3abb8e4169e5dda/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2260412462">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Saul Loeb/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt defended President Donald Trump's decision to exclude Democrats from the historically bipartisan event.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/34/85/eb2f23e94cc2b3abb8e4169e5dda/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2260412462" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most of the nation’s Democratic governors pledged to not attend events hosted by the White House later this month, after President Donald Trump snubbed some state executives amid his ongoing feud with blue states.</p> 
<p>POLITICO <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/white-house-excluding-dems-from-annual-governors-meeting-00769972" target="_blank">reported last week</a> that the White House decided to invite only Republicans to a meeting between the president and governors that was timed to the National Governors Association’s annual gathering — a break from its bipartisan past. And while a dinner celebrating governors of both parties was still planned, some Democrats — including Wes Moore of Maryland and Jared Polis of Colorado — confirmed they did not receive an invitation.</p> 
<p>White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Tuesday that while the White House is the people’s house, “it's also the president's home, and so he can invite whomever he wants to dinners and events here at the White House.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s decision not to invite Moore — the association’s vice chair — and Polis sparked backlash from Democrats, with 18 sitting governors announcing that they would boycott the dinner.</p> 
<p>“If the reports are true that not all governors are invited to these events, which have historically been productive and bipartisan opportunities for collaboration, we will not be attending the White House dinner this year,” the Democratic governors wrote in a joint statement Tuesday. “Democratic governors remain united and will never stop fighting to protect and make life better for people in our states.”</p> 
<p>Moore also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/08/wes-moore-race-governors-trump-00770586" target="_blank">suggested Sunday</a> that his race may have played a role in the White House’s decision not to invite him to the event.</p> 
<p>“It’s not lost on me that I’m the only Black governor in this country, and I find that to be particularly painful, considering the fact that the president is trying to exclude me from an organization that not only my peers have asked me to help to lead, but then also a place where I know I belong in,” he said in an interview with CNN’s “State of the Union.”</p> 
<p>POLITICO previously reported that the NGA decided not to sponsor the planned meeting between Trump and the governors once it became clear only Republicans would be invited, with the organization writing in an email to people involved in planning that “no NGA resources will be used to support transportation for this activity.”</p> 
<p>Brandon Tatum, the CEO of the NGA, said in a statement last week that the group was “disappointed in the administration’s decision to make it a partisan occasion this year.”</p> 
<p>At last year’s annual meeting between Trump and the governors, the president <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/21/dem-governor-trump-court-022015" target="_blank">got into an argument</a> with Maine Gov. Janet Mills over his administration’s moves to restrict transgender athletes’ participation in school sports, with Trump ultimately threatening to pull funding and Mills promising to sue.</p> 
<p>The NGA has undergone considerable turmoil in the last year, with Democratic governors raising alarm about the association’s unwillingness to more vocally criticize the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>California Gov. Gavin Newsom and Illinois Gov. JB Pritzker <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/06/newsom-pritzker-threaten-to-pull-out-of-national-governors-association-over-trumps-troop-deployments-00595741" target="_blank">threatened to withdraw</a> from the group over Trump’s decision to deploy other states’ National Guard troops to their states.</p> 
<p>Oklahoma Gov. Kevin Stitt, the group’s Republican chair, also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/09/kevin-stitt-republican-governor-national-guard-00600305" target="_blank">criticized the administration’s National Guard deployments</a>, telling The New York Times in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/09/us/politics/oklahoma-governor-national-guard.html?smid=nytcore-ios-share&amp;amp;referringSource=articleShare" target="_blank">an October interview</a> that he worried the president was undermining states’ rights.</p> 
<p>In a letter sent Monday by Stitt to other governors and <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-kevin-stitt-governors-meeting-washington-ee4e696534082638795e1804d71f4966" target="_blank">obtained by The Associated Press</a>, he urged members to unite together, writing “the solution is not to respond in kind, but to rise above and to remain focused on our shared duty to the people we serve.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/02/06/us/politics/trump-republican-governors-white-house.html" target="_blank">The New York Times also first reported</a> last week that some Democratic governors weren’t invited to the dinner.</p> 
<p>“The President has the discretion to invite whomever he wants to the White House, and he welcomes all those who received an invitation to come, and if they don't want to, that's their loss,” Leavitt said of the dinner on Tuesday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Epstein files are creating headaches for the Sununus and Shaheens in New Hampshire</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/the-epstein-files-are-creating-headaches-for-new-hampshires-most-powerful-political-dynasties-00772857</link>
      <description>The founder of Segway has longstanding ties with the Sununu and Shaheen families — and, we now know, Jeffrey Epstein.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4541-d0f8-adde-ff5b30910000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 11:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/04/9d/0cdc67a347859325863da7ca084f/ninth-breakthrough-prize-awards-38955.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Dean Kamen arrives at the ninth Breakthrough Prize Awards on Saturday, April 15, 2023, at The Academy Museum of Motion Pictures in Los Angeles. (Photo by Jordan Strauss/Invision/AP)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/04/9d/0cdc67a347859325863da7ca084f/ninth-breakthrough-prize-awards-38955.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A New Hampshire magnate with ties to power players in both parties has appeared in successive batches of the Epstein files, roiling politics in his home state and threatening its two most influential political dynasties.</p> 
<p>Documents recently released by the Department of Justice suggest that entrepreneur Dean Kamen, the inventor of the Segway and other devices, <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2010/EFTA02142810.pdf" target="_blank"><u>kept in contact</u></a> with Jeffrey Epstein <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%209/EFTA00664167.pdf" target="_blank"><u>long after Epstein pleaded guilty</u></a> to soliciting prostitution from a minor in 2008, with emails indicating he visited the disgraced financier’s Caribbean island in 2013. Kamen has not been accused of wrongdoing and did not respond to requests for comment through his companies Monday.</p> 
<p>The recently released files indicate a closer relationship between the two than was previously known. The disclosures have prompted Kamen’s organizations to launch investigations into their ties. And the situation has ratcheted up scrutiny of the New Hampshire politicians who have worked with him, received <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/receipts/individual-contributions/?contributor_name=kamen%2C+dean" target="_blank"><u>campaign contributions</u></a> from him or helped his organizations secure <a href="https://www.nhpr.org/nh-news/2024-07-03/armi-manchester-lands-another-44m-in-federal-funds-as-part-of-tech-hubs-program" target="_blank"><u>tens of millions</u></a> in federal funds.</p> 
<p>That includes members of the Shaheen and Sununu families, the best-known and most powerful clans in the state’s Democratic and Republican parties. Both have scions running for Congress this year: House candidate Stefany Shaheen, the daughter of retiring Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.), and former Sen. John E. Sununu (R-N.H.), the son of a former governor, who is seeking to return to the Senate.</p> 
<p>They now face Epstein-fueled attacks from their lower-polling rivals.</p> 
<p>“Anywhere Epstein pops up these days, it’ll become a campaign issue,” said Ryan Williams, a GOP strategist who has worked with Sununu and his father. “And there are certainly politicians who have worked with Kamen in New Hampshire, taken his money and associated with him. And those who did will have to answer for it.”</p> 
<p>Kamen is a New Hampshire institution and local celebrity — often described as a quirky one — in a state that has few big-name figures but exerts a powerful hold on the presidential nominating process. The pioneering inventor and entrepreneur who developed the first portable insulin pump and a wheelchair that can climb stairs, Kamen is also widely credited for driving the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/14/realestate/commercial/commercial-real-estate-manchester-millyard.html#:~:text=%E2%80%9CThe%20millyard%20is%20going%20to,the%20University%20of%20New%20Hampshire." target="_blank"><u>transformation of Manchester’s old mill district into a technological and health care hub</u></a>. He was lauded as a “hero” for <a href="https://www.unionleader.com/news/health/coronavirus/massive-shipment-of-ppe-arrives-courtesy-of-nh-dean-kamen/article_4aa969e8-581d-562c-b3c9-a0600f90fce8.html" target="_blank"><u>helping secure 91,000 pounds of protective equipment</u></a> for first responders and health care workers at the height of the Covid-19 pandemic when such resources were scarce.</p> 
<p>Kamen has donated roughly $90,000 to federal candidates and campaign committees on both sides of the aisle over the past four decades, according to federal campaign finance filings. That includes over $7,000 apiece to Sununu, Sen. Shaheen and Kelly Ayotte, the former senator who’s up for reelection as governor this year. Kamen has not made any federal campaign contributions this election cycle, per federal reports.</p> 
<p>He’s hosted a raft of high-profile politicians at his businesses and his Bedford home over the years, from Ayotte to then-President <a href="https://www.csmonitor.com/2007/0918/p13s01-bogn.html" target="_blank"><u>George W. Bush</u></a>. He traveled to Dubai with Sununu’s younger brother, then-Gov. Chris Sununu, in 2019 during a <a href="https://www.unionleader.com/news/politics/sununu-recounts-his-days-in-dubai/article_7ffc3e50-b78a-5457-9724-546d2f3513f3.html" target="_blank"><u>trip in which the two attended the World Government Summit</u></a>. Chris Sununu, through Airlines for America, the lobbying firm he now leads, did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Those ties, once promoted in press releases and splashed across social media, have turned into a political liability after successive document drops showed deeper connections between Kamen and Epstein.</p> 
<p>Photos <a href="https://www.nepm.org/2025-12-22/dean-kamen-epstein-segway-photo-files-nh" target="_blank"><u>released in December</u></a> show Kamen socializing with Epstein in a tropical location and riding a Segway with Ghislaine Maxwell, the Epstein associate who was convicted of sex trafficking in 2021. Documents released on Jan. 30 showed Kamen <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2010/EFTA01796649.pdf" target="_blank"><u>made plans</u></a> to <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2010/EFTA02021195.pdf" target="_blank"><u>visit</u></a> Epstein’s Caribbean island in 2013. At the time, <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%209/EFTA00392548.pdf" target="_blank"><u>assistants sent emails discussing</u></a> “which flight Dean prefers the girls to be on.” Days later, <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2010/EFTA01785295.pdf" target="_blank"><u>he wrote to Epstein</u></a>: “thank you for hosting an incredible visit to [sic] a magical place. It really is almost unbelievable.”</p> 
<p>Kamen did not respond to questions from POLITICO about his association with Epstein, including whether he visited Little Saint James. He previously <a href="https://www.wmur.com/article/dean-kamen-on-leave-from-first-amid-review-into-epstein-involvement/70213104" target="_blank"><u>described having “limited interactions” with Epstein</u></a> in statements to other media outlets and has <a href="https://www.wmur.com/article/dean-kamen-jeffrey-epstein-photo-121225/69714045" target="_blank">denied knowledge of his “horrific actions”</a> beyond what he learned from news reports. He told <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2026/02/05/metro/nh-armi-dean-kamen-epstein-review/" target="_blank"><u>The Boston Globe</u></a> that Epstein had reached out to him about becoming involved in international development projects but after initial meetings, “it became apparent that his only interest was self-promotion” and “I avoided further meetings.” He did not respond to The Globe’s inquiry about the reference to “the girls.” After the latest tranche of documents was released, he <a href="https://www.armiusa.org/news/statement-from-armi-board-of-directors/" target="_blank"><u>recused himself</u></a> from <a href="https://www.wcax.com/2026/02/06/beta-technologies-board-member-appears-newly-released-epstein-files/" target="_blank"><u>board activities</u></a> of at least four companies he’s involved with as they <a href="https://www.firstinspires.org/about/press-room/a-statement-from-first-board-chair-laurie-leshin" target="_blank"><u>engage outside law firms</u></a> to conduct <a href="https://www.sequelmedtech.com/news" target="_blank"><u>independent investigations</u></a> into the disclosures.</p> 
<p>Williams, the Republican strategist, said “the Epstein episode is the first real blemish that’s marked his reputation in the state, and it’s an extremely hot issue right now.”</p> 
<p><b>EPSTEIN FILES AS A CAMPAIGN CUDGEL</b></p> 
<p>Stefany Shaheen, who is running for New Hampshire’s open House seat and served as chief strategy officer for Kamen’s Advanced Regenerative Manufacturing Institute from September 2018 until last month, is facing intensifying scrutiny over her dealings with Kamen. She has posted photos of her with Kamen on social media over the years, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/stefany-shaheen-91a19180_definitely-too-soon-to-add-co-pilot-to-my-activity-6413150118186487808-0s9h/?utm_source=social_share_send&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop_web&amp;rcm=ACoAAAxanxMBraY7XdtdOsyaKlgkR24SDzgVw-Q" target="_blank"><u>one of the two of them in the cockpit of a plane</u></a> that was uploaded to LinkedIn seven years ago, and another from a <a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DIMlB6px6sv/?igsh=MTFvYXE2M2k2aWI2ag%3D%3D" target="_blank"><u>gala for Type 1 Diabetes research</u></a> last April where she was an honoree. Her campaign said the former was taken during a flight to Washington with others affiliated with ARMI for an American Society Of Mechanical Engineers meeting on June 14, 2018, <a href="https://www.asme.org/topics-resources/society-news/asme-news/hosts-congressional-briefing-highlighting" target="_blank"><u>where Kamen spoke</u></a>.</p> 
<p>She is now facing calls from two of her Democratic primary rivals to publicly <a href="https://indepthnh.org/2026/02/03/stefany-shaheens-dean-kamen-ties-become-a-problem/" target="_blank"><u>condemn Kamen</u></a>. One of them, Christian Urrutia, has also <a href="https://x.com/urrutiafornh/status/2018682284048539705?s=20" target="_blank"><u>accused her of potentially helping Kamen craft his statements</u></a> in response to the files, which she has denied.</p> 
<p>“There’s certainly an element of transparency. I think there is a fundamental question of: Do we want our members of Congress and our senators to have these types of relationships?” said Urrutia, who also asked why Sen. Shaheen did not disclose her daughter’s role at ARMI when <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6986333b0f06cb8bead582f2&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoFwlEKgDAIANAbKURfXWbIdOVgU6Y0un2892R6XIh7byD3Zb6UUm0GhExKgdte1GE4hJWQrWL7jrPUHqVygHP7AYJTGZ4%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=www.appropriations.senate.gov" target="_blank"><u>securing a $1.2 million earmark</u></a> for the company in 2023. A spokesperson for the senator said that her daughter was paid through non-federal funding sources and that her office was advised by Senate Ethics Committee staff that the request for funding for ARMI did not violate ethics rules.</p> 
<p>A Republican running for the seat, state Rep. Brian Cole, has <a href="https://x.com/cole4nh/status/2020291693153579107?s=20" target="_blank"><u>called on the younger Shaheen to drop out</u></a>: “Until Stefany Shaheen provides full and honest answers about her association with Dean Kamen and ARMI, she should end her campaign,” he said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Sununu, who is running to reclaim the Senate seat he lost to Shaheen’s mother in 2008, has faced questions over a possible reference to him <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%209/EFTA00892582.pdf" target="_blank"><u>in a 2010 email</u></a> between Epstein and Boris Nikolic, a former Bill Gates adviser. In the email, Epstein emailed Nikolic that “john sununu, has good stories,” but did not provide any additional details. It’s unclear what he meant or whether he was referring to the senator or his father, former governor and White House chief of staff John H. Sununu.</p> 
<p>The younger Sununu was a director of operations at Teletrol Systems, one of Kamen’s companies, in the 1990s before he was elected to Congress.</p> 
<p>His GOP primary rival, former Sen. Scott Brown, has seized on the email to attack the Sununu family’s “‘insider’ ties” as he attempts to gain traction in a race where the Republican establishment and the president have lined up behind his opponent. Brown <a href="https://nhjournal.com/podcast-scott-brown-is-not-backing-down/" target="_blank"><u>said on a local podcast</u></a> that Sununu “needs to fully explain why” his surname is mentioned in the files. Brown <a href="https://x.com/SenScottBrown/status/2019499395209699644?s=20" target="_blank"><u>added on X</u></a> that voters “shouldn’t have to guess who, or which one of their representatives were associated, or what ‘stories’ are being referenced in federal documents.”</p> 
<p>The Shaheen and Sununu campaigns have sought to dismiss the criticism from their opponents.</p> 
<p>Shaheen said in a statement that she “never advised Dean Kamen on these matters” and that the “extent of my knowledge” about his and Epstein’s relationship is what has been publicly reported. Harrell Kirstein, a spokesperson for her campaign, dismissed the criticism as “desperate political attacks — flat out lies — that ignore basic facts.”</p> 
<p>Both Shaheens said they supported outside investigations of Kamen.</p> 
<p>Sen. Shaheen said in a statement that Kamen “was right to step back” from his organizations, and that it was appropriate for them “to conduct independent reviews to fully understand his connection to Epstein and take any action merited by the findings of those reviews.”</p> 
<p>Stefany Shaheen is the polling leader in the Democratic primary for New Hampshire’s blue-leaning 1st Congressional District, a position operatives in both parties attribute in large part to name recognition. A <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1921&amp;context=survey_center_polls" target="_blank"><u>University of New Hampshire survey from January</u></a> showed her with 33 percent support, and no other candidate with more than 10 percent, with 39 percent of likely primary voters undecided.</p> 
<p>Sununu led Brown by 23 percentage points in the same poll, with 26 percent of likely GOP primary voters undecided. They both trail Democratic Rep. Chris Pappas in hypothetical general-election matchups.</p> 
<p>Mike Schrimpf, a spokesperson for Sununu’s campaign, said in a statement that “John had no knowledge whatsoever of any relationship between Dean Kamen and Epstein” and believes the latter “was a despicable human being.” Neither Sununu or his father “have ever met or communicated in any way with Boris Nikolic, Jeffrey Epstein or Ghislaine Maxwell.”</p> 
<p>He went on to attack Shaheen and Pappas — who, along with other members of the all-Democratic congressional delegation, had touted federal funding for ARMI before the Kamen scandal broke — over their connections to the entrepreneur: “Unlike Chris Pappas who celebrated federal funding for Kamen's ARMI, or Stefany Shaheen who worked for him last week, John never advocated or requested funding for any of Kamen's ventures,” Schrimpf said.</p> 
<p>Gates MacPherson, a spokesperson for Pappas’ campaign, said in a statement that the congressman “believes Dean Kamen’s relationship with Epstein is deeply troubling and must be independently investigated, and all federal contractors and grant awardees should be held to the highest possible standards, including ARMI and FIRST.”</p> 
<p>In the governor’s race, Democrats are preparing to attack Ayotte over Kamen’s past contributions to her campaigns and his appearance in an ad <a href="https://www.wmur.com/article/wmur-first-new-ayotte-ad-shows-her-as-independent-leader-fighting-for-nh/5211839" target="_blank"><u>for her 2016 Senate reelection campaign</u></a>. Ayotte has yet to draw a serious opponent in her bid for a second term. Representatives for the governor did not respond to an email to her official and campaign inboxes seeking comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Wisconsin’s voters are America's most valuable</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/most-competitive-states-2026-elections-00772069</link>
      <description>A new initiative breaks down which zip codes have the most competitive elections in America.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4446-d647-addc-efc7cebf0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b9/02/248c2f3d4ba28259ba817544d188/election-2025-new-jersey-68024.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Matt Rourke/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A "Vote Here" sign indicates a polling place in Cherry Hill, New Jersey, on Oct. 28, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b9/02/248c2f3d4ba28259ba817544d188/election-2025-new-jersey-68024.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Not all Americans’ votes are equal. And some have a way bigger impact than others.</p> 
<p>Every four years, a small handful of swing states are bombarded with advertising, candidate visits and more when the country picks the next president, while a majority of other voters are mostly ignored. But even in the key swing states, some House contests, governor’s races and even legislative districts are far more competitive than others.</p> 
<p>That’s why the nonpartisan nonprofit Power Moves is rolling out a new Voter Impact Index — the details of which were <a href="https://www.powermoves.vote/voter-impact-index-map" target="_blank">shared first with POLITICO</a> — to help people take into account their voting power.</p> 
<p>“We all learned in elementary school and middle school that every vote counts, and a vote is a vote,” said Heather Weston, one of the group’s co-founders. “But we kind of intuit that that's not true. So what we really wanted people to understand is how geography really is connected to the impact of your vote.”</p> 
<p>The project utilizes all of America’s 41,000-plus zip codes to measure how much of an impact a voter can have, something the organization’s co-founders say is unique to their product.</p> 
<p>To get the “Voter Impact” score, which ranges from 0-100, Power Moves has a <a href="https://www.powermoves.vote/our-methodology" target="_blank">complex methodology</a>. But in short, it weighs the competitiveness of recent elections in the zip code for six public offices, ranging from the presidency to legislative races — and the higher the score, the more competitive elections an American has the opportunity to vote in.</p> 
<p>It weights some of those offices as more important than others. For example, the competitiveness of the presidential election, Senate seat and House district in a given zip code each get 25 percent of the score, while governor’s races get 15 percent and state House and Senate seats only get five percent each.</p> 
<p>No individual zip code got either a zero or a 100, based on their methodology. But voters in the Eau Claire, Wisconsin, zip code of 54703 came out on top with a score of 85. And most of Wyoming ties for the lowest score at 14. (Perhaps not coincidentally: The state with the highest statewide average is Wisconsin, and Wyoming is the lowest.)</p> 
<p>With more than 40 million Americans moving each year — and some millions of college students moving to new states — the tool is aimed at helping people really understand where their vote can go the furthest.</p> 
<p>People move for a variety of factors, and Power Moves emphasized that the tool is not supposed to be the only factor people weigh when deciding their new home. But as home-buying and renting tools like Zillow already factor things like walkability and school systems into their own algorithms, they hope voting can crack that list of priorities. Plus, because of the wonky ways district lines are drawn, apartments and houses that are just minutes apart can garner completely different voting scores.</p> 
<p>“We really don’t care what your political stripes are,” said Charles Simon, another co-founder. “We just want to help everybody to understand their vote impact score and give them the opportunity to maximize that score.”</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Georgia Republicans allow RNC to break party neutrality to support Burt Jones</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/rnc-burt-jones-georgia-gov-00772790</link>
      <description>Any move to intervene in Georgia could reshape a crowded race for an open governor’s seat in a premiere battleground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4526-d0f8-adde-ff7e391a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/6f/90/d880288d4ef4bdc9875c357186da/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2178614117">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Kevin Dietsch/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Georgia Lt. Gov. Burt Jones speaks during a campaign rally at the Cobb Energy Performing Arts Centre on Oct. 15, 2024 in Atlanta.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/6f/90/d880288d4ef4bdc9875c357186da/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2178614117" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Top state Republicans in Georgia have quietly opened the door for the Republican National Committee to support Lt. Gov. Burt Jones in the state’s hotly contested primary for governor.</p> 
<p>The RNC normally maintains strict neutrality in party primaries to let voters — not party leaders — choose its nominee. Any move to intervene in Georgia, however, could dramatically reshape a crowded race for an open governor's seat in a premiere battleground state. It could give Jones, President Donald Trump’s handpicked choice, a boost in a field that includes Secretary of State Brad Raffensperger, a target of Trump’s ire ever since he refused to echo the president’s falsehoods about the 2020 election in his state.</p> 
<p>Georgia’s three RNC members signed letters late last year and early this year waiving the party rule that bars the RNC from intervening in contested primaries, according to three people familiar with the agreement. That move allows the national party to provide financial or operating support to Jones and coordinate with him ahead of the May primary.</p> 
<p>It’s unclear whether the RNC will move to support Jones in the crowded primary now that it’s been cleared to do so. But it was the RNC that first reached out to the Georgia party leaders about waiving the rule, according to a person familiar with the process — a sign the national party has at least considered getting off the sidelines. The RNC did not provide a comment.</p> 
<p>Josh McKoon, the chair of the Georgia Republican Party, said he signed the letter waiving the RNC’s neutrality rule because Jones has Trump's endorsement.</p> 
<p>“It was a no-brainer for me to sign the letter,” McKoon told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“From my perspective, I was going to remove any barriers to working with the RNC from a candidate that the president has clearly signaled as the candidate he wants to be the next governor,” he said.</p> 
<p>Jones has long been a vocal supporter of Trump. He endorsed him for president in 2015, and as a state senator, was among the 16 Republicans who attempted to serve as electors in 2020 and falsely certify Trump’s loss in Georgia as a win. Jones received Trump’s official endorsement in August, and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=1714167236228311" target="_blank">released a video with Jones last week</a> calling him a “friend” who’s “going to make a great, great governor.”</p> 
<p>Limited early public polling shows Jones leading the field, and he maintains a sizable war chest, but the race remains fluid, and a prolonged and expensive primary could complicate Republicans’ general election prospects. RNC support could help Jones fend off rivals and potentially avoid a prolonged primary fight, especially if he can avoid a run-off.</p> 
<p>Last week, health care business owner Rick Jackson injected new uncertainty into the race by launching a surprise gubernatorial bid, pledging to spend $50 million of his own money to support his campaign. He has presented himself as a Trump-aligned political outsider, a message that could cut into Jones’ base.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/2026/02/rick-jacksons-campaign-for-governor-resets-fight-for-maga-base-in-georgia/" target="_blank">Cygnal poll</a> released Monday, after Jackson’s surprise campaign launch, found Jones leading with 22 percent support among likely primary voters. Jackson followed at 16 percent, with Raffensperger at 10 percent and Attorney General Chris Carr at 7 percent.</p> 
<p>To avoid a June run-off, a candidate must secure an outright majority of the vote in the May 19 primary — a high bar in an increasingly crowded field.</p> 
<p>“I can see a path to victory for all four of them right now.” said Jason Shepherd, a former Cobb County GOP chair who is backing Carr. “But Burt Jones’ path to victory just got a lot harder” with Jackson’s entrance.</p> 
<p><a href="https://prod-static.gop.com/media/Rules_Of_The_Republican_Party.pdf" target="_blank">Under RNC rules</a>, the national party is barred from backing candidates in primaries unless the filing deadline has passed and a candidate is running unopposed. That requirement, known as Rule 11, can be waived if all three of a state’s RNC members sign off. Such Rule 11 agreements have been used sparingly in recent cycles.</p> 
<p>State party leaders in North Carolina have green-lit early support for former RNC chair Michael Whatley, another Trump-backed candidate running for the state’s open Senate seat.</p> 
<p>Both Georgia and North Carolina are top priorities for the Republican Party in November. In Georgia, Republicans are looking to retain control of the governor’s mansion in a state that Trump flipped in 2024. The steps taken in both states raise questions about whether the RNC could face pressure to take similar moves in other states’ primaries where Trump decides to take sides, such as in Louisiana, where he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/letlow-senate-cassidy-trump-00736200" target="_blank">endorsed Rep. Julia Letlow</a>in her primary challenge against Sen. Bill Cassidy.</p> 
<p>“We all look very carefully at when [Trump] decides to weigh in a race, because he doesn't always do that,” McKoon said. “I certainly didn't want to be serving as an obstacle to the RNC being able to coordinate with his campaign and provide support.”</p> 
<p><i>Alec Hernández contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-09T16:48:20-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘The worst, ever’: MAGA rages about Bad Bunny’s halftime set</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/09/bad-bunny-show-maga-america-00771503</link>
      <description>For an audience of millions, the Puerto Rican superstar put on the NFL’s first-ever Spanish-led show. Trump and his allies said he didn't represent America.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4384-de8a-a1fc-fbc4f88e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 13:35:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/bc/d7/878d5a3a40c68a8c1a38c4ffe781/super-bowl-football-41559.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark J. Terrill/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Bad Bunny performs during halftime of the NFL Super Bowl 60 football game between the New England Patriots and the Seattle Seahawks on Feb. 8, 2026, in Santa Clara, California.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bc/d7/878d5a3a40c68a8c1a38c4ffe781/super-bowl-football-41559.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Riya Misra and Finya Swai</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Riya Misra and Finya Swai</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump’s MAGA movement furiously denounced Bad Bunny’s Super Bowl LX halftime show, denigrating the Puerto Rican superstar and claiming he does not truly represent America.</p> 
<p>Trump, who previously <a href="https://nypost.com/2026/01/24/us-news/trump-tells-the-post-hes-skipping-the-super-bowl-slams-halftime-performers-bad-bunny-and-green-day/" target="_blank">called Bad Bunny a “terrible choice”</a> to head up the NFL’s largest annual broadcast, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/08/trump-bashes-bad-bunnys-halftime-spectacle-00771021" target="_blank">chimed in with complaints</a> about the show’s first-ever mostly-Spanish performance: “Nobody understands a word this guy is saying,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116038200403048483" target="_blank">he wrote in a lengthy Truth Social post</a>, calling it "one of the worst, EVER!"</p> 
<p>At Levi’s Stadium in Santa Clara, California, Bad Bunny delivered a 13-minute homage to his homeland, weaving through a sugarcane field studded with bodegas and a traditional casita. His show was lauded by fans as a vibrant celebration of Puerto Rican heritage — but Trump and MAGA faithfuls weren’t so convinced.</p> 
<p>Benito Antonio Martínez Ocasio, the Puerto Rican-born singer better known as Bad Bunny, made his Super Bowl debut in 2020 alongside Shakira and Jennifer Lopez. But since the NFL announced him as the Super Bowl headliner in September, he became a focal point for conservative ire — thanks, in part, to his high-profile political activism.</p> 
<p>An <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/08/bad-bunny-super-bowl-immigration-00770475" target="_blank">outspoken critic of the Trump administration’s hard-line</a> immigration crackdown, he declared “ICE out” onstage at last week’s Grammy Awards — where his album "DeBÍ TiRAR MáS FOToS" made history as the first all-Spanish record to snag the show’s coveted album of the year trophy — and left viewers wondering what message he might have for the millions of football fans tuning into his set.</p> 
<p>But Bad Bunny did not directly call out any of the president’s policies or supporters during his Super Bowl show. The only English he spoke during Sunday’s show was him saying, “God bless America,” as he was marching off the field with a procession of Latin and South American flags — led by the U.S.’s flag. He then spiked a football that read: “together, we are America.”</p> 
<p>His show also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/03/30/puerto-rico-electric-grid-blackouts-hurricanes-00257176" target="_blank">referenced the island’s long-struggling power grid</a>.</p> 
<p>In the hours after the performance, MAGA allies took issue with the show’s mostly-Spanish discography and Puerto Rican inspiration.</p> 
<p>“Was a single word of English spoken during the Super Bowl Halftime Show?” Nick Adams, Trump’s pick to become ambassador to Malaysia, <a href="https://x.com/NickAdamsinUSA/status/2020671666020376722?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. “Someone needs to tell Bad Bunny he’s in America. This is an abomination.”</p> 
<p>Far-right influencer Laura Loomer railed against his set in a series of X posts, urging border czar Tom Homan to <a href="https://x.com/LauraLoomer/status/2020672109018481057?s=20" target="_blank">deploy an immigration raid on site</a>.</p> 
<p>“There’s nothing American about any of this,” <a href="https://x.com/LauraLoomer/status/2020678486646534164?s=20" target="_blank">she wrote</a>. “This isn’t White enough for me. Cant even watch a Super Bowl anymore because immigrants have literally ruined everything.”</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, MAGA-friendly influencer Jake Paul <a href="https://x.com/jakepaul/status/2020615566436815275?s=20" target="_blank">urged his X followers to “turn off this halftime,”</a> decrying Bad Bunny as a “fake American citizen performing who publicly hates America.” Paul, who was recently seen with Vice President JD Vance at the Olympics in Milan, received swift blowback online, including from Paul’s own brother, Logan. </p> 
<p>Many, including <a href="https://x.com/AOC/status/2020855353223545156?s=20" target="_blank">Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez</a> (D-N.Y.), pointed out that Puerto Ricans are U.S. citizens — and that Paul himself <a href="https://nypost.com/2026/02/09/sports/jake-paul-clarifies-bad-bunny-fake-citizen-stance/" target="_blank">has been living there since 2021</a>.</p> 
<p>Other figures within the president’s orbit echoed their disapproval. Former FBI Deputy Director Dan Bongino reacted to Bad Bunny’s performance in a <a href="https://rumble.com/v75ijp4-kid-rock-sad-bunny-ep.-2448-02092026.html" target="_blank">podcast episode on Rumble</a> titled “Kid Rock &gt; Sad Bunny,” <a href="https://rumble.com/v75ijp4-kid-rock-sad-bunny-ep.-2448-02092026.html" target="_blank">telling viewers the show “sucked.”</a> Meanwhile, Harmeet Dhillon, assistant attorney general for civil rights, wrote on X that <a href="https://x.com/HarmeetKDhillon/status/2020660639350616256?s=20" target="_blank">she and her family “aren’t watching him.”</a></p> 
<p>Rep. Randy Fine (R-Fla.) called the show “disgusting” and said it violated broadcast standards, <a href="https://x.com/RepFine/status/2020925409043313023?s=20" target="_blank">writing on X</a> that he plans to send a letter to FCC Chair Brendan Carr demanding a review.</p> 
<p>“Had he said these lyrics — and all of the other disgusting and pornographic filth in English on live TV, the broadcast would have been pulled down and the fines would have been enormous,” Fine wrote. "Lock them up."</p> 
<p>Conservatives did rally behind alternative programming. Turning Point USA, the conservative organizing group founded by Charlie Kirk, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/turning-point-usa-super-bowl-halftime-show-00761040" target="_blank">aired a rival halftime show</a> headlined by longtime Trump ally Kid Rock, drawing support from Republican officials including Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth and House Speaker Mike Johnson, who praised the event.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bad Bunny created a cultural phenomenon. Can he spark a political one?</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/08/bad-bunny-super-bowl-immigration-00770475</link>
      <description>The Puerto Rican superstar’s music has brought Latinos together. Democrats are jealous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-3a19-d0f8-adde-fa5b64bd0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/96/a3/87b309a04ee9b5de7f2cf08ccaee/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2260110168">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mike Coppola/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Bad Bunny appears at the Super Bowl LX Pregame &amp;amp; Apple Music Super Bowl LX Halftime Show Press Conference in San Francisco on Thursday, Feb. 5.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/96/a3/87b309a04ee9b5de7f2cf08ccaee/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2260110168" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez and Ali Bianco</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez and Ali Bianco</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The world is watching for Bad Bunny to make a political statement at the Super Bowl. Democrats are watching closely to figure out how to make their own.</p> 
<p>Benito Antonio Martínez Ocasio, the Puerto Rican recording artist known globally by his stage name, has created a pop culture phenomenon that will converge at a historic halftime show performance at the Super Bowl on Sunday when the New England Patriots play the Seattle Seahawks. Though Bad Bunny already made his Super Bowl debut alongside Shakira and Jennifer Lopez back in 2020, this time the spotlight will be on him and his exclusively in-Spanish catalog. And while his invitation triggered a harsh backlash on the right from the president on down, it’s also marking a major inflection point for Hispanic Americans of all backgrounds.</p> 
<p>Sunday may prove to be Bad Bunny’s biggest chance to move the dial.</p> 
<p>There’s an opportunity here, Democrats told POLITICO, to turn Bad Bunny’s cultural phenomenon into a political one, right as the party is mounting its strongest resistance to Trump’s sweeping deportation agenda — and with months to go before the midterms to make amends with Latino voters who have left their tent.</p> 
<p>Former Rep. Luis Gutiérrez (D-Ill.), who is of Puerto Rican descent and whose tenure in the House was marked by his outspokenness for the Latino communities he represented, emphasized that Democrats need to seize this moment to win back Latino support.</p> 
<p>Democrats “do too little to engage the Latino community, and then they wonder why all these Latinos voted for Trump? Because you didn't knock on their doors asking to vote for the Democrat. You failed to message us in so many ways,” he said. “They should embrace it.”</p> 
<p>“It's such a huge watershed moment,” Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez (D-N.Y.) said. “I wouldn't be surprised if he used this as a very unifying moment, but also on very resonant and salient grounds to send a message to people.”</p> 
<p>There’s already signs of what’s on the Latino rapper’s mind.</p> 
<p>“Before I say thanks to God, I’m going to say, ‘ICE out,’” Bad Bunny said last Sunday as he accepted the Grammy for Best Música Urbana Album for his record-smashing “DeBÍ TiRAR MáS FOToS” — just hours before taking home the night’s biggest prize, Album of the Year. “We’re not savage, we’re not animals, we’re not aliens — we are humans, and we are Americans.”</p> 
<p>Bad Bunny isn’t new to political endeavors. But he has long focused primarily on island politics — he’s a big activist for Puerto Rican independence — and has only occasionally weighed in on mainland issues.</p> 
<p>In 2024, shortly after comedian Tony Hinchcliffe infamously disparaged Puerto Rico as a “floating island of garbage” during the pre-show for Trump’s rally at Madison Square Garden, Bad Bunny posted an endorsement of Kamala Harris to his tens of millions of Instagram followers. But he never appeared with Harris on the campaign trail.</p> 
<p>His political trajectory has followed other Latino voters’ in recent months, however. <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/race-and-ethnicity/2025/11/24/majorities-of-latinos-disapprove-of-trump-and-his-policies-on-immigration-economy/" target="_blank">Polls show many Hispanics</a> have been particularly outraged at the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown. And they are highly motivated to vote and could shift left, after consecutive election cycles where Trump made significant inroads with Latinos.</p> 
<p>Americans overall <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/poll-republicans-ice-immigration-deportations-00744668" target="_blank">in recent polling</a> have shown an increasing souring on Trump’s handling of immigration. The two fatal shootings in Minneapolis and the stream of videos of ICE raids online are driving a fierce grassroots opposition that is pushing Democrats to hold the line on the Hill and not cave in negotiations on the DHS funding bill. But Trump's crackdown has been felt most acutely in Latino communities. For many, the <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/five-year-old-boy-detained-by-ice-has-returned-minnesota-lawmaker-says-2026-02-01/" target="_blank">stories of families being detained</a> have fueled a feeling of solidarity across the diaspora.</p> 
<p>“That's bringing people of all kinds together — especially the Latino community, the diaspora of Latino communities, that come from so many different places, so many different subcultures. It's bringing us together in a new vision of latinidad,” said Chicago Alderman Michael Rodriguez, who represents the city’s historically Mexican Little Village community. “Our community is being assaulted right now.”</p> 
<p>During Bad Bunny’s massive world tour last year, the artist did not schedule any shows on the U.S. mainland, in part due to concerns that ICE would target his concerts for immigration enforcement operations. “It’s something that we were talking about and very concerned about,” <a href="https://i-d.co/article/bad-bunny-puerto-rico-residency-issue-375-cover/" target="_blank">he told i-D magazine in a September interview</a>.</p> 
<p>After the rapper was announced as the halftime performer in September, Corey Lewandowski <a href="https://variety.com/2025/music/news/trump-advisor-ice-agents-bad-bunny-super-bowl-halftime-show-1236536667/" target="_blank">said there would be</a> ICE enforcement operations at the Super Bowl — seemingly bringing to life some of the concerns that Martínez Ocasio voiced. Local leaders in the Bay Area have said this week they’ve privately been told no ICE officers will be at the show. DHS has <a href="https://apnews.com/article/super-bowl-bad-bunny-trump-politics-1447163cfa820cbb0c96973c20ccd976" target="_blank">remained more vague publicly</a> about enforcement plans around the game. DHS did not respond to a request for comment on this story.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Republicans this weekend — many of whom in the MAGA universe have referred to Martínez Ocasio as “Woke Bunny” — are holding their own halftime performance to make a statement. Turning Point is counterprogramming Bad Bunny’s performance with a made-for-television “All American Halftime Show” featuring Kid Rock. “I think that that part of the country just felt offended,” said Andrew Kolvert, a spokesperson for Turning Point. “There needs to be a counter voice that says, ‘Hey, you know, we love this country. We love the rule of law, we love our troops, we love law enforcement, we love traditional America.’”</p> 
<p>For Democrats, the question of how to better engage and win in Latino communities has dogged them as the party searches for a way out of the wilderness since their 2024 election losses. Bad Bunny has shown a natural ability to bring those communities together with his music, filling stadiums across the world for multi-night shows.</p> 
<p>“It’s not that easy. We’re 23 countries, we fight each other every day,” said Rep. Delia Ramirez (D-Ill.), who represents the largest Puerto Rican community in the Midwest — and whose city of Chicago was an early target of Trump's increased immigration enforcement efforts. “For Bad Bunny to be able to bring Puerto Ricans, Mexicans, Guatemalans, Dominicans together, and all feel like they’re being heard and that he can represent them, says a lot about who is.”</p> 
<p>As for Martínez Ocasio, he’s keeping mum about what to expect from his performance on Sunday night. “It’s going to be a huge party,” <a href="https://apnews.com/article/bad-bunny-super-bowl-halftime-show-f441549a00166a39309233f689163105" target="_blank">he said at a preview event on Thursday</a>. “I want to bring to the stage, of course, a lot of my culture. But I really don’t, I don’t want to give any spoilers. It’s going to be fun.”</p> 
<p>The cultural solidarity that Bad Bunny’s music has fostered could translate into political unity, Rodriguez, the Chicago alderman, said. And some of his fellow Democrats are ready to build on the moment.</p> 
<p>“There's just no scenario where he is not going to have a message,” Rep. Robert Garcia (D-Calif.) said. “There are moments in history that really move a community and solidify them within a political movement. And I think that's happening right now.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
