<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 15:48:00 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Democrats float DHS changes in shutdown stalemate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/democrats-dhs-minnesota-shutdown-00753256</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-064e-d1ea-a5de-36ced07d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 15:48:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats on Wednesday revealed the DHS restrictions they need in exchange for helping Republicans avert a shutdown Friday night, including the tightening of rules on warrants.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer outlined the asks after a closed-door caucus meeting, telling reporters that Democrats were united around “common sense and necessary policy goals.”</p> 
<p>The list – featuring several demands previously <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">reported by POLITICO</a> — also included a prohibition on agents using masks, mandates for body cameras and IDs and a “uniform code of conduct and accountability,” including requiring independent investigations of incidents like Saturday’s fatal shooting of Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p>“Republicans must work with Democrats to find legislative solutions,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Wednesday’s caucus meeting was the first time Senate Democrats had gathered in person and talked strategy since the killing of Pretti by federal agents in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>The shooting and the initial response by top administration officials have fueled widespread calls for changes to the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement strategy. On Capitol Hill, it has upended the debate over government funding ahead of Friday’s midnight shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>The Senate will vote Thursday on a six-bill package that would fund several departments, including DHS. But Democrats have demanded that Senate Majority Leader John Thune strip out the DHS bill and negotiate new policy changes for immigration agencies. Senators are widely expecting the bill to fail to advance Thursday, which would force them to pivot to a Plan B. </p> 
<p>“There has to be accountability,” Sen. Tina Smith (D-Minn.) said. “This is not like some wish list. This is like really practical, common sense stuff that would actually go a long way towards minimizing the harm that we’re seeing in Minnesota right now.”</p> 
<p>Republicans are loath to strip out the Department of Homeland Security bill because any changes to the funding package would require it to go back to the House, where GOP hardliners are already vowing to throw up roadblocks.</p> 
<p>Though talks have been ongoing between Senate Republicans, Democrats and the White House, Republicans have been waiting for Schumer to outline specifically what Democrats want.</p> 
<p>“There's been overtures and attempts to try to connect on what they want and then see if it's something the administration could accommodate without having to change the language of the bill,” Senate Majority Leader John Thune told reporters.</p> 
<p>But Schumer said the “White House has had no specific, concrete ideas.”</p> 
<p>Without a deal to pass the funding package as is, a partial government shutdown will start Saturday. Privately, Republicans are hoping if there is a partial shutdown that they would be able to negotiate an off-ramp by Monday or early next week.</p> 
<p>Republicans have floated that the administration could take executive actions to address some of Democrats' concerns.</p> 
<p>But Smith dismissed that Wednesday, adding, “If you believe that I’ve got a bridge.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans set to make ‘best and final’ Obamacare offer, Moreno says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/republicans-set-to-make-best-and-final-obamacare-offer-moreno-says-00752843</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-05d1-d452-a99e-6dff53160005</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:16:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>GOP Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> said that Republicans will make their “best and final” offer after weeks of bipartisan talks to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/senate-deal-obamacare-subsidies-00714048" target="_blank">revive lapsed Obamacare subsidies</a>.</p> 
<p>“It’s going to be in the hands of the Democrats very shortly. … Here’s the exact thing that we think is the maximum we can sell our conference,” Moreno told reporters.</p> 
<p>“This would be it,” the Ohioan added. “This is the best and final” offer.</p> 
<p>Moreno is one of the lead GOP negotiators involved in months of talks about a potential two-year revival of the enhanced Obamacare tax credits that lapsed Jan. 1. The senators involved have discussed immediate new restrictions such as an income limit, as well as more sweeping changes kicking in the second year, including expanding the use of health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>Moreno separately told reporters the group is proposing to maintain the status quo on the Hyde amendment, which restricts the use of federal dollars on abortion services.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine), who has been involved with the talks, appeared optimistic about the chances of a deal, telling reporters Wednesday he expected to receive text later in the day. The health care discussions have been largely back-burnered as Congress has spent recent weeks dealing with an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">approaching government shutdown deadline</a>.</p> 
<p>“I think we’re very close,” said King, who caucuses with Democrats. “We have a solid bipartisan group, and hopefully we can move the bill once we get through this budget situation.”</p> 
<p>But others involved in the negotiations have been surprised by Moreno’s comments about the impending release of a bill, noting that Democrats had not seen or signed off on anything yet, according to two people granted anonymity to speak candidly about the talks.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-28T13:43:37-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Rubio digs in on cooperation with Venezuela’s Rodríguez, lack of immediate elections</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/rubio-venezuela-hearing-00752750</link>
      <description>Democrats lashed Rubio for the administration’s lack of transparency about the Jan. 3 operation to capture ousted Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-05b0-dabb-ad9c-3ffdd1260000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:49:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c8/ae/fc02637e4d878ddc67890e35a3fe/unlimiteduse-01-28-2025-rubio-congress-0007-47495.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Secretary of State Marco Rubio testifies before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee on Capitol Hill in Washington, on Jan. 28, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c8/ae/fc02637e4d878ddc67890e35a3fe/unlimiteduse-01-28-2025-rubio-congress-0007-47495.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Secretary of State Marco Rubio defended the Trump administration’s decision to work with the remnants of ousted Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro’s regime on Wednesday, as Democrats raise questions about the timeline for elections and a transition to democracy in the South American petrostate.</p> 
<p>Testifying before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Rubio reiterated previous statements that the ultimate goal in Venezuela is to restore democracy, but emphasized that the country needs to stabilize so that the opposition can actually participate in free and fair elections.</p> 
<p>“You can have elections, you have elections all day, but if the opposition has no access to the media, if opposition candidates are routinely dismissed and unable to be on the ballot because of the government, those aren't free and fair elections,” Rubio said. “That's the end state that we want: a free, fair, prosperous and friendly Venezuela. We're not going to get there in three weeks. It's going to take some time.”</p> 
<p>Rubio has consistently pushed the need for elections in Venezuela, though without giving a timeline. His comments suggest that a ballot could be well into the future. Some others inside the administration have argued that elections aren’t needed, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/trump-demands-venezuela-leader-00711728" target="_blank">as POLITICO has reported</a>.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump’s comments around U.S. access to Venezuela’s vast oil reserves and his praise of acting Venezuelan leader Delcy Rodriguez have raised questions about how much democracy in Venezuela is a priority for the administration.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Rodriguez, long an ally of Maduro who rose up the ranks in Caracas, has in recent days said her country will not take orders from Washington. Her comments have rankled the Venezuelan opposition and their friends in Washington, who already see the longtime regime official as an untrustworthy partner for the United States.</p> 
<p>Rubio’s comments Wednesday make clear the administration’s view that a pragmatic course is necessary to restore democracy in Venezuela. Rubio, who noted he’s meeting later Wednesday with Venezuelan opposition leader Maria Corina Machado, said that the administration does want to see more progress towards stabilizing the country over the next few months.</p> 
<p>But Rubio reiterated that more steps need to be taken, including reopening the U.S. embassy in Caracas.</p> 
<p>“One thing is for me to pick up the phone and talk to Delcy Rodriguez three times a week,” Rubio said. “Another thing is to have someone on the ground on a daily basis that's following these events, is talking to civil society, but also engaging with interim authorities.”</p> 
<p>In the face of sharp questions from Democrats — who’ve argued Rodriguez staying in power reflects an impediment to a transition to democracy — Rubio also insisted that working with Rodriguez is a necessary step.</p> 
<p>“No one here is telling you this is what we want to see in the long term,” Rubio said. “Whether we like it or not, the elements of control in that country — the people with the guns, the people that control the guns and the institutions of government there — are in the hands of this regime.”</p> 
<p>It was the first time the secretary of State and acting national security adviser had spoken to lawmakers in a public hearing since the campaign against Venezuela began months ago. Republicans largely praised the operation and focused questions on the structures to open up access to Venezuela’s oil reserves.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Democrats used that setting to criticize the administration for a lack of transparency around the military operations in Venezuela. Democrats had protested that only Republicans were directly briefed by Rubio in the immediate aftermath of the Jan. 3 operation to capture Maduro — and that all briefings occurred after the operation had begun.</p> 
<p>“Consulting with Congress is not just some high-minded principle, not some abstract thing, not a nice-to-have. It's a got-to have,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151823" data-person-id="151823">Chris Coons</a> (D-Del.).</p> 
<p>Democrats and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.) also raised questions about the timeline for future elections in Venezuela. The administration has not committed to a hard plan to see elections in the South American petrostate, but worries have mounted on both sides of the aisle that a long wait for elections may allow Rodriguez and the remnants of the Maduro regime to entrench their grip on power.</p> 
<p>The secretary of State, who served in the Senate for over a decade before his appointment, received a friendly welcome from Republicans, many of whom took pains to praise the operation and Rubio’s contributions to the administration. Senate Foreign Relations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66832" data-person-id="66832">Jim Risch</a> (R-Idaho) said Americans were “lucky” to have Rubio as secretary of State. Others, meanwhile, focused their questions on efforts to expand U.S. access to Venezuela’s vast oil reserves.</p> 
<p>Still, Rubio faced some tough questioning from his former Republican colleagues. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151828" data-person-id="151828">Rand Paul</a> (R-Ky.), critical of the campaign against Venezuela since the U.S. began striking alleged drug boats off Venezuelan waters, needled the secretary on the legal basis of the operation and whether Congress should have authorized it.</p> 
<p>Rubio responded that the short duration of the actual capture of Maduro, coupled with the fact that Maduro faced federal indictment in U.S. courts and was seen as the illegitimate leader of Venezuela, meant the operation did not reflect an act of war such that it would require congressional authorization.</p> 
<p>That answer did not satisfy Paul.</p> 
<p>“We’re in violation of both the spirit and the law of the constitution by bombing a capital, blockading a country and removing elected officials. And we certainly wouldn’t tolerate it, not would I, if someone did it to us,” Paul said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol police report spike in threats made toward lawmakers in 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/congress-threats-rise-2025-00752137</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0551-dabb-ad9c-3ffdfce30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:22:48 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Threats toward members of Congress, their families, staff and the Capitol complex surged in 2025, according to the U.S. Capitol Police, with over 5,000 more incidents reported than the previous year.</p> 
<p>The police force’s Threat Assessment Section investigated 14,938 “concerning” statements, behaviors and communications, the agency <a href="https://www.uscp.gov/media-center/press-releases/uscp-threat-assessment-cases-2025" target="_blank">said in a news release this week</a>.</p> 
<p>It’s a sharp increase from 2024, when 9,474 threats were investigated by USCP. These threats — which include everything from social media posts to more direct targeting of lawmakers — mark the third year in a row that USCP has seen an increase in the number of threats made.</p> 
<p>As the number of incidents continues to rise, Capitol Police Chief Michael Sullivan said in a statement that USCP has been “strengthening” its partnerships with law enforcement agencies across the country so members can remain safe when they are away from Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>“We want to make sure agencies have the resources they need to be able to enhance protection, which is critical to the democratic process,” Sullivan said.</p> 
<p>In recent years, the nation has seen <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/09/12/charlie-kirk-political-violence-expert-analysis-00558638" target="_blank">an increase in political violence</a>, with some targeting members of Congress.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, a man was arrested after charging Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) and spraying her with an unknown substance <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540" target="_blank">during a town hall</a>.</p> 
<p>In September, conservative activist Charlie Kirk was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/10/charlie-kirk-tpusa-shot-00555826" target="_blank">killed while speaking at a college campus</a>. Last summer, a gunman <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/14/minnesota-lawmakers-targeted-shooting-00406125" target="_blank">shot two Minnesota state lawmakers,</a> killing one. Two months before that, an arsonist <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/14/josh-shapiro-pennsylvania-arson-attack-00288601" target="_blank">set fire to the Pennsylvania governor’s mansion</a> while Democratic Gov. Josh Shapiro and his family slept inside. And during the 2024 presidential campaign, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/09/15/trump-gunshots-florida-golf-club-00179228" target="_blank">a gunman shot President Donald Trump</a> at a political rally during an attempted assassination.</p> 
<p>USCP on Wednesday said one of the best ways to combat the number of threats facing legislators around the country is to decrease violent political rhetoric — a sentiment both Democrats and Republicans have been urging their counterparts to do each time violence breaks out.</p> 
<p>As Capitol Police continue to monitor threat assessments, the department has expanded its Protective Intelligence Operations Center, which launched in 2024 as a way to process reports regarding the safety of the legislators. The 24/7 center works with the House and Senate Sergeant at Arms to monitor members’ safety, the agency says.</p> 
<p>“We, and both Sergeant at Arms, are seeing an increase of reporting through our outreach efforts with the Congressional Community,” said Jeanita Mitchell, acting assistant chief of police for protective and intelligence operations.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump dings Murkowski, Tillis after their Noem criticism, calls them ‘losers’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/trump-attacks-tillis-murkowski-00752089</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-053b-d9a8-a7be-87bbb1210000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:45:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump took a swing at Sens. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) and Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) after they called for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem to be fired, dismissing both as “losers.”</p> 
<p>“They’re terrible senators. One is gone, and the other should be gone,” Trump said in an interview with <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/trump-hints-relaxed-federal-tactics-minnesota-after-shootings/story?id=129626425" target="_blank">ABC News posted Wednesday</a>. “What Murkowski says — she’s always against the Republicans anyway. And Tillis decided to drop out. So you know, he lost his voice once he did that.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski and Tillis became <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/thom-tillis-kristi-noem-fired-00750580" target="_blank">the first Republicans in Congress to publicly state</a> that Noem should lose her job after her response to a second highly publicized shooting in Minnesota involving federal immigration agents.</p> 
<p>“I think what she’s done in Minnesota should be disqualifying,” Tillis, who is not seeking reelection, told reporters Tuesday. “It’s just amateurish. It’s terrible. It’s making the president look bad.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski told reporters separately that “she should go,” adding to mounting pressure for Trump to fire Noem following the killing of 37-year-old nurse Alex Pretti on Saturday.</p> 
<p>Trump has remained supportive of Noem, telling reporters at the White House on Tuesday, “I think she’s doing a very good job.” When asked if Noem would step down, he replied, “No.”</p> 
<p>Noem faced backlash for her comments soon after Pretti’s shooting, <a href="https://youtu.be/bocDdL_a-IM?si=xtETRzUjjy6gSYKk" target="_blank">in which she labeled him a “domestic terrorist”</a> and claimed without evidence that he intended to kill law enforcement.</p> 
<p>While a growing number of Democrats in Congress have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/democratic-house-leaders-kristi-noem-impeachment-00749643" target="_blank">called for Noem’s impeachment</a>, Trump signaled that he has little patience for Republicans joining in that narrative.</p> 
<p>Trump also took a jab at Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540" target="_blank">she was attacked by a man and sprayed</a> with an unknown substance Tuesday while she spoke at a Minnesota town hall. The man, later identified by local police as 55-year-old Anthony Kazmierczak, was tackled to the ground and detained.</p> 
<p>When asked for his thoughts on Omar’s attack, Trump told ABC News, “I don’t think about her. I think she’s a fraud. I don’t really think about that.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Shutdown threat weighs on Senate lunches</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/shutdown-senate-lunches-dhs-funding-00751643</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-02de-d452-a99e-6bfe7dbf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans and Democrats will head into separate lunches Wednesday for their first in-person conference meetings on how to avoid a partial shutdown at the end of the week.</p> 
<p>No one wants to see the vast majority of federal agency funding lapse at 12:01 a.m. Saturday. But partisan divisions over the Homeland Security bill are reaching the brink amid a weather-shortened week.</p> 
<p>Senators have a few days to turn the tide.</p> 
<p><b>— Democratic demands:</b> Democrats expect to come out of lunch with a firmer wish list of policy changes they want incorporated into the Homeland bill.</p> 
<p>“The things that we care most about are getting an independent investigation and ending these roving patrols that are terrorizing Minneapolis,” said Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.), the top Democrat on the Homeland funding panel. “And solving these problems [with] secret police and getting some identification of body cams.”</p> 
<p>A new <a href="https://www.searchlightinstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Memo-Play-Hardball-and-Use-Your-Leverage-to-Reform-ICE.pdf" target="_blank">polling memo</a> circulating among senators, obtained by POLITICO, is <a href="http://politico.com/news/2026/01/28/ice-polling-memo-searchlight-00751569" target="_blank">providing some encouragement for Democrats</a>. The Searchlight Institute found that “bipartisan majorities of voters oppose ICE’s lawless tactics, including detaining U.S. citizens (73 percent), entering people’s homes without warrants (79 percent), and failing to wear clearly identifying uniforms (70 percent).”</p> 
<p><b>— GOP looks to the White House:&nbsp;</b>Republicans are trying to come up with alternative solutions to address frustrations with President Donald Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader John Thune told reporters he’s encouraging dialogue between the administration and Senate Democrats to reach “some mechanism whereby you don’t have to change the bill or split it out and have to send something back to the House.” He acknowledged members of his own conference would block any attempt to strip DHS funding from the six-bill appropriations package.</p> 
<p>Appropriations Chair Susan Collins said Tuesday she’s also hoping for an off-ramp via executive action. The Maine Republican is in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/susan-collins-dhs-ice-shutdown-00751545" target="_blank">middle of the fight</a> to hold the funding package together as she navigates a DHS enforcement surge in her own state and a likely reelection campaign.</p> 
<p><b>— Will the House return? </b>Democrats want House leaders to bring the chamber back from recess to be ready to pass amended legislation — but Republicans say they have no plans to do so. One senior House Democrat told POLITICO it “seems inevitable at this point the House will be involved” and doubted the administration could do anything to convince Senate Democrats to pass the bill in its current form.</p> 
<p>“I know the House loves recess — they do,” Murphy said. “The House does not like doing their jobs, but sometimes they might actually have to show up when the country is exploding.”</p> 
<p>The Senate will vote Thursday on advancing the six-bill package as is. Thune said it’s “to be determined” what happens if that vote fails.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Rubio testifies on Venezuela: </b>Secretary of State Marco Rubio will appear before Senate Foreign Relations at 10 a.m. to give his first public testimony to Congress since the capture of Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro. Expect questions from lawmakers in both parties about the administration’s plan to get to democracy in Venezuela and who will profit from Venezuelan oil.</p> 
<p><b>— ACA compromise? </b>Sen. Angus King (I-Maine) said Tuesday he’s expecting the bipartisan group of senators working to revive expired Affordable Care Act subsidies to release bill text “hopefully in the next day or so.” It comes after lead GOP negotiator Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) spoke with senators on the floor Tuesday evening about the health care framework.</p> 
<p>Democrats in the negotiating group were initially caught off guard by Moreno’s apparent prediction of text, since they had neither seen nor signed off on anything, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss the private talks. Other lawmakers were pessimistic Tuesday about the state of the discussions, which have been overshadowed by the fight over DHS funding after Saturday’s fatal shooting of Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Katherine Tully-McManus, Jennifer Scholtes, Adam Wren and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top Hunt aide charged taxpayers $44,000 in hotel expenses</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/top-hunt-aide-charged-taxpayers-44-000-in-hotel-expenses-00750033</link>
      <description>The Texas Republican’s top aide, James Kyrkanides, racked up the tab over three years, with an average nightly stay costing four times the federal benchmark rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-013f-d1ea-a5de-31bf8c7f0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/43/22/4879d4a24d57a308f907a55309f3/ap24179069272208-edit.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Gerald Herbert/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>James Kyrkanides, right, is seen with Rep. Wesley Hunt (R-Texas), left, at an event in Fairburn, Georgia, on June 26, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/43/22/4879d4a24d57a308f907a55309f3/ap24179069272208-edit.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Lippman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Lippman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The travel expenses of a Republican campaign manager in the crowded Texas Senate race have raised eyebrows for their seemingly exorbitant amount.</p> 
<p>James Kyrkanides, the campaign manager for Senate candidate Wesley Hunt, charged taxpayers more than $44,000 in hotel expenses over three years as Hunt’s congressional chief of staff. The charges average $457 per night, four times the <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/about-us/newsroom/news-releases/gsa-releases-fy-2025-conus-per-diem-rates-for-federal-travelers-08162024" target="_blank">national standard rate set by General Services Administration rate</a> for many federal employees, according to a POLITICO analysis of House expense records.</p> 
<p>That total accrued over 97 nights during 49 different stays. For instance, on Jan. 3, 2025, when Congress was being sworn in, Kyrkanides expensed a one-night hotel bill of $805. For May 20 to 22, 2024, he submitted a hotel bill of $1,692. And for a stay starting Aug. 6, 2024, he expensed two nights for a total of $1,321.</p> 
<p>The expense records do not require the hotels or the city in which they’re located to be listed, and Kyrkanides declined to name the hotels.</p> 
<p>Kyrkanides said all of the expenses were reviewed and approved by the House finance office, which handles disbursements of member money. He said less than half of the money that was reimbursed went to him personally and the remainder covered travel expenses for other Hunt staffers. He declined to provide receipts to verify that claim.</p> 
<p>Kyrkanides confirmed Washington was his primary workplace during that period of time. He said a number of the reimbursements were in Hunt’s hometown of Houston, where the GSA’s <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/travel/plan-book/per-diem-rates" target="_blank">recommended federal lodging rate</a> is $128 per night. Krykanides said expenses also included stays in Washington, San Diego and New York, which have had average GSA rates of $234, $205 and $277 over the last year, respectively. Krykanides said the hotel stays in those cities were expensed on behalf of Hunt staffers for work travel, including a district director conference in San Diego and communications staffers going to New York for Fox News interviews related to policy.</p> 
<p>Kyrkanides also noted that costs of food, beverage and parking aren’t included in the GSA rates, but his reimbursements folded in those items. He said subtracting them brings his average nightly lodging costs, excluding taxes, to $269. He also pointed to GSA policy that allows federal employees to be reimbursed up to 300 percent of the recommended rate if <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/travel/plan-a-trip/per-diem-rates/faqs" target="_blank">no other rooms</a> are available.</p> 
<p>Asked for comment about the expenses, a Hunt spokesperson said in a statement: “All transactions in this office are approved by the chief administrative officer, made public, and carried out in accordance with the highest ethical guidelines.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the chief administrative officer which oversees House finance declined to comment.</p> 
<p>House members are given broad discretion in how they use their office budget. But some members and committees abide by GSA hotel rates, which serve as a reference point for the federal government. Senate staffers have to limit their hotel expenses to $165 per night but can obtain waivers for additional reimbursement in line with GSA hotel rates.</p> 
<p>Hunt is now in a fiercely contested Senate primary against Sen. John Cornyn and Texas Attorney General Ken Paxton and, according to a <a href="https://share.google/W09eP2hI5HkEqTDmv" target="_blank">RealClearPolitics average</a> of recent polls, is running in third place. Trump hasn’t weighed in with an endorsement and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">has no plans to endorse</a> in the race.</p> 
<p>When briefed about the expenses, Donald Sherman, the president and CEO of Citizens for Responsibility and Ethics in Washington, said the pattern of expenses appeared to be “excessive” and that instances like these show “there needs to be more robust independent oversight of Congress and how it spends taxpayer dollars.”</p> 
<p>“The expenses themselves certainly suggest that there should be more scrutiny on Congressman Hunt and his staff about how they are spending taxpayer funds,” he said in an interview. “Costs aren’t getting real oversight. People [who approve such expenses] are simply checking boxes and giving deference to members.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elon Musk is flexing his political muscle again — and the GOP is responding</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/elon-musk-gop-comeback-00751572</link>
      <description>His recent footprint includes a $10 million investment in the Kentucky Senate race and an all-out influence campaign targeting Senate Republicans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-028a-d9a8-a7be-868aa6e30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/29/44/3c8a7d5148d7b35c8ac647043014/main-congress-elon.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Bill Kuchman/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images, iStock, Creative Commons)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.Congress.Elon.jpg</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/29/44/3c8a7d5148d7b35c8ac647043014/main-congress-elon.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just six months ago, most congressional Republicans kept their distance from Elon Musk after the tech mogul’s messy political breakup with President Donald Trump and his feverish attempt to kill their signature megabill.</p> 
<p>Musk is persona non grata no longer, thanks to his mega checkbook and mega platform — both of which he is now using to influence the future of the GOP.</p> 
<p>Republicans see his recent donation to a Kentucky Senate candidate as an encouraging sign that Musk will make good on his promises to back the GOP, and top House leaders are elated — especially those in charge of defending their razor-thin majority. Musk spent more than $260 million in the last election helping to elect Trump and Republicans.</p> 
<p>“It's definitely a positive development for us,” NRCC Chair Richard Hudson said in an interview.</p> 
<p>He added, “By the way, when they had their rift, I told you all this would happen.”</p> 
<p>That rift seemed unlikely to heal early on, with Musk accusing the president of covering up the Jeffrey Epstein files because Trump was named in the documents, then threatening to start his own political party.</p> 
<p>But just six months later, Musk is back having dinners with Trump and attempting to steer GOP policy again — and he is making his presence felt in key offices on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Musk, who <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/2006832891024781722" target="_blank">posted on New Year’s Day</a> that “America is toast if the radical left wins,” did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>Recently he has used his 233-million-follower X account to push Senate Republicans to pass the SAVE Act — a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2025/04/14/the-house-passed-the-save-act-what-comes-next-00288458" target="_blank">bill meant to tighten election laws</a> to prevent noncitizens from voting, in part by imposing new proof-of-citizenship requirements and restricting mail voting.</p> 
<p>The campaign has driven a huge volume of calls to member offices, according to two aides granted anonymity to discuss internal matters, forcing Republican after Republican to publicly state their support for the legislation. It has no Democratic support and has not been called up for a vote because it cannot overcome the Senate’s 60-vote filibuster hurdle.</p> 
<p>Two of the Senate’s most endangered Republican incumbents — Sens. Bill Cassidy and John Cornyn — have leaned into Musk’s push to hold a vote on the bill, often reposting his messages on their accounts. Cornyn also spoke privately with Thune about the bill last week.</p> 
<p>When Sen. John Boozman of Arkansas announced on X Saturday he was “reviewing” the bill, Musk <a href="https://x.com/JohnBoozman/status/2015097398951911921" target="_blank">reposted the message</a> with a pair of American flag emojis.</p> 
<p>Asked about the bill, Senate Majority Leader John Thune said in an interview Tuesday night that he was sure it would come up for a vote “at some point” but “we’ll have to figure out where we can get it done.”</p> 
<p>“We’ve got a lot of interest in it, and I’m supportive of it,” Thune said, noting he has co-sponsored the bill previously.</p> 
<p>The public pressure campaign appears to have caught some Republicans by surprise given that there’s been little internal rush to formally sign onto the bill since it’s currently not moving and can’t pass the Senate.</p> 
<p>Congressional Republicans, who have fresh memories of the trail of destruction he has often left on Capitol Hill, see Musk’s re-emergence as a mixed blessing. He blew up a carefully negotiated bipartisan government funding deal in December 2024 and almost sunk the GOP megabill in the final stages of passage over his personal objections to the cancellation of electric vehicle subsidies and other policies.</p> 
<p>“He’s a big voice,” said Rep. Blake Moore (R-Utah), a member of House GOP leadership, who recalled how Musk was “really antagonistic” about the huge Republican policy bill last year.</p> 
<p>But, he added, “I think if he's willing to be accurate, yeah, then I then totally want him on board.”</p> 
<p>That’s especially true when it comes to Musk’s money. Even amid his feuding with Trump, he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/31/elon-musk-donations-clf-slf-00487699" target="_blank">cut $10 million worth of checks</a> to the GOP super PACs charged with preserving the House and Senate majorities.</p> 
<p>But with Musk dropping another $10 million into Kentucky Senate candidate Nate Morris’ campaign effort — and ending his dalliance with a third party — the expectation is that more checks will now be on the way.</p> 
<p>Hudson said he hasn’t talked to Musk yet about any future financial commitments to helping House Republicans. But members are straining to get in his good graces as Republicans face huge midterm challenges without Trump on the ballot.</p> 
<p>“History is not on our side,” Rep. Carlos Gimenez (R-Fla.) said, referring to the typical midterm losses suffered by the president’s party. “We'll take any and all help possible to reverse that trend in history, because I think it's important for the Republican Party.”</p> 
<p>Whether they want Musk as a presence on the campaign trail is a more complicated question. His Department of Government Efficiency initiative is widely seen as a bust nearly a year later, and his post-2024 election efforts to vocally back conservatives — like a Wisconsin Supreme Court candidate — backfired at the ballot box.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman (R-S.C.), a hard-liner who is running for governor of South Carolina, said Musk “did an unbelievable job in identifying waste, fraud and abuse” and would be welcome both on the campaign trail and in his potential administration as an efficiency consultant.</p> 
<p>But Republicans in swingier territory are cooler to the idea of a large Musk presence in their races this fall.</p> 
<p>Rep. Rob Bresnahan (R-Pa.), one of the most vulnerable Republicans in the House, said he was pleased to see Trump and Musk patch up their rift — that “obviously we are better when we are united and as a team.”</p> 
<p>Asked if he wanted Musk to campaign in his district, Bresnahan was more equivocal.</p> 
<p>“I’m not really sure — I’m impartial,” Bresnahan said. “We look at whoever's going to be supportive of what we're trying to do for northeastern Pennsylvania, and if their mission aligns with our mission, then we're going to embrace it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T21:33:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Ilhan Omar sprayed with liquid at Minneapolis town hall</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540</link>
      <description>The attack on the progressive lawmaker briefly interrupted her remarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0258-d1ea-a5de-32dc80180000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:29:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/2b/64/9fac20b44870aed536fea3bfcd0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2257991042">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Octavio Jones/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Ilhan Omar reacts after being sprayed with an unknown substance by a man as she hosted a town hall in Minneapolis, Minnesota, on Jan. 27.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2b/64/9fac20b44870aed536fea3bfcd0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2257991042" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Minnesota Rep. Ilhan Omar was attacked by a man who sprayed a liquid while lunging at her before being detained at a town hall in Minneapolis on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Omar was speaking to constituents in her district, which includes much of Minneapolis, about the turmoil in the city in the wake of federal immigration agents shooting Alex Pretti, the second U.S. citizen killed by federal agents in the city in less than a month.</p> 
<p>As she spoke, a man charged at Omar and sprayed her with an unknown substance before being detained by security. She did not appear to be injured and, after a pause, continued the town hall despite a security officer’s advice to halt the event, asking him to “please not let them have the show.”</p> 
<p>“Here’s the reality that people like this ugly man don’t understand,” Omar said. “We are Minnesota strong and we will stay resilient in the face of whatever they might throw at us.”</p> 
<p>The lawmaker's office later said <a href="https://x.com/ilhan/status/2016334654949777714?s=46" target="_blank">on social media</a> that the man who threw the liquid is in custody. "The Congresswoman is okay," it said. "She continued with her town hall because she doesn’t let bullies win.” </p> 
<p>Omar has been the subject of frequent rhetorical attacks from Republicans, including President Donald Trump, who have sought to tie the lawmaker to investigations into public benefits fraud linked with Minnesota’s Somali community. On Tuesday, Trump said the Department of Justice is investigating her personal finances while suggesting she illegally profited from her service in Congress.</p> 
<p>The incident heightens the tensions in Minneapolis, where anti-Trump protests continue to embroil the city in response to a surge of federal immigration enforcement. Two Minneapolis residents, Pretti and Renee Good, were killed by immigration officers, sparking further backlash to the Trump administration’s immigration policies from protesters around the city.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The DHS crisis is squeezing Susan Collins</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/susan-collins-dhs-ice-shutdown-00751545</link>
      <description>The Maine Republican is under immense pressure as a huge funding package hangs by a thread and federal agents swarm her state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0268-dabb-ad9c-3fed275e0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:24:04 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fc/66/b90a782b4c13ad7fd81507163c69/2026-0127-congress-francis-44-2-50610.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) is seen at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 27, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fc/66/b90a782b4c13ad7fd81507163c69/2026-0127-congress-francis-44-2-50610.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> is stuck in the middle of an ICE storm.</p> 
<p>The Maine Republican and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/16/susan-collins-reelection-appropriations-00455206" target="_blank">Senate Appropriations Committee chair</a> is working overtime to salvage a package of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">six funding bills hanging by a thread</a> after the Saturday killing of a Minnesota man by federal agents. The scramble follows months of work to put the appropriations process back on track in the wake of a record government shutdown.</p> 
<p>How Collins navigates the fight will have reverberations far beyond whether or not Congress manages to avoid falling over the shutdown cliff for the second time in four months. The 73-year-old — who intends to seek a sixth term this November — is already under a microscope from Democrats back home after the Trump administration launched an immigration enforcement operation in her state.</p> 
<p>Collins, who said earlier this month she didn’t “see the rationale for a large number of ICE agents” in Maine, spoke with Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem on Monday, later telling reporters Tuesday <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/susan-collins-speaks-with-noem-about-immigration-enforcement-00747915" target="_blank">she urged Noem</a> to pause “this surge of enforcement” in Minnesota and Maine “until we can get far better focus.”</p> 
<p>On Capitol Hill, she’s part of a group of senators who are trying to defuse the shutdown fight, including by exploring actions President Donald Trump could have his agencies take without needing to strip DHS funding out of the pending spending package as Democrats are demanding.</p> 
<p>“We are having conversations with all the parties,” Collins said in an interview Tuesday, referring to the White House and Democrats.</p> 
<p>As to whether or not a shutdown is inevitable, she separately told reporters “it depends on whether people look at the consequences.”</p> 
<p>She pointed to Trump’s decision to send <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis</a> as a sign that the administration is willing to make policy changes in the wake of Saturday’s shooting. But just sending in Homan won’t be enough to appease Democrats.</p> 
<p>Republicans, including Collins, are loath to do that because any changes to the six-bill package would virtually guarantee a partial shutdown starting 12:01 a.m. Saturday. The House would need to approve any changes to the package, and the chamber is in recess until Monday.</p> 
<p>Republican leaders are also wary of an internal backlash to any revised bill, with the ultra-conservative Freedom Caucus warning Monday that they would oppose any measure that did not include money for DHS.</p> 
<p>Democrats say the deployment of DHS agents in Collins’ home state is justification enough for pulling apart the funding package she’s trying to salvage this week.</p> 
<p>“All you have to do is look at what's happening in Minnesota, look at what's happening in Maine,” Maryland Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51658" data-person-id="51658">Chris Van Hollen</a>, a senior Democratic appropriator, told reporters. “And I think that this is why everyone's got to vote to rein in Trump's ICE operation.”</p> 
<p>Collins acknowledged on the Senate floor Monday that the killing of Alex Pretti in Minnesota Saturday refocused attention on Homeland Security funding and whether more guardrails are needed for the immigration agencies under its purview.</p> 
<p>“I recognize that and share the concerns,” she said.</p> 
<p>But she noted that the funding package includes “many safeguards” on DHS funding and that the majority of the department’s budget covers work unrelated to immigration enforcement, including TSA, the Coast Guard and FEMA.</p> 
<p>The political backdrop could hardly be more fraught for Collins. She was already dealing with a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/09/susan-collins-trump-reelection-00719283" target="_blank">complicated relationship with Trump</a>, with the president attacking her and several other GOP senators just this month for supporting an effort to rein in military action in Venezuela. They “should never be elected to office again,” Trump announced — with Collins the only in-cycle Republican among those targeted.</p> 
<p>Collins also voted against the Trump-backed “Big, Beautiful Bill” last year and a separate $9 billion funding clawback pushed by the White House. Still, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and other GOP colleagues have publicly defended Collins as essential to keeping the Maine seat in Republican hands.</p> 
<p>But her well-documented willingness to break from her party has done little to stop Democrats back home from linking her to Trump’s immigration enforcement policies. The Maine Democratic Party <a href="https://www.mainedems.org/media/susan-collins-slammed-refusing-hold-trump-accountable-ice" target="_blank">accused Collins</a> of “choosing Donald Trump over the people of Maine” and “<a href="https://www.mainedems.org/media/collins-call-out-collins-pushing-bill-fund-ice-no-reforms-or-accountability" target="_blank">leading the charge</a> to pass more funding for ICE.”</p> 
<p>One of her aspiring Democratic challengers, Gov. Janet Mills, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/janet-mills-ice-raids-state-address-00751216" target="_blank">leaned into the immigration fight</a> during her State of the State speech Tuesday night — the latest indication of how it is potentially reorienting midterm politics.</p> 
<p>“Tonight, I say to the people of Maine: We will not be intimidated. We will not be silenced,” Mills said.</p> 
<p>Back in Washington, Collins is speaking with Democrats on the Appropriations Committee and members of the Trump administration, as well as fellow Republicans including Thune and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a>, the top Homeland Security appropriator.</p> 
<p>Whether Collins can hold the funding package together and avoid a partial shutdown, most Hill Republicans believe, will ultimately come down to what Trump and congressional Democrats can agree to.</p> 
<p>Thune cited “good conversations” involving Collins and Britt, before adding: “The other thing too is making sure that they’re engaged in the White House.”</p> 
<p>Democrats believe Republicans are open to immigration enforcement changes — and are speaking out about Saturday’s shooting — in large part because of the potential electoral ramifications coming in November.</p> 
<p>Oregon Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66836" data-person-id="66836">Jeff Merkley</a>, another Democratic appropriator, said Republicans are only concerned about the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement actions “in the context of elections right now.”</p> 
<p>“So they talk about Maine — there's a reason that there's extra attention to Maine,” Merkley said in an interview. “I'd like to see some actual principles exhorted by the Republican leadership in both houses — to stand up.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alex Pretti was shot by 2 CBP agents, not just 1, report finds</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/pretti-shot-by-two-cbp-agents-00751207</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01f7-d9a8-a7be-87f78d8a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:34:43 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Authorities believe two federal officers fired their weapons in the shooting that killed Alex Pretti as he was wrestled to the ground in Minneapolis, according to a preliminary Homeland Security report to Congress.</p> 
<p>The report obtained by POLITICO provides the government’s most detailed account yet of the killing of the 37-year-old Pretti, whose death has sparked widespread outrage and prompted the government to modify its immigration enforcement campaign in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>U.S. Customs and Border Protection’s Office of Professional Responsibility said in the report that two of its officers fired after another officer on the scene yelled “He’s got a gun” while restraining Pretti on the snowy street.</p> 
<p>Video from bystanders showed officers had already taken the gun from Pretti, an ICU nurse with a permit to carry a concealed weapon, when he was shot. He appeared to be attempting to intercede in a confrontation between agents and a woman who was protesting immigration operations when the officers grabbed him and forced him to the ground.</p> 
<p>The new details come as the Trump administration scrambles to respond to intense blowback over the killings of Pretti and Renee Good, a Minneapolis woman who was killed by a federal immigration officer earlier in January. Some Republican lawmakers have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/john-thune-kristi-noem-minnesota-00750451" target="_blank">declined to offer their support</a> for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem’s handling of the shootings.</p> 
<p>Earlier on Tuesday, President Donald Trump suggested Pretti shouldn’t have been armed when confronting immigration agents. Other administration officials have indicated that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/trump-pretti-shouldnt-have-been-carrying-a-gun-00750241" target="_blank">Pretti risked provoking the officers</a> by carrying a weapon.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tillis, Murkowski say Noem should be fired</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/thom-tillis-kristi-noem-fired-00750580</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01bd-d9a8-a7be-87bfe06d0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:16:44 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican Sens. Thom Tillis and Lisa Murkowski said Tuesday that Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem should be fired given her response to the killing of a 37-year-old Minneapolis man by DHS agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>Tillis, of North Carolina, said Noem should be "out of a job." Murkowski, of Alaska, said separately that "she should go."</p> 
<p>“I think what she’s done in Minnesota should be disqualifying,” Tillis told reporters. “It’s just amateurish. It’s terrible. It’s making the president look bad.”</p> 
<p>Tillis and Murkowski are the first two Republican lawmakers to say outright that Noem should lose her Cabinet job. Trump is facing intense pressure to fire Noem in the wake of Saturday’s shooting, as well as calls from Democrats for her to be impeached.</p> 
<p>In addition to Noem, Tillis faulted deputy White House chief of staff Stephen Miller for castigating victim Alex Pretti in the immediate aftermath of his shooting: “Those two people told the president before they even had any incident report whatsoever that the person who died was a terrorist. I mean that is amateur hour at its worst.”</p> 
<p>Tillis also signaled he is open to operational changes at DHS in the wake of the shooting, including requiring an independent investigation. And he said he would be OK with a Democratic demand to split off DHS funding from a six-bill package up for debate in the Senate this week, with a stopgap measure in place while funding for the department is renegotiated. </p> 
<p>“I wouldn’t have a problem with its absence,” Tillis said about the DHS bill.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Thune declines chance to back Noem after Minnesota killing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/john-thune-kristi-noem-minnesota-00750451</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-019c-dabb-ad9c-3ffde9330000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:40:47 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> declined to say Tuesday whether he had confidence in Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem as President Donald Trump faces calls to fire her and Democrats push for her impeachment.</p> 
<p>“That's the president's judgment call,” Thune told reporters when asked about Noem, a fellow South Dakota native who previously served with him in the state’s congressional delegation.</p> 
<p>Noem has been at the center of intense scrutiny over the administration’s immigration enforcement tactics after federal agents killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti during a street skirmish on Minneapolis Saturday. Trump said Tuesday he was standing by the embattled secretary.</p> 
<p>While Thune’s comments fell well short of an endorsement of Noem’s performance, he has similarly withheld comment on other embattled Trump officials in recent months, including Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth in December.</p> 
<p>Thune said Tuesday he backs an impartial investigation of the Pretti killing, including probes by state and local officials, as well as a federal investigation outside of DHS.</p> 
<p>“Clearly, there a lot of questions that have to be answered,” he said, adding that investigations are “necessary … any time there's a shooting like that and lives lost.”</p> 
<p>He doubled down on praise for Trump’s decision to send White House border czar Tom Homan to Minnesota to oversee immigration enforcement operations there, calling him “an experienced pro” and calling the moment an “opportunity to evaluate and to really assess the policies and the procedure.”</p> 
<p>Thune’s GOP counterpart across the Capitol, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, has been silent since the shooting, with the House out of session for a one-week break.</p> 
<p>The fallout from Pretti’s killing has upended the Senate’s plan to pass a six-bill spending package by the Friday midnight deadline to avoid a partial government shutdown. Democrats want DHS funding stripped out of the bill and renegotiated, but Republicans are hoping that they can appease Democrats with other actions.</p> 
<p>Thune said Democrats should make their policy demands “clear and known and see to what degree the administration will be able to address that,” adding that he “would prefer that there be a way that we keep the package together.”</p> 
<p>If Democrats block the six-bill package, as they have vowed to do, Thune said the Senate would move to “Plan B,” which is “to be determined.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Henry Cuellar warns against shutdown, handing DHS ‘blank check’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/cuellar-dhs-blank-check-00749995</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0125-d1ea-a5de-31a5a4f50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:30:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a>, who helped craft and backed the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">Homeland Security funding bill</a> now fueling a standoff in the Senate, said in an interview Tuesday that he supports putting more guardrails on federal immigration enforcement agencies but urged senators to pass the legislation the House approved last week.</p> 
<p>The partial government shutdown senators are barreling toward after Saturday’s DHS-involved killing of a Minneapolis man, he warned, would be “the worst situation,” leaving the controversial agencies operating with “a blank check.”</p> 
<p>“If you have a government shutdown, what really happens? ICE got $75 billion in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/26/trump-megabills-name-not-good-for-explaining-what-it-does-00527379" target="_blank">big-beautiful-slash-ugly bill</a>. [But] you shut down FEMA, you shut down TSA, you shut down the Coast Guard, you shut down CISA,” the moderate Texas lawmaker said. “I don't think that's a good alternative.”</p> 
<p>Cuellar, the ranking Democrat on the Homeland Security Appropriations Subcommittee, said he supports many strictures that got left on the cutting room floor in the House, including banning agents from wearing masks and requiring identification, codifying parts of the agency’s use of force policy and notifying Congress about large surges in ICE activity.</p> 
<p>But he suggested those could be revisited in the next yearly funding cycle if Democrats are unable to secure commitments from Republicans before the shutdown deadline. And he said there are steps the Trump administration could take now to defuse tensions, such as increasing training and enforcing ICE’s internal use-of-force policy.</p> 
<p>“I sense an opening where I think we can get more Republicans to work with us,” Cuellar said.</p> 
<p>Amid <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707'" target="_blank">bipartisan backlash</a> to Alex Pretti’s killing, Senate Democrats are seeking to strip the DHS funding bill from a larger <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill appropriations packag</a>e and renegotiate it. They’re seeking a raft of new provisions, including requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, mandating federal agents identify themselves and compelling DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations.</p> 
<p>But Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">scrambling to avoid making changes</a> to the massive bill as the Friday midnight deadline for a partial government shutdown approaches. With the House out till next week, passing the funding package intact is the only viable path to avoiding a shutdown.</p> 
<p>Cuellar joined his fellow Democrats and many Republicans in calling for independent investigations into the shootings of both Pretti and Renee Good, who was also killed in a confrontation with a DHS officer. And he didn’t rule out joining House Democrats’ push to impeach DHS Secretary Kristi Noem if President Donald Trump doesn’t fire her first.</p> 
<p>“I’ll wait until a later time” to weigh in, Cuellar said. “But I’m certainly looking at everything that’s going on, and [Trump and his team] definitely need to change course on it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ICE, Border Patrol leaders to testify in House, Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/ice-border-officials-hearing-00749840</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00f3-d1ea-a5de-30f760b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:53:36 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Top officials from ICE and U.S. Customs and Border Protection will testify before the House and Senate Homeland Security committees next month, as lawmakers ramp up scrutiny of the Trump administration's immigration crackdown after the killing of Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p>ICE acting director Todd Lyons, Customs and Border Protection Commissioner Rodney Scott and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services Director Joseph Edlow have agreed to appear in the House on Feb. 10 and in the Senate on Feb. 12.</p> 
<p>House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) and Senate Homeland Security Chair Rand Paul (R-Ky.) called for the oversight hearings after federal agents shot and killed Pretti in Minneapolis Saturday.</p> 
<p>“Transparency and communication are needed to turn the temperature down,” Garbarino said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem, who has overseen the Minneapolis operation, isn't set to testify on Capitol Hill until March 3. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freedom Caucus pushes to fund DHS amid funding fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/freedom-caucus-dhs-ultimatum-00749816</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00f3-d1ea-a5de-30f774530000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:36:10 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Freedom Caucus leaders are warning they will oppose a proposal favored by Senate Democrats to send an amended spending package back across the Capitol without <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">Department of Homeland Security funding</a>.</p> 
<p>The ultimatum from the hard-right group comes as top leaders try to find a way to avoid a partial government shutdown late this week after Saturday's DHS-involved shooting in Minneapolis threw the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">massive funding package</a> passed by the House last week into jeopardy. Members of the group could potentially tank procedural votes required to advance any alternative funding package.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://x.com/freedomcaucus/status/2016223256445956146" target="_blank">letter to President Donald Trump</a> sent Tuesday, senior members of the group said they would "not allow Democrats to strip [DHS] funding out to pass other appropriations separately."</p> 
<p>"We cannot support giving Democrats the ability to control the funding of our Department of Homeland Security," they added.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats want to break up the six-bill package sent over from the House, stripping out the DHS funding to renegotiate terms following the killing of 37-year-old Alex Pretti. But House GOP leaders privately believe that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">would open a new "hellscape"</a> in the funding talks within the divided House Republican conference.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T15:41:18-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democratic House leaders join push to impeach Kristi Noem</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/democratic-house-leaders-kristi-noem-impeachment-00749643</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00c1-d1ea-a5de-30c5adef0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:02:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The leaders of the House Democratic caucus vowed on Tuesday to impeach Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem if President Donald Trump does not fire her, citing a “DHS killing spree unleashed in Minnesota.”</p> 
<p>The threat comes as Noem <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/kristi-noem-scrutiny-minneapolis-shootings-00748618?can_id=bb0274a7e273dbe000778c447d392e4c&amp;email_referrer=email_3071138&amp;email_subject=tuesday-minnesota-update-add-your-name-if-you-agree-impeach-secretary-of-homeland-security-kristi-noem&amp;link_id=8&amp;source=email-tuesday-minnesota-update-add-your-name-if-you-agree-impeach-secretary-of-homeland-security-kristi-noem" target="_blank">faces heightened scrutiny</a> over her response to the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by Customs and Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis on Saturday, the second killing by federal immigration agents in the city this month.</p> 
<p>Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, whip Katherine Clark (D-Mass.) and caucus Chair Pete Aguilar (D-Calif.) in a joint statement called for “dramatic changes” at DHS and criminal prosecution of federal agents who have broken the law.</p> 
<p>“Taxpayer dollars are being weaponized by the Trump administration to kill American citizens, brutalize communities and violently target law-abiding immigrant families,” the leaders wrote. “The country is disgusted by what the Department of Homeland Security has done.”</p> 
<p>More than 140 House Democrats have signed on to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865" target="_blank">an impeachment resolution</a> against Noem, who is <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610" target="_blank">set to testify</a> before the Senate Judiciary Committee in March. GOP lawmakers and influential MAGA commentators have also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/john-curtis-kristi-noem-minnesota-investigation-00747397" target="_blank">publicly rebuked the Homeland Security secretary</a> in recent days, saying her department’s aggressive immigration operation in Minnesota has overstepped.</p> 
<p>“If Democrats cared this much about deporting violent, criminal illegal aliens, the American people would be much safer," White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson said in response to the statement. </p> 
<p>DHS spokesperson Tricia McLaughlin said in a statement that Democrats should "focus on protecting the American people," which the DHS does "every day under Secretary Noem's leadership."</p> 
<p>"DHS enforces the laws Congress passes, period. If certain members don’t like those laws, changing them is literally their job," McLaughlin said.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration signaled a possible shift in strategy on Monday, with the president sending border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis and announcing that Homan “will report directly to me.” The White House also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">pulled Border Patrol Commander Gregory Bovino</a>, a close ally of Noem’s whose response to the shooting also drew backlash, from his assignment in the city.</p> 
<p>Still, White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Monday that Noem retains “the utmost confidence and trust of the president of the United States,” and Trump told reporters Tuesday that “she's done a very good job” and will not step down.</p> 
<p>The Democratic leaders wrote in their statement that “the violence unleashed on the American people by the Department of Homeland Security must end forthwith,” adding: “We can do this the easy way or the hard way.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eleanor Holmes Norton confirms her retirement as DC delegate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-statement-00749099</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-003d-dabb-ad9c-3ffdeff70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:32:11 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Eleanor Holmes Norton, Washington's nonvoting House delegate for 35 years, confirmed Tuesday she is retiring from office — more than 48 hours after a public filing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/eleanor-holmes-norton-retires-dc-delegate-00731986" target="_blank">terminating her reelection campaign</a>.</p> 
<p>“With pride in our accomplishments, gratitude to DC, and confidence in the next generation, I announced I'll retire at the end of this term,” she said in a statement. </p> 
<p>Norton, who is 88 and has faced serious questions about her fitness for office, said she would complete her 18th term.</p> 
<p>“Although I’ve decided not to seek reelection, I will never falter in my commitment to the residents I have long championed,” she said, touting her success in securing the transfer of federal lands to local government control and the establishment of a federally funded college tuition assistance program for D.C. residents.</p> 
<p>Norton stayed silent for days after her campaign filed termination paperwork Sunday morning — even as local politicians and dignitaries paid public tribute to Norton and her service to the city.</p> 
<p>Norton has made limited public appearances in the past year, even as President Donald Trump targeted the city for a police takeover and immigration enforcement surge. She insisted for months she would run for reelection but raised barely any campaign cash as pressure to retire mounted and challengers began to line up against her. </p> 
<p>Among the Democrats already vying to succeed her are D.C. Council members Brooke Pinto and Robert White, political strategist Kinney Zalesne and former Norton aide Trent Holbrook. The June 16 primary is all but certain to decide the next delegate in a city that hasn’t given a Republican presidential nominee more than 10 percent of the vote since 1988.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T17:08:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Florida Republican Vern Buchanan won’t seek reelection</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/vern-buchanan-florida-retirement-00748961</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0016-d9a8-a7be-869687cf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:35:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Florida Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51853" data-person-id="51853">Vern Buchanan</a> announced Tuesday that he will be retiring from Congress after 20 years in office, the latest Republican to forgo seeking reelection amid a challenging midterm environment for the party.</p> 
<p>Buchanan, who represents the red 16th District that includes some of Tampa’s suburbs along the Gulf Coast, is a longtime member of the House Ways and Means Committee.</p> 
<p>“Serving the people of Southwest Florida has been the honor of my lifetime,” Buchanan said in a statement. “After 20 years of service, I believe it’s the right time to pass the torch and begin a new chapter in my life.”</p> 
<p>First elected in 2006, Buchanan became a key player on tax, trade and health care policy.</p> 
<p>His decision to step aside has sparked chatter among Republicans over potential successors. Shortly after news of Buchanan’s retirement broke, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260192" data-person-id="260192">Randy Fine</a> (R-Fla.) voiced support for Republican National Committee Chair Joe Gruters, writing <a href="https://x.com/VoteRandyFine/status/2016170411755462822?s=20" target="_blank"><u>“Run, Joe, run!” in a post on X</u></a>.</p> 
<p>But Gruters is not interested in running to replace Buchanan in the Florida district, according to two people with direct knowledge of the matter granted anonymity to discuss his thinking, and is instead interested in remaining the RNC chair. </p> 
<p>But another person close to Gruters, similarly granted anonymity, said he “wouldn’t shut any doors just yet” over whether Gruters might run, despite him being elected to lead the RNC in August. The person added that Gruters would be a “significant frontrunner should he do it.”</p> 
<p>Christian Ziegler, a former Florida GOP chair, floated other possible names for the seat, including Buchanan’s son, Florida state Rep. James Buchanan, who is running for the state Senate; Manatee County Commissioner Mike Rahn; former state Senate President Bill Galvano; state Rep. Fiona McFarland; and former state Rep. Tommy Gregory.</p> 
<p>Ziegler added there was “always a chance” wealthy self-funders could also enter the race.</p> 
<p>Buchanan’s early years in Congress drew scrutiny after he was <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2011/10/report-doj-investigating-buchanan-066301" target="_blank"><u>investigated by the Justice Department in 2011</u></a> over allegations that he asked a former associate in the auto industry to improperly reimburse his employees for their contributions to his campaign. Buchanan denied any wrongdoing, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2012/09/doj-drops-case-against-rep-buchanan-081069" target="_blank"><u>the case was dropped in 2012</u></a>.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Kimberly Leonard contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: No shutdown deal in sight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/shutdown-dhs-ice-funding-minnesota-shooting-00748768</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fda2-d1ea-a5df-fda680270000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senators are scrambling to avoid a partial government shutdown later this week after Saturday’s fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by a federal agent has members of both parties debating what guardrails they can place on President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p>There’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">no deal</a> in sight.</p> 
<p>The Homeland Security appropriations measure is a part of a multi-bill funding package the House sent over to the Senate last Thursday before leaving town for recess, and which the Senate now must clear before 12:01 a.m. Saturday, Jan. 31 — or spark funding lapses across multiple agencies. Making changes to any portion of that package at this point would jeopardize its chances for being signed into law in time.</p> 
<p>But recent developments in Minnesota have Democrats calling for changes to the DHS measure. Among their list of demands are requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, mandating federal agents identify themselves, requiring DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations and limiting the “mission creep of federal agencies.”</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer wants the DHS bill stripped out of the larger funding package entirely and renegotiated.</p> 
<p>Republicans are reluctant to engage, taking the first step Monday to set up an initial vote on the package Thursday. Instead, GOP senators are dangling alternatives that would let them avoid having to tweak the package at the eleventh hour, floating new potential executive actions or a commitment to passing a separate piece of legislation that would address shared priorities.</p> 
<p>Democrats aren’t biting. Many believe they have leverage as Americans recoil at the administration’s immigration enforcement tactics in Minnesota and elsewhere. Plenty of Democrats are also skeptical the administration can be trusted to bring accountability to DHS operations or that standalone legislation reining in the department would ever make it through the House.</p> 
<p>“My options are to do nothing or to recognize that two U.S. citizens were recently … executed by federal agents,” Sen. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.) told reporters Monday. “We need to at least bring some level of pressure on DHS or on our Republican colleagues to explain to the American public why we are going to continue funding this without any changes.”</p> 
<p>Democrats are also increasingly <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865" target="_blank">calling for DHS Secretary&nbsp;Kristi Noem’s impeachment</a> amid the fallout. Noem will testify March 3 for an oversight hearing <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610" target="_blank">before Senate Judiciary</a>, according to an aide for Chair Chuck Grassley (R-Iowa), where questions about her leadership are sure to arise.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans could still have the upper hand. A group of conservatives, including Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah), is vowing to oppose any effort to strip out DHS funding. And due to the time crunch ahead of Friday’s shutdown deadline, a single senator can block an attempt to quickly amend the legislation.</p> 
<p>Privately, many Republicans believe any off-ramp will need to come from the White House, anyway, according to two people granted anonymity to disclose private thinking — and the administration said Monday it wants to see the funding package passed as written.</p> 
<p>Over in the House, Speaker Mike Johnson’s leadership circle is still weighing its options but there are no plans to bring the chamber back early from recess, according to three people granted anonymity to comment on private planning.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No off-ramp in sight for DHS-fueled shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628</link>
      <description>Republicans are dangling options that would avoid having to change a massive spending bill. Democrats aren’t biting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fcf0-d1ea-a5df-fcf431d30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:55:52 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c9/02/7b3ffafc4e3ea5110a323ac21399/u-s-congress-53267.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Katie Britt (R-Ala.), who leads the Appropriations subcommittee dealing with DHS, said actions “within the purview of the administration” could address Democrats’ concerns.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c9/02/7b3ffafc4e3ea5110a323ac21399/u-s-congress-53267.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Washington is charging toward a partial government shutdown over President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda even as senators and the White House scramble to find an elusive off-ramp.</p> 
<p>Democrats, Republicans and the White House each say they want to avoid another costly lapse in government funding. But Saturday’s killing of a 37-year-old Minnesota man by federal agents has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">badly complicated the approach pattern</a> for a massive six-bill appropriations package that the Senate planned to approve this week.</p> 
<p>In the wake of the Minnesota shooting, Democrats want Republicans to join them in stripping out funding for the Department of Homeland Security from the sprawling package. Yet any changes would require further action in the House, which is out of town until Monday — after a shutdown would start at 12:01 a.m. Saturday.</p> 
<p>Republicans are dangling alternatives that would avoid having to change the massive bill, including potential executive actions or an agreement to pass a separate piece of legislation. But Democrats believe they have leverage as Americans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">recoil at Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement tactics</a> in Minnesota and elsewhere.</p> 
<p>The captured-on-video killing of Alex Pretti has sparked public unease even from Trump allies in Congress and fueled new questions about how the administration is enacting its agenda, putting intense pressure on Democrats to dig in and fight.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said Monday that the “responsibility to prevent a partial government shutdown” lies in the hands of Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and his fellow Senate Republicans. He called on them to agree to strip out and renegotiate the DHS bill while allowing the rest of the package — which would fund nearly three-quarters of annual agency spending — to be passed into law.</p> 
<p>As recently as Friday, enough senators were expected to help pass the full set of funding bills, which was negotiated over the course of months by bipartisan appropriators. Now, according to a person granted anonymity to disclose private discussions, Democrats are quickly “coalescing” around a number of changes they want to the DHS bill, which won only seven Democratic votes in the House.</p> 
<p>Those include requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, overruling a recently disclosed ICE memo asserting they are not required. Other potential Democratic amendments would mandate federal agents identify themselves, require DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations and limit the “mission creep of federal agencies.”</p> 
<p>Despite the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">concern that has emerged within the GOP ranks</a> after Saturday’s shooting, Republicans are moving forward with the six-bill package as currently drafted, taking a first step Monday to put it on the floor. Senators are expected to take an initial vote Thursday, when at least eight Democrats will be needed to leap a 60-vote hurdle.</p> 
<p>Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) told reporters Monday that she did not favor removing the DHS bill from the six-bill package but that there are ongoing discussions about “further reforms or procedural protections.”</p> 
<p>“My hope is that we’re not going to get to that point, that everyone would recognize that a government shutdown is extremely harmful and should be avoided,” Collins said when asked about the prospects for a partial shutdown.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a> (R-Ala.), who leads the Appropriations subcommittee dealing with DHS and met with Collins Monday, also told reporters the Senate should pass the funding package as is but that there could be actions taken “within the purview of the administration” to address Democrats’ concerns.</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers and aides held out hope that some of Trump’s moves Monday, which included sending border czar Tom Homan to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">oversee the Minnesota enforcement surge</a>, would soften the ground for a possible deal. Others were encouraged that lines of communications remained open between the parties early in the week.</p> 
<p>Republicans are facing their own internal pressures as they seek to avoid a shutdown. A group of conservatives, including Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah), is vowing to oppose any effort to strip out DHS funding. And because the Senate is locked in a time crunch with the Friday midnight deadline looming, any one senator can block an attempt to quickly amend the legislation.</p> 
<p>At the same time, there are some Democratic qualms about pushing agencies to the brink less than three months after ending a record 43-day shutdown fought over health care. Some are noting that ICE and Border Patrol will continue to be funded in any case through the GOP megabill enacted last year while other DHS agencies such as FEMA and TSA would be subject to the shutdown.</p> 
<p>But so far Democrats are insisting that Republicans agree to rewrite the bill. Democrats are skeptical that the administration can be trusted to take executive action or that standalone legislation reining in DHS would ever make it through the House.</p> 
<p>“My options are to do nothing or to recognize that two U.S. citizens were recently … executed by federal agents,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189136" data-person-id="189136">Ruben Gallego</a> (D-Ariz.) told reporters Monday. “We need to at least bring some level of pressure on DHS or on our Republican colleagues to explain to the American public why we are going to continue funding this without any changes.”</p> 
<p>Even sending an amended bill back to the House would carry the risk of an extended standoff. One senior House Republican granted anonymity said that would open a new "hellscape" in the funding talks, with the fractious GOP conference divided over the way forward.</p> 
<p>“Democrats already had a say in DHS funding during the bipartisan negotiations that occurred on each and every individual appropriations bill," said a House GOP aide granted anonymity to speak candidly about the dynamics. “If they renege on the agreement on any of these bipartisan bills, then it would open a bigger can of worms.”</p> 
<p>Privately, many Republicans on Capitol Hill believe that any off-ramp to be found before Friday night’s deadline will need to come from the White House, according to two people granted anonymity to disclose private thinking.</p> 
<p>But <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/white-house-backs-appropriations-package-with-dhs-funding-00746971" target="_blank">the administration said Monday</a> it wants to see the six-bill package passed as written — without the DHS funding separated out.</p> 
<p>“Policy discussions on immigration in Minnesota are happening,” White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said, adding that those talks “should not be at the expense of government funding for the American people.”</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson's leadership circle is still weighing options as the partial shutdown looms. While some Senate Democrats are calling on the House to cut its one-week break short and reconvene, there are no plans to bring the chamber back early, according to three people granted anonymity to comment on private planning.</p> 
<p>While GOP leaders plan for now to bring the House back next Monday as scheduled, some rank-and-file Republicans are wary that Johnson might re-run his strategy from the last shutdown and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/09/mike-johnson-shutdown-no-show-00601215" target="_blank">keep the House out even longer</a> in a bid to jam the Senate.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Susan Collins speaks with Noem about immigration enforcement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/susan-collins-speaks-with-noem-about-immigration-enforcement-00747915</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc6c-d452-a99b-fdfe0abf0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:28:56 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>GOP Sen. Susan Collins said she spoke Monday to embattled Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem after the administration launched an immigration enforcement campaign in her home state.</p> 
<p>Collins declined to divulge details of her conversation with Noem to reporters — though her office indicated earlier this month that the senator had reached out to DHS about ICE’s activities in Maine.</p> 
<p>Regarding the ICE presence there, Collins said in a statement last week that “people who are in this country legally should not be targets of ICE investigations,” while those who have “entered this country illegally and who have engaged in criminal activity …. could be subject to arrest and deportation.” </p> 
<p>She added, “People who are exercising the right to peacefully gather and protest their government should be careful not to interfere with law enforcement efforts while doing so.</p> 
<p>But the conversation comes at a critical moment. Federal agents shot and killed a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis over the weekend, prompting public outrage and sparking criticism from a growing number of Senate Republicans about the Trump administration’s handling of the situation. It’s the second such shooting to occur in the city since January began.</p> 
<p>Collins is also the chair of the Senate Appropriations Committee who helped negotiate legislation to fund several agencies — including DHS — through the end of September. That bipartisan package is now imperiled as Democrats now say they won’t vote to support any bill that funds DHS without significant guardrails in place to rein in immigration enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>DHS is among several agencies that would shut down after Jan. 30 unless lawmakers can reach some sort of compromise.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kristi Noem to testify before Senate Judiciary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc32-dabb-ad9f-fffff7b80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:35:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem will testify March 3 before the Senate Judiciary Committee, according to an aide for Chair Chuck Grassley.</p> 
<p>Grassley has been haggling for weeks to schedule Noem’s testimony as part of his panel’s regular oversight of DHS. But her high-profile appearance will likely be dominated by senators’ questions regarding the agency’s immigration enforcement tactics following two fatal shootings by federal agents in Minneapolis in the past month.</p> 
<p>Some GOP senators — including Sen. Thom Tillis of North Carolina, who is a member on the committee — have called for an independent investigation into the latest shooting over the weekend, while others have criticized initial comments from top administration officials that suggested the victim bore responsibility and not the officers involved.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rand Paul summons Trump immigration officials to testify after Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/rand-paul-dhs-hearing-minneapolis-00747012</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbef-d1ea-a5df-fbefeffb0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:14:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151828" data-person-id="151828">Rand Paul</a>, chair of the Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee, called on three top immigration enforcement officials to testify before his panel in the wake of Saturday’s killing of a Minneapolis man by federal agents.</p> 
<p>The Kentucky Republican <a href="https://x.com/SenRandPaul/status/2015868311825785113/photo/1" target="_blank">sent letters Monday</a> to Rodney Scott, the commissioner of Customs and Border Protection; Joseph Edlow, director of U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services; and Todd Lyons, who is serving as acting director of ICE, requesting that the three men testify at a Feb. 12 hearing.</p> 
<p>“As you know, the Department of Homeland Security has been provided an exceptional amount of funding to secure our borders and enforce our immigration laws,” Paul said in the letters to the administration officials. “Congress has an obligation to conduct oversight of those tax dollars and ensure the funding is used to accomplish the mission, provide proper support for our law enforcement, and, most importantly, protect the American people.”</p> 
<p>Paul’s letters don’t mention this weekend’s killing of 37-year-old Alex Pretti, which has sparked a wave of new scrutiny of the immigration enforcement actions in Minnesota ordered by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>But the hearing would be the first chance senators will have to question Trump administration officials’ over the shooting and the president’s broader immigration and Homeland Security agenda.</p> 
<p>Separately, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/52983" data-person-id="52983">Todd Young</a> (R-Ind.) joined the growing ranks of Republicans raising questions about the shooting, saying he supports a “full and transparent investigation into the tragic event in Minneapolis.”</p> 
<p>“Congress has requested testimony from ICE, CBP, and USCIS leaders in an open hearing, and they should testify soon,” said Young, who is not a member of Paul’s committee, in a statement to POLITICO. “Providing the American people with the full facts is an important part of maintaining public trust. We also need state and local officials to better cooperate with federal enforcement efforts.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House backs appropriations package with DHS funding</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/white-house-backs-appropriations-package-with-dhs-funding-00746971</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbe1-d452-a99b-fbff7a170000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:58:58 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The White House on Monday urged the Senate to pass the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill appropriations package</a> to avert a partial government shutdown and signaled it doesn’t want <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">Department of Homeland Security money</a> separated out.</p> 
<p>“At this point, the White House supports the bipartisan work that was done to advance the bipartisan appropriations package and we want to see that passed,” press secretary Karoline Leavitt said at a White House briefing when asked if the administration would be willing to separate DHS funding.</p> 
<p>Leavitt said that “policy discussions on immigration in Minnesota are happening,” pointing to President Donald Trump’s call with Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz earlier Monday. She said the discussions “should not be at the expense of government funding for the American people.”</p> 
<p>The press secretary also pointed to the winter storms across the country and the effect a lapse in FEMA funding could have on the response effort.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer has pressed Republicans to rewrite the DHS funding legislation in the wake of the killing of Alex Pretti in Minnesota and signaled that the other five appropriations bills could move forward without it. Senate Republican leadership want to move forward all six bills, including DHS funding, and the first votes are expected Thursday.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More Hill Democrats want Kristi Noem out as DHS secretary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fbb8-dabb-ad9f-fffde7210000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:37:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A growing number of Hill Democrats are calling for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem to step aside or be impeached following the shooting of a Minneapolis man by DHS agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>A House impeachment resolution targeting Noem now has <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HRES_996?q=H.Res.996" target="_blank">140 cosponsors</a>, nearly two-thirds of the Democratic Caucus, according to a spokesperson for Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/204795" data-person-id="204795">Robin Kelly</a> (D-Ill.), who authored the legislation. Dozens signed on over the weekend, including after a private caucus call Sunday in which a number of House Democrats spoke out for impeachment.</p> 
<p>Although impeaching President Donald Trump remains a highly divisive issue among Democrats, calling for Noem’s impeachment or resignation is fast becoming a mainstream position in the party.</p> 
<p>On the cosponsor list for Kelly's resolution are purple-district lawmakers such as Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422300" data-person-id="422300">Laura Gillen</a> (D-N.Y.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/422519" data-person-id="422519">Greg Landsman</a> (D-Ohio), as well as members of the party leadership team including Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/152934" data-person-id="152934">Debbie Dingell</a> (D-Mich.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198811" data-person-id="198811">Suzan DelBene</a> (D-Wash.). </p> 
<p>Others in the party are calling for Noem's removal without mentioning the prospect of impeachment. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a>, for instance, declared in a Monday <a href="https://x.com/SenSchumer/status/2015840890112057442?s=20" target="_blank">social media post</a> that Noem "must be fired.” </p> 
<p>In a statement provided first to POLITICO, 15 House Democrats who are veterans said Noem should resign.</p> 
<p>“We call for an immediate stand down of ICE and CBP interior enforcement operations and demand the resignation of the Secretary of Homeland Security,” said the lawmakers, including California Democratic Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189606" data-person-id="189606">Ted Lieu</a>, <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259485" data-person-id="259485">Salud Carbajal</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307601" data-person-id="307601">Gil Cisneros</a>. “Current leadership has failed to protect civil liberties, ensure accountability, or maintain the public trust.”</p> 
<p>With Republicans in control of the House floor, it could be difficult for Democrats to force the issue anytime soon. Absent a GOP groundswell, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> will be able to bottle up the measure indefinitely though Kelly could try to call up her impeachment legislation as a privileged matter, allowing it to bypass committees and move to a quick House vote.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suozzi: ‘I failed’ when voting to pass DHS funding bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-suozzi-dhs-funding-vote-00746598</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb59-d452-a99b-fbffc8740006</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:29:47 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Tom Suozzi (D-N.Y.) on Monday said he regretted his vote last week for a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">funding bill for the Department of Homeland Security</a>, amid intense backlash surrounding the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“I failed to view the DHS funding vote as a referendum on the illegal and immoral conduct of ICE in Minneapolis,” <a href="https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=1428888331927735&amp;id=100044197461606&amp;mibextid=wwXIfr&amp;rdid=39dD6MhX9Elb42eK#" target="_blank">he said in a statement</a>. “I hear the anger from my constituents, and I take responsibility for that. I have long been critical of ICE’s unlawful behavior and I must do a better job demonstrating that.”</p> 
<p>Suozzi was one of seven Democrats who crossed party lines to join Republicans in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402" target="_blank">narrowly passing the DHS funding bill</a> in a 220-207 vote. The bill funded agencies including FEMA and the Coast Guard — and ICE, keeping it funded at $10 billion for the fiscal year.</p> 
<p>Suozzi expressed his regret amid mounting tensions following federal immigration operations in Minnesota and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">killing of a second U.S. citizen protester</a>, 37-year-old ICU nurse Alex Pretti, on Saturday.</p> 
<p>“The senseless and tragic murder of Alex Pretti underscores what happens when untrained federal agents operate without accountability,” Suozzi said. “President Trump must immediately end ‘Operation Metro Surge’ and ICE’s occupation of Minneapolis that has sown chaos, led to tragedy, and undermined experienced local law enforcement.”</p> 
<p>Before the weekend killing, the DHS funding was slated to be part of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill package</a> that seemed likely to pass in the Senate. But Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said over the weekend that Democrats would not help <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/shutdown-senate-democrats-minneapolis-shooting-00745642" target="_blank">advance the current package</a> if it included the DHS funding — significantly raising the risk of a partial government shutdown at the end of the week.</p> 
<p>Rep. Laura Gillen (D-N.Y.), another one of the seven House Democrats who voted for the DHS package, called for DHS Secretary Kristi Noem’s impeachment following Pretti’s killing.</p> 
<p>“Another U.S. citizen has been killed at the hands of ICE and there must be accountability, which is why Secretary Noem must be impeached immediately,” Gillen <a href="https://gillen.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-gillen-urges-accountability-following-events-minnesota" target="_blank">said in a statement Sunday</a>. “Under her leadership, ICE has targeted U.S. citizens and children and killed Americans.”</p> 
<p>But Vicente Gonzalez (D-Texas), another member of the group of breakaway House Democrats, <a href="https://x.com/RepGonzalez/status/2015795510762787001" target="_blank">defended his vote in a video message Monday</a>, calling the footage out of Minnesota "appalling” but defending voting for the DHS funding.</p> 
<p>“ICE has all the resources they need that they got from that big ugly bill Republicans passed last year, that I voted against,” he said, adding he voted for funding for agencies like FEMA and the TSA.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T13:59:49-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans offer early support for Trump’s Minnesota pivot</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-homan-gop-support-00746206</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb00-d1ea-a5df-fb8404090005</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:52:21 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Republicans on Capitol Hill expressed relief after President Donald Trump announced Monday he would send border czar Tom Homan to handle immigration enforcement in Minnesota after Department of Homeland Security agents shot and killed a second U.S. citizen there.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) said in an interview that the move was "a positive step to get the situation under control" while calling for a "full and transparent investigation" into the two Minneapolis shootings.</p> 
<p>"There needs to be greater coordination and cooperation between federal, state, and local officials — which is why sanctuary policies need to end and local officials must work with ICE so they can do their jobs without interference," he said. "It is paramount that we work to keep the public and law enforcement safe, while respecting the rights of everyone involved, including the right to peacefully protest."</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> <a href="https://x.com/LeaderJohnThune/status/2015841218182152505" target="_blank">called the move</a> a "positive development," while Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) also offered praise Monday, saying on X “we need a new set of eyes and someone with his experience to help turn around the problems of the moment and the future."</p> 
<p>“Tom is the right man to find a way to de-escalate the situation,” Graham added.</p> 
<p>A growing number of Hill Republicans have been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">pushing publicly and privately</a> for a lowering of the temperature, including from the federal government, after DHS agents shot and killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Saturday.</p> 
<p>GOP lawmakers largely view Homan as a more practical enforcer of Trump’s mass deportation plans as some grow increasingly wary of how Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem and Border Patrol commander Gregory Bovino are handling the campaign, according to six GOP lawmakers granted anonymity to discuss internal conversations.</p> 
<p>“There needed to be a change,” said one of the GOP lawmakers. But other at-risk Republicans have been wary to publicly embrace Homan, who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/16/tom-homan-50k-sting-operation-00611219" target="_blank">denied reports</a> that he took a $50,000 bribe from federal agents.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T13:25:07-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump says Justice Department is investigating Ilhan Omar</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/trump-justice-department-ilhan-omar-00746103</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fac6-d9a8-a7bf-fec66b6c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:30:55 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Monday said the Justice Department is investigating Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.).</p> 
<p>Trump made the <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115961647505369753" target="_blank">announcement on Truth Social</a>, writing: “the DOJ and Congress are looking at ‘Congresswoman’ Illhan Omar, who left Somalia with NOTHING, and is now reportedly worth more than 44 Million Dollars. Time will tell all.”</p> 
<p>It is the latest attack the president has levied at Omar, and the most recent instance of the president directing an investigation into his political rivals.</p> 
<p>Trump has previously said Omar <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/01/trump-ilhan-omar-somalia-00632599" target="_blank">should be jailed or deported to Somalia</a>, where she was born, though Omar has been a U.S. citizen since 2000. He has also linked Omar to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/29/us/fraud-minnesota-somali.html" target="_blank">government services fraud</a> investigations in Minnesota, accusing her of being “one of many scammers,” despite no clear evidence linking her to the cases.</p> 
<p>Tensions have only grown between the two as immigration officials continue to patrol the city of Minneapolis, which Omar represents.</p> 
<p>Omar on Monday appeared unperturbed by Trump's announcement. <a href="https://x.com/IlhanMN/status/2015818278728257569?s=20" target="_blank">In her own post on X</a>, Omar said Trump was "deflecting."</p> 
<p>"Sorry, Trump, your support is collapsing and you’re panicking," she wrote. "Right on cue, you’re deflecting from your failures with lies and conspiracy theories about me. Years of 'investigations' have found nothing. Get your goons out of Minnesota."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Omar's office said she has not received anything from DOJ about an investigation.</p> 
<p>Omar’s net worth skyrocketed in the last year, and House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) <a href="https://nypost.com/2026/01/24/us-news/house-gop-prepares-for-court-to-establish-how-ilhan-omar-her-husband-are-worth-up-to-30m/" target="_blank">recently told the New York Post</a> that he plans to launch an investigation into what caused the dramatic spike.</p> 
<p>According to <a href="https://disclosures-clerk.house.gov/public_disc/financial-pdfs/2024/10068415.pdf" target="_blank">financial disclosures filed last year</a>, Omar’s net worth principally increased due to her spouse — and not her work with the government. She disclosed her spouse having stakes worth collectively between $6 million and $30 million in a venture capital firm and a winery.</p> 
<p>Members of Congress’ and their spouses’ sources of income and assets are traditionally disclosed in broad ranges, not as a specific dollar amount.</p> 
<p>Omar has previously denied the allegations of anything untoward and has said Trump has <a href="https://x.com/ilhanmn/status/1995957774510162165?s=46" target="_blank">a “creepy” obsession</a> with her.</p> 
<p>Trump also announced Monday that he is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">sending border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis</a>. Residents have flooded the streets of the city this month, protesting the shootings of Renee Good, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/woman-killed-by-ice-agent-in-minneapolis-was-a-mother-of-3-poet-and-new-to-the-city-00715809" target="_blank">who was killed by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement officer</a> Jan. 7, and Alex Pretti, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">who was killed by a Border Patrol</a> agent Saturday.</p> 
<p>The Department of Justice did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: Due to an editing error, an earlier version of this report misstated the value of Omar's spouse's business partnerships.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Shutdown odds spike after Minnesota killing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/what-were-watching-00745892</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f841-dabb-ad9f-ffede4950000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The killing of Alex Pretti at the hands of federal agents is hitting hard on Capitol Hill, ratcheting up the odds of a partial government shutdown and spurring Republican lawmakers to make another break with the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Here’s the latest on how the fallout from the Minnesota shooting is playing out in Congress:</p> 
<p><b>— Shutdown looks likely: </b>The Senate is set to take its first vote on the last tranche of government funding bills Thursday, and things aren’t looking good.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer is insisting that Republicans work across the aisle to rewrite DHS funding legislation but also signaling that Democrats would be willing to help advance the other five pending appropriations bills in the meantime. Several Democrats who helped end the previous shutdown say they plan to vote against the funding bills unless there are changes to the ICE operation in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>At this stage, Senate GOP leadership expects to move forward as planned on the six-bill package including DHS. Republicans and the White House have reached out to Senate Democrats about how to proceed, but one Senate Democratic leadership aide granted anonymity said they haven’t raised “realistic solutions.” A number of rank-and-file Senate Republicans are speaking out against any attempt to “defund” DHS — and leadership would need buy-in from all 100 senators to quickly strip out the DHS bill. President Donald Trump is <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115958123338296139" target="_blank">now pushing Republicans</a> to pass a bill to “END Sanctuary Cities.”</p> 
<p>A couple key reminders: The pending funding bills include money for the departments of Defense, Health and Human Services and State, and account for more than 75 percent of federal discretionary spending.</p> 
<p>And don’t forget the House is out this week and wouldn’t be around to pass any revamped funding bills before Friday. The Senate won’t hold its first vote of the week until Tuesday afternoon because of the snow storm.</p> 
<p><b>— Trump faces nervous GOP: </b>A growing number of House and Senate Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">voicing public concerns</a> about the incident and calling for an investigation, as top administration officials defend the agents involved.</p> 
<p>Even close Trump allies are beginning to speak out. Sen. David McCormick (R-Pa.) <a href="https://x.com/SenMcCormickPA/status/2015562528114520255" target="_blank">said on X Sunday night</a> that he supports the Border Patrol and ICE but that he agrees <a href="https://x.com/NRA/status/2015227627464728661?s=20" target="_blank">with the NRA</a> about the need for a “full investigation.”</p> 
<p>House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) is calling for DHS officials to testify. House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) suggested to Fox News that Trump would want to “maybe go to another city” as Minnesota officials push back.</p> 
<p>Some Republicans have been privately warning administration officials and GOP leaders for months that Trump’s immigration crackdown is not going over well in some pockets of the country.</p> 
<p>“Many of us wonder if the administration has any clue as to how much this will hurt us legislatively and electorally this year,” said one House Republican.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
