<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/politics-news.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Bad Bunny created a cultural phenomenon. Can he spark a political one?</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/08/bad-bunny-super-bowl-immigration-00770475</link>
      <description>The Puerto Rican superstar’s music has brought Latinos together. Democrats are jealous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-3a19-d0f8-adde-fa5b64bd0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/96/a3/87b309a04ee9b5de7f2cf08ccaee/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2260110168">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mike Coppola/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Bad Bunny appears at the Super Bowl LX Pregame &amp;amp; Apple Music Super Bowl LX Halftime Show Press Conference in San Francisco on Thursday, Feb. 5.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/96/a3/87b309a04ee9b5de7f2cf08ccaee/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2260110168" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez and Ali Bianco</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez and Ali Bianco</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The world is watching for Bad Bunny to make a political statement at the Super Bowl. Democrats are watching closely to figure out how to make their own.</p> 
<p>Benito Antonio Martínez Ocasio, the Puerto Rican recording artist known globally by his stage name, has created a pop culture phenomenon that will converge at a historic halftime show performance at the Super Bowl on Sunday when the New England Patriots play the Seattle Seahawks. Though Bad Bunny already made his Super Bowl debut alongside Shakira and Jennifer Lopez back in 2020, this time the spotlight will be on him and his exclusively in-Spanish catalog. And while his invitation triggered a harsh backlash on the right from the president on down, it’s also marking a major inflection point for Hispanic Americans of all backgrounds.</p> 
<p>Sunday may prove to be Bad Bunny’s biggest chance to move the dial.</p> 
<p>There’s an opportunity here, Democrats told POLITICO, to turn Bad Bunny’s cultural phenomenon into a political one, right as the party is mounting its strongest resistance to Trump’s sweeping deportation agenda — and with months to go before the midterms to make amends with Latino voters who have left their tent.</p> 
<p>Former Rep. Luis Gutiérrez (D-Ill.), who is of Puerto Rican descent and whose tenure in the House was marked by his outspokenness for the Latino communities he represented, emphasized that Democrats need to seize this moment to win back Latino support.</p> 
<p>Democrats “do too little to engage the Latino community, and then they wonder why all these Latinos voted for Trump? Because you didn't knock on their doors asking to vote for the Democrat. You failed to message us in so many ways,” he said. “They should embrace it.”</p> 
<p>“It's such a huge watershed moment,” Rep. Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez (D-N.Y.) said. “I wouldn't be surprised if he used this as a very unifying moment, but also on very resonant and salient grounds to send a message to people.”</p> 
<p>There’s already signs of what’s on the Latino rapper’s mind.</p> 
<p>“Before I say thanks to God, I’m going to say, ‘ICE out,’” Bad Bunny said last Sunday as he accepted the Grammy for Best Música Urbana Album for his record-smashing “DeBÍ TiRAR MáS FOToS” — just hours before taking home the night’s biggest prize, Album of the Year. “We’re not savage, we’re not animals, we’re not aliens — we are humans, and we are Americans.”</p> 
<p>Bad Bunny isn’t new to political endeavors. But he has long focused primarily on island politics — he’s a big activist for Puerto Rican independence — and has only occasionally weighed in on mainland issues.</p> 
<p>In 2024, shortly after comedian Tony Hinchcliffe infamously disparaged Puerto Rico as a “floating island of garbage” during the pre-show for Trump’s rally at Madison Square Garden, Bad Bunny posted an endorsement of Kamala Harris to his tens of millions of Instagram followers. But he never appeared with Harris on the campaign trail.</p> 
<p>His political trajectory has followed other Latino voters’ in recent months, however. <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/race-and-ethnicity/2025/11/24/majorities-of-latinos-disapprove-of-trump-and-his-policies-on-immigration-economy/" target="_blank">Polls show many Hispanics</a> have been particularly outraged at the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown. And they are highly motivated to vote and could shift left, after consecutive election cycles where Trump made significant inroads with Latinos.</p> 
<p>Americans overall <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/poll-republicans-ice-immigration-deportations-00744668" target="_blank">in recent polling</a> have shown an increasing souring on Trump’s handling of immigration. The two fatal shootings in Minneapolis and the stream of videos of ICE raids online are driving a fierce grassroots opposition that is pushing Democrats to hold the line on the Hill and not cave in negotiations on the DHS funding bill. But Trump's crackdown has been felt most acutely in Latino communities. For many, the <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/five-year-old-boy-detained-by-ice-has-returned-minnesota-lawmaker-says-2026-02-01/" target="_blank">stories of families being detained</a> have fueled a feeling of solidarity across the diaspora.</p> 
<p>“That's bringing people of all kinds together — especially the Latino community, the diaspora of Latino communities, that come from so many different places, so many different subcultures. It's bringing us together in a new vision of latinidad,” said Chicago Alderman Michael Rodriguez, who represents the city’s historically Mexican Little Village community. “Our community is being assaulted right now.”</p> 
<p>During Bad Bunny’s massive world tour last year, the artist did not schedule any shows on the U.S. mainland, in part due to concerns that ICE would target his concerts for immigration enforcement operations. “It’s something that we were talking about and very concerned about,” <a href="https://i-d.co/article/bad-bunny-puerto-rico-residency-issue-375-cover/" target="_blank">he told i-D magazine in a September interview</a>.</p> 
<p>After the rapper was announced as the halftime performer in September, Corey Lewandowski <a href="https://variety.com/2025/music/news/trump-advisor-ice-agents-bad-bunny-super-bowl-halftime-show-1236536667/" target="_blank">said there would be</a> ICE enforcement operations at the Super Bowl — seemingly bringing to life some of the concerns that Martínez Ocasio voiced. Local leaders in the Bay Area have said this week they’ve privately been told no ICE officers will be at the show. DHS has <a href="https://apnews.com/article/super-bowl-bad-bunny-trump-politics-1447163cfa820cbb0c96973c20ccd976" target="_blank">remained more vague publicly</a> about enforcement plans around the game. DHS did not respond to a request for comment on this story.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Republicans this weekend — many of whom in the MAGA universe have referred to Martínez Ocasio as “Woke Bunny” — are holding their own halftime performance to make a statement. Turning Point is counterprogramming Bad Bunny’s performance with a made-for-television “All American Halftime Show” featuring Kid Rock. “I think that that part of the country just felt offended,” said Andrew Kolvert, a spokesperson for Turning Point. “There needs to be a counter voice that says, ‘Hey, you know, we love this country. We love the rule of law, we love our troops, we love law enforcement, we love traditional America.’”</p> 
<p>For Democrats, the question of how to better engage and win in Latino communities has dogged them as the party searches for a way out of the wilderness since their 2024 election losses. Bad Bunny has shown a natural ability to bring those communities together with his music, filling stadiums across the world for multi-night shows.</p> 
<p>“It’s not that easy. We’re 23 countries, we fight each other every day,” said Rep. Delia Ramirez (D-Ill.), who represents the largest Puerto Rican community in the Midwest — and whose city of Chicago was an early target of Trump's increased immigration enforcement efforts. “For Bad Bunny to be able to bring Puerto Ricans, Mexicans, Guatemalans, Dominicans together, and all feel like they’re being heard and that he can represent them, says a lot about who is.”</p> 
<p>As for Martínez Ocasio, he’s keeping mum about what to expect from his performance on Sunday night. “It’s going to be a huge party,” <a href="https://apnews.com/article/bad-bunny-super-bowl-halftime-show-f441549a00166a39309233f689163105" target="_blank">he said at a preview event on Thursday</a>. “I want to bring to the stage, of course, a lot of my culture. But I really don’t, I don’t want to give any spoilers. It’s going to be fun.”</p> 
<p>The cultural solidarity that Bad Bunny’s music has fostered could translate into political unity, Rodriguez, the Chicago alderman, said. And some of his fellow Democrats are ready to build on the moment.</p> 
<p>“There's just no scenario where he is not going to have a message,” Rep. Robert Garcia (D-Calif.) said. “There are moments in history that really move a community and solidify them within a political movement. And I think that's happening right now.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A MAGA push to erase a Dem House seat is triggering accusations of fraud and violence in Utah</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/07/trump-backed-redistricting-initiative-in-utah-goes-sideways-00767959</link>
      <description>Assault allegations, potential fraud and a roster of Trumpworld supporters are rocking the Beehive State.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2fb1-de8a-a1fc-fff100610001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2026 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/2c/b0/e8b765914ce490f57de941a9342f/republican-meeting-89338.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Wong Maye-E/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>The Utah State Capitol is illuminated against the setting sun in Salt Lake City, on Nov. 15, 2020.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2c/b0/e8b765914ce490f57de941a9342f/republican-meeting-89338.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>National Republicans are throwing money and bodies at a down-ballot initiative to try to wrest back a congressional seat in Utah. Their efforts could blow up in their face.</p> 
<p>With a looming February 15 deadline, Republicans have seen only half the number of verified signatures they need to move things forward. And the effort, which has the <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115946953654029014" target="_blank"><u>backing of President Donald Trump</u></a> and support from multiple MAGA groups, has devolved into chaos.</p> 
<p>Local county clerks are flagging hundreds of potentially fraudulent submissions. People have <a href="https://www.ksl.com/article/51440458/i-felt-tricked-ksl-investigates-some-misleading-claims-from-those-working-to-repeal-prop-4" target="_blank"><u>reportedly been repeatedly misled</u></a> into signing the petition by signature-gatherers, with some telling local news outlets that <a href="https://www.sltrib.com/news/politics/2026/01/31/prop-4-decline-sign-volunteers-gop/" target="_blank"><u>they were told it was an anti-ICE petition</u></a>. Those signature-gatherers have reported <a href="https://www.deseret.com/politics/2026/01/29/utah-republican-signature-gatherers-assaulted-as-national-activist-groups-aim-to-repeal-redistricting-law/" target="_blank"><u>being assaulted</u></a> by hecklers and their signature packets stolen or destroyed.</p> 
<p>In the Beehive State, where politics are often seen by outsiders as cartoonishly friendly, this effort has turned so tumultuous that Republican Gov. Spencer Cox — who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/11/disagree-better-spencer-cox-stop-hate-00557293" target="_blank"><u>earned national attention for his pleas for civility</u></a> after conservative influencer Charlie Kirk was assassinated in the state — <a href="https://x.com/GovCox/status/2017242349081092452" target="_blank"><u>called on Utahns</u></a> to “resolve [their] disagreements peacefully.”</p> 
<p>While the GOP groups insist they’ll have the numbers needed, they’re still far short — which would represent a major failure in a ruby-red state.</p> 
<p>The effort aims to overturn <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/11/utah-judge-denies-gop-passed-congressional-map-00646183" target="_blank"><u>a new judge-ordered congressional map</u></a> that hands Democrats one safe blue seat by attempting to repeal an anti-gerrymandering law that would allow the Republican-controlled legislature to reinstall a more favorable map ahead of the 2028 elections. It has garnered support from Trump and his allies, who had already spent $4.3 million on the effort as of November — and have only ramped up since.</p> 
<p>The signature-gathering initiative represents an early test of Republicans’ ground-game efforts in a midterm year <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/house-fundraising-midterm-campaign-finance-fec-00759382" target="_blank"><u>where they face strong headwinds</u></a> in the polls.</p> 
<p>Trump and his son, <a href="https://x.com/DonaldJTrumpJr/status/1980266166439350277" target="_blank"><u>Donald Trump Jr,</u></a> have signaled support to the Utah initiative, with Trump recently encouraging his Truth Social followers to support the “very important effort” to ”KEEP UTAH RED.”</p> 
<p>Turning Point Action — the 501(c)(4) founded by the late Charlie Kirk, who was killed in the state last summer — is “all in” on the effort, <a href="https://www.deseret.com/politics/2025/12/09/turning-point-action-joins-utah-republican-effort-to-repeal-proposition-4-redistricting-law/" target="_blank">its COO said</a><u>,</u> and is canvassing the state with <a href="https://www.tpaction.com/superchase/ut" target="_blank">a half-dozen events over the next week.</a> A fleet of about 700 paid workers, many of them from out of state, have been hired to gather signatures, bankrolled by Securing American Greatness Inc., a 501(c)(4) previously run <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/05/31/trump-dark-money-group-00161122" target="_blank">by former Trump White House official Taylor Budowich</a>. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/30/the-maga-celebrity-trying-to-turn-new-jersey-red-in-2025-00235357" target="_blank">MAGA celebrity Scott Presler</a> parachuted in last month for a series of events. And Trump Jr. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xH8z2DfebdI" target="_blank">cut an 11th-hour ad</a> begging Utah outdoorsmen to protect "their pioneer heritage" by signing the petition at the state's largest hunting expo in Salt Lake City next week. (Trump-loving country singer Ted Nugent, who will attend the expo, will autograph merch for signers.)</p> 
<p>But so far, those efforts don’t appear to be paying off. As of Friday, the initiative had garnered <a href="https://vote.utah.gov/repeal-of-the-independent-redistricting-commission-and-standards-act-direct-initiative-list-of-signers/" target="_blank">just over 76,000 verified signatures</a>, about half of the more than 140,000 required statewide for a measure to be added to this November’s ballot. A daily analysis <a href="https://utahpolitics.news/prop-4-qualifies-in-third-senate-district-but-still-miles-from-the-ballot/" target="_blank">conducted by independent journalist Bryan Schott</a> shows the initiative on track to fall well short of the required signature thresholds: eight percent of all active registered voters statewide, and eight percent in at least 26 of the 29 Utah state Senate districts.</p> 
<p>“The only thing that will matter is on the very last day, do we have enough signatures, and I strongly believe that we will,” said Brad Bonham, a Republican National Committeeman and initiative sponsor.</p> 
<p>The initiative’s Republican backers claim the lagging signature count is part of their strategy. Bonham said the initiative’s sponsors have “many, many thousands of signatures” they are independently verifying and have not yet submitted. Utah Republican Party Chairman Rob Axson said “many tens of thousands” more have been submitted to county clerks and are undergoing verification.</p> 
<p>“We feel very, very good about the strategy that we are executing on and the momentum that we're building,” Axson said.</p> 
<p>Dropping a large tranche of signatures close to the February 15 deadline could backfire, said Elizabeth Rasmussen, the executive director of Better Boundaries, the anti-gerrymandering group opposing the repeal, as signers still have a 45-day window after their signature is verified to remove it.</p> 
<p>Rasmussen said her group mailed <a href="https://static.politico.com/b5/46/ca0b5b254bf6b01fe6d8b32b8dad/utah-petition-nonpartisan-english.pdf" target="_blank"><u>nearly 8,000 letters</u></a> last week to petition signers encouraging them to remove their names, and will continue to do so in coming weeks. Her groups’ previous efforts have led to over 500 signatures removed, Rasmussen said.</p> 
<p>And she’s not so sure that Trump’s involvement will help the GOP in a heavily conservative state whose voters nonetheless have long been skeptical of the president.</p> 
<p>“Trump’s approval rating in Utah is at an all-time low,” Rasmussen said. “We’re not seeing that as a value add, if anything.”</p> 
<p>The ongoing saga in Utah is an odd addendum to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/the-redistricting-fight-that-dominated-american-politics-in-2025-00703193" target="_blank"><u>the nationwide redistricting push</u></a>. In 2018, Utah voters passed Proposition 4, a ballot measure that created an independent redistricting commission to prevent partisan gerrymandering. Earlier this year, District Judge Dianna Gibson ruled that the GOP-controlled state legislature <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/25/utah-congressional-maps-2026-00524388" target="_blank"><u>failed to comply</u></a> with Prop 4 when it drew four safe Republican districts in the 2022 map. The GOP submitted another map with four safe seats last fall, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/11/utah-judge-denies-gop-passed-congressional-map-00646183" target="_blank">the judge selected a different map</a>, which includes a blue seat in Salt Lake County, in November.</p> 
<p>The GOP-controlled state legislature is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/utah-redistricting-congressional-map-appeal-00668098" target="_blank"><u>appealing Gibson’s decision</u></a> to the state Supreme Court, and two sitting U.S. House members <a href="https://www.deseret.com/politics/2026/02/02/congressmen-sue-utah-lieutenant-governor-over-new-congressional-map-chosen-by-district-judge-because-violates-us-constitution/" target="_blank"><u>joined a federal lawsuit</u></a> pushing for the current, Republican-friendly map to be used in 2026. The state GOP’s signature-gathering push would repeal Prop 4 and allow the legislature to redraw a map ahead of the 2028 cycle.</p> 
<p>If they meet the requisite signature threshold, the initiative will go on the ballot this November, where voters will decide.</p> 
<p>In Utah County, the state’s second-most-populous county, the clerk’s office has <a href="https://www.fox13now.com/news/politics/bogus-efforts-used-to-gain-prop-4-repeal-signatures-called-most-extensive-fraud-that-weve-seen" target="_blank"><u>flagged hundreds of signatures</u></a> for possible fraud. Some appear to be forged signatures, and when the clerk’s office called the signers, they denied ever signing the petition; others appear to be made-up names and addresses.</p> 
<p>“I think it's just the signature gatherers that are doing this are just trying to find an easy way to make money,” Aaron Davidson, the Utah County Clerk, told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>The Salt Lake and Davis county clerks — the first- and third-most populous counties in the state — said they have not seen any significant irregularities. “The number of alleged fraudulent voters that Utah County has found, that is startling,” said Lannie Chapman, the Salt Lake County clerk. “We all take this very seriously.”</p> 
<p>Axson, the GOP state chair, said some of the signature-gatherers under review were flagged by his team before submission, and several paid signature-gatherers who are under review for fraud have been fired. "I don't want a single fraudulent signature counted,” Axson said.</p> 
<p>“Are there going to be a couple of bad actors, or bad examples, or places where the process has fallen short, or whatnot? Of course there are,” added Axson. “But what's not being talked about in all of these stories is the fact that out of 3,000 people engaged in this effort, you only have a small handful of bad actors.”</p> 
<p>But as the signature push enters its home stretch, tensions have only accelerated.</p> 
<p>“Violence is not the answer to any of this. I don't understand anybody that would do that,” added Bonham, the initiative sponsor. “It brings me back to Charlie Kirk losing his life here in our own backyard. It's like, what on earth is going on here?”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Epstein scandal is taking down Europe’s political class. In the US, they’re getting a pass.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/epstein-europe-america-fallout-00769506</link>
      <description>As Europe moves to address its shame, it’s highlighting the comparative lack of accountability in the U.S.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-34aa-d0f8-adde-fefa08600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 18:16:44 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0a/b8/511757df49319e4f39e946ad0f82/main-lippman-epsteinukvusfallout.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Claudine Hellmuth/POLITICO (source images via AP and Getty)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, Sarah Ferguson, Keir Starmer, Peter Mandelson, Elon Musk, Donald Trump, Stephen Bannon, Howard Lutnick</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0a/b8/511757df49319e4f39e946ad0f82/main-lippman-epsteinukvusfallout.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Lippman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Lippman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Across the Atlantic, heads are rolling over the Jeffrey Epstein revelations.</p> 
<p>In Norway, one prominent diplomat has <a href="https://www.straitstimes.com/world/europe/norway-suspends-celebrated-diplomat-in-epstein-probe" target="_blank">already been suspended</a> and a police investigation <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/former-norway-pm-investigated-corruption-suspicion-over-jeffrey-epstein-files/" target="_blank">has been opened</a> into a former prime minister. In the U.K., the former ambassador to the U.S. <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/peter-mandelson-resigns-as-british-ambassador-to-us-over-jeffrey-epstein-friendship/" target="_blank">has been fired</a>; on Tuesday, <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/peter-mandelson-built-britains-labour-establishment-now-its-torching-him/" target="_blank">he resigned from the House of Lords</a>. Police are reviewing reports <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/peter-mandelson-appeared-send-uk-government-plans-epstein/" target="_blank">he shared market-sensitive information with Epstein</a>.</p> 
<p>Andrew Mountbatten-Windsor, formerly known as Prince Andrew, <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/prince-andrew-titles-stripped-royal-lodge/" target="_blank">was stripped of his royal titles and residence</a>. A charity founded by his ex-wife Sarah Ferguson, the former Duchess of York, will shut down indefinitely following <a href="https://apnews.com/article/sarah-ferguson-duchess-york-epstein-andrew-b7cd2158ef6bd2ac06ad06e8b2f3dbd5" target="_blank">the release of emails</a> where she called Epstein a “legend” and “the brother I have always wished for.”</p> 
<p>But as Europe’s political class moves to clean up its mess and address its shame concerning ties with the convicted sex offender, it’s inadvertently highlighting something else — the comparative lack of accountability in the U.S.</p> 
<p>No prominent politicians have taken a fall. Consequences have been limited. Wagons have been circled around the most prominent political figures whose names have surfaced in the legal document dumps.</p> 
<p>In the U.K., former ambassador to the U.S. Peter Mandelson — who has said he was wrong to believe Epstein following his conviction and to continue his association with him afterwards — has emerged as a millstone around <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/keir-starmer-apologizes-jeffrey-epstein-victims-for-appointing-peter-mandelson/" target="_blank">British Prime Minister Keir Starmer’s neck</a>. While Starmer never actually met Epstein, some are calling for his resignation over his appointment of Mandelson. The prime minister publicly apologized Thursday to Epstein’s victims.</p> 
<p>“I am sorry,” Starmer said. “Sorry for what was done to you, sorry that so many people with power failed you, sorry for having believed Mandelson’s lies and appointed him and sorry that even now you’re forced to watch this story unfold in public once again.”</p> 
<p>It’s a different story in the U.S. Donald Trump’s Republican Party has largely averted its eyes or rallied to the president’s defense despite his documented ties to Epstein and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/epstein-files-todd-blanche-photos-00759045" target="_blank">the unverified additional allegations</a> against the president that appeared last week.</p> 
<p>Trump has denied wrongdoing in relation to the Epstein allegations, and no evidence has suggested that he took part in Epstein’s trafficking operation. The president also has maintained that he and Epstein had a falling out years ago.</p> 
<p>Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick remains unscathed in his Cabinet post. Lutnick said on a podcast last year that he was so disgusted by his neighbor Epstein in 2005 that he vowed to never be in the same room with him again. But when the Justice Department released more than three million pages of materials related to the late American financier last Friday, emails surfaced suggesting a closer relationship and that Lutnick had actually seen Epstein <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/30/us/howard-lutnick-epstein-island.html" target="_blank">some years later</a> on a trip to Epstein’s Caribbean island. A spokesperson said the Commerce secretary “<a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/politics/2026/02/03/lutnick-invited-epstein-hillary-clinton-fundraiser/88494105007/" target="_blank">had limited interactions with Mr. Epstein in the presence of his wife and has never been accused of wrongdoing.</a>” So far, there are no signs it affected his standing in the Trump Cabinet.</p> 
<p>Likewise, Goldman Sachs and its CEO David Solomon have stood shoulder-to-shoulder with the company’s general counsel Kathryn Ruemmler as she’s faced brutal headlines for months for her associations with Epstein, <a href="https://freebeacon.com/democrats/oh-my-god-i-am-dying-jeffrey-epstein-showered-obama-white-house-counsel-kathryn-ruemmler-with-gifts-including-9400-hermes-handbag-and-four-seasons-spa-treatment-emails-show/" target="_blank">which include gifts of a $9,400 Hermes bag</a> and a spa treatment at the Four Seasons Hotel in D.C. Solomon <a href="https://www.wsj.com/finance/goldman-sachs-ruemmler-epstein-8c8255fd" target="_blank">told the Wall Street Journal</a> several weeks ago that Ruemmler, a former White House counsel to Barack Obama, “is widely respected and admired at the firm.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.wsj.com/finance/goldman-sachs-ruemmler-epstein-8c8255fd?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqcwhGjNvZpfXNrb24oB08Ybr86Ku69B7IO988qXsma5P6VA0Dxh6hb8iMIPCAk%3D&amp;gaa_ts=69864071&amp;gaa_sig=qS3dRhQ1NZox8EuCg4Ft7rp3qPMsqK-6hZZY2Qxkr1eSzzg6c2fKOVgHt1V4U2e4qcbna-ez_R2q6zenF5BlrQ%3D%3D" target="_blank">Ruemmler has said</a> she regrets “ever knowing him, and I have enormous sympathy for the victims of Epstein’s crimes.”</p> 
<p>Even Dr. Peter Attia, the author and influential longevity researcher who is a contributor to CBS News, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/business/story/2026-02-04/cbs-news-peter-attia-keeps-cbs-news-role-despite-epstein-files-controversy" target="_blank">remains on the job</a> despite his appearance in numerous emails with Epstein, where they discussed female genitalia and how Epstein’s life was “so outrageous.” <a href="https://x.com/PeterAttiaMD/status/2018350892395774116" target="_blank">In an email that he posted on X</a>, Attia apologized and said he was not involved in any criminal activity, his interactions with Epstein had nothing to do with his sexual abuse or exploitation of anyone and that he was never on his plane or island, and never present at any sex parties.</p> 
<p>Some see the relatively limited fallout — in a public arena where infidelity or even smoking marijuana were once enough to sink a career — as a reflection of the diminished standards of the Trump era, when the president’s own indiscretions and extreme polarization has led to a greater tolerance of the scent of scandal. They point to the Cabinet nominations of former Rep. Matt Gaetz of Florida and Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth, both of whom would have been unthinkable in the past given allegations about their involvement in sex crimes that both men have denied.</p> 
<p>“Some of that has to do with the general chaos on this side of the pond where it’s a never ending stream of scandal emanating from 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue and Trump has set a tone of defiance on refusal to accept and feel any shame,” said Norm Eisen, a former U.S. ambassador to the Czech Republic who is now a top Trump critic and the founder of Democracy Defenders Action, a bipartisan group that tracks what it calls “autocratic” behavior by the administration. “Those who should feel shame are hunkering down instead.”</p> 
<p>It’s true that several American figures linked to Epstein have been forced to step away from public life. They include former Treasury Secretary Larry Summers, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/11/17/politics/elizabeth-warren-larry-summers-harvard-epstein" target="_blank">who has said</a> he is “deeply ashamed of my actions and recognize the pain they have caused,” and Paul Weiss chairman Brad Karp, who <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/02/04/business/brad-karp-paul-weiss-resigns-epstein.html?searchResultPosition=1" target="_blank">resigned as the law firm’s chair on Wednesday</a> saying it’s in the best interest of the firm. David Ross, former director of the Whitney Museum of American Art, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/02/04/nyregion/epstein-emails-david-ross-school-visual-arts.html" target="_blank">stepped down this week</a> from his position at a Manhattan art school and said in a statement that he felt ashamed for falling for Epstein’s lies. But for many of the best-known elites who were in contact with the late convicted sex offender — including former Trump aide Steve <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/jeffrey-epstein-files-bannon-musk-00758613" target="_blank">Bannon and billionaire tech mogul</a> Elon Musk — the only consequence has been the reputational hit.</p> 
<p>“What matters is not release of some subset of the Epstein files, but rather the prosecution of those who committed heinous crimes with Epstein,” <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/jeffrey-epstein-files-bannon-musk-00758613" target="_blank">Musk wrote on X</a>. “When there is at least one arrest, some justice will have been done. If not, this is all performative. Nothing but a distraction.”</p> 
<p>Bannon has said little publicly about their relationship, but he did previously call for an independent investigation into the files.</p> 
<p>Bannon, a frequent visitor to Epstein’s New York house, <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/general-news/bannon-epstein-doc-wolff-1236433536/" target="_blank">was planning a documentary</a> to help revive Epstein’s image and even was texting documentary scheduling questions with Epstein the day he was arrested in 2019. Even so, there are few outward signs that the scandal has touched him: Bannon still does his “War Room” show on Rumble and his political musings are widely covered in the press.</p> 
<p>It’s an approach in keeping with Trump’s own never-concede-an-inch style.</p> 
<p>“We as Americans need to be looking at ourselves in the mirror. Why are we not having that same reaction [as Europe]?” said Rufus Gifford, a former Obama-appointed ambassador to Denmark. “Without a doubt how Trump has acted has filtered down to broader society. But I think the question that we have to ask is whether or not this existed before Trump, and Trump is just a symptom of that larger problem.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-06T17:08:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>‘It’s pissing people off’: Centrist Democrats are livid with AIPAC after primary fiasco</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/centrist-democrats-are-livid-with-aipac-after-primary-meddling-00769461</link>
      <description>AIPAC spent $2 million attacking moderate-leaning Tom Malinowski in a House special election — and may have handed the race to progressive Analilia Mejia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-349a-d0f8-adde-feda02e70009</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 15:30:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/a0/51/92d0df24489880637ca0d3702d40/https-delivery.gettyimages.com/downloads/1228547982">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Stefani Reynolds-Pool/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Tom Malinowski speaks during a House Foreign Affairs Committee hearing in Washington, D.C.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a0/51/92d0df24489880637ca0d3702d40/https-delivery.gettyimages.com/downloads/1228547982" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The American Israel Public Affairs Committee uncorked $2 million to try to sink a mainstream Democrat in a multi-candidate special House election primary in New Jersey — and it’s infuriating mainstream Democrats and some of the pro-Israel lobby’s supporters.</p> 
<p>“It’s pissing people off,” said Steve Schale, a longtime Democratic strategist and former Obama campaign adviser, who described it as “maddening.”</p> 
<p>The organization spent heavily through its super PAC, Unite Democracy Project, to attack former Rep. Tom Malinowski (D-N.J.), a pro-Israel moderate who would not support unconditional aid to Israel. In doing so, it provided an opening to Analilia Mejia, a progressive organizer backed by Bernie Sanders who <a href="https://youtu.be/aQCOQ6R5mok?si=Y5JC0rVICOoIzIee&amp;t=2987" target="_blank"><u>has said Israel committed genocide in Gaza</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Malinowski, who has not conceded the race, now trails Mejia by around 500 votes, with some outstanding votes left to be counted for the affluent, suburban seat.</p> 
<p>AIPAC’s interventions in the New Jersey special election for Democratic Gov. Mikie Sherrill’s House seat was the first test of the group’s muscle ahead of the 2026 primary season, when they are expected to spend millions on Democratic primaries across the country. AIPAC’s super PAC is expected to weigh in on House primaries, starting in Illinois’ March primaries. Democratic candidates and strategists are also bracing for them to potentially wade into contentious Senate primaries in Michigan and Minnesota.</p> 
<p>And their first foray of 2026 backfired spectacularly.</p> 
<p>Matt Bennett, the co-founder of the center-left think tank Third Way, called their efforts “one of the greatest own-goals in American political history,” and warned that “It hurt everybody in the moderate movement” as they head into a competitive primary season.</p> 
<p>Even steadfast allies are frustrated. Rep. Brad Schneider (D-Ill.), a longtime AIPAC supporter, said its moves in the New Jersey primary, held Thursday, “raised eyebrows this morning.”</p> 
<p>“There’s a chance that it’s not going to be a New Dem that’s in that seat,” Schneider said, referring to the New Democrat Coalition, the centrist caucus he leads in the House. “As we do the analysis, a lot of factors play into that, but certainly any group spending against a candidate that would’ve been a New Dem and instead electing a far-left candidate … Come on, guys, this is not what we were hoping for here.”</p> 
<p>Former Rep. Steve Israel (D-N.Y.), another AIPAC supporter who led House Democrats’ campaign efforts in 2012 and 2014, said he “wasn’t privy to AIPAC’s strategy and I certainly wouldn’t have advised it,” but “they are not the first group to make a bet that didn’t pan out on election day.”</p> 
<p>Malinowski said AIPAC’s attacks on him sent a clear message to “other mainstream Democrats.”</p> 
<p>“They are now demanding 100 percent fealty,” Malinowski said. “On some level, they may have preferred to elect an anti-Israel progressive versus a mainstream Democrat, who departs from their hard line in a small way.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for UDP said in a statement shared with POLITICO: “The outcome in NJ-11 was an anticipated possibility, and our focus remains on who will serve the next full term in Congress.” The spokesperson added that UDP will “be closely monitoring dozens of primary races, including the June NJ-11 primary,” which will be held ahead of the November 2026 general election, “to help ensure pro-Israel candidates are elected to Congress.”</p> 
<p>Progressives, meanwhile, took a victory lap. Justice Democrats communications director Usamah Andrabi said AIPAC’s spending in primaries “is becoming a kiss of death” because “of the work our movement has done to expose them.” Mejia told reporters on Friday that she’s “glad that New Jersey 11 voters got to see the terrible tactics so that we could reject it in the future” and denounced AIPAC’s heavy spending.</p> 
<p>Sanders, who rallied for his former adviser Mejia on the eve of the election, said Democrats are starting to realize that "not only is [AIPAC's] policy bad, but it's going to hurt me politically,'" and predicted candidates will start throwing the AIPAC spending back at them.</p> 
<p>"I think you're going to see a lot of candidates saying, 'I'm being attacked by AIPAC. You should vote for me for that reason alone,'" Sanders said. "They’re going to turn it around because AIPAC is increasingly unpopular."</p> 
<p>Much of UDP’s playbook in the New Jersey primary has been deployed by them before — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/07/25/israel-divide-democratic-primaries-00047625" target="_blank"><u>attacking candidates on issues unrelated to Israel.</u></a> The group hit Malinowski in TV ads for a 2019 vote he took, along with most House Democrats at the time, that, in part, provided funding to Immigration and Customs Enforcement. ICE funding is a particularly hot-button issue, after President Donald Trump’s immigration crackdown in Minnesota led to two fatal shootings of protesters by federal agents.</p> 
<p>There are signs that AIPAC is already getting involved in Illinois. Two super PACs, Elect Chicago Women Now and Affordable Chicago Now, are now supporting three Democrats in House races with six-figure TV ad buys — <a href="https://evanstonnow.com/whos-behind-the-new-super-pac-ads-on-tv/" target="_blank"><u>which some of their primary opponents have publicly accused the groups of shell groups.</u></a></p> 
<p>The super PACs were formed last month, so they have not yet been required to disclose any information yet with the Federal Elections Commission. UDP’s spokesperson did not respond to a request for comment on these super PACs.</p> 
<p>“We’re bracing [for AIPAC's spending], yes, and it is alarming in a cycle where five seats are open, which almost never happens in Illinois,” said a Democratic strategist working on Illinois races, granted anonymity to speak candidly. “AIPAC is actively trying to buy three or possibly four seats.”</p> 
<p>The winner of Thursday’s special primary election in New Jersey will face Joe Hathaway, a Republican councilmember from Randolph, N.J., on April 16, to fill the remainder of Sherrill’s term. Then, Democrats will hold another primary on June 2.</p> 
<p>Though some centrist Democrats fretted that Mejia’s potential victory could hurt their chances to hold on to the seat, pollster Patrick Murray said a Republican victory is highly unlikely, both in the special general election in April or in November.</p> 
<p>“It’s just so anti-Trump now,” he said. “We saw in the 2025 general election that there was more motivation among Democrats than Republicans. And that mood still holds.”</p> 
<p>Of the upcoming primary season, where dark money from an array of outside groups is expected to saturate Democratic primaries, Malinowski called it “a significant challenge to the Democratic Party that needs to be addressed.”</p> 
<p>“My election was the beta test,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misstated the month in which Illinois holds its primaries.</i><br><i>Madison Fernandez and Matt Friedman contributed reporting.&nbsp;</i><br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists on the week in politics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2026/02/06/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00768100</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's an offering of the best of this week's crop, picked fresh off the Toonosphere. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-3000-d0f8-adde-fa5ae1500000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>María Corina Machado and Brian Tyler Cohen | The Conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/05/maria-corina-machado-and-brian-tyler-cohen-the-conversation-1905679</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2fe9-d647-addc-afef97df0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 23:59:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">María Corina Machado and Brian Tyler Cohen | The Conversation</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6388840382112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/241d3cd0-e92f-49d0-8b16-1316983118fb/a7378da3-b676-4cbe-ae0a-4fe53c133dc3/main.mp4" src="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/241d3cd0-e92f-49d0-8b16-1316983118fb/1c7ae846-1f64-420e-a7e5-cc3c2f7289aa/1280x720/match/image.jpg">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump’s geopolitical tensions spill into the Winter Olympics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/05/trump-geopolitics-winter-olympics-00766982</link>
      <description>Beating the Americans will feel even sweeter for the U.S.’ top allies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2e7a-d0f8-adde-fe7a2d150000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 16:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/09/06/3ed184ff4948a6d0d448835de9b2/winterolympicsjdvance.jpeg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Natália Delgado/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>The Olympics have long collided with geopolitics — and President Donald Trump has made this year's games no different.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/09/06/3ed184ff4948a6d0d448835de9b2/winterolympicsjdvance.jpeg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump won’t be representing the U.S. at the opening ceremony of the Italian Olympic Games in Milan’s famous San Siro Stadium. But his shadow will surely loom over the two-week-long sporting spectacle, which kicks off Friday.</p> 
<p>The president’s repeated jabs at longtime partners, his inconsistent tariff policy and repeated plays for Greenland have shown just how much he's shifted the traditional world order. The resulting <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/carney-trump-davos-great-powers-00736740" target="_blank">international “rupture,” as described by Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney</a> in Davos last month, has turned beating the Americans in Italy from a crowning sporting achievement to an even greater moral imperative for the president's rivals.</p> 
<p>“This is life and death,” said Charlie Angus, a former member of Parliament in Canada with the New Democratic Party and prominent Trump critic. “If it’s the semifinals and we’re playing against the United States, it’s no longer a game. And that’s profound.”</p> 
<p>The Trump administration has big plans for these Olympics, according to a State Department memo viewed by POLITICO. It hopes to “promote the United States as a global leader in international sports” and build momentum for what the White House sees as a “Decade of Sport in America,” which will see the country host the Summer Olympics and Paralympics in 2028 and the Winter Olympics and Paralympics in 2034, as well as the FIFA World Cup this summer.</p> 
<p>But a combative administration may well complicate matters.</p> 
<p>He’s <a href="https://x.com/VP/status/2019414633753506049" target="_blank">sending Vice President JD Vance</a>, a longtime critic of Europe’s leaders, to lead the presidential delegation in Milan. Then there’s ICE. News that American federal immigration agents <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/its-not-like-the-ss-are-coming-italy-quell-ice-furor-winter-olympics/" target="_blank">would be on the ground</a> providing security during the games sparked widespread fury throughout the country.</p> 
<p>Trump has also clashed with many of the countries vying to top the leaderboards in Milan. Since returning to the White House in January, he’s antagonized Norway, which took home the most <a href="https://www.olympics.com/en/olympic-games/beijing-2022/medals" target="_blank">medals in the 2022 Beijing Winter Olympics</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/norway-pm-store-says-us-trump-peace-prize-snub-for-greenland-ambitions/" target="_blank">over a perceived Nobel Peace Prize snub</a> and clashed repeatedly with Canada, which finished fourth.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/e6/0c/9b65401a43dd8d7af4b82b4001e9/france-italy-olympics-ice-hockey-47526.jpg" alt="Italy goalie Gabriella Durante skates before a women's hockey game against France at the Milano Santagiulia ice hockey arena at the Milan Cortina Winter Olympics, in Milan, on Feb. 5, 2026. " data-portal-copyright="Darryl Dyck /The Canadian Press via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26036533347526" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Italy goalie Gabriella Durante skates before a women's hockey game against France at the Milano Santagiulia ice hockey arena at the Milan Cortina Winter Olympics, in Milan, on Feb. 5, 2026. "/><p>“We’re looking at the world in a very different light,” Angus said. “And we’re looking at a next-door neighbor who makes increasingly unhinged threats towards us. So to go to international games and pretend that we’re all one happy family, well, that’s gone.”</p> 
<p>Trump has also <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/trump-on-macrons-sunglasses-what-the-hell-happened/" target="_blank">sparred with Emmanuel Macron</a>, the president of France (the 13th-place finisher in Beijing), and threatened a military incursion in pushing Denmark (a Scandinavian country which <a href="https://www.olympics.com/en/news/look-to-the-past-the-three-nations-with-a-single-olympic-winter-games-medal" target="_blank">curiously hasn’t medaled in the Winter Olympics since 1998</a>) to cede Greenland.</p> 
<p>All while seeming to placate Russia, whose <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/6991592/2026/01/28/winter-olympics-russians-individual-neutral-athletes/" target="_blank">athletes competed under a neutral flag in 2022 due to doping sanctions</a> and secured the second-most medals in the Beijing games, which ended just days before President Vladimir Putin invaded Ukraine.</p> 
<p>The Olympics have <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/5-times-the-winter-olympics-got-political/" target="_blank">long collided with geopolitics</a>, from Russia’s ban in response to its war in Ukraine to <a href="https://www.olympics.com/en/news/why-south-africa-barred-from-the-olympics-apartheid" target="_blank">South Africa’s 32-year-long exclusion</a> as punishment for apartheid. And Beijing’s time in the limelight was marred by a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/12/06/white-house-boycott-beijing-olympics-523817" target="_blank">U.S. diplomatic boycott over China’s treatment of its Uyghur population</a>. </p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Anna Kelly said Trump’s political agenda of putting America First is paying off.</p> 
<p>“Fairer trade deals are leveling the playing field for our farmers and workers, NATO allies are taking greater responsibility for their own defense, and drugs and criminals are no longer entering our country,” she said. “Instead of taking bizarre vendettas against American athletes, foreign leaders should follow the President’s lead by ending unfettered migration, halting Green New Scam policies, and promoting peace through strength.”</p> 
<p>When reached for comment, the State Department deferred to the White House about the political ramifications of the games. A State Department spokesperson also highlighted the role that its Diplomatic Security Service would serve as the security lead for Americans throughout Olympic and Paralympic competition.</p> 
<p>Hockey, arguably one of the winter Olympic Games’ highest-profile sports, has already been roiled by Trump’s global agenda. Just <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/20/hockey-trump-canada-tariffs-00002396" target="_blank">look at last year’s 4 Nations Face-Off</a>, which pitted the U.S. and Canada against each other in preliminary play and then again in the final.</p> 
<p>Canadian fans booed the American national anthem mercilessly when the two sides faced off in Montreal. Trump called the U.S. locker room on the morning of the final and showered the Great North with incessant 51st state gibes, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/21/trudeau-trump-us-canada-hockey-four-nations-final-00205421" target="_blank">then-Prime Minister Justin Trudeau responded boisterously</a> when Canada won the championship in overtime.</p> 
<p>“You can’t take our country — and you can’t take our game,” he wrote.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://www.espn.com/olympics-mens-ice-hockey/game/_/gameId/401845676/denmark-united-states" target="_blank">American men’s team will play Denmark</a> in Milan — fittingly — on Valentine’s Day, and could see the Canadians at the medal rounds.</p> 
<p>“I'm sure they'll concentrate on the events they compete in rather than get involved in politics,” Anders Vistisen, a member of the European Parliament from Denmark, said of his compatriots in a statement. “Maybe Trump's antics will give them even more motivation? Who knows?”</p> 
<p>Elsewhere in Italy, Americans Sean Doherty, Maxime Germain, Campbell Wright and Paul Schommer will match up against 2022 champion Quentin Fillon Maillet from France in biathlon throughout the games. And Canadian short track speedskater and medal favorite William Dandjinou will look to hold off multiple Americans at the Milano Ice Skating Arena.</p> 
<p>“With the current American president, no one knows what he will do or say tomorrow,” said legendary goaltender Dominik Hasek, a <a href="https://www.olympics.com/en/athletes/dominik-hasek" target="_blank">gold medalist with Czechia in the 1998 Nagano Games</a> and a one-time rumored presidential candidate in his home nation. “If he doesn't make negative comments about athletes from other countries in the coming weeks, everything will be fine. But that could change very quickly after one of his frequent hateful attacks.”</p> 
<p>Hasek, a <a href="https://www.espn.com/nhl/story/_/id/44815228/czech-leaders-condemn-russian-threats-dominik-hasek" target="_blank">frequent critic of Putin’s war in Ukraine</a>, said Trump “has antagonized most of the people of the democratic world with his attitudes and actions.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/0e/f4/612fbe49403b9c4c0e5891f7212e/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2251647748" alt="“With the current American president, no one knows what he will do or say tomorrow,” said legendary goaltender Dominik Hasek, a Gold medalist with Czechia in the 1998 Nagano Games." data-portal-copyright="Robert Sullivan/AFP via Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2251647748" data-licensor-name="AFP via Getty Images" data-title="“With the current American president, no one knows what he will do or say tomorrow,” said legendary goaltender Dominik Hasek, a Gold medalist with Czechia in the 1998 Nagano Games."/><p>That doesn’t exactly scream “Faster, Higher, Stronger — Together,” the <a href="https://www.olympics.com/ioc/olympic-motto" target="_blank">Olympic motto</a> revamped by the IOC in 2021.</p> 
<p>“It was personal,” Angus, the former Canadian lawmaker, said of the tense Canada-U.S. showdown in the 4 Nations Face-Off last year. “This was deeply personal. We were at the moment of people brawling in the stands, and that was because of Donald Trump and the constant insults. He turned that game into war.”</p> 
<p>But now at the Olympics, the <a href="https://support.olympics.com/hc/en-gb/articles/43002339567763-How-many-countries-will-participate-in-the-Winter-Olympics-2026#:~:text=Milano%20Cortina%202026-,How%20many%20countries%20will%20participate%20in%20the%20Winter%20Olympics%202026,disciplines%20and%20six%20Paralympic%20sports" target="_blank">U.S. is just one of more than 90 nations competing</a>. And Trump’s international critics say they’re determined to not let their anger with Trump ruin the games — if just not to give him the satisfaction.</p> 
<p>“People are done with Donald Trump’s flagrant attempts to goad us and poke at us and insult us,” Angus said. “It’s like water off our back. We’re a much tougher people than we were last year.”</p> 
<p><i>Nahal Toosi contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Virginia Supreme Court will hear redistricting challenge</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/04/virginia-supreme-court-will-hear-redistricting-challenge-00765490</link>
      <description>The state's High Court will decide if Virginia Democrats' gerrymander push can move forward.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2a61-d3b5-addf-eae57fcf0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 16:04:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d7/86/57d5b15d4097aa54f5ddc043dc1e/virginia-legislature-51563.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Steve Helber/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Virginia House Speaker Don Scott (D) speaks at POLITICO Transition of Power: What’s next for Virginia in December. He’s one of the leading Democrats pushing for an aggressive redrawing of Virginia’s Congressional seats ahead of the midterms.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d7/86/57d5b15d4097aa54f5ddc043dc1e/virginia-legislature-51563.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Virginia’s state Supreme Court will decide whether state Democrats’ gerrymander push can proceed after an appeals court on Wednesday pushed the case to the high court.</p> 
<p>The state Circuit Court of Appeals, in a motion, stated that the case is of “such imperative public importance as to justify the deviation from normal appellate practice and to require prompt decision in the Supreme Court.”</p> 
<p>The move comes after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/virginia-redistricting-blocked-court-ruling-00750060" target="_blank">a court in Tazewell County last week blocked</a> Virginia Democrats from going forward with gerrymandering, ruling that the Democrat-led Legislature had wrongly approved a constitutional amendment that would allow for mid-decade redrawing of congressional districts ahead of the midterms this fall.</p> 
<p>The move is a potential bright spot for Democrats, who had been stymied by the lower court ruling blocking the party’s attempt to gain upwards of four seats in the midterms through redistricting. Currently, Democrats hold six seats in the state while Republicans control five.</p> 
<p>The Republican-backed group Virginians for Fair Maps, one of the main organizations against redistricting in the state, declined to comment.</p> 
<p>Virginians for Fair Elections, the Democrat-affiliated group launched last month to urge voters to approve the measure, declined to comment on the record.</p> 
<p>Last October, Democratic lawmakers began the process of redrawing maps in the state, an effort that only gained traction after voters elected Democratic Gov. Abigail Spanberger in the November election and the GOP lost 13 seats in the House of Delegates.</p> 
<p>Virginia Democrats had been so confident prior to the Tazewell County court ruling that party leaders vowed to unveil new maps it wanted Virginia voters to approve by the end of last month, with promises of unveiling a map that goes as far as 10-1 in favor of their party.</p> 
<p>Virginia is seen as the top prize in Democrats’ redistricting push, especially if Republican-led Florida redraws its maps under Gov. Ron DeSantis. More GOP-led states could also move to draw more red-leaning states if the Supreme Court rules to strike down portions of the Voting Rights Act.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>February</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/cartoons/2026/02/04/matt-wuerker-cartoons-february-2026-00764928</link>
      <description>Politico cartoons from the desk of Matt Wuerker</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2a30-d3b5-addf-eaf48b3e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 14:52:11 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Matt Wuerker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Matt Wuerker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shapiro needs big policy wins for a 2028 run. He’s gunning for a Democratic trifecta to achieve them.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/04/shapiro-pennsylvania-democratic-trifecta-00764233</link>
      <description>The Pennsylvania governor is mounting an aggressive down-ballot push this year alongside his reelection bid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2947-d3b5-addf-e9c76fd40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/55/87/7405ed8f4b62a97fe265dbad30ad/pennsylvania-budget-91798.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Matt Rourke/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro speaks at last year's budget address in Harrisburg.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/55/87/7405ed8f4b62a97fe265dbad30ad/pennsylvania-budget-91798.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro has made his ability to navigate a sharply divided Legislature a core part of his national sales pitch. But as 2028 approaches, what he really wants is a Democratic trifecta in Harrisburg.</p> 
<p>Shapiro helped Democrats flip the state House in 2022 when he won the governor’s mansion. But the Republican-controlled Senate has been his Achilles' heel since, stymieing his attempts to pass core Democratic policies like raising <a href="https://pro.bloomberglaw.com/insights/labor-employment/these-states-have-the-highest-and-lowest-minimum-wages/#lowest-minimum-wage" target="_blank">one of the lowest state minimum wages in the country</a>. And the split Legislature left Shapiro mired in a monthslong budget standoff last year that <a href="https://www.spotlightpa.org/news/2025/10/pennsylvania-budget-impasse-county-crisis-layoffs-service-cuts-capitol/#:~:text=Some%20of%20the%20counties%20affected%20by%20the,than%20the%20Federal%20Reserve's%20current%20baseline%20rates." target="_blank">held up billions of dollars in state funding</a> for counties, schools and nonprofits.</p> 
<p>Now, Shapiro is leading the charge to help Democrats wrest back the chamber from Republican control by a slim 27-23 majority and expand their single-seat majority in the House — part of an aggressive down-ballot push the governor is undertaking alongside his own reelection bid.</p> 
<p>Shapiro has repeatedly voiced his desire to win unified control of the commonwealth both in private conversations with donors and in public. He’s touted what he could do with it — outlining a policy agenda rooted in increasing affordability that includes raising the state’s minimum wage and boosting energy production, including through renewables.</p> 
<p>When asked his second-term goals and whether he needs unified Democratic control to achieve them, the governor said his record proves “I can bring the Republicans and Democrats together to get stuff done.”</p> 
<p>“There are some things, though, that the Republican Senate has blocked me on that I would like us to be able to get done,” he said at an event in Washington last week. “And certainly, having a trifecta would allow me to do that.”</p> 
<p>During his state budget address Tuesday, Shapiro unloaded on Senate Republicans who’ve stood in the way of his priorities, saying they’ve “refused to act” on raising wages and needling them to “stop making excuses” on advancing <a href="https://www.cityandstatepa.com/policy/2025/01/what-know-about-gov-josh-shapiros-lightning-plan-pa-energy/402665/" target="_blank">his energy plans</a>. His voice ringing with emotion, he accused them of “cowering to … special interests” and “tying justice for abused kids to your pet political projects” over stalling enhanced protections for sexual abuse victims.</p> 
<p>Shapiro’s effort to secure unified control of Harrisburg will serve as a critical test of his coattails in the nation’s largest swing state. And it’s a prerequisite for him to be able to score some big-ticket liberal policy wins he can brag about on a 2028 presidential primary stage that could be jam-packed with governors who already have their own achievements to tout.</p> 
<p>“If he can add to the appeal he already has with things like a higher minimum wage, with other pieces of the puzzle that state government can do to make things more affordable, it just gives his candidacy and his message that extra spark that is missing right now,” said longtime Democratic strategist Pete Giangreco, who worked on Barack Obama’s and Amy Klobuchar’s presidential campaigns but is not working for any likely 2028 contenders.</p> 
<p>But Pennsylvania Democrats haven’t had a trifecta in three decades. And they face a narrow path to achieving it even in a year when national Democrats are bullish on a <a href="https://www.politico.com/interactives/2025/democrats-2026-midterm-flips-redistricting-data/" target="_blank">blue wave</a>.</p> 
<p>Just half the Pennsylvania Senate is on the ballot this year, and operatives on both sides say the battlefield is even smaller, pointing to a handful of districts in the Philadelphia suburbs through the Lehigh Valley and more rural swaths of the state. Prognosticators <a href="https://centerforpolitics.org/crystalball/handicapping-the-2026-state-legislative-map-a-first-look/" target="_blank">say the Pennsylvania Senate “leans Republican.”</a></p> 
<p>“If you look at the Republican map on who needs to be defeated, it’s a lot of more rural, red areas,” said Pennsylvania-based GOP consultant Josh Novotney. “Nothing’s impossible in such a bad year for Republicans. But it’s going to be tough.”</p> 
<p>But Keystone State Democrats are emboldened by last year’s elections. The party <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/04/democrats-win-pennsylvania-supreme-court-00633675" target="_blank">swept judicial retention races for the state’s highest court</a> and <a href="https://www.spotlightpa.org/news/2025/03/special-election-pennsylvania-lancaster-allegheny-house-senate/" target="_blank">flipped a state Senate seat</a> during a special election in a district Democrats said President Donald Trump carried by 15 percentage points in 2024. They’re encouraged by Democratic wins and overperformances across the country over the past year.</p> 
<p>And, top Democrats say, they have Shapiro.</p> 
<p>The governor remains highly popular, with an approval rating that’s <a href="https://poll.qu.edu/poll-release?releaseid=3933" target="_blank">cracked 60 percent</a> in <a href="https://pro.morningconsult.com/trackers/governor-approval-ratings" target="_blank">some surveys</a>. He’s a fundraising juggernaut who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/shapiro-launches-reelection-pennsylvania-00715593" target="_blank">amassed a $30 million war chest</a> to unload against likely GOP rival Stacy Garrity, the state treasurer, who raised just a fraction of that amount.</p> 
<p>Democrats rode to power in the Pennsylvania House in 2022 on what <a href="https://x.com/RepBradford/status/2015576224521752678?s=20" target="_blank">one top lawmaker described as “Shapiro’s landslide coattails,”</a> and they credit the governor for helping them hold their razor-thin majority in 2024, even as Trump won Pennsylvania and Democrats lost every statewide election.</p> 
<p>“He is a huge part of the reason we have the majority. He’s a huge part of the reason that we were able to hold the majority in 2024,” said state Rep. Mike Schlossberg, the House majority whip. “I have no doubt he will lean in very, very heavily to making sure that we not only expand our majority in the House, but hopefully take control of the Senate — something that’s realistically in play for the first time probably in my entire career.”</p> 
<p>Shapiro poured $1.25 million into the Pennsylvania House Democrats’ campaign committee in 2024 and helped raise another $1 million toward defending their majority that year. He also donated $250,000 to state Senate Democrats’ campaign committee. And he cut ads and hit the campaign trail in key legislative districts.</p> 
<p>Last year, Shapiro gave the state party $250,000 to fund infrastructure improvements heading into the midterms, with a promise of more to come. His political team is in “regular communication” with Pennsylvania Democrats’ campaign arms, said state Sen. Vincent Hughes, a Philadelphia Democrat who chairs the party’s Senate campaign committee.</p> 
<p>The governor’s political operation declined to share an estimate of how much Shapiro plans to spend down-ticket this year, or where he plans to campaign. Manuel Bonder, a spokesperson for Shapiro, said the governor “has a long track record of working to elect Democrats up and down the ballot” and will “continue to focus on” that alongside his reelection bid.</p> 
<p>Shapiro and his allies have <a href="https://www.spotlightpa.org/news/2025/08/septa-cuts-josh-shapiro-transit-funding-senate-republican-plan-capitol/#:~:text=Shapiro%20added%20that%20he%20thinks,the%20good%20people%20of%20Pennsylvania.%E2%80%9D" target="_blank">repeatedly lamented</a> Republican roadblocks to an agenda that includes raising wages, boosting housing and energy production and securing sustainable funding for public transportation. House Speaker Joanna McClinton, a Philadelphia Democrat, accused the GOP of “political gamesmanship” in an interview, claiming the opposition is trying to “keep down the productivity” to hurt Shapiro and state Democrats in 2026 and beyond.</p> 
<p>Senate Republican leaders signaled more friction to come as they fired back on several fronts after Shapiro’s speech Tuesday, skewering his plan to overhaul the state’s energy sector, accusing him of being “more interested in the political talking point” on hiking wages to $15 an hour (while indicating they’re open to compromise) and saying there are “different paths” to helping victims of abuse.</p> 
<p>As 2028 looms, Democratic legislative leaders and political strategists acknowledged the potential political benefit of a trifecta for Shapiro, who could get a boost from both turning a purple state blue and passing policies that could pad a potential presidential platform.</p> 
<p>“If he can help us win the trifecta, and then use it to actually govern and get good results — or as he likes to say, ‘get shit done’ — that looks really good at the national level,” Schlossberg said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Choppier seas await Mamdani-backed candidates after Diana Moreno's landslide win</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/04/choppier-seas-await-mamdani-backed-candidates-after-diana-morenos-landslide-win-00764051</link>
      <description>A pair of June congressional primaries Mamdani has endorsed in are expected to be far more competitive than Moreno’s race.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-290b-d647-addc-abcfee360000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 10:32:43 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/df/f1/3214e36240ed87010464559b4523/copy-of-dsc-8516.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Silas Emerson Harris</media:credit>
        <media:title>Diana Moreno seen with Mayor Zohran Mamdani at a recent campaign rally.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/df/f1/3214e36240ed87010464559b4523/copy-of-dsc-8516.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Emily Ngo and Chris Sommerfeldt</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Emily Ngo and Chris Sommerfeldt</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NEW YORK — New York City Mayor Zohran Mamdani’s pick to succeed him in the state Assembly cruised to an easy victory Tuesday night. But Diana Moreno’s win in that Queens special election is likely the last cakewalk we’ll see from a Mamdani-backed candidate in the near future.</p> 
<p>The new mayor has endorsed <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/brad-lander-set-to-challenge-rep-dan-goldman-from-the-left-00682619" target="_blank">Brad Lander in his quest</a> to unseat Rep. Dan Goldman in New York’s 10th Congressional District and Assemblymember Claire Valdez for the NY-07 seat being vacated by Rep. Nydia Velázquez.</p> 
<p>The pair of Democratic congressional primaries is expected to be far more competitive than Moreno’s race, raising a central question: How far can a Mamdani endorsement get you?</p> 
<p>“We’re testing that out,” said Grace Mausser, co-chair of the Democratic Socialists of America’s New York City chapter, which has endorsed both Moreno and Valdez, but not Lander. “He has a lot of hard resources that come with an endorsement: his impressive volunteer and donor lists, his strong reach on social media … There’s also the soft power that we’re testing out now, right? Who is the leader of left and progressive politics in New York right now?”</p> 
<p>Mamdani has so far been more involved in boosting Valdez than Lander.</p> 
<p>The mayor appeared with Valdez — a Queens lawmaker, former United Auto Workers union organizer and the first elected official to stand with Mamdani in his campaign for mayor — at an event the day after she launched her bid. He also filmed a <a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DUBCgnIDvpH/" target="_blank">whimsical social media video</a> set in a subway station to boost her fundraising.</p> 
<p>Valdez is running <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/04/nyregion/reynoso-velazquez-dsa-congress.html" target="_blank">against Antonio Reynoso,</a> the Brooklyn borough president who Velázquez has endorsed as her preferred successor. Queens City Council Member Julie Won also recently entered the race in the progressive Brooklyn and Queens district.</p> 
<p>The mayor has been largely hands-off in Lander’s campaign after endorsing the former city comptroller on the day of his launch for Congress. Lander, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/13/mamdani-lander-cross-endorsing-mayor-00405357" target="_blank">who cross-endorsed Mamdani</a> in last year’s mayoral race, is running in Brooklyn and Manhattan against an incumbent with more than three times as much campaign cash on hand and the backing of Democratic House leadership, including Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries.</p> 
<p>A political adviser to Mamdani said his team is still assessing how much to get involved in the two congressional contests and cautioned against reading anything into the fact that the mayor has been more involved in Valdez’s race so far. The adviser said the Mamdani team is waiting to make major moves in NY-10 pending the outcome of a court case that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/new-york-judge-sides-with-democrats-on-redistricting-case-threatening-gop-control-of-staten-island-00740171" target="_blank">could scramble the lines</a> of the district in such a way that Goldman may run in the neighboring 11th District instead.</p> 
<p>Regardless, the Mamdani adviser, who was granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy, said the mayor simply lending his name to Lander and Valdez “already carries a lot of weight that these campaigns can make the most of.”</p> 
<p>“His direct involvement is always going to be second to governing,” said the aide. “Ninety-nine percent of his energy is going to be focused on running the city.”</p> 
<p>The politics-versus-governance balance is part of Mamdani’s clash with Velázquez, the highly respected progressive who effectively warned him in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/nyregion/nydia-velazquez-antonio-reynoso-mamdani.html" target="_blank">a New York Times interview</a> to stay in his lane.</p> 
<p>And the mayor does have a lot of work to do at the helm of the country’s largest city. June’s congressional primaries fall around the same time he and the City Council will be putting finishing touches on the city budget amid <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/mamdani-ratchets-up-tax-the-rich-rhetoric-as-hochul-launches-a-reelection-run-00753931" target="_blank">serious fiscal headwinds.</a></p> 
<p>“I don’t know if that was the wisest thing for him to do because the job of being mayor is so big,” Democratic strategist Lupe Todd-Medina said, arguing Mamdani could end up in a situation where he's not able to stump for Lander and Valdez as much as they want and need him to due to the sheer burden of governing New York City. </p> 
<p>As June's primaries still loom more than four months away, a Lander campaign official, granted anonymity to share sensitive considerations, said his team is also still waiting to see if <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/new-york-judge-sides-with-democrats-on-redistricting-case-threatening-gop-control-of-staten-island-00740171" target="_blank">a court decision could rip up the lines of NY-10</a>.</p> 
<p>But if the race ends up competitive, the Lander aide said his team is confident Mamdani will help fundraise and campaign for the former comptroller. The fact that Mamdani hasn’t done so yet, the aide said, is understandable since the mayor has been focused on governing in his first month in office.</p> 
<p>The two House primaries have different dynamics but they’ll determine whether Mamdani can replicate the magic that catapulted him from relative obscurity to the nation’s second toughest job.</p> 
<p>“He has a lot at stake by pushing in some chips on two fronts, but I think he has more at stake in the 7th District,” said Michael Lange, an analyst who specializes in progressive politics. Valdez “is a really close ally who comes from his political movement and his political home.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inside Trump’s critical minerals push | Energy Pod</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/02/04/what-to-know-about-trumps-12-billion-critical-minerals-strategy-energy-pod-1904859</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2683-d4f7-a9dd-27d76f4e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 05:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">Inside Trump’s critical minerals push | Energy Pod</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6388762345112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/4894ea96-02bf-46b8-9b1a-66c756d58b40/72d3453b-5cfa-43c3-9c76-7a4429719b04/main.mp4" src="4b/37/46876ca44490aecb28e241f451e1/ep-2-hannahtle.png">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats want to find out why their voters stayed home in 2024 — and how to get them to show up this year</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/04/democrats-2026-listening-program-00763666</link>
      <description>The DNC is launching an outreach campaign to win over voters who skipped the 2024 election with a new "listening first approach."</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-25d9-d345-a3bf-27fdd9b40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/3c/cf/24b3c60b4146b42792831999bf0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2182507632">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Olivier Touron/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Voters line up to cast their ballots in-person at a polling station in Tempe, Arizona, on Election Day, November 5, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/3c/cf/24b3c60b4146b42792831999bf0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2182507632" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are launching a new program Wednesday to try to reach voters in their corner who opted to stay home in 2024 instead of voting against then-candidate Donald Trump, as the party continues its search for its identity in the second Trump era.</p> 
<p>The Democratic National Committee program — details of which were shared first with POLITICO — targets over a million voters they view as likely Democrats in battleground House districts who voted in 2020 but didn’t vote four years later.</p> 
<p>The large-scale voter contact operation called “Local Listeners” is a tacit acknowledgement of one of the ways Democrats fell short in 2024, when then-Vice President Kamala Harris failed to engender enough enthusiasm from likely Democrats frustrated with the Biden administration’s economic agenda and its handling of the war between Israel and Hamas.</p> 
<p>“We didn’t lose to Donald Trump. We lost to the couch,” DNC Deputy Executive Director Libby Schneider said in an interview. “We saw our voters, many of our important voters, stay home. Obviously, that is a trend that cannot continue.”</p> 
<p>A key element of the strategy, according to the party, will be training volunteers to engage infrequent voters with a “listening first” approach that prioritizes “active listening” and “having difficult conversations about politics.”</p> 
<p>Part of President Donald Trump’s winning strategy included engaging with unlikely voters his campaign identified as being potential Republicans. Trump aggressively courted people who had skipped previous elections, focusing predominantly on young men, and ultimately defeated Harris among <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/26/2024-election-turnout-trum-00426544" target="_blank">voters who skipped</a> the previous midterm and presidential elections.</p> 
<p>“If we want to keep earning back the trust and support of voters, we have to listen to them,” DNC Chair Ken Martin said in a statement. “The Democratic Party is done with waiting until the last minute to engage voters — these conversations need to happen early and often.”</p> 
<p>Rima Mohammad, an executive board member of the Michigan Democratic Party and a former delegate who represented the “Uncommitted” movement at the Democratic convention in 2024, said she welcomed the attempts to engage voters who remain disenchanted by Democrats.</p> 
<p>“I saw the level of disengagement, the frustration from people about the party, starting with Gaza and now with what's happening now with ICE, what's happening with all these corporate Dems,” Mohammad — who said she ultimately did support Harris — said in an interview.</p> 
<p>“I'm glad that the DNC is doing this. I don't know if it's too late. I think that work should have happened right after Kamala lost,” she added.</p> 
<p>Jenifer Fernandez Ancona, co-founder of liberal donor group Way To Win, said the DNC’s push to win back unreliable voters is supported by her group’s December <a href="https://waytowin.docsend.com/view/e3nfk8hegk97mktb" target="_blank">analysis of the party’s shortcomings</a> in 2024 and the lessons that can be learned ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>“They weren’t uninformed, right?” Ancona said of potential Harris voters who stayed home. “They just didn't like what they heard. So that's why I feel like it's so important for any engagement plan to recognize how kind of burned and cynical these voters are.”</p> 
<p>The outreach to 2024 skippers marks one of the few public strategy shifts acknowledging the roots of Democrats’ electoral defeat to Trump, following a year of heated internal debate over the direction of the party. In December, the DNC announced it would not be <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/dnc-kills-its-own-public-2024-autopsy-00697403" target="_blank">publicly releasing an autopsy report</a> diagnosing the causes of the party’s losses, in part to redirect focus to Democrats’ electoral victories in 2025.</p> 
<p>Schneider said the outreach to voters who stayed home in 2024 is an extension of the introspection party organizers undertook following Trump’s victory.</p> 
<p>“The work started immediately after we lost, and it was sort of a self-reflection of ... what can we do differently and what is within our control?” she said. "This is one of those things that it's a no-brainer that it should live with the DNC, and that we should have been doing it for a lot longer.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans are freaking out about Hispanic voters after a Texas upset</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/republicans-hispanic-voters-texas-special-00763560</link>
      <description>Democrats flipped a deep-red state senate district over the weekend that has the party worried about November.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-25be-d5e0-a1fe-affe01e80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:56:13 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/11/74/1b0726414d549e42ba7e117b7668/201101-trump-az-ap-773.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Andrew Harnik/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump arrives for a Latinos for Trump Coalition roundtable at Arizona Grand Resort &amp;amp; Spa in Phoenix on Sept. 14, 2020.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/11/74/1b0726414d549e42ba7e117b7668/201101-trump-az-ap-773.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republicans are in full-out panic mode over their plunging support with Hispanic voters after losing a special election in a ruby-red Texas district over the weekend.</p> 
<p>On Saturday, a Democrat posted a 14-point victory in a Fort Worth-based state senate district President Donald Trump had won by 17 points in 2024, a staggering swing that was powered by significant shifts across the district’s Hispanic areas.</p> 
<p>It's the clearest sign yet that the GOP’s newfound coalition that propelled Trump’s return to the White House may be short-lived. Many Republicans are warning the party needs to change course on immigration, focus on bread-and-butter economic issues and start pouring money into competitive races — or risk getting stomped in November.</p> 
<p>Polling already showed that Republicans were rapidly losing support from Hispanic voters. But the electoral results were a confirmation of that drop.</p> 
<p>“It should be an eye-opener to all of us that we all need to pick up the pace,” U.S. Rep. Tony Gonzales, a Republican from a majority-Hispanic district in South Texas, said in an interview. “The candidate has to do their part, the party has to do their part. And then those of us in the arena, we have to do our part to help them as well.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas) told reporters Tuesday that the election was a “very concerning outcome.” Texas Lt. Gov. Dan Patrick <a href="https://x.com/DanPatrick/status/2017858075932217719" target="_blank">posted on X that the results should be a</a> “wake-up call for Republicans across Texas. Our voters cannot take anything for granted.” Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis said “a swing of this magnitude is not something that can be dismissed.”</p> 
<p>Taylor Rehmet, the Democrat who flipped the state Senate seat over the weekend, made huge gains with Hispanic voters amid national pushback to the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration enforcement tactics and widespread economic frustration across demographic groups.</p> 
<p>Ahead of the election, Texas Gov. Greg Abbott — an immigration hardliner who bused migrants to Democratic-led cities during the Biden administration — said the White House needed to “recalibrate” on its immigration crackdowns following the shooting of Alex Pretti by an immigration officer in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>“That imagery coming out of Minnesota in the last few days has had a huge impact on not only Hispanic voters, but swing voters, independents in Texas and around the country,” said Texas GOP consultant Brendan Steinhauser. “What's transpired there has definitely led to a bit of a political backlash.”</p> 
<p>As Republicans panic, Democrats are feeling a renewed jolt of optimism after they swept statewide races last year in Virginia and New Jersey. They believe they found a winning formula with Rehmet, whose working-class biography as a union leader, Air Force veteran and Lockheed Martin machinist resonated with voters, along with his narrow focus on local issues like maintaining public school funding.</p> 
<p>Tory Gavito, president of Democratic donor network Way to Win, said she received excited texts from several major donors over the weekend after the win. “Knowing it's a wave year, this just adds a little bit of more wind in our sails,” she said. “It's not just a question around Texas, it's a question around Texas and Mississippi and Alabama and what does this mean for lots of places.”</p> 
<p>Texas Republicans have the most to worry about of any in their party about a major Hispanic snapback towards Democrats.</p> 
<p>Hispanics are now the largest ethnic group in Texas, making up 40 percent of the population. Trump carried Latinos in the state in 2024, exit polls showed, a massive swing from earlier elections, and Republicans had been making especially strong gains with rural, more conservative Hispanic voters in the Rio Grande Valley. But as Texas Democrats look to win a U.S. Senate election for the first time since 1988, they’re eyeing an opportunity to pull those voters back in.</p> 
<p>“They are leaving in droves and going in the opposite direction,” said Javier Palomarez, president and CEO of the U.S. Hispanic Business Council. “This is a warning sign.”</p> 
<p>And Texas Republicans also banked on retaining at least some of their newfound Hispanic support when they redrew their Congressional map last year, creating several majority-Hispanic districts that Trump would have carried by double digits last year. That includes rejiggering district lines for two top GOP targets, Democratic Reps. Henry Cuellar and Vicente Gonzalez, as well as a third district outside San Antonio.</p> 
<p>“They've banged three of these five new Republican seats on a demographic that Democrats were never able to turn out for 30-40 years, " said GOP consultant and Trump critic Mike Madrid, referring to young, Hispanic male voters. But now, Trump’s hardline immigration policies have “angered and upset them.”</p> 
<p><i>Samuel Benson and Alex Gangitano contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pirro appears to walk back threats to arrest gun owners in DC</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/jeanine-pirro-second-amendment-washington-00762347</link>
      <description>The US attorney previously said anyone who brought a firearm to Washington would go to jail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-247f-df17-afbf-7d7f506b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 12:39:35 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/cd/a6/21590adc44c3a85c8c95fe779c9a/fbi-pipe-bomb-investigation-36359.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Brandon/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>U.S. Attorney Jeanine Pirro speaks during a news conference at the Justice Department on Dec. 4, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/cd/a6/21590adc44c3a85c8c95fe779c9a/fbi-pipe-bomb-investigation-36359.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>D.C. U.S. Attorney Jeanine Pirro appeared to walk back a previous threat to arrest anyone who brings a gun to Washington amid an uproar from Second Amendment groups.</p> 
<p>The backtrack came after Pirro’s initial comments sparked fierce criticism from GOP members of Congress and gun rights advocates. It’s the latest in a series of statements from the administration that have rankled many in the party’s pro-Second Amendment base.</p> 
<p>“I don’t care if you have a license in another district, and I don’t care if you’re a law-abiding gun owner somewhere else — you bring a gun into this district, count on going to jail, and hope you get the gun back” Pirro said during a Monday appearance on Fox News, where she previously hosted the show “Justice with Judge Jeanine.”</p> 
<p>But less than 24 hours later, Pirro attempted to reframe her earlier comments, writing in a social media post that she is “a proud supporter of the Second Amendment.”</p> 
<p>“Washington, D.C. law requires handguns be licensed in the District with the Metropolitan Police Department to be carried into our community,” she wrote in <a href="https://x.com/JudgeJeanine/status/2018681644337500637" target="_blank">a Tuesday morning post on X</a>. “We are focused on individuals who are unlawfully carrying guns and will continue building on that momentum to keep our communities safe.”</p> 
<p>She also referenced the response in <a href="https://x.com/JudgeJeanine/status/2018711681153597756?s=20" target="_blank">a video posted to her social media page</a>, acknowledging that “some people are concerned about something I said yesterday” before further clarifying her position.</p> 
<p>The conservative National Association for Gun Rights swiftly came out in opposition to Pirro’s stance, <a href="https://x.com/gunrights/status/2018449837117563183" target="_blank">calling her remarks</a> “unacceptable and intolerable comments by a sitting US attorney.”</p> 
<p>Kentucky Rep. Thomas Massie, one of the administration’s most frequent critics in the House GOP Conference, <a href="https://x.com/RepThomasMassie/status/2018696857048776767" target="_blank">also denounced Pirro</a>, writing on social media: “Why is a ‘conservative’ judge threatening to arrest gun owners?” Reps. Greg Steube (R-Fla.), Chip Roy (R-Texas) and Andrew Clyde (R-Ga.) criticized the U.S. attorney, too, and <a href="https://x.com/RonDeSantis/status/2018680205120819486" target="_blank">Florida Gov. Ron DeSantis said</a> “Second Amendment rights are not extinguished just because an American visits DC.”</p> 
<p>Washington does not recognize concealed carry permits from other states, and local law requires all firearms in the district to be registered with local police.</p> 
<p>John Commerford, executive director of the National Rifle Association's legislative arm, said Pirro's remarks "highlight the need for Congress to pass <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_38?q=h.r.+38" target="_blank">H.R. 38</a>, the National Concealed Carry Reciprocity Act." That bill, introduced last year by Rep. Richard Hudson (R-N.C.), would allow anyone with a state-issued concealed carry license to carry a firearm in any other state.</p> 
<p>"Law-abiding citizens' right to self-defense should not end simply because they crossed a state line or entered Washington, D.C.," Commerford said in a statement to POLITICO.</p> 
<p>The backlash to Pirro’s comments comes as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/gun-rights-groups-blast-trump-over-minnesota-response-00748217" target="_blank">the Trump administration faces uproar</a> from Second Amendment advocates for its rhetoric following the killing of U.S. citizen Alex Pretti by federal immigration enforcement officers in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>Just days after the fatal shooting, President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/trump-pretti-shouldnt-have-been-carrying-a-gun-00750241" target="_blank">criticized Pretti for carrying a firearm</a>, saying: “I don’t like that he had a gun.”</p> 
<p>Other members of the administration also disparaged Pretti, with White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt contending that carrying a weapon raises “the assumption of risk” during interactions with law enforcement and FBI Director Kash Patel saying “you cannot bring a firearm loaded with multiple magazines to any sort of protest that you want.”</p> 
<p>Those remarks triggered fury from Second Amendment groups like the NRA, which <a href="https://x.com/NRA/status/2015227627464728661" target="_blank">called federal prosecutor Bill Essayli’s response</a> to the shooting “dangerous and wrong.” The rhetoric has also fueled concern that the administration could be <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/2nd-amendment-advocates-issue-dire-warning-over-trumps-pretti-gun-remarks-00758740" target="_blank">harming the GOP’s chances</a> of defending its slim majority in Congress in this fall’s midterm elections.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DHS watchdog investigating use of force by ICE</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-investigation-use-of-force-ice-00761953</link>
      <description>Congressional Democrats urged the inspector general to conduct its review “expeditiously.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-240f-df8c-a99d-f5ffbbc60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:46:04 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/62/85/4c28fa614305b57b4b990c1c50aa/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-99671.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Abbie Parr/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Federal immigration officers deploy tear gas after the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Jan. 24.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/62/85/4c28fa614305b57b4b990c1c50aa/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-99671.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Department of Homeland Security’s inspector general is investigating use of force by ICE agents, according to a letter sent to the watchdog by congressional Democrats.</p> 
<p>The probe comes as the Trump administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">faces intense scrutiny</a> over its nationwide immigration crackdown, which has at times turned violent in recent weeks, sparking concern from a bipartisan group of lawmakers.</p> 
<p>The letter, sent Monday to DHS Inspector General Joseph Cuffari, cites the fatal shootings of U.S. citizens Renee Good and Alex Pretti by federal agents in Minneapolis last month. The letter says the inspector general launched a review on Jan. 8 of the tactics undertaken by ICE and Customs and Border Protection, urging the watchdog to speed up the timeline of the probe.</p> 
<p>“Given the urgency of this situation — with communities facing severe, and sometimes fatal, harm from ICE’s tactics on American streets every day — we request that your office conduct this review expeditiously and share any preliminary findings with Congress and the public on an expedited basis,” the Democrats wrote, according to <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-240c-df17-afbf-7d3f17b40000" target="_blank">a copy of the letter</a> reviewed by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>Democratic Massachusetts Sens. Elizabeth Warren and Ed Markey — who led the letter along with Reps. Ayanna Pressley (D-Mass.), Dan Goldman (D-N.Y.) and Lou Correa (D-Calif.) — first requested the probe in June.</p> 
<p>Thirty-six of their colleagues across the House and Senate signed on to the letter, which was <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/02/03/us/politics/democrats-ice-watchdog-use-force-inquiry.html" target="_blank">first reported by The New York Times</a>.</p> 
<p>The inspector general’s office is conducting an “audit of ICE’s Processes for Investigating and Addressing Allegations of Excessive Use of Force,” per the office’s <a href="https://www.oig.dhs.gov/reports/ongoing-projects?order=field_project_publish_date&amp;sort=desc" target="_blank">list of ongoing projects</a>.</p> 
<p>The probe seeks to “determine whether ICE investigates allegations of excessive use of force and holds personnel accountable in accordance with applicable Federal laws, DHS policies, and ICE directives.”</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for the inspector general’s office and Immigration and Customs Enforcement did not immediately respond to requests for comment on the probe.</p> 
<p>The lawmakers asked the watchdog to prioritize its review in light of the fact that the office routinely misses its own goal of completing audits within 397 days, according to <a href="https://www.gao.gov/assets/gao-26-107341.pdf" target="_blank">a January report</a> from the Government Accountability Office.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration has signaled a willingness to soften its approach to immigration enforcement in recent weeks, with Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/democratic-house-leaders-kristi-noem-impeachment-00749643" target="_blank">threatening to impeach</a> DHS Secretary Kristi Noem and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/senators-block-funding-package-amid-dhs-standoff-00754927" target="_blank">withhold funding for the department</a> over its aggressive tactics.</p> 
<p>In a move seen widely as <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-homan-gop-support-00746206" target="_blank">an attempt to tamp down tensions</a> in Minnesota, the White House pulled Border Patrol commander Gregory Bovino from the state and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">dispatched border czar Tom Homan</a> to Minneapolis last week.</p> 
<p>Following meetings between Homan and Democratic leaders in the state, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/ice-cbp-minneapolis-body-cameras-00760996" target="_blank">Noem announced on Monday</a> that ICE and CBP officers in the city will begin wearing body cameras during immigration enforcement operations there — a key demand from congressional Democrats in their push for reforms of the agencies.</p> 
<p>And White House deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller — a central figure in the administration's immigration enforcement campaign — conceded that CBP agents <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/stephen-miller-cbp-alex-pretti-00751583" target="_blank">may not have been following protocol</a> during the fatal shooting of Pretti, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/doj-investigation-pretti-shooting-minnesota-00757544" target="_blank">which is under review</a> by the Justice Department’s Civil Rights Division and DHS.</p> 
<p>Still, President Donald Trump has aimed to downplay the shift in strategy, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/trump-downplays-changes-in-minnesota-amid-uproar-over-shootings-00750613" target="_blank">rebuffing suggestions that his administration is retreating</a> from its aggressive deportation operation last week and continuing to disparage Pretti.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Election officials grapple with a brain drain as threats rise</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/election-officials-threat-midterms-00761210</link>
      <description>Two new reports portend a potentially bleak future for an American democracy that counts on its engaged citizenry to do everything from count votes to make laws.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2086-df8c-a99d-f5f608610001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9b/a2/66c401e3489b850456ad1a2a7df8/voting-lists-states-sued-95344.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Charles Krupa/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>The new report is particularly concerning because it shows departures haven’t tapered off, marking a 10 percentage point uptick since the group’s 2023 report survey.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9b/a2/66c401e3489b850456ad1a2a7df8/voting-lists-states-sued-95344.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Increasingly violent threats toward and harassment of public officials — from county clerks up to the president — are driving more and more of those figures out of their jobs, a particular concern among local election officials, who have struggled with attrition for years.</p> 
<p>In the years since the 2020 election, roughly 50 percent of top local election officials across 11 western states have left their jobs since November 2020, <a href="https://issueone.org/articles/turning-the-tide-on-turnover/" target="_blank">according to a new report from Issue One</a>, a bipartisan organization that tracks election issues and supports campaign finance reforms.</p> 
<p>The election administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/03/10/election-officials-exhausted-under-threat-00015850" target="_blank">world has been grappling</a> with <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-nightly/2023/06/14/election-officials-sound-the-alarm-about-violence-against-poll-workers-00102041" target="_blank">a significant brain drain</a> since the one-two punch of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/06/16/election-workers-mass-retirements-494790" target="_blank">2020 pandemic and threats arising</a> from conspiracy theories surrounding that year’s election. But the new report — which focuses on election offices in Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Oregon, Utah, Washington and Wyoming — is particularly concerning because it shows departures haven’t tapered off, marking a 10 percentage point uptick since <a href="https://issueone.org/articles/the-high-cost-of-high-turnover/" target="_blank">the group’s 2023 report</a> survey.</p> 
<p>The new data on election officials comes at the same time as another report from the Institute for Strategic Dialogue — <a href="https://www.isdglobal.org/digital_dispatches/tick-tock-traitor-the-rise-of-violent-rhetoric-targeting-us-public-officials/" target="_blank">shared first with POLITICO</a> — found a more than 200 percent increase in violent rhetoric toward public officials when comparing Oct. 2021 to Sept. 2022 with Oct. 2024 to Sept. 2025.</p> 
<p>Taken together, the two reports portend a potentially bleak future for an American democracy that counts on its engaged citizenry to do everything from count votes to make laws.</p> 
<p>“There's a real problem here,” Institute for Strategic Dialogue CEO Sasha Havlicek told POLITICO, adding that violent rhetoric online is increasingly becoming normalized and accepted. “People feel emboldened to speak in certain ways because of the anonymity of online environments that perhaps wouldn't mirror the way that they behave in their daily lives.”</p> 
<p>Election officials across the country are taking notice and are taking new levels of precaution to protect themselves and their staff. </p> 
<p>“It definitely raises some concerns when people are using threatening and violent language and know where I live. And it just takes one, right?” Maine Secretary of State Shenna Bellows, a Democrat <a href="https://nbcmontana.com/news/nation-world/maine-secretary-of-state-says-shes-been-doxed-after-standing-up-to-ice" target="_blank">who recently faced doxxing and death threats</a> after she paused undercover license plate requests for ICE agents in Maine, told POLITICO last week.</p> 
<p>The threats are not limited to members of a particular party. In fact, the Institute for Strategic Dialogue found in its report that “Republican leaders, particularly President [Donald] Trump, were disproportionately targeted,” by violent rhetoric and threats.</p> 
<p>The July 2024 failed assassination attempt targeting Trump led to a rapid uptick in threats online, according to ISD’s report. And it hasn’t slowed much since.</p> 
<p>Republicans have seen a 364 percent uptick in threats online in the time period ISD studied, a number that “far outpaced” the 124 percent increase for Democrats.</p> 
<p>Despite repeated calls to tamp down violent rhetoric in the wake of events like Trump’s assassination attempt, there’s often an opposite effect, Havlicek said. “Instead of inspiring some sense of compassion or a deescalation, they do the opposite,” Havlicek said. “Those acts of violence in the real world really push much much more [online] activity in this violent direction, which is quite depressing.”</p> 
<p>Taken together, the uptick in violent threats coupled with election officials leaving their posts is worrying elected officials.</p> 
<p>“I'm always concerned when people feel like their personal safety is at risk, and when they can't stand to do a job that they want to do anymore because of circumstances outside of that job, that sucks,” Arizona Secretary of State Adrian Fontes, a Democrat, told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>The turnover among election officials is especially high in competitive areas that are subject to the most scrutiny, per Issue One’s report.</p> 
<p>Across the West, 80 percent “of counties with close margins in the 2020 presidential election have experienced turnover among their chief local election officials,” while just 40 percent of counties with a margin of 50 percent or more saw turnover.</p> 
<p>It’s a problem election officials have long tried to quell. Many officials say that while the departure of longtime officials is concerning, there has been a next generation of workers willing to step up. </p> 
<p>In Arizona, where all 15 of the state’s counties have experienced turnover from top election officials since 2020, according to Issue One’s report, Fontes said he <a href="https://www.votebeat.org/2025/06/09/arizona-election-administration-fellowship-program-adrian-fontes/" target="_blank">is using a fellowship program</a> to bring new blood into election administration.</p> 
<p>“Instead of just kind of only being concerned, we're actually doing stuff about it,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO Pro’s Morning Score. Want to receive the newsletter every weekday? Subscribe to POLITICO Pro. You’ll also receive daily policy news and other intelligence you need to act on the day’s biggest stories.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A ‘mediocre’ comment has put Talarico's Texas Senate campaign in the hot seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/a-mediocre-comment-has-put-talaricos-texas-senate-campaign-in-the-hot-seat-00761260</link>
      <description>An influencer said Senate candidate James Talarico called former opponent Colin Allred a “mediocre Black man. ” He insists he was only talking about Allred’s “method of campaigning. ”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2099-df8c-a99d-f5ffb02a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 18:58:49 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/18/cf/ec81ce9e4de3af83450fe5c946da/us-election-2026-senate-texas-democrats-82129.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Bob Daemmrich/Texas Tribune</media:credit>
        <media:title>Primary candidates for U.S. Senate, Texas state Rep. James Talarico (D-Austin), left, and Rep. Jasmine Crockett (D-Texas) participate in a debate during the Texas AFL-CIO Committee on Political Education Convention, Jan. 24, 2026, in Georgetown, Texas.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/18/cf/ec81ce9e4de3af83450fe5c946da/us-election-2026-senate-texas-democrats-82129.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The tense Texas Democratic Senate primary has been roiled by yet another online firestorm after an influencer accused state Rep. James Talarico of calling a former opponent a “mediocre Black man” — a claim he said was a “mischaracterization of a private conversation.”</p> 
<p>The influencer, Morgan Thompson, who posts under the username @morga_tt on TikTok, <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@morga_tt/video/7602078773206338847" target="_blank">posted the accusation in a video</a> Sunday in which she claimed that Talarico told her in a private conversation after a Jan. 12 town hall in Plano, Texas, that he had “signed up to run against a mediocre Black man, not a formidable, intelligent Black woman.” That reference was allegedly to former Rep. Colin Allred (D-Texas), who was in the Senate race until December, when he dropped out right before Rep. Jasmine Crockett joined. Both Allred and Crockett are Black; Talarico is white.</p> 
<p>Talarico pushed back on Thompson’s description of their conversation.</p> 
<p>“In my praise of Congresswoman Crockett, I described Congressman Allred’s method of campaigning as mediocre – but his life and service are not. I would never attack him on the basis of race,” Talarico said in the statement.</p> 
<p>Thompson <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@morga_tt/video/7602154339192360222" target="_blank">said in a video Monday</a> that she has no recording of the conversation but laid out evidence that she had been in contact with Talarico’s campaign to arrange it, including a photo of her standing with Talarico at the event, along with multiple texts she says were exchanged with an unnamed campaign staffer to plan the interaction. She had endorsed Talarico but said she now supports Crockett.</p> 
<p>In an interview with POLITICO before Talarico issued his statement, Thompson said she anticipated that not having a recording of the conversation with Talarico would raise skepticism of her account, but she still “felt like it was important enough to bring forward, given the nature of everything.” She declined to provide the name and contact information for that staffer so that POLITICO could verify their connection to the campaign.</p> 
<p>The alleged exchange threatens to upend a primary <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/talarico-crockett-texas-senate-primary-poll-00730929" target="_blank">in which polls show voters are sharply dividing along racial lines</a>, <a href="https://texaspublicopinionresearch.substack.com/p/they-all-want-to-win-new-poll-shows" target="_blank">with most Black voters supporting Crockett</a>, and majorities of white and Latino voters supporting Talarico.</p> 
<p>Allred fired back. “James, if you want to compliment Black women, just do it. Just do it. Don't do it while also tearing down a Black man,” he said in <a href="https://x.com/ColinAllredTX/status/2018384625899294820" target="_blank">a video he posted</a> to Instagram on Monday.</p> 
<p>“When you make an accusation, you often have a bit of confession in it,” continued Allred, who is now running for Congress in the 33rd District against Rep. Julie Johnson (D-Texas). “Maybe you use the word mediocre because there was something creeping into your mind about yourself.”</p> 
<p>Crockett, in a statement, said that by posting his response video, Allred “drew a line in the sand.”</p> 
<p>“He made it clear that he did not take allegations of an attack on him as simply another day in the neighborhood, but more importantly, his post wasn’t about himself,” she said. “It was a moment that he decided to stand for all people who have been targeted and talked about in a demeaning way as our country continues to be divided.”</p> 
<p>Thompson said in the video that she had been offered the chance to talk to Talarico because she was unhappy that Talarico’s campaign had sent out fundraising messages from Democratic strategist James Carville given Carville’s calls for Democrats to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/24/opinion/democrats-platform-economic-rage.html" target="_blank">move away from “woke” politics</a>. She had previously endorsed Talarico and said she worked with his campaign as part of its content creator outreach program but now supports Crockett.</p> 
<p>It’s the latest online explosion related to the primary. Last month, the hosts of popular podcast “Las Culturistas” urged people not to send money to Crockett because she had a history of “making it too obviously about” herself, a comment from host Matt Rogers that cohost Bowen Yang agreed with. That some of her supporters said the remarks were racist and misogynist, setting off off a fierce debate about what type of Democratic candidate can do well in red states like Texas. The hosts later apologized.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Allred, Sandhya Raghavan, said in a statement that his response to Talarico’s alleged remarks “speaks to a frustration that resonates far beyond this moment.”</p> 
<p>“When a former NFL player, civil rights attorney, and former congressman can be dismissed as ‘mediocre,’ it reveals the impossible standards Black candidates are held to,” she said. “Colin refused to accept that disrespect in silence — and in doing so, he stood up for every Black professional who has had their qualifications unfairly dismissed.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dan Bongino’s first podcast back: Score-settling, technical glitches and a Trump interview</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/bongino-podcast-return-trump-00760561</link>
      <description>During his first show back, Bongino attempted to skewer his old enemies and reconnect with the audience that, years ago, launched his name into the MAGA stratosphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-201e-df8c-a99d-f5fe4bdc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 16:21:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8f/a2/63f6ad694896a03d065339f39d5f/gettyimages-2249298283.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Andrew Harnik/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Then-FBI Deputy Director Dan Bongino speaks during a news conference at the Department of Justice on Dec. 4, 2025, in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8f/a2/63f6ad694896a03d065339f39d5f/gettyimages-2249298283.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Riya Misra</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Riya Misra</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After a nine-month stint helping run the FBI, former deputy director Dan Bongino is a podcaster once again.</p> 
<p>On Bongino’s first show back on Monday, President Donald Trump briefly dialed in, offering Bongino — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/dan-bongino-fbi-resignation-00696112" target="_blank">who resigned from the agency in December</a> — well wishes.</p> 
<p>But otherwise, the episode was more of a two-hour monologue that saw Bongino attempting to skewer old enemies — namely the mainstream media — and reconnect with the masses that launched his name, years ago, into the MAGA stratosphere.</p> 
<p>“The podfather is back,” he declared, “and I’m here to take back this movement.”</p> 
<p>Before joining the FBI last year, Bongino was a prolific right-wing podcaster who peddled in deep-state <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/11/18/dan-bongino-election-fraud-messaging-437164" target="_blank">conspiracy theories</a>. As the agency’s No. 2, working alongside the real-world powers he used to rail against, Bongino was often caught between his past digital footprint and his new job helping lead one of the nation’s premier law enforcement agencies. </p> 
<p>For years, he entertained <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/05/30/nx-s1-5407856/conspiracy-theorists-dan-bongino-epstein-fbi" target="_blank">conspiracies about sex offender Jeffrey Epstein’s</a> death, dismissing the authorities’ claims that the late financier killed himself. Bongino built a fanbase by stoking these very fires — and angered many when, after joining the FBI, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/11/fbi-patel-bongino-epstein-files-00400434" target="_blank">he swiftly backtracked his rhetoric</a>. Online, some of Bongino’s former supporters have slammed him as a sellout.</p> 
<p>The show was a big moment for Bongino, whose tenure at the FBI was <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/justice-department/dan-bongino-weighs-resigning-fbi-heated-confrontation-pam-bondi-epstei-rcna218388" target="_blank">at times chaotic</a>. The show’s launch <a href="https://x.com/dbongino/status/2018409834249331010" target="_blank">included a Times Square billboard</a>, and opened with around 140,000 viewers — according to conservative video platform Rumble’s view count — and peaked at around 220,000.</p> 
<p>After a victory lap around the nation’s top law enforcement agency, Bongino is not returning to the friendliest audience. And he had some choice words for any critics.</p> 
<p>“I want to address the grifters out there who mistakenly thought I wasn’t coming back,” he said during the livestream. “This movement’s been hijacked by a small group of dipshits and bums and losers, who are nothing but doomers under the frame of accountability.”</p> 
<p>This was the throughline for much of the two-hour segment, which saw Bongino ripping into a number of his critics. “Get your lips and just pucker them up and plant a big wet one on my ass,” he told “the libs and their media pals.”</p> 
<p>The “dipshits” in media, he said, remain “totally divorced from reality.”</p> 
<p>And to alleged leakers at the FBI: “You guys destroyed the place, and you tried to destroy us too,” he said. “But I’m back now, and you can go fuck yourself.”</p> 
<p>Bongino, exhaling at the end of his minutes-long diatribe, smiles into the camera: “We’re so back. Aren’t we?”</p> 
<p>But unlike the first version of his podcast, Bongino largely shied away from conspiracy theories — except for when, 15 minutes into the show, his livestream abruptly cut off thanks to a technical glitch. </p> 
<p>“Rumble is under attack, this show is under attack, this is what these scumbags do,” he said. “Can’t have a voice like me speaking out.”</p> 
<p>“They just don’t want me to talk,” he repeated for the rest of the show.</p> 
<p>He also offered “behind the scenes” insights into his time at the FBI, defending himself against critics who misunderstood, he said, the decisions they made — including the agency’s handling of the Epstein files. </p> 
<p>“When you get selected for one of these principal or deputy positions, everything you do is a level 10 decision,” Bongino said. “Find out which one is the shittier decision and avoid it. That’s the best you can do.</p> 
<p>“Here’s the problem with the Epstein mess,” he continued. “The FBI doesn’t have the evidence many thought it did. … There were not tapes with powerful men raping kids. There was not a list. Epstein’s rolodex was already public. The files are largely unreleasable for many reasons.”</p> 
<p>The files didn’t contain the smoking gun people were expecting, Bongino said, but “this administration got you the information.”</p> 
<p>Near the end of the show, Trump — who hand-picked Bongino for his post last year — dialed in for a brief interview, where the two discussed the administration’s crime crackdown, Minnesota’s welfare fraud scandal and National Guard deployments.</p> 
<p>“I’ll tell you what, if I were a Democratic governor and I were in charge of Chicago, as an example, I would be begging Donald Trump to come,” Trump told Bongino.</p> 
<p>Trump took another chance to rail at the results of the 2020 election (“I won in a landslide,” he said), urging Republicans to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/trump-nationalize-elections-2026-midterms-00760015" target="_blank">“nationalize the voting”&nbsp;and suggesting taking over voting “in&nbsp;at least 15&nbsp;places,”</a> which he didn’t name. And he patted himself on the back for his military actions in Iran and Venezuela, saying the U.S. is “respected again like never before.”</p> 
<p>“Listen, you did great in the FBI,” Trump told Bongino. “I’m very torn. I think, maybe, I’d rather have you where you are. “Very few people can do what you do, and your voice is a very important one.”</p> 
<p>Bongino, who has generally been a reliable supporter of Trump, intends to host his show every weekday. And for those expecting a Bongino chastened by his time in government — or those looking to take his space in the MAGA media sphere — he had a direct closing message.</p> 
<p>“All my bullshit detractors or whatever,” Bongino said at the end of the episode, “don’t know shit about anything. Throwing popcorn from the front row. We’re the number one livestream in the world. … I’m such a target that they came after the whole damn website. That’s how bad they want to keep me off the air.”</p> 
<p>“But I have my first — guys, you ready for this screenshot? — double barrel to those who tried to stop us,” he continued, silently flipping two middle fingers to the camera.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-02T14:20:30-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Tina Smith endorses Peggy Flanagan over Angie Craig in Minnesota Senate race</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/tina-smith-endorses-lt-gov-peggy-flanagan-in-minnesota-senate-race-00759890</link>
      <description>The retiring senator is choosing a fellow progressive and lieutenant governor as her successor over moderate Rep. Angie Craig.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1f39-d1ed-a59e-df7db7ad0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 12:00:09 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e1/4a8882174cc7ae40848f16059fdc/smith-and-flanagan.jpeg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Flanagan campaign</media:credit>
        <media:title>Minnesota Lt. Gov. Peggy Flanagan (left) and Sen. Tina Smith (D-Minn.) at the video shoot for Smith's endorsement. Photo courtesy of Flanagan's campaign.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b3/e1/4a8882174cc7ae40848f16059fdc/smith-and-flanagan.jpeg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Tina Smith is endorsing Minnesota Lt. Gov. Peggy Flanagan as her successor over Rep. Angie Craig, taking sides in a hotly contested primary to fill Smith’s Senate seat that’s been roiled in recent weeks by the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration enforcement efforts.</p> 
<p>“Today, 3,000 federal agents are terrorizing our communities,” Smith said in a <a href="https://youtube.com/shorts/qYxv_Zhtqqs?feature=share" target="_blank"><u>video announcing her pick</u></a> that was shared first with POLITICO. “I know that right now there is no one that I trust more to stand with Minnesota than Lt. Gov. Peggy Flanagan.”</p> 
<p>Flanagan, in the video, called it an “honor” to have the retiring senator’s endorsement and pledged to “continue in her footsteps.”</p> 
<p>“We’re going to push back against the status quo and send a progressive fighter to continue representing us in Washington, D.C.,” Flanagan said.</p> 
<p>Smith’s endorsement comes a day before the state’s Democratic and Republican precinct caucuses, the first step in each party’s formal endorsement process.</p> 
<p>In selecting Flanagan, Smith is elevating a fellow lieutenant governor and progressive over Craig, a moderate, for the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/13/tina-smith-wont-seek-reelection-senate-2026-00204058" target="_blank"><u>seat she has held since 2018</u></a>. Smith is the eighth sitting senator to endorse Flanagan, who also has the backing of Sens. Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.), Elizabeth Warren (D-Mass.) and other members of the so-called Fight Club of progressive senators of which they are all a part. Former Sen. Al Franken (D-Minn.), who held the seat before Smith, also endorsed Flanagan.</p> 
<p>Craig has some high-profile endorsements of her own, with five senators including Sens. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.), Tammy Baldwin (D-Wis.) in her corner, as well as former Speaker Nancy Pelosi (D-Calif.) and former Transportation Secretary Pete Buttigieg.</p> 
<p>Smith's decision comes against the backdrop of deadly incidents involving federal agents enforcing President Donald Trump’s immigration crackdown in the state that have opened new fissures in the Senate primary. While both candidates have called for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem’s impeachment, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/18/minnesota-ice-midterm-campaigns-00735146" target="_blank"><u>Flanagan has attacked Craig for taking “pro-Trump” immigration votes last year, while Craig has countered that her rival is being “disingenuous”</u></a> about the content and context of the measures.</p> 
<p>Antoine Givens, a spokesperson for Craig’s campaign, said in a statement that Craig “is the only candidate who has proven she can both win tough, competitive races against a Republican and go toe-to-toe with the Trump administration.”</p> 
<p>“From voting to impeach Donald Trump twice and now taking on Kristi Noem and ICE, to writing the law that capped the cost of insulin at $35 for seniors and banning members of Congress from trading stocks, Angie Craig has shown she’s the fighter Minnesotans need to hold the powerful accountable,” Givens said.</p> 
<p>Nonpartisan public polling in the race has been scant. Polling conducted in the past month for Flanagan’s team, as well as a separate survey commissioned by a pro-Flanagan group, shows the lieutenant governor with a <a href="https://x.com/lisakashinsky/status/2014350124999184445?s=20" target="_blank"><u>double-digit lead over Craig</u></a>. A poll commissioned by Craig’s campaign <a href="https://x.com/lisakashinsky/status/2016923932566196478?s=20" target="_blank"><u>showed the race </u></a>within the margin of error.</p> 
<p>Craig has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/senate-fundraising-campaign-finance-fec-00759078" target="_blank"><u>built a fundraising advantage in the race</u></a>, raising $2 million in the fourth quarter of 2025 and starting the election year with $3.7 million in cash on hand. Flanagan, meanwhile, raised roughly $1 million in that timeframe and ended the year with $810,646 in the bank.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump endorses John E. Sununu in New Hampshire Senate race over Scott Brown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/trump-endorsement-john-e-sununu-senate-00759336</link>
      <description>Trump’s support would once have been hard to imagine for the moderate critic of his. Now it further boosts Sununu as the GOP aims to flip an open Senate seat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1af3-d1ed-a59e-dbffa3880000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 16:18:54 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/24/29/5e4591584da9833f1ad39427b13b/nh-senate-debate-1.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jim Cole/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Then-Sen. John E. Sununu speaks during a debate in Conway, New Hampshire, on Oct. 1, 2008.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/24/29/5e4591584da9833f1ad39427b13b/nh-senate-debate-1.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump on Sunday endorsed former Sen. John E. Sununu in New Hampshire’s open Senate race, boosting a longtime critic over one of his former ambassadors, Scott Brown.</p> 
<p>Trump hailed Sununu, who Republicans see as their best chance to flip the blue Senate seat, as an “America First Patriot” in a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115996882630849069" target="_blank">Truth Social post Sunday afternoon</a>. And Trump said Sununu will “work tirelessly to advance our America First Agenda.”</p> 
<p>“John E. Sununu has my Complete and Total Endorsement — HE WILL NOT LET YOU DOWN. MAKE AMERICA GREAT AGAIN — ELECT JOHN E. SUNUNU,” he posted.</p> 
<p>Sununu, a moderate who has opposed Trump across his presidential runs, thanked him in a statement and quickly pivoted to talking about his priorities for New Hampshire.</p> 
<p>“I want to thank the President for his support and thank the thousands of Granite Staters who are supporting me,” Sununu said. “This campaign has and always will be about standing up for New Hampshire — every single day.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s endorsement further tips the scales in an already pitched GOP primary between Sununu and Brown, who represented Massachusetts in the Senate before moving to New Hampshire and running unsuccessfully for Senate there in 2014. He served as Trump’s ambassador to New Zealand and Samoa in his first term, and has been presenting himself as the more Trump-aligned candidate as he courts the MAGA base.</p> 
<p>Brown vowed to fight on. And he took a veiled shot at Sununu, accusing him of not being sufficiently dedicated to the MAGA movement.</p> 
<p>“I am running to ensure our America First agenda is led by someone who views this mission not as a career path, but as a continuation of a lifelong commitment to service,” Brown said in a <a href="https://x.com/SenScottBrown/status/2018064672117678232?s=20" target="_blank">post on X</a>. “Let’s keep working.”</p> 
<p>The two are competing to take on Democratic Rep. Chris Pappas for the seat being vacated by retiring Democratic Sen. Jeanne Shaheen. Pappas issued a simple response to Trump’s endorsement of Sununu: “I’m Chris Pappas, and I approve this message,” he <a href="https://x.com/ChrisPappasNH/status/2018056253658849537?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. His campaign manager, Rachel Petri, said in a statement that Trump’s endorsement “confirms” that Sununu “will sell out Granite Staters to advance his political career.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s support for Sununu once would have seemed unfathomable. The scion of a moderate New Hampshire Republican dynasty, Sununu served as a national co-chair of former Ohio Gov. John Kasich’s 2016 presidential campaign and joined his family in backing former U.N. Ambassador Nikki Haley for president against Trump in the 2024 GOP primary.</p> 
<p>Ahead of New Hampshire’s 2024 presidential primary, Sununu penned an op-ed lambasting Trump as a “loser.” (Trump went on to win by 11 points). And he later derided Trump’s 2020 election conspiracies as “completely inappropriate.”</p> 
<p>Republicans initially were bullish about flipping an open seat in purple New Hampshire that’s already changed hands between parties twice this century — Sununu defeated Shaheen to win the seat in 2002, then lost it to her in 2008 — and coalesced quickly behind the moderate Republican as their best option against Pappas. Sununu received instant backing from the GOP’s Senate campaign arm <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/22/john-sununu-new-hampshire-senate-00618083" target="_blank">upon his launch last October</a> and has wracked up <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook/2025/11/17/trumps-message-to-maga-00654111?nname=playbook&amp;nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nrid=b3fddf54-40a1-41f4-a5a6-b76118141c45" target="_blank">endorsements from the majority of Republican senators</a>. He’s also won support from Republican leaders in New Hampshire — all of which Trump noted in his Truth Social post Sunday.</p> 
<p>Trump also <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/5235266-chris-sununu-potential-senate-bid/" target="_blank">initially supported Sununu's younger brother</a>, former Gov. Chris Sununu, running for the Senate seat. Chris Sununu, also a vocal Trump critic, declined to launch a bid, prompting GOP interest in his brother.</p> 
<p>But some in Trump’s Granite State MAGA base quickly rejected his endorsement of Sununu, calling it a “slap in the face to grassroots supporters” long loyal to the president.</p> 
<p>“The Sununu family openly mocked, degraded, and worked against the America First movement, the President himself, and the policies that energized New Hampshire voters,” a group of MAGA activists <a href="https://x.com/Nh4Trump603/status/2018048300658614638?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. “We will continue and intensify our campaign opposition to the Sununu operation.”</p> 
<p>Sununu holds a wide lead over Brown in polling of the GOP primary. The latest, a University of New Hampshire online <a href="https://scholars.unh.edu/survey_center_polls/922/" target="_blank">survey of likely primary voters from mid-January</a>, showed Sununu up 48 percent to 25 percent with 26 percent of likely voters undecided. But Pappas is ahead of both Republicans in hypothetical general-election matchups, leading Sununu by 5 percentage points and Brown by 10 percentage points in the UNH poll. The survey of 967 likely GOP primary voters had a margin of error of +/-3.2 percent.</p> 
<p>Pappas also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/senate-fundraising-campaign-finance-fec-00759078" target="_blank">outraised both Republicans</a>, bringing in $2.3 million last quarter and amassing a $3.2 million war chest heading into the year. Sununu hauled in $1.3 million and had $1.1 million in cash on hand in his primary campaign account while Brown raised $347,000 through his main account and had $907,000 in the bank.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-01T12:57:14-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democrats post early fundraising edge in marquee 2026 Senate races</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/senate-fundraising-campaign-finance-fec-00759078</link>
      <description>Competitive primaries in a few key states have helped Republicans maintain a cash advantage, according to new filings submitted to the Federal Election Commission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-19d3-df8c-a99d-fdf77f1a0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 11:08:42 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/ca/29/506e68fa428ebc4ae92bb121783e/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2064217743">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Jon Ossoff, pictured in 2024, is handily outraising his Republican challengers as he seeks reelection in Georgia this year.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ca/29/506e68fa428ebc4ae92bb121783e/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2064217743" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty and Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty and Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One bright spot for Democrats as they face a tough path to taking back the Senate this year: Their candidates are raising a lot of money.</p> 
<p>Democrats outraised their GOP counterparts across several of this year’s marquee Senate races heading into 2026, according to new filings submitted to the Federal Election Commission on Saturday.</p> 
<p>Sen. Jon Ossoff, the only Democrat running for reelection in a state Donald Trump won, enters the year with a massive fundraising advantage over any of his GOP rivals in battleground Georgia. Democrats in North Carolina and Ohio also started the year with a major financial edge over their GOP rivals.</p> 
<p>But heated Democratic primaries have helped Republicans maintain a cash advantage in a few key states, including Michigan, Maine and Iowa.</p> 
<p>Strong fundraising will be critical to Democrats’ efforts to hold all their seats — including several that are open following battleground senators’ retirements — while also flipping four Republican ones.</p> 
<p>In a handful of primaries, including the Democratic contests in Michigan and Texas and the Republican lineup in Georgia, fourth-quarter fundraising numbers largely did not show any one candidate majorly distinguishing themselves from the rest.</p> 
<p>Here’s a rundown of what the fundraising looked like in key Senate races.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Georgia</h4> 
<p>Ossoff holds a significant fundraising advantage over his Republican opponents duking it out in the primary. He raised $9.9 million in the final quarter of 2025 and ended the year with $25.5 million in his war chest — numbers that are substantially higher than all of his GOP rivals combined.</p> 
<p>Georgia Rep. Buddy Carter brought in the most in the GOP primary, raising $1.7 million and entering 2026 with $4.1 million cash on hand. Ex-football coach Derek Dooley reported raising $1.1 million, while Rep. Mike Collins raised just shy of $825,000. Dooley ended the quarter with $2.1 million left in the bank, while Collins reported having $2.3 million.</p> 
<p>While Ossoff holds a massive fundraising advantage, the gap is likely to shrink when the Republican nominee is selected in May and the party, including its donors, coalesces around one candidate.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">North Carolina</h4> 
<p>Democratic former governor Roy Cooper maintains a fundraising advantage in North Carolina over former Republican National Committee Chair Michael Whatley.</p> 
<p>Cooper <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/29/roy-cooper-raises-3-4-million-in-first-24-hours-of-his-senate-candidacy-00481528" target="_blank">broke fundraising records</a> when he launched his campaign and has continued to bring in large sums, raising $7 million from October through December last year, according to his filings with the FEC — nearly double the $3.8 million Whatley raised during the same period. Cooper entered 2026 with $12.3 million in his campaign coffers, a sizable haul that will be necessary as he prepares for November.</p> 
<p>Whatley, who has been endorsed by Trump, ended the fourth quarter with $3.7 million in cash on hand. Both candidates — the likely nominees in the state’s Senate race — bring extensive donor networks from their prior roles, setting up North Carolina to be one of the most expensive contests this cycle.</p> 
<p>Operatives in both parties say spending could reach $650 million to $800 million. Democrats are eying the North Carolina seat, left open by the retirement of GOP Sen. Thom Tillis, as one of their best pick up opportunities in November.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Michigan</h4> 
<p>In Michigan, where Democrats are looking to hold retiring Sen. Gary Peters’ seat, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/michigan-senate-mcmorrow-stevens-el-sayed-00758408" target="_blank">three Democratic front-runners are locked in a tight race</a> — and their fundraising reflects it.</p> 
<p>Rep. Haley Stevens holds an early fundraising advantage, raising $2.1 million during the fourth quarter of 2025 and entered the year with roughly $3 million in the bank. Widely seen as the establishment candidate in the contentious primary, Stevens benefits from being able to tap into her existing donor networks, but her opponents are not far behind. State Sen. Mallory McMorrow and physician Abdul El-Sayed each raised roughly $1.7 million and ended the year with around $1.9 million in the bank.</p> 
<p>With Michigan’s Aug. 4 primary — later than most states — the Democratic candidates will need to sustain strong fundraising numbers through what is shaping up to be a long and expensive intraparty fight.</p> 
<p>Former Rep. Mike Rogers, the frontrunner on the GOP side, raised $1.9 million and ended the fourth quarter with $3.5 million in cash on hand.</p> 
<p>Rogers — the candidate most national Republicans have coalesced around — will benefit from being the main GOP candidate while Democrats get through <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/michigan-senate-mcmorrow-stevens-el-sayed-00758408" target="_blank">their bruising primary</a>. He also ran for the Senate in 2024, giving him a network of donors to tap into. The GOP is eying Michigan — where <a href="https://www.politico.com/2024-election/results/michigan/" target="_blank">Trump won by just</a> over a point in 2024 — as a top pickup opportunity in November.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Maine</h4> 
<p>Political newcomer and oysterman Graham Platner outraised both Gov. Janet Mills, his main Democratic rival, and incumbent Sen. Susan Collins, who is one of the party’s top targets as the only GOP senator representing a state won by Vice President Kamala Harris in 2024.</p> 
<p>Platner raised $4.6 million in the fourth quarter compared to $2.2 million for Collins and $2.7 million for Mills, who launched her campaign in mid-October.</p> 
<p>But Collins, who has not formally launched her campaign yet, sits on far more cash than both her Democratic rivals, with a little over $8 million in the bank compared to $3.7 million for Platner and $1.3 million for Mills.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Ohio</h4> 
<p>Former Sen. Sherrod Brown significantly outraised Sen. Jon Husted (R-Ohio) in the fourth quarter, giving Democrats a boost in their longshot bid to flip the Senate seat in the state that has turned increasingly red. Brown raised $7.3 million, while Husted — appointed last year to fill the seat vacated by JD Vance becoming vice president — raised $1.5 million.</p> 
<p>Brown, a prolific fundraiser, began 2026 with $9.9 million in his war chest. He is expected to need deep reserves again, after cryptocurrency-linked groups spent heavily against him during his unsuccessful 2024 reelection bid. Husted started the year with just under $6 million.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">New Hampshire</h4> 
<p>In New Hampshire, Democratic Rep. Chris Pappas continued to comfortably outraise his Republican competition in the race to replace retiring Democratic Sen. Jeanne Shaheen. Pappas brought in $2.3 million in the fourth quarter and ended 2025 with $3.2 million cash on hand.</p> 
<p>Former Sen. John Sununu, who was defeated by Shaheen in 2008 and is running with the backing of the National Republican Senatorial Committee, raised $1.3 million and had $1.1 million cash on hand. His Republican primary rival Scott Brown, who briefly represented neighboring Massachusetts in the Senate, raised just $374,000 and had $907,000 in the bank.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Texas</h4> 
<p>Money is flowing into the Democratic primary in Texas, where Rep. Jasmine Crockett and state Rep. James Talarico both raised over $6 million during the fourth quarter.</p> 
<p>Crockett, who launched her Senate campaign in early December, raised $2 million from donors through the end of the month and transferred another $4.5 million from her previous House campaign account. But Talarico, a state representative from Austin, outraised Crockett with a $6.9 million quarter and ended the year with more money in the bank. He started 2026 with $7.1 million in his war chest, compared to $5.6 million for the Dallas-area representative.</p> 
<p>Both candidates outraised the Republican field by a wide margin. On the GOP side, state Attorney General Ken Paxton raked in $1.1 million, while incumbent Sen. John Cornyn raised $1 million for his campaign and another $6 million through two joint fundraising committees, which he has used to run TV ads on his behalf. Rep. Wesley Hunt, polling in third in the GOP primary, raised just over $429,000.</p> 
<p>Cornyn — whose reelection bid has been <a href="https://www.nrsc.org/press-releases/nrsc-chairman-tim-scotts-statement-on-texas-senate-race-2025-04-09/" target="_blank">endorsed by the NRSC</a> — still maintains a huge cash-on-hand advantage for the primary. He has more than $15 million in the bank between his campaign account and two joint fundraising committees, a war chest that could prove pivotal in the final stretch of the March 3 primary — or an extended runoff. He is locked in a neck-and-neck race with Paxton, according to public polls.</p> 
<p>Paxton entered 2026 with $3.7 million in the bank. Hunt had $778,660.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Iowa</h4> 
<p>Democrats duking it out in Iowa’s Senate primary posted modest fundraising hauls in the fourth quarter. State Rep. Josh Turek raised $677,000, while state Sen. Zach Wahls brought in $741,000. Nathan Sage, the third Democrat viewed as competitive for the nomination, brought in $229,000.</p> 
<p>Wahls entered 2026 with the cash-on-hand advantage. He had $733,000 left in his war chest, while Turek had just shy of $400,000. Sage had $86,000 in the bank at the start of the year.</p> 
<p>Whichever Democrats wins will need serious money to try flipping the seat left open by retiring Sen. Joni Ernst.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ashley Hinson brought in $1.6 million and had nearly $5.2 million in the bank at the end of 2025, a substantial fundraising advantage over all of her potential Democratic opponents.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Minnesota</h4> 
<p>In Minnesota, Lt. Gov. Peggy Flanagan and Rep. Angie Craig are front-runners on the Democratic side vying for the open Senate seat. Craig has built a fundraising advantage, raising $2 million in the fourth quarter and ending it with $3.7 million left in the bank, while Flanagan raised roughly $1 million and ended the year with $810,646 in the bank.</p> 
<p>On the Republican side, Michele Tafoya, a former sideline reporter for “Sunday Night Football” and conservative commentator, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/michele-tafoya-minnesota-senate-00738041" target="_blank"><u>launched her bid in late January</u></a>, so her campaign launch fundraising isn’t yet public.Tafoya quickly received the backing of the Republicans' Senate campaign arm after launching her bid, so she is expected to have strong fundraising support to carry her through the August primary and into the general.</p> 
<p>The GOP contest has a handful of other primary contenders, including former Minnesota Republican Party Chair David Hann.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Alaska</h4> 
<p>Former Democratic Rep. Mary Peltola launched her Senate <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/peltola-alaska-senate-2026-midterms-00721596" target="_blank"><u>bid in mid-January</u></a>, so her fourth quarter FEC report did not capture her Senate fundraising. But she raised $1.5 million in the first 24 hours of her bid to unseat Republican Sen. Dan Sullivan, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/mary-peltola-alaska-fundraising-00726856" target="_blank"><u>POLITICO previously reported</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Sullivan raised $1.4 million during the fourth quarter, according to his FEC report, and entered 2026 with $5.8 million in his war chest.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Michigan’s 3-car pileup of a primary has Senate Democrats worried</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/michigan-senate-mcmorrow-stevens-el-sayed-00758408</link>
      <description>The race is a crucial test for what the next generation of Democrats will look like — and whether they can prevail in a must-win race for their Senate chances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-10de-d1ed-a59e-d3dfadc20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/png" url="https://static.politico.com/9e/8a/cde4b5444f4eb6811566ac33b771/michigan-senate-a.png">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Anna Wiederkehr/POLITICO (source images via AP and Getty)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Michigan-Senate-Lede-Art-A</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9e/8a/cde4b5444f4eb6811566ac33b771/michigan-senate-a.png" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Adam Wren</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Adam Wren</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>DETROIT — As a professional driver navigated a gleaming new Ford Bronco Sport up a steep ridge, Mallory McMorrow found herself pinned in the back seat clinging to the overhead roll bar.</p> 
<p>The Detroit Auto Show course is designed to show off the Bronco’s capabilities — while putting an escapist scare into its thrill-seeking passengers. But it just reminded McMorrow of her day-to-day reality running for Michigan’s open Senate seat.</p> 
<p>“It’s a teeter-totter, man,” McMorrow told POLITICO about her race, after having navigated a very literal giant teeter-totter in the Bronco. “It could go any direction.”</p> 
<p>McMorrow is locked in a tight three-way primary with Rep. Haley Stevens and physician Abdul El-Sayed that has emerged as a test for what the next generation of Democrats will look like — and whether they can win a key swing-state election that will help determine Senate control.</p> 
<p>In recent days, the trio of candidates’ squabbles careened hour to hour from whether they should embrace Medicare for All, to how far Democrats should go in fighting ICE. In fact, the contest has emerged as a catch-all for every question and problem plaguing Democrats politically and tactically: Where should they stand on Israel and Gaza? Should they send their aging congressional leaders packing? What does electability look like in this political environment? Should Democrats tap into the attention economy or focus on traditional campaigning?</p> 
<p>El-Sayed, on the left, has taken consistently maximalist positions fitting for a man who wrote a book titled “Medicare For All: A Citizen’s Guide” and has vocal support from Sen. Bernie Sanders. Stevens, a classic swing-state centrist favored by many establishment Democrats, has taken smaller-bore stances. Between them sits McMorrow, who’s aiming to appeal to voters in both of their lanes.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/5d/32/3fbb1ef0403f9dd7966afb101a27/detroit-auto-show-49568.jpg" alt="Mallory McMorrow listens to a speaker talk about Toyota vehicles at the Detroit Auto Show on Jan. 14." data-portal-copyright="AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26014822249568" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Mallory McMorrow listens to a speaker talk about Toyota vehicles at the Detroit Auto Show on Jan. 14."/><p>But this three-way battle to replace retiring Sen. Gary Peters (D-Mich.) isn’t just about what direction the Democratic Party takes in Washington — it’s whether they can get there in the first place.</p> 
<p>Democrats think they see a route back to the Senate majority. But if they don’t hold on to their seat in Michigan, that faint path won’t materialize.</p> 
<p>“It's already a long shot, but it's a doable thing — but not without Michigan,” said David Axelrod, the longtime senior adviser to former President Barack Obama.</p> 
<p>Axelrod called it the “most fascinating and consequential primary” in the country.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders both in Michigan and D.C. are growing more worried by the day that the hard-fought contest, which won’t be decided until the August primary, will exacerbate ideological tensions and leave the nominee in a weakened position heading into a contest against former Rep. Mike Rogers (R-Mich.).</p> 
<p>“We're used to having long primaries,” Sen. Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.) told POLITICO. “No one loves them, but we're used to having them. And I don't think it's insurmountable.”</p> 
<p>For now, the race is wide open.</p> 
<p>Most <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/campaign/5709140-democratic-senate-race-michigan/" target="_blank">public polls have found</a> a <a href="https://www.detroitnews.com/story/news/politics/2026/01/14/michigan-senate-race-poll-mike-rogers-haley-stevens-mallory-mcmorrow-abdul-el-sayed/88148893007/?gnt-cfr=1&amp;gca-cat=p&amp;gca-uir=true&amp;gca-epti=z11xx50p119950c119950d00----v11xx50d--65--&amp;gca-ft=169&amp;gca-ds=sophi" target="_blank">tight three-way race</a> in the primary, with Stevens or McMorrow holding a slight lead depending on the survey; in those same polls, Stevens runs slightly ahead of Rogers in the general election, with McMorrow just a bit behind her and El-Sayed a bit further back.</p> 
<p>Stevens has a fundraising edge. According to the latest Federal Election Commission reports, which posted on Saturday, she brought in $2.1 million in the past quarter and has $3 million cash on hand; McMorrow and El-Sayed both raised around $1.75 million and each has just under $2 million in the bank. Rogers raised just under $2 million and has just under $3.5 million cash on hand.<br></p><p>Part of the lack of separation in the polls is that voters haven’t engaged yet. The campaigns don’t expect cleavage until paid media starts happening in full (El-Sayed is the only candidate so far to roll out a statewide ad.)</p> 
<p>“Only the most political have started to click in,” Slotkin said.</p> 
<p>Michigan Democrats also worried about the impact the primary could have on the rest of the party as they fight to hold on to term-limited Gov. Gretchen Whitmer’s office and win back control of the Legislature.</p> 
<p>Whitmer, with her 60 percent approval rating, is facing a pressure campaign from some in the party to endorse either Stevens or McMorrow early in the race to narrow the field, according to two senior Michigan Democratic officials granted anonymity to speak about private discussions. Otherwise, one of them worried, “we could see real losses.”</p> 
<p>Whitmer and El-Sayed duked it out in a 2018 gubernatorial primary, and the officials say bad blood remains between them.</p> 
<p>A Whitmer spokesperson declined to comment.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/2a/84/60dcb5b2431cb454798f01730d41/democratic-national-convention-58746.jpg" alt="Gov. Gretchen Whitmer is facing a pressure campaign from some in the party to endorse either Haley Stevens or Mallory McMorrow early in the race to narrow the field." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Gov. Gretchen Whitmer is facing a pressure campaign from some in the party to endorse either Haley Stevens or Mallory McMorrow early in the race to narrow the field."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large">A clash of ideologies</h4> 
<p>The candidates have sharp ideological divides on major issues including health care, Israel and Gaza and accepting corporate PAC money.</p> 
<p>After a second person was killed by a federal immigration agent in Minneapolis, the three candidates' diverging approach to ICE and its funding supercharged the primary.</p> 
<p>While McMorrow and Stevens glad-handed at the Detroit Auto Show and union halls around the MLK holiday, after immigration agents killed Renee Good and before they killed Alex Pretti, El-Sayed, who has championed the Abolish ICE movement since 2018, went to Minneapolis and filmed <a href="https://x.com/AbdulElSayed/status/2013413511624315184?s=20" target="_blank">man-on-the-street</a> interviews for social media that were reminiscent of New York Mayor Zohran Mamdani’s successful viral campaign videos.</p> 
<p>He told POLITICO he was there to “understand what it looks like when an arm of the government lays siege to a city in America.” (El-Sayed also jetted to California for a fundraiser earlier that week).</p> 
<p>McMorrow has <a href="https://x.com/MalloryMcMorrow/status/2015856774931169545?s=20" target="_blank">expressed support</a>for reforms to ICE, such as requiring agents to be unmasked, and argues Republicans and Democrats should “deny DHS one penny more until complete overhaul and accountability of this agency” happens.</p> 
<p>Stevens, meanwhile, is co-sponsoring a bill that would divert what she called ICE’s $75 billion "slush fund" to state and local law enforcement agencies; she has also called for DHS Secretary Kristi Noem’s impeachment.</p> 
<p>The candidates are also at odds over health care, an issue over which they’ve sparred in recent days.</p> 
<p>In an interview with Democratic influencer Brian Tyler Cohen last week, El-Sayed reignited the health care debate. He said, “if you like your insurance from your employer or from your union, that can still be there for you,” apparently flipping on his stance on Medicare for All. McMorrow and her allies seized on his remarks as El-Sayed seemingly embracing a position he had repeatedly attacked her on. El-Sayed hosted a December <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TE43EDDNHw0" target="_blank">health care town hall with Sanders</a> where he contrasted his Medicare for All support with McMorrow’s and Steven’s backing of a public option.</p> 
<p>“It’s wild to call yourself the ‘next generation’ of Democratic leadership and be running AGAINST Medicare for All in 2026,” <a href="https://x.com/AbdulElSayed/status/2005687425260302589?s=20" target="_blank">he posted on X</a> a month ago, quote-tweeting McMorrow.<br></p><p>In an interview with POLITICO after the dustup, El-Sayed declined to discuss specifics of his position on the record. In a statement, a spokesperson said that he supports Medicare for All as a baseline option for everyone, "and if folks want additional private coverage through a union or an employer then that can be there for them too."</p> 
<p>The conflict in Gaza has also led to sharp divisions in the race.</p> 
<p>El-Sayed, who is the son of Egyptian immigrants, has been an outspoken critic of Israel, which he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/06/mallory-mcmorrow-michigan-democratic-primary-gaza-genocide-00594679" target="_blank">has long said</a> was committing genocide in Gaza. That’s a major issue in a state with the highest percent of Arab-Americans in the country; more than 100,000 people voted “uncommitted” instead of backing then-President Joe Biden in the 2024 primary over his administration’s support of Israel — an effort El-Sayed helped lead.</p> 
<p>He told POLITICO that when he talks about U.S. tax dollars “being misappropriated to weaponize food against children and to subsidize a genocide, rather than to invest in real people in their communities and their kids and their schools and their health care, it is the single biggest applause line in every speech.”</p> 
<p>McMorrow took a bit more time to come to that view. In October, when asked whether she thought the conflict was a genocide, she paused for several seconds, exhaled, and responded, “Based on the definition, yes.” Her campaign said her view was informed by a September <a href="https://www.ohchr.org/en/press-releases/2025/09/israel-has-committed-genocide-gaza-strip-un-commission-finds" target="_blank">United Nations Commission of Inquiry report</a>.</p> 
<p>Stevens has been more supportive of Israel, and has the support of AIPAC, the politically influential pro-Israel lobby. Some senior Michigan Democrats have expressed concern that an AIPAC independent expenditure campaign backing Haley could make the primary even more toxic ahead of the general election. Asked about their plans, an AIPAC spokesperson told POLITICO they had no updates.</p> 
<p>Asked by POLITICO in November whether she was comfortable with AIPAC support, Stevens dodged, saying she’s delighted to “see the hostages get home,” and added she “wanted to see an enduring ceasefire where Hamas surrenders and so that we can get the people of Palestine and Israel in long standing peace, living peacefully, side by side with one another.”</p> 
<p>Stevens' campaign also attacked both El-Sayed and McMorrow's record on manufacturing, a sector that employs some 600,000 in Michigan. She told POLITICO that McMorrow "has a history of criticizing Michigan's key industries" and that El-Sayed "supports policies that would decimate Michigan's manufacturing economy," citing his support for the Green New Deal.</p> 
<p>“I’m going to call out what isn’t working for Michigan’s manufacturing economy, whether it is Mike Rogers or members of my own party,” Stevens said in an interview in the conference room of the Teamsters Local 234 union hall in Plymouth.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/3b/e9/f1daf64949928b1776673a1caba2/u-s-congress-37720.jpg" alt=" Some senior Michigan Democrats have expressed concern that an AIPAC independent expenditure campaign backing Rep. Haley Haley could make the senatorial primary even more toxic ahead of the general election." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title=" Some senior Michigan Democrats have expressed concern that an AIPAC independent expenditure campaign backing Rep. Haley Haley could make the senatorial primary even more toxic ahead of the general election."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Old school vs. new school</h4> 
<p>The race is also shaping up as a test of offline coalitional politics at a moment increasingly defined more by viral videos than baby-kissing and union hall campaign stops.</p> 
<p>Stevens has leaned hardest into traditional brick-and-mortar campaigning, while El-Sayed has been much more focused online, with McMorrow’s approach once again falling between them.</p> 
<p>McMorrow’s biggest splash of the campaign so far came with a <a href="https://x.com/MalloryMcMorrow/status/1964673063175307685?s=20" target="_blank">viral video</a> that attacked NFL RedZone for adding ads as “the latest example of corporate greed,” and tied it to spiking grocery costs. It earned nearly 2 million views.</p> 
<p>El-Sayed has built a national profile and fundraising network in part with a health care-focused podcast on Crooked Media, the network run by the Pod Save America team made up largely of former Obama senior advisers. At least three members, Jon Favreau, Jon Lovett and Ben Rhodes, appeared as hosts on an invite to El-Sayed’s fundraiser earlier this month in California.<br></p><p>Stevens has taken a different tack, putting more focus on campaign stops and meat-and-potatoes fights for local industry, especially auto and other factory jobs.</p> 
<p>In a year-out-from-election day memo, Stevens’ campaign argued that her “strength with Black Michiganders and union workers, her relentless focus on lowering costs and protecting Michigan manufacturing, and her record fighting for Michiganders — which has led to her winning tough primaries and general elections — will propel her to victory.”</p> 
<p>Campaigning at a Teamsters Local 234 union hall in Plymouth, she spent a lot more time talking about a local labor contract dispute than national concerns.</p> 
<p>“Look, manufacturing might not light up the internet, but it fuels a lot of jobs here,” she told POLITICO afterward.</p> 
<p>That dogged approach helped her flip and <a href="https://www.michiganpublic.org/politics-government/2020-11-05/stevens-wins-second-term-in-us-house-11th-district" target="_blank">hold a swing seat</a>, then <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/08/02/rep-haley-stevens-beats-levin-in-battle-of-democratic-incumbents-00049449" target="_blank">win a tough incumbent-on-incumbent primary</a> in 2022, and is one she thinks will pay dividends now.</p> 
<p>“I’ve had a couple of tough primaries before, and I’m just out here trying to win it for Michiganders,” she said.</p> 
<p>But it remains unclear how well it will translate in a statewide campaign.</p> 
<p>“Haley seems to have more institutional support — whether or not it’s admitted as such — and that is a strength, but it also could be a weakness,” said a longtime Michigan Democratic operative who remains neutral in the race and was granted anonymity to assess the primary. “Her presence on the campaign trail I’m not sure is one that’s really like, <i>Man, I got to be with her.”</i></p> 
<p>Stevens has earned criticism over whether she can galvanize the online, grassroots activists, or electrify crowds on the trail. “She's [an] uneven campaigner when it comes to the retail stuff,” said Adam Jentleson, a longtime Democratic campaign strategist who<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/09/17/us/politics/democrats-liberals-jentleson-searchlight.html" target="_blank">is pushing for the party to break more with left-wing interest groups</a> and focus more on expanding the party’s coalition to win (he also voiced concern about El-Sayed as a general-election candidate).</p> 
<p>Right now, both El-Sayed and Stevens have been training most of their fire on McMorrow rather than each other, seeing her as the bigger threat to their potential voting coalitions.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/c5/8a/6b1ce2b846acbe373c2d5ba562ff/michigan-governor-2018-30366.jpg" alt="Abdul El-Sayed, left, is running with the support of progressives such as Sen. Bernie Sanders, who also supported him in his 2018 run for governor." data-portal-copyright="AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="18217765630366" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Abdul El-Sayed, left, is running with the support of progressives such as Sen. Bernie Sanders, who also supported him in his 2018 run for governor."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Insiders and outsiders</h4> 
<p>Stevens’ electoral track record is part of why many establishment-leaning Democrats in D.C. prefer her in the race.</p> 
<p>Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee Chair Kirsten Gillibrand (D-N.Y.) invited her to attend a fundraising retreat in Napa Valley that featured a crypto roundtable, but Stevens told POLITICO she did not attend due to the government shutdown.</p> 
<p>In an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/schumer-thinks-these-four-states-will-deliver-for-dems-in-november-00727181" target="_blank">interview with POLITICO</a>, Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer was bullish on defending Michigan but declined to appraise any individual candidacies; a DSCC spokesperson declined to comment on whether the committee would officially endorse in the race.<br></p><p>McMorrow has taken a very different approach to D.C.’s Democratic leadership.</p> 
<p>She<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/03/25/mallory-mcmorrow-michigan-senate-chuck-schumer-00246369?utm_campaign=5/16/25++AM:&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=Sailthru&amp;utm_term=Punchbowl+AM+and+Active+Subscribers+from+Memberful+Combined" target="_blank">told POLITICO last March</a>, before she was even officially a candidate, that she wouldn’t vote for Schumer as party leader should she win her Senate seat. She also previously penned a scathing letter to Biden following his disastrous debate with Donald Trump, urging him to drop out.</p> 
<p>“We’re drawing a contrast that is really about defining my lane,” McMorrow said in an interview at a campaign stop at a park in Grand Rapids late last year, suggesting Stevens, without naming her, was running “an uninspiring campaign that’s right out of the D.C. playbook” and that El-Sayed, also without naming him, was campaigning on the idea “that there’s just one weird trick to fix democracy.”</p> 
<p>Stevens has said it’s too early to determine whether to would back Schumer; she has called him “<a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/03/16/politics/video/sotu-panel-breaks-down-democrat-infighting-after-shutdown-battle" target="_blank">a great leader.”</a></p> 
<p>El-Sayed also hasn’t said whether he’d back Schumer for leader. But he’s made it clear he is running headlong against the Democratic establishment.</p> 
<p>“The movement we’re building is about taking a bet on the divide in our politics not really being about left versus right, but being about the folks who are locked out and the folks who are locking them out,” El-Sayed told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>About the only thing the candidates can all agree on is the stakes of the contest.</p> 
<p>“The future of this party is going to be based on what happens in this race,” McMorrow said.</p> 
<p><i>Elena Schneider contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lame duck no more? Trump stockpiles hundreds of millions ahead of midterms.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/donald-trump-fundraising-midterms-00759005</link>
      <description>Campaign finance disclosures filed late Saturday revealed details of the president’s unmatched political fundraising operation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1796-df17-afbf-7fb7cbb20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:31:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b1/b3/56f121c8465b8717682ed2a2177a/trump-19434.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump gestures after stepping off Air Force One, Saturday, Jan. 31, 2026, at Palm Beach International Airport in West Palm Beach, Fla.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b1/b3/56f121c8465b8717682ed2a2177a/trump-19434.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump’s political war chest grew dramatically in the second half of 2025, according to new campaign finance disclosures submitted late Saturday, giving him an unprecedented amount of money for a term-limited president to influence the midterms and beyond.</p> 
<p>Trump raised $26 million through his joint fundraising committee in the back half of last year, and another $8 million directly into his leadership PAC. And a super PAC linked to him has more than $300 million in the bank.</p> 
<p>All together, a web of campaign accounts, some of which he controls directly and others under the care of close allies, within the president’s orbit have $375 million in their coffers.</p> 
<p>The funds far outstrip those of any other political figure — Republican or Democrat — entering 2026, and have no real historical precedent. And Trump could put them to use this year for the midterms, or to shape future elections, even as he cannot run for president again.</p> 
<p>Trump continues to outpace any other Republican in raising money, both from large and small-dollar donors. His joint fundraising committee — Trump National Committee, which pools fundraising for a variety of Trump-aligned groups — accounted for 1 in 8 dollars raised on WinRed, the primary Republican online fundraising platform, during the second half of 2025, according to a POLITICO analysis.</p> 
<p>And no super PAC raised even half as much in 2025 as the $289 million from MAGA Inc., the Trump-aligned super PAC that both the president and Vice President J.D. Vance appeared at fundraisers for last year.</p> 
<p>Trump has given few clues as to how he might put the funds to use. Trump National Committee primarily sends funds to the president’s leadership PAC, Never Surrender, with a bit of money also going to the Republican National Committee and Vance’s leadership PAC, Working For Ohio.</p> 
<p>Candidates cannot use leadership PAC money for their own election efforts. But the accounts — which are common across Washington and have long been derided by anti-money in politics groups as “slush funds” — allow politicians to dole out money to allies or fund political travel.</p> 
<p>Never Surrender spent $6.7 million from July through December, with more than half of that total going toward advertising, digital consulting and direct mail — expenses typically linked to fundraising.</p> 
<p>So far, Trump’s groups have held their powder in Republican primaries. While Trump has endorsed against a handful of Republican incumbents now locked in competitive primaries — including Sen. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana and Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky — and threatened others, he hasn’t used money. A super PAC targeting Massie, MAGA KY, is run by Trump allies but has largely been funded by GOP megadonor Paul Singer.</p> 
<p>MAGA Inc.’s only election-related spending last year was to boost now-Rep. Matt Van Epps in the special election in Tennessee’s 7th District.</p> 
<p>Trump’s massive war chest makes him a political force, independent of the traditional party infrastructure. The RNC — which derives a significant portion of its fundraising from Trump — had $95 million in the bank at the end of the year, roughly a quarter of what the Trump-linked groups have.</p> 
<p>And their rivals at the Democratic National Committee are far worse off — at just over $14 million, while owing more than $17 million in debt.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Houston Democrat wins former Rep. Sylvester Turner’s seat ahead of contested primary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/texas-18-district-run-off-00758972</link>
      <description>Christian Menefee's victory will set up another generational battle for Democrats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1615-df17-afbf-7f37bfe60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 23:11:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/81/83/42f938b64a91b6d78eb446e50546/election-2026-texas-congress-69740.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Karen Warren/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>Democrat Christian Menefee speaks to supporters during his watch party at The Post Houston on Election Day, in Houston, Saturday, Jan. 31, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/81/83/42f938b64a91b6d78eb446e50546/election-2026-texas-congress-69740.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Harris County Attorney Christian Menefee, a Democrat, won a special runoff election on Saturday to serve the remainder of former Texas Rep. Sylvester’s term, who died last year.</p> 
<p>The Associated Press projected that Menefee beat Amanda Edwards, an attorney and former member of the Houston City council, after a protracted process to fill the central Houston seat after Turner's death in March 2025. The process was drawn out by GOP Gov. Greg Abbott’s refusal to quickly schedule a special election following Turner’s death and a crowded field that triggered a runoff following the first round of voting in November.</p> 
<p>But the contest between the pair will continue: Both Menefee, 37, and Edwards, 44, are participating in the March primary for a newly refashioned 18th Congressional District, going up against Rep. Al Green, 78. That winner will be heavily favored to win a full two-year term in November.</p> 
<p>The March primary is the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/texas-18-runoff-dems-00758614" target="_blank"><u>latest example</u></a> of the generational change debate animating the Democratic Party, as the two young Democrats take on progressive icon Green, who has been in Congress for more than two decades. It's a fight that’s taking place nationwide, pitting young and old factions of the party against each other as they both argue they’re better fighters against Republicans.</p> 
<p>Residents in this district have been without consistent representation since former Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee died in 2024. Lee held the seat for three decades.</p> 
<p>Green’s current district was scrambled by the Texas GOP’s redistricting, prompting him to jump into the race to represent a new district that contains many of his constituents.</p> 
<p>Menefee’s victory is a huge boost to his public profile ahead of the primary. Early voting begins in two weeks.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elon Musk pours millions more into helping Republicans keep Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/elon-musk-2026-election-donations-00758992</link>
      <description>The tech billionaire, who once said he had “done enough” political spending, remains a significant benefactor for the Republican Party after patching things up with President Donald Trump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-16be-dbc5-a7bd-1fbe62810001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 20:25:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/1d/af/cf03bb784de5837de753bb120c75/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2216318870">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Elon Musk listens in the Oval Office at the White House on May 21, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1d/af/cf03bb784de5837de753bb120c75/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2216318870" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tech mogul Elon Musk poured $10 million into two major Republican super PACs at the end of last year, according to campaign finance disclosures submitted Saturday, as he once again <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/elon-musk-gop-comeback-00751572" target="_blank">takes a more active role</a> in GOP politics.</p> 
<p>The Tesla and SpaceX CEO, who had a public falling out with President Donald Trump last spring and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/20/elon-musk-political-spending-00358398" target="_blank">said he was giving up on political spending</a>, gave $5 million in December to each of the Congressional Leadership Fund and Senate Leadership Fund, two groups that aim to help the GOP keep control of Congress this year.</p> 
<p>It was Musk’s second round of donations to both groups this cycle, having <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/31/elon-musk-donations-clf-slf-00487699" target="_blank">previously given in June</a>, amid his feud with Trump. Those contributions came shortly before Musk floated starting his own political party, an initiative that never seemed to gain much headway.</p> 
<p>But Musk and Trump have patched up their differences more recently, with the tech CEO joining Trump for dinner at Mar-a-Lago earlier this month. Musk has also been back to advocating for Republican politics on X, which he owns, pushing for senators to pass a plussed up version of the SAVE Act, a bill that would require states to <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2025/04/14/the-house-passed-the-save-act-what-comes-next-00288458" target="_blank">collect proof of citizenship</a> from people registering to vote.</p> 
<p>Musk has thrown his support behind a version called the SAVE Act Plus, calling for ID requirements and a <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/2013271550636826797?s=20" target="_blank">ban of mail voting</a> for most Americans along with other changes to election administration.</p> 
<p>Musk was the biggest individual donor to political committees during the 2024 election cycle, spending roughly $290 million, mostly through his own super PAC, America PAC, in support of Trump.</p> 
<p>In the first few months of the Trump administration, he played an active role with the Department of Government Efficiency, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/03/elon-musk-trump-bill-00382653" target="_blank">began fighting with Trump</a> and Republicans around the president’s One Big Beautiful Bill Act. Musk also threw himself into a Wisconsin Supreme Court election in April where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/elon-musk-wisconsin-loss-reaction-00006129" target="_blank">his preferred candidate lost by 10 points</a>.</p> 
<p>Musk’s funds accounted for just a fraction of total fundraising for both SLF and CLF. SLF raised nearly $77 million in the final six months of 2025 and had $100 million cash on hand, while CLF raised over $38 million over that period and had more than $54 million cash on hand.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-31T14:36:54-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>'There’s something bigger going on': State election chiefs rebuff Trump bid to seize voter rolls</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/democrats-election-trump-voter-rolls-00758940</link>
      <description>Roughly two dozen states have rejected the Trump administration’s request, prompting an unprecedented legal clash between the Justice Department and state election officials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-156e-d1ed-a59e-d77f3b410000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 14:30:18 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/54/7d/f9a2ad7e4cd5953a876add6bfd75/ap22146721014362.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Scott Sonner/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>People wait to vote in-person at Reed High School in Sparks, Nevada, prior to polls closing on Nov. 3, 2020.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/54/7d/f9a2ad7e4cd5953a876add6bfd75/ap22146721014362.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty and Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty and Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic state election officials say the Justice Department’s letter to Minnesota over its voter rolls represents a significant escalation, with several warning that the Trump administration could use immigration enforcement to exert influence over November’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>The officials are baffled by the Trump administration’s continued demand for access to state voter information and refuse to comply, telling POLITICO they view the requests as part of a broader effort by the administration to insert itself into state election proceedings.</p> 
<p>Minnesota Secretary of State Steve Simon, a Democrat, has been at the center of the push after Attorney General Pam Bondi wrote in <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26508586-bondiwalzltr012426/?q=voter&amp;mode=document#document/p3" target="_blank">a letter</a> to Gov. Tim Walz that one condition of restoring “law and order” in the state amid the administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown would be for Minnesota to turn over its voter rolls to the federal government.</p> 
<p>Minnesota — one of two dozen states, along with the District of Columbia, sued by the administration — has rejected the request, prompting an unprecedented legal clash between the Justice Department and state election officials.</p> 
<p>“To me, [it] seems to be a project in service of the president's longstanding but false view that election systems around the country are rigging elections,” Simon told POLITICO. “And this project seems to be in service of that, and that's the best I can tell.”</p> 
<p>Simon said he has not heard back from the Trump administration since responding to the Bondi letter. “This was already a dispute, but it was a dispute being fought where it belongs, which is in a court of law,” he said.</p> 
<p>Arizona Secretary of State Adrian Fontes, a Democrat running for reelection this year, called the letter to officials in Minnesota “extortion” and echoed the suggestion that the effort was aimed at something beyond voter rolls.</p> 
<p>"The voter roll stuff is not about voter rolls. There’s something bigger going on,” Fontes said in an interview this week, as dozens of secretaries of state gathered in Washington for a meeting of the National Association of Secretaries of State. “They’re bits and pieces, interchangeable in this jigsaw puzzle, and we're being told something that's not true,” he added.</p> 
<p>The highly unusual push for access to states’ voter rolls is part of a yearlong campaign by the Trump administration, which says it is seeking to ensure that states’ voter registration practices comply with federal law and safeguard election integrity. The White House has requested voter records from nearly every state and Washington, D.C. The move comes as Trump frequently <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/trump-2020-election-prosecutions-00738778" target="_blank">repeats his false claim</a> that the 2020 presidential election was “rigged.”</p> 
<p>The White House said it was authorized to make the requests under longstanding laws such as the Civil Rights Act.</p> 
<p>“The Civil Rights Act, National Voting Rights Act, and Help America Vote Act all give the Department of Justice full authority to ensure states comply with federal election laws, which mandate accurate state voter rolls. President Trump is committed to ensuring that Americans have full confidence in the administration of elections, and that includes totally accurate and up-to-date voter rolls free of errors and unlawfully registered non-citizen voters,” said White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department did not immediately respond to POLITICO’s request for comment.</p> 
<p>At least 11 states have complied with the administration’s request, according to the <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/research-reports/tracker-justice-department-requests-voter-information" target="_blank">Brennan Center</a>.</p> 
<p>Wyoming is one of the states that complied, and its secretary of state, Chuck Gray, a Republican, told reporters on Friday that it has been “very disturbing” to watch Democrats rebuff the administration’s request to engage in what he described as regular upkeep of voter rolls.</p> 
<p>“We've been engaging in routine voter list maintenance that people support in making sure the voter lists are clean,” he said.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department has sued the 24 states — most, but not all, of which are helmed by Democrats — that have refused to comply, with most citing concerns over exposing sensitive voter information.</p> 
<p>“I'm certainly concerned that people may fear that the Department of Justice having access to the voting rolls might make them a target in some way,” said Maine Democratic Secretary of State Shenna Bellows.</p> 
<p>“This Justice Department has weaponized its office to target people based on identity and based on political affiliation,” she said.</p> 
<p>Uzoma Nkwonta, a partner at Elias Law Group, which is representing voters and civic organizations in several states who are also trying to prevent the release of voter rolls, called the effort “another example of overreach by the Department of Justice and the federal government.” “The fact that DOJ officials have stated publicly that they expect to see hundreds of thousands individuals removed from the rolls once they have this data … should set off a red flag,” Nkwonta said, noting that maintaining voter registration lists is a responsibility for the states, not the federal government.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ICE halted its surge in Maine. The state might not be quick to forget.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/maine-senate-ice-campaign-00758811</link>
      <description>Sen. Susan Collins’ announcement of ICE’s drawdown relieved some of the pressure in the blue state. But Democrats still say it’s not enough.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-11e5-dbc5-a7bd-19fdd4120000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/32/15/736b70614c48b37da1cd891552cd/immigration-enforcement-maine-07716.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Robert F. Bukaty/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Attendees hold signs at a news conference held by public officials and faith leaders calling for the abolishment of the U.S. Immigrant and Customs Enforcement, Jan. 30, 2026, in Portland, Maine.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/32/15/736b70614c48b37da1cd891552cd/immigration-enforcement-maine-07716.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BANGOR, Maine — The federal immigration crackdown in Maine may have ended, but the political fallout could continue to reverberate through the 2026 election.</p> 
<p>Democratic Gov. Janet Mills <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/janet-mills-tv-ad-ice-00756765" target="_blank">launched her first Senate campaign ad on Friday</a> — and it’s focused on attacking Immigration and Customs Enforcement. Political newcomer Graham Platner, competing with Mills for the Democratic nomination, held an anti-ICE protest at Sen. Susan Collins’ offices in Maine on Thursday, calling for her to block funds for the agency.</p> 
<p>The message from both Democrats was clear: Immigration enforcement politics is not going away, and they think it could be a winning issue as they look to unseat the only Republican senator up for reelection this year in a state former Vice President Kamala Harris won in 2024.</p> 
<p>But Collins’ Thursday announcement that ICE was ending its immigration enforcement campaign in Maine — dubbed Operation Catch of the Day by the Department of Homeland Security — released some of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/susan-collins-dhs-ice-shutdown-00751545?utm_content=topic/politics&amp;utm_source=flipboard" target="_blank">pressure that had been building</a> in the state for more than a week, with local leaders expressing an initial sense of relief.</p> 
<p>That campaign had left the state’s immigrant communities hiding in fear and Democrats and activists raging at their treatment. The surge disrupted life for many in southern Maine, with decreased attendance in schools, legal immigrants afraid to go to work and observers trailing ICE agents in the state.</p> 
<p>Now, in the aftermath of an operation that led to more than 200 arrests and prompted widespread protests, lawmakers and community leaders are navigating the upheaval left behind. The political impact continues to ripple.</p> 
<p>Collins' announcement Thursday morning, which implied her conversations with Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem had helped sway the decision, is emblematic of how she wants voters to think of her: a powerful pragmatist who can get results, including by standing up to her own party. And it was a high-profile reminder of her longstanding case that her senior role in Washington helps her deliver for the Pine Tree State.</p> 
<p>Still, Democrats and activists, buoyed by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270" target="_blank">rapidly shifting public opinion around immigration enforcement</a> after videos of violent arrests and two fatal shootings in Minneapolis, are redoubling efforts for broader restrictions on ICE and its funding — along with a reckoning on what happened in Maine. Reports of the end of the operation in Maine, they said, are not enough.</p> 
<p>“Senator Collins is going to try to use this moment to trick us. To say that she, somehow, used her power to impose upon ICE,” Platner said in protests at the senator’s Portland and Bangor offices on Thursday, held hours after the end of the surge was announced.</p> 
<p>He mocked what he called a “pinky promise” she received from Noem to cheers from dozens of supporters who had gathered in Bangor in single-digit temperatures. “We all know it’s nonsense. What she is actually doing is trying to justify to us why she is about to try to give them 9 billion more dollars in funding."</p> 
<p>Platner demanded that Collins, the Senate’s top appropriator, cut off funding for ICE entirely, saying the Trump administration could not be trusted to follow the law.</p> 
<p>Collins advocated for passing a DHS funding bill that Democrats blocked this week, citing its funding for body cameras for federal officers as well as de-escalation training. Negotiations are likely to continue in Washington after lawmakers agreed to pass just a two-week stopgap. Failure to pass DHS funding would not stop ICE, as the agency is well-funded from Trump’s major budget bill last summer, but Democrats are hoping to leverage anger at the agency to pressure the GOP for reforms. A Collins spokesperson declined to comment for this story.</p> 
<p>The Maine senator’s positioning still held her somewhat as an outlier. Maine Republicans largely expressed support for federal immigration operations in the state while accusing Mills and Democrats of ginning up conflict with law enforcement. Local Republicans were largely quiet about Collins’ news of the drawdown.</p> 
<p>Mills, in an interview earlier in the week, derided Collins’ calls for retraining ICE officers, telling POLITICO that the “horse was out of the barn already.” On Thursday, she characterized the drawdown of ICE operations as insufficient, calling for Noem’s removal at DHS as well as congressional action to halt ICE funding until measures are in place at the agency to prevent what she characterized as “abuses of power.”</p> 
<p>“Until there are substantive measures and changes in place, no state — including Maine — is protected from the weaponization of Federal law enforcement agencies against its own citizens by the Trump Administration,” she said in a statement on Thursday.</p> 
<p>Mills and Maine Attorney General Aaron Frey, a Democrat, sent a letter to Noem and Acting ICE Director Todd Lyons on Friday demanding information about the immigrants arrested in the state and where they are now.</p> 
<p>Community leaders and lawmakers are also working to understand what the drawdown means in practice, what happened to those detained by ICE and how to begin restoring trust among immigrants who have barely left their homes in weeks.</p> 
<p>“It is welcome news. ICE operations in Maine have failed to improve public safety and have caused lasting damage to our communities,” said Carl Sheline, the mayor of Lewiston, which is home to a large Somali American population and was one of the Maine cities to see significant ICE activity. “We will continue working to ensure that those who were wrongfully detained by ICE are returned to us.”</p> 
<p>Maine House Speaker Ryan Fecteau, a Democrat from Biddeford, said among those detained by ICE was a man named Marcos, whom Fecteau had previously employed as a contractor working on his home. Fecteau said he talked on Thursday to the man’s wife, who said he was at an ICE facility in Arizona two days earlier, but the ICE database was no longer showing his whereabouts.</p> 
<p>“Over the last week and a half there have been people in Maine who have been arrested and detained unlawfully. We want answers for those people. Who they are, where they are, what was the reason for their detention. Those things need to be answered,” Fecteau said. “I hope that Senator Collins, who clearly has some influence here — she spoke with Kristi Noem yesterday — I hope that was part of the conversation as well.”</p> 
<p>In Augusta on Thursday, Maine lawmakers heard testimony over a bill that would require ICE to obtain judicial warrants to search private spaces of schools and health care facilities, among other locations.</p> 
<p>Mills on Thursday threw her weight behind the new bill, citing in part the destabilizing effects of the recent surge. It was a notable move for the former prosecutor, who faced heat from progressives and Platner for not taking a stronger stance last year when she allowed a bill limiting law enforcement cooperation with ICE to go into effect without her signature, rather than signing it outright.</p> 
<p>Activists and observers who had been trailing ICE in Maine noted some agents appeared to be off duty on Thursday, reflecting the drawdown.</p> 
<p>“It's good news. I hope it's true. I hope that we can all find peace and rest in the next coming days,” Eric Nathanson, an activist with Jewish Action Maine who was arrested alongside other faith leaders earlier in the week while protesting at Collins’ Portland office. “If the surge is on pause, we reiterate the goal of no additional funding even more strongly.”</p> 
<p>But the images and experiences from the past week were not easily forgotten.</p> 
<p>“Three people in the past week were abducted in front of my workplace. My coworkers had to watch an ICE agent beat and drag people out of cars,” Nathanson said. “We will stay strong and stay vigilant.”</p> 
<p><i>Correction: An earlier version of this story misstated Maine's state nickname. It is the Pine Tree State.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Houston runoff sets up next Democratic generational fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/texas-18-runoff-dems-00758614</link>
      <description>Saturday’s oddly timed runoff is occurring after months of delays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1127-df17-afbf-7d3785d00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 07:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a9/3d/516941bd4914876b52948dce09f3/election-2025-congress-texas-28887.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ashley Landis/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Democratic 18th Congressional District candidate Amanda Edwards arrives for an election night watch party on Nov. 4, 2025, in Houston.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a9/3d/516941bd4914876b52948dce09f3/election-2025-congress-texas-28887.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>HOUSTON — House Republicans’ slim majority will be even leaner after Saturday, when Democrats vote to fill the Texas seat left open when Rep. Sylvester Turner unexpectedly died last year.</p> 
<p>But the vote will just be the next step in choosing who ultimately represents Texas’ 18th Congressional District for a full two-year term — and sets up the next generational change debate that has roiled the party nationwide.</p> 
<p>Just five weeks after Saturday’s special election runoff, voters in this Democratic hub of Black political power will return to the polls for a March primary to pick someone to represent the district after the seat was redrawn as part of Texas’ redistricting.</p> 
<p>On Saturday, voters are choosing between Harris County attorney Christian Menefee, 37, or former Houston City Councilmember Amanda Edwards, 44, to fill the current seat. The pair emerged as the top two vote-getters in a crowded 16-person primary in November, with Menefee finishing ahead of Edwards by 3 percentage points.</p> 
<p>The winner will then hold the incumbency for just a few weeks before challenging activist icon Rep. Al Green, 78. That March election, all three candidates argue, is about choosing the best fighter to stand up to House Republicans, the Trump administration and the Texas GOP, which has been encroaching on Houston’s autonomy in recent years as Republicans try to weaken Democrats’ influence in the one of the nation’s largest cities.</p> 
<p>“It’s going to be a fight between generations,” said Marc Campos, a longtime Democratic consultant in Houston, who is unaffiliated with any campaign.</p> 
<p>Saturday’s oddly timed runoff is occurring after months of delays by Gov. Greg Abbott, who didn’t call for the special election to fill the seat until eight months after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/05/texas-democrat-sylvester-turner-dies-00213068" target="_blank">Turner's death</a>. Turner, in 2022, revealed he had been recovering from bone cancer and his family said he died from “enduring health complications.” He had been elected to replace former Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/07/20/texas-rep-sheila-jackson-lee-dies-at-age-74-00169909" target="_blank">died in office</a> in 2024 after being diagnosed with pancreatic cancer. She served the district for nearly three decades.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/9f/7f/011bbdc14490b3132df6ffc7fe1d/election-2025-congress-texas-71344.jpg" alt="Democratic 18th Congressional District candidate Christian Menefee greets voters near a polling place on Nov. 4, 2025, in Houston. " data-portal-copyright="Ashley Landis/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25308654371344" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Democratic 18th Congressional District candidate Christian Menefee greets voters near a polling place on Nov. 4, 2025, in Houston. "/><p>Abbott justified the special election hold up by saying he didn’t trust Harris County to conduct a swift and valid election. The governor, who has set his sights on flipping the county in November, has <a href="https://gov.texas.gov/news/post/governor-abbott-calls-for-investigation-of-harris-county-elections" target="_blank">claimed for years</a> that there are widespread problems with electoral administration in Houston.</p> 
<p>Texas Democrats said Abbott’s foot-dragging to fill the seat — which has advantaged House Republicans' paper-thin majority in Washington — is another example of GOP meddling with Democratic power in major cities. Republicans’ off-cycle redistricting last year scrambled Democratic seats in Houston, Dallas and Austin. Green, a towering figure in Houston political circles, jumped into the race for the newly gerrymandered 18th seat after the neighboring district he held for more than 20 years was carved up by the GOP.</p> 
<p>In another sign of how redistricting has muddled campaigns, Menefee and Edwards are running in Saturday’s runoff under different lines from the upcoming March primary — forcing the pair to run simultaneous campaigns with two overlapping but not identical sets of voters. Early voting in the March primary begins in two weeks.</p> 
<p>“This is a microcosm of forced redistricting,” said Odus Evbagharu, a Menefee aide. “It’s something that got forced down our throats, and now we just have to live with that.”</p> 
<p>During the final stretch of the runoff, candidates crisscrossed both the old and new 18th districts, an area of central Houston with a large Black population. About a quarter of the district’s current constituents live within its new iteration.</p> 
<p>At a candidate forum held in a Catholic church on Thursday evening, Green, Menefee, Edwards and a fourth candidate running in the primary with little name recognition, newcomer Gretchen Brown, quickly rattled off their biographies and what they would bring to Washington.</p> 
<p>For Green, it wasn’t an introduction as much as a reminder to the audience that he has represented many of them for two decades. A significant share of Green’s constituents in the new 18th district were shuffled over from Green's old district.</p> 
<p>“It is important for people to understand that I'm not moving into a new congressional district,” Green said while taking the microphone and brandishing his signature gold-capped cane. “I am not. The congressional district moved to me.”</p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ad/40/ec994b5049a8b0500a435bcdb265/supreme-court-voting-rights-73810.jpg" alt="Rep. Al Green (D-Texas) speaks to demonstrators in front of the Supreme Court as the court hearings oral arguments in the Louisiana second majority black Congressional district, in Washington, Oct. 15, 2025. " data-portal-copyright="Cliff Owen/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25288543573810" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Rep. Al Green (D-Texas) speaks to demonstrators in front of the Supreme Court as the court hearings oral arguments in the Louisiana second majority black Congressional district, in Washington, Oct. 15, 2025. "/><p>In this era when Democrats are eager to forcefully counter Republicans, voters here have a choice: Support a trusted figure who can navigate Washington or take a chance on a younger representative seen as the future of the party. It's an urgent debate within the party as Democrats plot their strategy for regaining power, and is playing out in primaries across the country. Some other top Democrats facing generational primaries, including Reps. Nancy Pelosi of California and Steny Hoyer of Maryland, opted not to run again.</p> 
<p>“Al Green has a great name,” said Harris County Commissioner Rodney Ellis, who endorsed Menefee in the runoff but has not weighed in on the primary. “But then, on the other hand, whoever wins [the runoff] will get a bump of celebrity status.”</p> 
<p>Menefee made local history as the youngest elected Harris County attorney — the first Black person in the job — and has built his reputation on going head-to-head with Abbott, suing the governor’s ban on mask mandates and challenging his demands to audit local elections. It’s his first stint in public office after he ran a surprise campaign ousting the three-term incumbent in 2020.</p> 
<p>Menefee — who is <a href="https://www.facebook.com/ChristianDMenefee/videos/1554491595797005/" target="_blank">running ads</a> playing on 90’s millennial nostalgia — has racked up endorsements from organizations like Leaders We Deserve and Houston Black American Democrats, more than a dozen labor groups, and prominent figures like Rep. Jasmine Crockett and former Rep. Beto O’Rourke.</p> 
<p>Edwards draws on broad support from women and from her years as an attorney and at-large member of the city council. She won the endorsement of past opponent Jolanda Jones, a state representative who has served as a main Menefee antagonist, criticizing him for continuing to collect his government salary while campaigning.</p> 
<p>Edwards is also a familiar face on campaign mailers: She ran unsuccessfully for U.S. Senate in 2020, Houston mayor in 2023 and U.S. House in 2024. Her career in politics began when she was a congressional aide for Lee as a recent college graduate.</p> 
<p>Menefee and Edwards dismiss the idea that the primary will be a referendum on age, seeing it instead as an expression of voters’ desire to see broad change in Congress.</p> 
<p>“What I think people want is something new,” Menefee said in an interview. “They want new strategic thinkers who are going to come in and have a plan for opposition against the president.”</p> 
<p>Edwards argues it's also an issue of continuity. A Green victory would mean that some constituents living in the district will have been represented by four lawmakers in three years. “They want to pass that torch forward and this is an opportunity to do that,” she said. “It's not a question of age. It's a question of succession.”</p> 
<p>Green, in an interview, said he expects people will vote for him if they primarily value experience and accomplishments, ticking off his leadership on the Homeland Security and Oversight committees, along with the billions he has steered toward his district and recommendation of three judges confirmed during the Obama administration.</p> 
<p>“I bring to the table traditionally what people have looked for when they were trying to make a decision,” he said. “So we'll find out whether tradition continues or whether we'll have a different circumstance.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘A pretext to rig the election’: Democrats scramble to block ICE crackdowns near polling sites</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/democrats-ice-deployments-midterm-elections-00756490</link>
      <description>Election officials are preparing for the possibility of immigration enforcement activity at or near polling sites in November.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0c46-df8c-a99d-fdf6426f0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 10:01:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/05/cf/e7e58cb9444d8d8371e34fffcf26/imageedit-2-7863109265.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ashlee Rezin/Chicago Sun-Times via AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Federal immigration and border agents walk along West Wacker Drive in the Loop in Chicago on Sept. 28, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/05/cf/e7e58cb9444d8d8371e34fffcf26/imageedit-2-7863109265.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Immigration enforcement is sowing chaos in Minneapolis and across the country. Democrats, elections officials and civil rights groups fear it could interfere with this November’s elections — and are scrambling for a response.</p> 
<p>They’re warning that the White House’s deployments of Immigration and Customs Enforcement and Border Patrol agents could act as a voter suppression tool should armed officers conduct raids at or near polling locations, scaring citizens into staying home.</p> 
<p>“You have to see what's happening: Trump is trying to create a pretext to rig the election,” said Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.). “It stands to reason that this private police [force] that he’s building is, in part, to be used to try to suppress turnout in the election.”</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats considered a requirement banning ICE agents from polling sites as part of their demands in negotiating the Homeland Security funding bill, according to Murphy and Sen. Gary Peters (D-Mich.). But that policy was not included in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/democrats-dhs-minnesota-shutdown-00753256" target="_blank">Senate Democratic appropriators’ final list of demands</a> to avoid a partial government shutdown, leaving voting rights advocates and Democratic state election officials on edge about what’s to come.</p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson called fears of voter suppression “Democrat conspiracies” with “no basis in reality.”</p> 
<p>“President Trump cares deeply about the integrity of our elections — and so do the millions of Americans who sent him back to office based on his pledge to secure our elections,” Jackson said in a statement. “These Democrat conspiracies have no basis in reality and their claims shouldn’t be amplified uncritically by the mainstream media. ICE is focused on removing criminal illegal aliens from [the] country, who should be nowhere near any polling places because it would be a crime for them to vote.”</p> 
<p>ICE's aggressive crackdowns have already led to citizens hiding at home, and election officials worry that fears of harassment and arrest could keep them from exercising their right to vote.</p> 
<p>“In Maine, we saw people were afraid to leave their homes for groceries, to go to work or to go to school, because of fear of wrongful arrest and imprisonment,” Maine Secretary of State Shenna Bellows, a Democrat who’s running for governor, told POLITICO on Thursday. “If people are too afraid to go to the grocery store because armed ICE agents are patrolling the streets, that may increase fears about going to vote.”</p> 
<p>Bellows said her office is preparing for next month’s special legislative election by ensuring voters are comfortable with absentee voting procedures, especially those in areas with large immigrant populations that have been impacted by ICE’s recent crackdown in the state.</p> 
<p>Immigration enforcement activity near polling locations could dissuade those with noncitizen family members or voters of color, who fear being racially profiled, from turning out. And widespread deployments of immigration officers to battleground districts could cause chaos in key races and swing close elections.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration dispatched about 3,000 federal agents to Minneapolis to apprehend non-citizens in an operation that many in the state and elsewhere consider heavy-handed and excessive. The president and senior officials have indicated that the operation is about more than just law enforcement.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/trump-minnesota-reckoning-retribution-warning-00724534" target="_blank">called the Minnesota operation</a> a “day of reckoning and retribution” and has tied the operation to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/brace-for-impact-trump-turns-fraud-into-new-weapon-against-blue-states-00719401" target="_blank">welfare fraud</a> in the state. On Saturday, Attorney General Pam Bondi <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26508586-bondiwalzltr012426/" target="_blank">sent a letter</a> to Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz demanding he turn over the state’s voter rolls, an action <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/minnesota-operation-metro-surge-case-00746755" target="_blank">lawyers for the state of Minnesota described</a> as a “shakedown” and a “ransom note.”</p> 
<p>“The demand for the voter rolls tells you what this is really about,” Sen. Alex Padilla (D-Calif.), who oversaw California’s elections for six years as secretary of state, told reporters Wednesday. “It’s about trying to rig the next election, and a desperate attempt to hold onto power.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/USCODE-2011-title18/html/USCODE-2011-title18-partI-chap29-sec592.htm" target="_blank">Federal law is explicit</a> in banning “any troops or armed men at any place where a general or special election is held,” unless to “repel armed enemies of the United States[.]” Many local election officials also take great care to avoid spooking voters by placing law enforcement at polling places, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/10/30/election-threats-violence-00186377" target="_blank">some states even have laws regulating this</a>. Voter intimidation is illegal across the entire country.</p> 
<p>But Trump has falsely and repeatedly claimed for more than a decade <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-migrants-border-voter-fraud-campaign-40bbf5748615a3b1f6087ff920f59278" target="_blank">that millions of illegal immigrants vote</a> in the U.S., arguing that was one factor in his 2020 loss. He also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/08/23/meadows-trump-police-polls-400255" target="_blank">pledged before the 2020 election to send “sheriffs” and “law enforcement”</a> to polling places.</p> 
<p>Some Trump allies have openly described the possibility of deploying immigration enforcement officers to polling sites to ensure non-citizens do not vote.</p> 
<p>“They’re petrified over at MSNBC and CNN that, hey, since we’re taking control of the cities, there’s going to be ICE officers near polling places,” former White House chief strategist Steve Bannon said <a href="https://warroom.org/bannons-warroom-show-clip-roundup-19-august-25-am/" target="_blank">during his show last August</a>. “You’re damn right. … We’re not going to allow any illegal aliens to vote.”</p> 
<p>Civil rights groups are preparing for the possibility that Trump exercises emergency powers to allow such a move.</p> 
<p>Joanna Lydgate, CEO of the States United Democracy Center, told reporters this week that the Trump administration is “using these violent ICE operations as a weapon” for political ends.</p> 
<p>“[Trump] might try to use an executive order or his emergency powers in the 11th hour to interfere with the upcoming election, which is, of course, something that no president in American history has ever done, but something that we need to be prepared for,” Lydgate said Monday during a press briefing.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration has continued its focus on election administration. On Wednesday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/fbi-raid-georgia-elections-trump-2020-00753249" target="_blank">the FBI executed a search warrant</a> at the Fulton County elections office outside Atlanta. Last week, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-musk-doge-social-security-00737245" target="_blank">the Justice Department revealed</a> that DOGE employees were secretly communicating with an advocacy group seeking to “overturn election results in certain states” and may have used Social Security data to match voter rolls. Last week in Davos, Trump suggested <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/trump-2020-election-prosecutions-00738778" target="_blank">prosecutions are forthcoming</a> related to the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>State election officials in both parties <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/tulsi-gabbard-2020-election-investigation-00755487" target="_blank">are anxious to see</a> why Director of National Intelligence Tulsi Gabbard, Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem and Attorney General Pam Bondi will address the winter meeting of the National Association of Secretaries of State on Friday. A DHS spokesperson didn’t respond to request for comment for this story.</p> 
<p>Nonprofit legal groups are already gearing up to challenge any efforts to intimidate voters around the November midterms, said Skye Perryman, president and CEO of Democracy Forward.</p> 
<p>“Litigation is going to remain an incredibly important guardrail,” said Perryman, whose nonprofit <a href="https://democracyforward.org/work/legal/stopping-doges-unlawful-seizure-of-americans-social-security-data/" target="_blank">led one of the lawsuits</a> against DOGE’s access to voter information. “And there are many cases that can be swiftly filed on an emergency basis, or even potentially proactively, in order to try to keep the communities as safe as possible.”</p> 
<p>David Becker, the executive director and founder of the nonpartisan Center for Election Innovation &amp; Research, warned that election officials across the country — from secretaries of state to local officers — are seeing “a level of federal interference in their work which is unconstitutional and unprecedented.”</p> 
<p>“I want to stress how unusual this is,” Becker, a former DOJ civil rights attorney, told POLITICO. “County election officials shouldn't have to be thinking about what the president of the United States might say about elections.”</p> 
<p>Those elections officials are working to instill trust in the electoral process, Becker said, and will encourage voters to utilize a variety of alternative ways to cast a ballot, such as early voting or voting by mail, depending on the state.</p> 
<p>An attempt to heighten immigration enforcement before the election could just as easily backfire for Republicans. Trump is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270" target="_blank">now under water on the immigration issue</a>, with polls showing a majority of voters believe his deportation push went too far and want to see it reined in. Justin Levitt, a professor at Loyola Law School who worked in the Biden White House as an adviser on democracy and voting rights, pointed to high turnout in this week’s special elections for Minnesota legislature seats in Democratic-heavy districts, where Democrats romped.</p> 
<p>“In places where there might be disruption, Minnesota is proving that you might well earn yourself a real significant backlash,” Levitt said.</p> 
<p>But even talking about election suppression has a risk of discouraging voters, convincing them there is risk involved or that the elections might be rigged anyway. Conversely, talk of vote-rigging can do the same thing.</p> 
<p>“Our fight right now is both to protect the security of our elections and people's faith in them, because they're deeply intertwined and they're both under attack,” said Michigan Secretary of State Jocelyn Benson.</p> 
<p><i>Andrew Howard contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
