<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/politics-news.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 16:05:11 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Trump’s super PAC enters the midterms with $300 million in the bank</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/02/trump-super-pac-2026-midterm-election-00709395</link>
      <description>MAGA Inc. reported raking in over $100 million in the second half of the year, adding to Trump’s substantial war chest heading into the midterms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-8084-dba9-addb-b3bf93620000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 16:05:11 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ee/31/11bb21cf419fa2b0365ac92acea6/trump-55935.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Karl B DeBlaker/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump delivers remarks in Rocky Mount, North Carolina, Dec. 19, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ee/31/11bb21cf419fa2b0365ac92acea6/trump-55935.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump’s primary super PAC raised over $102 million in the second half of 2025, carrying a war chest stocked with hundreds of millions of dollars into the midterms.</p> 
<p>That massive sum, combined with even greater fundraising in the first half of the year and minimal spending throughout 2025, leaves the PAC with approximately $300 million cash on hand, positioning the president’s allies to wield massive influence over the midterms.</p> 
<p>The disclosure, which which was reported in <a href="https://docquery.fec.gov/cgi-bin/forms/C00892471/1930418" target="_blank">a filing submitted to the Federal Election Commission</a> this week and goes through Dec. 22, shows MAGA Inc. with $294 million cash on hand. In a statement, a MAGA Inc. spokesperson said the PAC ended the year with $304 million cash on hand.</p> 
<p>“Thanks to President Trump’s leadership, MAGA Inc will have the resources to help candidates who support President Trump's America First agenda of securing our border, keeping our streets safe, supercharging our economy, and making life more affordable for all Americans,” the organization said.</p> 
<p>The enormous sum of money doesn’t represent the entire war chest at Trump’s disposal; several affiliated PACs have continued to raise money in support of the president, adding to the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/01/trump-fundraising-midterms-00488165" target="_blank">growing stockpile of cash</a> that Republicans around the country will hope to tap into as they seek to maintain majorities in Congress in November.</p> 
<p>MAGA Inc. made its first independent expenditures of the year in support of Rep. Matt Van Epps, who won a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/a-nationalized-tennessee-special-election-has-both-parties-on-edge-00671736" target="_blank">hard-fought special election</a> in Tennessee’s 7th District in December. The super PAC spent $1.6 million to help boost Van Epps over Democrat Aftyn Behn in a district Trump won by 22 points in 2024.</p> 
<p>The super PAC, which does not face donation limits, drew contributions from regular GOP donors and from leaders in the artificial intelligence and cryptocurrency industries. </p> 
<p>OpenAI President Greg Brockman gave $25 million and Foris DAX Inc., the U.S.-based arm of the company that operates Crypto.com, contributed $20 million on top of an additional $10 million it gave at the beginning of 2025.</p> 
<p>Private equity investor Konstantin Sokolov donated $11 million, and NASA Administrator Jared Isaacman, who was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/jared-isaacman-nasa-head-00695557" target="_blank">confirmed in December</a> despite Trump withdrawing his nomination in May before renominating him, contributed $2 million to the PAC last year, including $1 million in the second half of the year.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats spy rare opening in rural America</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/27/democrats-rural-voters-economy-trump-midterms-00700822</link>
      <description>President Donald Trump's unpopular tariff and health care decisions have created an opportunity for the Democratic Party to court a GOP-loyal bloc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4d25-d651-a1ff-7f6575b60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7e/4e/69db3c884b4a91b0b1dc8c8c5152/voting-lists-states-sued-34269.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Kayla Wolf/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A voter leaves Albion Town Hall after casting their ballot on Election Day, Nov. 5, 2024, in Wisconsin.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7e/4e/69db3c884b4a91b0b1dc8c8c5152/voting-lists-states-sued-34269.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Marcia Brown, Samuel Benson and Rachel Shin</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Marcia Brown, Samuel Benson and Rachel Shin</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are accustomed to losing in rural America — especially to Donald Trump. Now they’re hoping the president’s own policies might prove to be the leverage they need going into next year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>The party faces immense challenges in farm country that have overwhelmingly voted Republican for decades and turned out in droves on the president’s behalf three times. But over the past year, those same communities have borne the brunt of <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/30/congress/trump-administration-readies-up-to-12-billion-for-initial-farm-aid-payment-00630700" target="_blank">his tariff agenda</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/15/the-rural-health-hunger-games-are-underway-00563763" target="_blank">health care center closures</a>, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/26/trump-thanksgiving-food-prices-groceries-poll-00669200" target="_blank">lingering inflation</a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/12/15/doge-cuts-donald-trump-montana-00681695" target="_blank">cuts to public lands programs</a>.</p> 
<p>Where Trump sees an “A++++++” economy, large percentages of both Republican and Democratic voters blame his decisions for stubbornly high prices for groceries and housing, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/poll-americans-trump-voters-affordability-crisis-00674747" target="_blank">according to recent polling from POLITICO and Public First.</a></p> 
<p>Democrats have a long way to go in rebuilding trust with rural voters. But conversations with more than a dozen current and former Democratic lawmakers, party officials and political strategists suggest they also feel the urgency of tapping into the discontent being generated by Trump’s agenda.</p> 
<p>The party is trying to replace wishful thinking with a new shoe-leather strategy in rural communities where it has long lacked a presence and is deploying unhappy farmers in media campaigns. If Democrats mean to retake Congress in the midterms or have a shot at the White House in 2028, their candidates don't necessarily need to sweep rural counties — they just need to eat into the margins Trump was getting, which were frequently north of 80 percent of the vote.</p> 
<p>“We have a unique opening because of all that's happening with this administration,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/congress/member/413257" target="_blank">Nikki Budzinski</a> (D-Ill.), whose district includes significant rural and farming interests. Farmers and rural voters “might be listening in a more unique way than they maybe have ever in the past. And we need to walk through that door.”</p> 
<p>Democrats have previously dedicated relatively modest amounts of money, staff and advertising to rural counties and districts outside of swing states. But after a string of off-year victories last month, House Democrats have launched <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/democrats-eye-gains-with-rural-voters-voters-of-color-ahead-of-2026-00667746" target="_blank">their first-ever rural outreach program</a>, an eight-figure campaign that will fund efforts to hire staffers for candidates, mobilize voters and run ads focusing on the cost of living.</p> 
<p>Even some Republicans acknowledge the GOP can’t take rural communities for granted.</p> 
<p>“Right now, the farm community is with [Trump]. I think the thing that Republicans should worry about is enthusiasm, in getting out and actually voting,” Senate Agriculture Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51287" data-person-id="51287">John Boozman</a> (R-Ark.) said. “It's one thing to be supportive, it's another thing to actually go vote on Election Day.”<br></p><p>Joe Manchin, a Democrat-turned-independent former senator and governor, won six statewide races running as a Democrat in solid-red West Virginia. He said the party needs to focus on finding candidates who can relate to rural Americans by focusing on key issues — “common sense shit,” he explained, like fiscal responsibility and affordability.</p> 
<p>For example, candidates like Abigail Spanberger and Mikie Sherrill <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/16/economy-voters-new-jersey-virginia-midterms-trump-00693015" target="_blank">won their gubernatorial elections last month</a> by distancing themselves from the Democratic Party’s brand and zeroing in on high prices. </p> 
<p>“They're the kind of the centrist Democrats you need,” Manchin said. “They're the only ones who are going to win in these tough areas.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium is-centered">The tariff play</h5> 
<p>The politics that defines much of the division between urban and rural voters <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-nightly/2024/02/22/they-surveyed-10-000-rural-voters-heres-what-they-learned-00142795" target="_blank">emerged in the late 1980s</a>, as post-Carter Democrats pushed policies that the latter saw as detrimental to agricultural and manufacturing sectors. That left rural voters especially primed for Trump’s brand of economic populism: He won 64 percent of them in 2024, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/11/21/nx-s1-5198616/2024-presidential-election-results-republican-shift" target="_blank">the best performance of any presidential candidate</a> in decades and beating his own 2016 margin.</p> 
<p>"One of the reasons we were in such a negative place with rural voters is we sort of ceded that ground, stopped showing up, stopped talking to these folks, and really relied on the urban centers," Libby Schneider, deputy executive director of the Democratic National Committee, said. “And we saw how that gamble failed in 2024 when folks in urban centers stayed home.”</p> 
<p>Then, in April, Trump began his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/trump-tariff-trade-partners-liberation-day-00267350" target="_blank">chaotic&nbsp;tariff rollout.</a></p> 
<p>While farmers had stomached Trump’s tariffs in the first term — and voted to bring him back in 2024 — their economic position is weaker and the tariffs are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/04/farmers-tariffs-trump-trade-war-00271146" target="_blank">much higher and more expansive this time around.</a> </p> 
<p>Farmers and businesses experienced whiplash as tariff deadlines came and went, confusing people throughout the food supply chain about how they would be impacted. Fertilizer and fuel costs rose and markets for exports like soybeans dried up. Some groups, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/27/like-eggs-part-two-trump-administration-scrambles-to-bring-down-beef-prices-00622680" target="_blank">cattle ranchers who have long allied with Trump</a>, publicly broke with the president's trade agenda when he suggested importing Argentinian beef to lower food prices.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/02/95/84e671e64b4db05a09327f90e7c2/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2242299726" alt="A combine harvests soybeans on Oct. 14, 2025, in Marion, Kentucky. " data-portal-copyright="Jan Sonnenmair/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2242299726" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="A combine harvests soybeans on Oct. 14, 2025, in Marion, Kentucky. "/><p>While most rural voters are not farmers, agriculture is a critical piece of the rural economy, making farm policy one of the primary ways federal policymaking affects those communities. Some voters may support tariffs in theory in the hopes they could revitalize the labor market and prompt fairer trade terms for farm goods, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/poll-affordability-cost-of-living-00678076" target="_blank">polling suggests&nbsp;they&nbsp;view&nbsp;Trump's&nbsp;plans&nbsp;as&nbsp;too&nbsp;arbitrary</a> to achieve those goals.</p> 
<p>A majority of people surveyed in an October POLITICO poll (53 percent) supported avoiding tariffs on imports if that meant keeping costs low for consumers.</p> 
<p>Spanberger, the Virginia governor-elect, won in part by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/30/democrats-rural-voters-tight-virginia-governor-race-00628974" target="_blank">focusing her messaging in rural counties</a> on tariffs and tying the economic discomfort voters were feeling to Trump and the Republican Party. She outperformed <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/06/democrats-spanberger-wins-rural-voters-00641266" target="_blank">Kamala Harris in 48 of Virginia’s 52 rural localities.</a></p> 
<p>National Democrats, excited by Spanberger’s success, have made their own moves: Beyond the DCCC’s eight-figure investment into rural voters and voters of color and the new farmer-focused ad campaigns, a caucus of more than 100 moderate Democratic lawmakers recently released a policy agenda that includes passing a farm bill, expanding rural broadband funding and federal funding for local food purchases.</p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Kush Desai defended the Trump administration’s policies and said “supporting rural Americans has been a key focus,” which is why the administration has sought to use tariffs to open up new export markets for farmers.</p> 
<p>The RNC isn’t fazed either.</p> 
<p>"Rural America won't suddenly be tricked into thinking elite Democrats stand for their beliefs and values. The DNC spending a few bucks won't fool rural Americans into thinking Democrats have touched grass,” RNC spokesperson Delanie Bomar said.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium is-centered">One Big Beautiful Mess</h5> 
<p>Trump’s signature tax-and-spending law provides Democrats with another opening to contrast their pitch against Republicans.</p> 
<p>Rural health care centers across the country have already shuttered in response to the law’s Medicaid cuts, which will disproportionately hit communities where hospitals are few and often primary employers. Low-income Americans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/15/food-stamps-snap-trump-one-big-beautiful-bill-impact-00653447" target="_blank">are quickly learning they may no&nbsp;longer qualify</a> for federal food aid — even as most of the tax breaks the GOP has touted <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/12/congress/gop-megabill-cbo-distributional-effects-00402674" target="_blank">will benefit the wealthy.</a></p> 
<p>Kentucky Gov. Andy Beshear, who chairs the Democratic Governors Association and represents a ruby red state, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/11/24/andy-beshear-democrats-politics-rural-voters/" target="_blank">recently called</a> the law “a slap in the face to rural America.”</p> 
<p>And POLITICO’s November poll revealed that voters are more likely to rely on Democrats when it comes to health care policy. More than 40 percent of those surveyed said they trusted Democrats to bring down health care costs for ordinary Americans, compared with 33 percent who said they trusted the GOP.</p> 
<p>The message for Democrats is “wrapped up and with a nice, tidy bow on it in the Big, Beautiful Bill,” said Christopher Borick, a political science professor who runs the Muhlenberg College Institute of Public Opinion. “It's cuts to your health care, it's cuts to rural hospitals. It's cuts to SNAP benefits, and it's just so tidy and neat for Democrats to go there.”</p> 
<p>The strategy seems to be working. In a heavily Republican congressional district in Tennessee, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/tennessee-aftyn-behn-matt-van-epps-democrats-00674118" target="_blank">Democrat Aftyn Behn&nbsp;beat expectations</a> and outperformed Harris' 2024 margins in a bid to unseat GOP Rep. Matt Van Epps this month.</p> 
<p>Behn’s ads largely focused on affordability and the fallout from the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, which she called the “<a href="https://tennesseelookout.com/2025/10/22/behn-works-to-counter-trump-endorsement-of-van-epps-in-tennessees-congressional-district-7/" target="_blank">one big BS bill</a>.”</p> 
<p>That tactic resonated with voters in an off-cycle election and will only gain steam: Americans' health care premiums are set to skyrocket ahead of the 2026 midterms after Republicans declined to extend Covid-era “enhanced” subsidies of Affordable Care Act plans in their big bill.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium is-centered">Will history repeat itself?</h5> 
<p>Still, some political experts question how much Democrats can loosen the GOP's hold on rural America.</p> 
<p>The president's first-term tariff war also hammered farmers, but their political ties to Republicans hardly wavered at the time. Democrats in 2024 used roughly the same playbook they’re seeking to capitalize on now, arguing that Trump’s proposed policies would increase the cost of living and that his tariffs would impose a new tax on the middle class — but they failed to gain enough ground with rural voters, enabling Republicans to win a trifecta.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/b7/68/b89e4f2242b6b99b24f895a2a797/unlimiteduse-12-08-2025-white-house-isp-0006.jpg" alt="Trump listens during a roundtable discussion where he announced a $12 billion aid plan for farmers on Dec. 8, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Yuri Gripas/Abaca" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Trump listens during a roundtable discussion where he announced a $12 billion aid plan for farmers on Dec. 8, 2025."/><p>Many voters are wary of Democrats’ support for free trade agreements over the last 30 years, which hollowed out rural job opportunities and allowed the unchecked growth of corporate power, said Anthony Flaccavento, executive director of the Rural Urban Bridge initiative, a progressive rural organizing group.</p> 
<p>“Both parties have really betrayed rural America, but the Republican Party got very, very good at seeing people and expressing solidarity and saying, ‘You're right to be angry,'” he explained.</p> 
<p>Part of winning is showing up and listening, say Democrats like Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/404824" data-person-id="404824">Shontel Brown</a> of Ohio, who is weighing a bid for the top spot on the House Agriculture Committee. Brown, who hails from a wholly urban district, has traveled to other parts of her state and to Florida on a listening tour to hear directly from farmers.</p> 
<p>“We've lost a lot of trust in rural America, so showing up and listening is half the battle, but then we have to be able to present an alternative,” she said in a recent interview. "We as Democrats have a real opportunity to make the case for policies that lower costs and make it easier for farmers, families and the entire food supply chain producers as well.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/09/fe/9924b69049528c59b725388163e0/dsc-0790.JPG" alt="Brown visited several farms outside her district in northern Ohio over the summer. " data-portal-copyright="Marcia Brown/POLITICO " data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Brown visited several farms outside her district in northern Ohio over the summer. "/>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The top 5 interview moments of 2025 | The Conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2025/12/25/the-top-5-interview-moments-of-2025-the-conversation-1893214</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4b92-d78e-af9f-fff7c06a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 23:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">The top 5 interview moments of 2025 | The Conversation</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6386870748112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/5f759524-2f7a-4519-9fd4-6f18844487a8/cf41cf62-3f7d-49ab-b80a-dfc464da982c/main.mp4" src="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/5f759524-2f7a-4519-9fd4-6f18844487a8/ce6dc308-1158-4276-a4b8-f5374e435f83/1280x720/match/image.jpg">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Donald Trump and Mike Lindell are targeting Tim Walz. Some Republicans are worried that could backfire.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/24/minnesota-elections-2026-tim-walz-mike-lindell-00701462</link>
      <description>Tim Walz wants a third term. Donald Trump and Mike Lindell want to beat him.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3c92-df0c-a5bb-3cd7071a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7f/60/9605c0ab427ab3dad1e9db523a6a/election-2026-minnesota-lindell-76273.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Steve Karnowski/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mike Lindell speaks to reporters at his MyPillow factory in the Minneapolis suburb of Shakopee, Minnesota, on Dec, 11, 2025, as he launches his campaign for the Republican nomination to challenge Democratic Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz in 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7f/60/9605c0ab427ab3dad1e9db523a6a/election-2026-minnesota-lindell-76273.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Minnesota has been the white whale for Republicans in the Trump era. And 2026 could be the year they finally break through — if President Donald Trump and one of the most prolific peddlers of conspiracy theories about the 2020 election don’t sink their chances.</p> 
<p>Republicans are growing optimistic about their chances of unseating Democratic Gov. Tim Walz next year, as he seeks a historic third term. But Trump’s increasingly caustic attacks on Walz and disparagement of Minnesota’s Somali community — and MyPillow CEO Mike Lindell’s entrance into the gubernatorial race — could hurt Republicans’ chances of regaining ground in the state, some party strategists argue.</p> 
<p>“When the president comes in with a flamethrower and just throws that type of rhetoric, there's no oxygen, and there's no space for the Republican to offer suggestions and to be thoughtful in that space, because the rhetoric of the president just paints them into a corner,” said Michael Brodkorb, a former deputy chair of the Minnesota GOP who backed the Democratic ticket in 2024.</p> 
<p>Republicans have insisted they can be competitive statewide in the blue-leaning Minnesota ever since Trump lost Minnesota by less than 2 points in 2016. But since then, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/05/17/donald-trump-flip-minnesota-00158551" target="_blank">winning the state has beguiled</a> both the president — who faced a 7-point loss in 2020 and a 4-point loss in 2024 — and Republicans in other statewide races, including two fairly comfortable wins for Walz in 2018 and 2022.</p> 
<p>Still, Republicans see an opportunity to win back the Minnesota governor’s seat for the first time since 2006 by hammering Walz, who is running despite scrutiny into his oversight of state benefits and a star turn as the Democratic vice presidential nominee that put him in the crosshairs of Republicans across the country.</p> 
<p>At the same time, Trump has also used the arrests of some Somali immigrants in federal fraud cases to broadly characterize the state’s Somali population as criminals — leaning on his trademark use of divisive rhetoric that some Republicans worry will fall flat.</p> 
<p>That risk, insiders warn, could be exacerbated if Lindell, a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/mike-lindell-minnesota-governor-race-00686859" target="_blank">Trump ally</a>, wins the Republican nomination.</p> 
<p>“We’d be cooked,” said Dustin Grage, a Minnesota Republican strategist. “I’d be moving to Florida very shortly. We would lose pretty badly if Mike Lindell were to get the nomination.”</p> 
<p>Those close to the president strenuously disagree, arguing the state remains on the map. House GOP Whip Tom Emmer, the most high-profile Minnesota Republican and an ally of the president, said he’s spoken to Trump about the governor’s race and is confident that any of the 13 Republicans seeking the party’s nomination could defeat Walz.</p> 
<p>“We should be able to beat Tim Walz with a dog,” Emmer told POLITICO in an interview. </p> 
<p>The White House declined to comment. At a rally in North Carolina on Friday, Trump praised Lindell and said he “deserves to be the governor of Minnesota.” </p> 
<p>Walz faces a tricky path to reelection, with no Minnesota governor winning three consecutive terms in the state’s history. That’s been made more difficult by several investigations during his tenure leading the state that revealed a ring of alleged fraudsters siphoning money from public programs. In 2022, federal prosecutors charged dozens of people for pocketing $250 million from a federally funded child nutrition program overseen by the Minnesota Department of Education during the Covid-19 pandemic.</p> 
<p>The massive scope of the fraud allegations (<a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-mn/pr/feeding-our-future-defendant-sentenced-10-years-prison" target="_blank">the Justice Department called it</a> the “largest Covid-19 fraud scheme in the United States”) triggered a state audit that found the Walz administration “did not effectively exercise its authority” to prevent the fraud.</p> 
<p>In September, <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-mn/pr/defendants-charged-first-wave-housing-stabilization-fraud-cases" target="_blank">federal prosecutors charged eight people</a> with defrauding a Minnesota housing and health benefits program of millions of dollars by submitting inflated and fake reimbursement claims. Six additional people were charged for participating in the scheme in December. That same month, a defendant previously charged in the pandemic program fraud <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-mn/pr/six-additional-defendants-charged-one-defendant-pleads-guilty-ongoing-fraud-schemes" target="_blank">pleaded guilty to attempting to steal $14 million</a> from a Minnesota health care program that offers services to children with autism.</p> 
<p>Prosecutors have <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/18/us/minnesota-fraud-scandal.html" target="_blank">broadened their inquiry</a> into benefits fraud in the state to investigate billions of dollars in flagged billings of 14 public programs supported by Medicaid. </p> 
<p>In response to a request for comment to a Walz spokesperson, Minnesota Democratic-Farmer-Labor Party Chair Richard Carlbom said in a statement that Walz “heads into reelection with a record focused squarely on working people and kitchen-table issues.” </p> 
<p>“While the GOP clown-car primary remains consumed by infighting and loyalty tests for Donald Trump, Minnesota families are falling behind as Republicans unleash higher grocery prices, skyrocketing health care bills, and giant tax breaks for billionaires,” Carlbom said. “Minnesotans see the difference — a governor delivering for working families, or Republicans delivering loyalty to Donald Trump and a Washington agenda that puts billionaires first.”</p> 
<p>In recent weeks, Trump has ramped up his efforts to link Walz to the abuse of government programs — while using incendiary rhetoric directed at the governor and the Somali community. In a <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115625429081411360" target="_blank">social media post</a> on Thanksgiving, he called Walz “seriously retarded” and accused Somali refugees of seeking to “prey” on Minnesotans. And at an early December rally in Pennsylvania, he again denigrated the Somali community while discussing “the great big Minnesota scam with one of the dumbest governors ever in history.”</p> 
<p>Emmer, who said he spoke with Trump about the governor’s race as early as July, said he believes the president recognizes an opportunity in Walz’s vulnerability. “I think the president knows that Tim Walz is the weakest he's ever been in his political career,” Emmer said.</p> 
<p>Former Minnesota House Speaker Kurt Daudt, a Republican, said the fraud investigations are part of the risk for Walz in seeking a third consecutive term.</p> 
<p>“If you can lay out a case that, ‘Well, you've been elected now for eight years, and you haven't fixed these problems,’ or ‘You haven't accomplished what you said you were going to’ … it kind of makes it an easier case to say, ‘Maybe it's time for someone new,’” Daudt said.</p> 
<p>But the rhetoric Trump is using to highlight the fraud may reframe the issue to the detriment of Walz’s Republican opponent, said Brodkorb,the former party official. He believes Minnesotans are eager to weigh ideas on immigration policy and how to tackle abuse of public programs.</p> 
<p>“The problem is when the president comes in and says things like, ‘Everyone in the entire Somali community is garbage,’” Brodkorb said.</p> 
<p>Emmer, who adamantly defended Trump’s approach and his rhetoric attacking both Walz and the Somali community, credited him with shining a light on the state.</p> 
<p>“If he hadn't said it exactly the way it is, and if he hadn't been so out there direct, guess what? Nobody would have covered it,” Emmer said.</p> 
<p>The barrage directed at Walz and the state — including attacks from Trump allies, targeted probes from Cabinet officials and an immigration crackdown in Minneapolis — underscores the governor’s newfound national prominence since campaigning as former Vice President Kamala Harris’ running mate in last year’s presidential race.</p> 
<p>Walz has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/08/tim-walz-2024-campaign-critiques-00219718" target="_blank">emerged as a vocal critic</a> of the second Trump administration, prompting a feud between the two. After a Democratic lawmaker was killed by a gunman and a second was seriously injured earlier this year, Trump said <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/17/trump-walz-phone-call-00410141" target="_blank">he would not “waste time” calling</a> the “whacked out” governor.</p> 
<p>Walz’s growing national profile both makes him a high-profile target in the 2026 midterms worthy of trying to defeat, GOP strategists say — but Trump’s intense focus on the race could also backfire given the state’s political makeup.</p> 
<p>“Having Donald Trump being active in the race for a particular Republican may not be helpful, but it would be extremely helpful to raise the attention on Tim Walz and his record here in the state,” Daudt said.</p> 
<p>And if Trump’s ends up throwing his weight behind Lindell — who conspired with Trump in 2020 to advance false claims that the presidential election was stolen — Republicans worry that could give Walz a clearer path to reelection.</p> 
<p>“If [Lindell] is the candidate, that’s what the election will be about,” Daudt said. “It'll definitely be easier for Walz to make the election about Trump if Mike Lindell is the candidate. No question.”</p> 
<p>Trump, who continues to claim the 2020 election was rigged, touted Lindell’s efforts to reverse the election results at the North Carolina rally, and empathized with how Lindell “suffered” as a result. </p> 
<p>"He was just a guy that said, ’This election was so crooked, it was so rigged.’ He fought like hell," Trump told his supporters.</p> 
<p>Lindell’s campaign did not respond to requests for comment. </p> 
<p>Some Minnesota Republicans hope that the party will back a more moderate candidate that can highlight Walz’s vulnerabilities.</p> 
<p>But Emmer said candidates should do what they can to win the endorsement of the hundreds of highly engaged party activists who serve as delegates at the party’s nominating convention next year.</p> 
<p>“I'm going to tell you the way you win this race. You go run your race to get an endorsement,” Emmer said. “As soon as you are the endorsed Republican candidate, you have won the primary in August, you are going to win the governor's race.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists look back on the year that was.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2025/12/24/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00706244</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's a look back on the past year through the eyes of the cartoonists. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-511e-dba9-addb-73bf470f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 11:47:11 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From the field to the ballot: Athletes crowd GOP tickets ahead of 2026</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/football-athletes-2026-midterms-republicans-00704825</link>
      <description>Former athletes and coaches are coming off the bench to run for office as political outsiders. So far, that strategy has produced mixed results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4cac-dba9-addb-7fbfb1630000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 15:05:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/07/93/c516ea014960bce045bd5e32be9d/u-s-congress-99640.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Tommy Tuberville gestures as he boards the Senate subway at the U.S. Capitol on Nov. 14, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/07/93/c516ea014960bce045bd5e32be9d/u-s-congress-99640.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After five years in the United States Senate, Republican Tommy Tuberville wants Alabamians to know one thing above all else as he embarks on a gubernatorial bid: his time as a college football coach.</p> 
<p>That his <a href="https://www.coachforgovernor.com/" target="_blank">campaign website is framed</a> by a banner reading “Coach Tuberville for Governor” speaks to how much the GOP is relying upon local sports heroes to compete for offices up and down the ballot as the pivotal midterm elections approach.</p> 
<p>Athletes and coaches are playing in some of the highest-profile races of the 2026 cycle, with control over Congress up for grabs in a year <a href="https://x.com/PpollingNumbers/status/2003110092598841398" target="_blank">expected to favor Democrats</a>. In Georgia, former University of Tennessee head coach Derek Dooley is hoping to capitalize on his athletic experience — and his <a href="https://georgiadogs.com/news/2022/10/28/football-former-uga-coach-athletic-director-vince-dooley-dies" target="_blank">father’s football fame</a> in Athens — to break through in a competitive Republican primary and unseat Democratic Sen. Jon Ossoff. Former NFL kicker Jay Feely is running for Congress in Arizona. And former MLB star Mark Teixeira is a front-runner for Rep. Chip Roy’s open House seat in Texas.</p> 
<p>Tuberville, who once led the Auburn University football team, still goes by “coach” around the Capitol.</p> 
<p>Athletes-turned-politicians are hardly a new concept: former Rep. Jack Kemp brought his football background to the halls of Congress and the 1996 GOP presidential ticket; Jesse Ventura leveraged his WWE fame to win Minnesota’s governorship; and two-time NBA champion Bill Bradley served New Jersey in the Senate for nearly two decades and mounted a bid for the White House.</p> 
<p>But at a moment of deep distrust and disdain for elected officials in Washington, both parties are looking for outsider candidates and athletes are increasingly fitting that mold. And the trend of leveraging sports fame for political gain has been supercharged in the era of Trump, who once owned a pro football team. The president has routinely campaigned alongside athletes and coaches, including Notre Dame hero Lou Holtz — whom he later awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom — and professional wrestling star Hulk Hogan. He backed Tuberville in his Senate run and endorsed former University of Georgia star running back Herschel Walker in his unsuccessful Senate bid in 2022.</p> 
<p>This trend has been especially prevalent in the southeast, where college football culture reigns. Tuberville’s successful entrance into politics has inspired a new crop of football figures to make their own bids as Republicans in the SEC corridor, and many of them have consulted directly with the coach-turned-legislator about how to replicate his win.</p> 
<p>Tuberville used his gridiron fame in Alabama to rocket to the Senate in 2020 without any experience in the public eye off the football field.</p> 
<p>“I spent a lot of time in public life going to a lot of alumni meetings, shaking hands, marketing our program, selling recruits on the road, dealing a lot with parents — and it's no different than being in politics,” he said in an interview.</p> 
<p>The party in Alabama isn’t making an active push to recruit former sports stars to run for office, but that hasn’t stopped other like-minded college athletes and sports figures from running their own plays for office.</p> 
<p>“I think there's a natural bend towards these figures,” said Alabama Republican Party Chair John Wahl, who worked on Tuberville’s 2020 Senate campaign. “They already have some name I.D., they have fundraising capabilities, but they're seen as political outsiders and people who are going to represent the average, everyday American.”</p> 
<p>Dooley, who is running for Senate with the backing of Georgia’s Republican Gov. Brian Kemp, approached Tuberville for some coaching prior to his run.</p> 
<p>“The people that have called me, they ask: what is this? What do I have to do? And what does it entail? You know, first of all, being a senator, they all want to know first about campaigning. They want to know the ins and outs of it and what you have to do with raising money,” Tuberville said.</p> 
<p>Dooley’s campaign did not make him available for an interview for this article.</p> 
<p>Earlier this year, former University of Alabama star quarterback AJ McCarron launched his own bid for lieutenant governor — opening the possibility that, alongside Tuberville, the state could have been helmed by figures representing rival local football programs. He ended his bid on Wednesday, announcing he would no longer seek Montgomery’s second-in-command post “in order to accept a new career opportunity in football.”</p> 
<p>Paul Finebaum, the lauded college football commentator, <a href="https://www.al.com/politics/2025/12/paul-finebaum-will-not-run-for-tubervilles-us-senate-seat.html" target="_blank">passed on a run</a> for Tuberville’s seat earlier this month. He, too, spoke with the senator about the job as he was exploring a run, according to Tuberville. So did fellow Auburn Tigers basketball coach Bruce Pearl, who similarly opted against a bid after retiring from coaching.</p> 
<p>But there will still be plenty of ‘Bama pride left: Sen. Katie Britt’s (R-Ala.) husband Wesley Britt starred for the Crimson Tide before playing three seasons in the NFL, a fact she was sure to highlight in her ads during her 2022 run for Senate.</p> 
<p>This same trend is playing out in other parts of the country too. Michelle Tafoya, the longtime NFL sideline reporter, is <a href="https://www.startribune.com/michele-tafoya-inches-closer-to-bid-for-us-senate/601547959" target="_blank">inching toward mounting a bid</a> as a Republican in Minnesota’s open Senate race. Meanwhile, Democrats have yet to significantly capitalize on that same trend in the deep-red part of the country to challenge the Republicans’ regional hegemony.</p> 
<p>That isn’t to say they don’t have a bench elsewhere: former Rep. Colin Allred leaned hard on his bio as an NFL player in his unsuccessful 2024 Senate bid in Texas (he’s now running for his old seat). Massachusetts Gov. Maura Healy played a few years of professional basketball in Europe before returning to the Bay State to launch her political career. Rep. Sharice Davids (D-Kansas) is a former professional mixed martial arts fighter.</p> 
<p>“Democrats tend to recruit a lot of ex-military or CIA people. They seem to think that’s more in their wheelhouse,” said long-time Democratic strategist James Carville.</p> 
<p>“I think as people become increasingly turned off by ‘politics of Washington, ’you’re going to find these parties are going to be looking for different kinds of candidates,” he continued. “It might be a good idea to look for more opportunities like this.”</p> 
<p>Nearly three-quarters of American adults are “frustrated” by the Democratic Party, an October <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2025/10/30/how-americans-feel-about-the-republican-and-democratic-parties/" target="_blank">Pew Research Center poll</a> found. Sixty-four percent of Americans held similarly negative views of Republicans. That dissatisfaction makes the appeal of an outsider candidate who hasn’t touched politics before even stronger.</p> 
<p>“I think people are ready for change,” said Amanda Litman, the co-founder and president of the progressive candidate recruitment organization Run for Something. “Often the best folks to shepherd that change are people who are new to the system, whether that's new to politics or new to community engagement.”</p> 
<p>“I wouldn't say athletes is, like, a specific profile we're looking for, because you have to be really in it to solve a problem,” she continued, adding that wants to see “more artists, I want more musicians, and I want more nurses and teachers to run for office. I want more people who really care and who maybe come with a fresh perspective.”</p> 
<p>While outsider candidates may prove a balm to those fiery sentiments, the public is not entirely sold on athletes wading into a political space. A late 2024 <a href="https://apnorc.org/projects/most-adults-feel-the-need-to-limit-political-news-consumption-due-to-fatigue-and-information-overload/" target="_blank">poll conducted by the Associated Press and the NORC at the University of Chicago</a> showed that 26 percent of adults approve of athletes speaking out about political issues. 36 percent of respondents said they explicitly disapprove of athletes specifically sharing their political opinions.</p> 
<p>“When you’re famous in athletics, everybody likes you,” Carville said. “In politics, as soon as you open your mouth, half the people hate you.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-23T14:00:40-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Hageman launches bid for Wyoming Senate seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/harriet-hageman-wyoming-senate-seat-00704620</link>
      <description>The two-term representative and strong Trump supporter announced her campaign on Tuesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4c20-dba9-addb-7fbf96380000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 12:03:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d2/0d/3737bc4b40f6844f3da6e3ea125a/house-judiciary-committee-00882.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Harriet Hageman (R-Wyo.) looks on during a House Judiciary Committee hearing on oversight of the FBI on Capitol Hill July 12, 2023.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d2/0d/3737bc4b40f6844f3da6e3ea125a/house-judiciary-committee-00882.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wyoming GOP Rep. Harriet Hageman on Tuesday announced her campaign for Senate, hoping to succeed retiring Republican Sen. Cynthia Lummis in next year’s election.</p> 
<p>The Wyoming Republican is a strong supporter of President Donald Trump, and with his backing she helped oust Republican then-Rep. Liz Cheney, a vocal critic of Trump’s, in the 2022 primary.</p> 
<p>"This fight is about making sure the next century sees the advancements of the last, while protecting our culture and our way of life,” Hageman said in her launch video. “We must dedicate ourselves to ensuring that the next 100 years is the next great American century."</p> 
<p>Lummis <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/cynthia-lummis-crypto-retirement-00700961" target="_blank">announced she would not seek reelection</a> last week, saying she felt like a “sprinter in a marathon” despite being a “devout legislator.” Hageman, who had been debating a gubernatorial bid, was expected to enter the Senate race.</p> 
<p>Hageman touted her ties to the president in her announcement video, highlighting her record of support for Trump’s policies during her time in the House and vowing to keep Wyoming a “leader in energy and food production.”</p> 
<p>“I worked with President Trump to pass 46 billion in additional funding for border security, while ensuring that Wyomingites do not pay the cost of new immigration. We work together to secure the border and fund efforts to remove and deport those in the country illegally,” she said.</p> 
<p>President Trump on Tuesday said Hageman has his "complete and total" endorsement, calling her "highly respected" in a post to Truth Social. </p> 
<p>"I know Harriet well, and she is a TOTAL WINNER!" Trump said. He added that Hageman "WILL NEVER LET YOU DOWN."</p> 
<p>Trump won the deep-red state by nearly 46 points in last year’s election, and Hageman herself was reelected by nearly 48 points, according to exit polling.</p> 
<p>Still, Hageman bore the brunt of voters’ displeasure earlier this year during a town hall. As she spoke of the Department of Government Efficiency, federal cuts and Social Security, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/congress/republican-lawmaker-booed-rowdy-town-hall-complaining-crowd-obsessed-g-rcna197278" target="_blank">the crowd booed her</a>.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ben Sasse says he has stage 4 pancreatic cancer</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/ben-sasse-cancer-diagnosis-00704507</link>
      <description>The former Nebraska senator said he is “going to die."</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4bfc-d78e-af9f-ffff99a40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 11:24:43 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d1/fe/20f7c86e4bedbed9d65f576cecfd/senate-sasse-52093.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Alex Brandon/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Sen. Ben Sasse listens during a confirmation hearing on Capitol Hill in Washington, on March 23, 2022.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d1/fe/20f7c86e4bedbed9d65f576cecfd/senate-sasse-52093.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Sen. Ben Sasse announced on Tuesday that he has been diagnosed with stage 4 metastatic pancreatic cancer.</p> 
<p>The Nebraska Republican shared the news on X, writing in a <a href="https://x.com/bensasse/status/2003483746540965891?s=46" target="_blank">lengthy social media post</a> that he had received the diagnosis last week.</p> 
<p>“Advanced pancreatic is nasty stuff; it’s a death sentence,” Sasse said. “But I already had a death sentence before last week too — we all do.”</p> 
<p>The two term senator retired in 2023 and then went on to serve as president of the University of Florida. He eventually left the school to spend more time with his wife, Melissa, after she was diagnosed with epilepsy.</p> 
<p>Sasse continued to teach classes at University of Florida’s Hamilton Center after he stepped down as president. He previously served as a professor at the University of Texas, as an assistant secretary at the Department of Health and Human Services and as president of Midland University.</p> 
<p>Sasse on Tuesday shared that he and his wife have only grown closer since and opened up about his children’s recent successes and milestones.</p> 
<p>“There’s not a good time to tell your peeps you’re now marching to the beat of a faster drummer — but the season of advent isn’t the worst,” Sasse said. “As a Christian, the weeks running up to Christmas are a time to orient our hearts toward the hope of what’s to come.”</p> 
<p>Sasse said he’ll have more to share in the future, adding that he is “not going down without a fight” and will be undergoing treatment.</p> 
<p>“Death and dying aren’t the same — the process of dying is still something to be lived. We’re zealously embracing a lot of gallows humor in our house, and I’ve pledged to do my part to run through the irreverent tape,” Sasse said.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poll: Major allies see US as unreliable and destabilizing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/us-allies-trump-trust-poll-00702908</link>
      <description>Pluralities in Germany and France — and a majority of Canadians — say the US is a negative force globally, new POLITICO-Public First polling finds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-475c-df0c-a5bb-775fd6130000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/png" url="https://static.politico.com/f0/c5/750f0e1b47748c245d07a7add5c8/global-view-of-america-protest.png">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Anna Wiederkehr/POLITICO (source images via AP)</media:credit>
        <media:title>TPP: Global views of America</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f0/c5/750f0e1b47748c245d07a7add5c8/global-view-of-america-protest.png" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Unreliable. Creating more problems than solving them. A negative force on the world stage. This is how large shares of America's closest allies view the U.S., according to new polling, as President Donald Trump pursues a sweeping foreign policy overhaul.</p> 
<p>Pluralities in Germany and France — and a majority of Canadians — say the U.S. is a negative force globally, according to new international <a href="http://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-47e5-d651-a1ff-7fe532280000" target="_blank">POLITICO-Public First polling</a>. Views are more mixed in the United Kingdom, but more than a third of respondents there share that dim assessment.<br></p><p>Near-majorities in all four countries also say the U.S. tends to create problems for other countries rather than solve them.<br></p><p>The findings offer a snapshot of how Trump’s reshaping of U.S. foreign policy — including through an expansive trade agenda, sharp rhetoric toward longtime allies and reoriented military posture — is resonating across some of Washington's closest allies.</p> 
<p>When asked whether the U.S. supports its allies around the world or challenges them, a majority of Canadians say the latter, as well as just under half of respondents in Germany and France. In the U.K., roughly 4 in 10 say the U.S. challenges, rather than supports, its allies, more than a third say it cannot be depended on in a crisis, nearly half say it creates problems for other countries, and 35 percent say the U.S. is a negative force overall.<br></p><p>Trump has blurred traditional lines of global alliances during his first year back in office, particularly in Canada and Europe. He called Europe a “decaying” group of nations led by “weak” people in a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/trump-dasha-burns-interview-europe-immigration-ukraine-00682016?amp" target="_blank">recent POLITICO interview</a> and his <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/05/trump-reveals-national-security-strategy-western-hemisphere-europe-00678265?_hsenc=p2ANqtz-8eihOUWYhQ6oo5DPvTgulJR88nC7bqkNAYITjeYtmCxbIR-Ax2MF5ulAOf8vUu51wbzDiM7-dY1jdBHhwfhHFOcACqGQ&amp;_hsmi=393131806&amp;utm_campaign=AFSA+Media+Digest&amp;utm_content=393131806&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=hs_email" target="_blank">sweeping National Security Strategy</a>argued that the continent has lost its “national identities and self-confidence." </p> 
<p>By contrast, the strategy reserved less scathing language for Russia — even as U.S. allies in Europe gear up for what leaders have called a “hybrid war” with Moscow.</p> 
<p>Secretary of State Marco Rubio defended the administration’s approach when asked about European criticisms, saying the transatlantic alliance remains rooted in shared “civilizational” values. “I do think that at the core of these special relationships we have is the fact that we have shared history, shared values, shared civilizational principles that we should be unapologetic about,” <a href="https://www.state.gov/releases/office-of-the-spokesperson/2025/12/secretary-of-state-marco-rubio-remarks-to-the-press-6/" target="_blank">Rubio said at a briefing</a> last week.<br></p><p>But as Trump disrupts long-standing relationships, skepticism among allied leaders may be seeping into public sentiment, said Matthew Kroenig, vice president and senior director of the Atlantic Council’s Scowcroft Center for Strategy and Security.</p> 
<p>“Public opinion in democracies often reflects elite opinion,” he said. “What you're probably seeing there is that you do have politicians in these countries expressing skepticism about the United States and about the Trump administration, and that's being reflected in the public opinion polling.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Leaders across Europe and Canada recalibrate under Trump’s foreign policy agenda</h5> 
<p>That dynamic is playing out across Europe and Canada, as leaders across the countries try to keep the increasingly strained relationships intact.</p> 
<p>In Germany, wavering U.S. military support for Ukraine, questions about Washington’s commitment to NATO and Trump's tariff war have added urgency for Chancellor Friedrich Merz to move beyond the country’s long-established limits on defense spending and economic policy. Weeks before taking office, Merz secured a historic spending overhaul that unlocked hundreds of billions of euros for defense and infrastructure investments after years of self-imposed austerity.</p> 
<p>“Every foreign policy statement by Trump is followed closely, and often discussed in light of what it may mean for U.S. policy shifts regarding European security issues, such as commitment to NATO, future U.S. troop presence in Europe, and support for Ukraine,” said Dominik Tolksdorf, a transatlantic expert at the German Council on Foreign Relations.</p> 
<p>In France, where skepticism toward the U.S. has long run deep, President Emmanuel Macron has pursued personal diplomacy with Trump while using the president’s unpredictability to bolster arguments for greater European strategic autonomy.</p> 
<p>“Handing over one’s sovereignty to another power is a mistake — De Gaulle said nothing else,” one high-ranking French military officer, who was granted anonymity to speak candidly, told POLITICO. Another defense official said Trump’s National Security Strategy had increased “awareness that something is not right.”</p> 
<p>In the U.K., Trump remains polarizing, but Prime Minister Keir Starmer has largely avoided public confrontation. His priorities now include finalizing a U.K.-U.S. trade deal and coordinating a European response to Trump’s efforts to end the war in Ukraine — without angering the White House, the delicate balance many allied leaders are trying to strike.</p> 
<p>Canada, meanwhile, has seen the sharpest deterioration in relations, which have soured amid a punishing trade war and Trump's intermittent rhetoric on annexation.</p> 
<p>Flavio Volpe, the president of Canada’s Automotive Parts Manufacturers' Association, described the economic disruption linked to Trump's trade moves. "People lost their jobs — ones they worked their entire lives — and billions of dollars in Canadian capital evaporated in an unexplainable turn away from the bankable post-Cold War balance of power by the White House," he <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/flaviovolpe1_what-a-year-2025-was-as-canadians-we-activity-7407791627521519616-b5LP/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAABluvCsBEHsx7-Lm-VkyQj40GhzivWTt5Ns" target="_blank">wrote on LinkedIn</a>.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Democrats remain skeptical of the U.S. on the world stage</h5> 
<p>Overall, Americans still view their country more favorably than their allies do. Nearly half — 49 percent — say the U.S. supports its allies around the world. A majority, 52 percent, say it can be depended on in a crisis, and 51 percent say the U.S. is a positive force globally.</p> 
<p>But Democrats — who have displayed deeply pessimistic views about their country since Trump’s return to office — hold far more negative views.<br></p><p>Almost half of voters who backed former Vice President Kamala Harris last year — 47 percent — also say the U.S. is a negative force in the world overall, compared with just 13 percent of Trump voters. Three in four Trump voters say the U.S. is a positive force in the world.<br></p><p>Many Democrats also don’t just express skepticism about the U.S., but view other countries and international blocs as stronger models: 58 percent of Harris voters say the European Union is a positive force in the world, and nearly two-thirds — 64 percent — say the same about Canada, greater than the shares who say the same about the U.S.</p> 
<p>"This tracks with our other research on the rapid change of perceptions of the U.S. over the last year,” said Seb Wride, head of polling at Public First. “Americans themselves are not blind to it.”</p> 
<p>Prior to the 2024 election, strong majorities of both Democrats and Republicans — 71 percent and 69 percent — said the U.S. was a positive force in the world over the course of its entire history, Public First polling from October of last year found.</p> 
<p>Exactly one year later, Democrats have sharply changed their views, with 77 percent of Trump voters still saying the U.S. is positive, compared with just 58 percent of Democrats.</p> 
<p>“That's around 1 in 8 Democrats changing their views on the role the U.S. has played in its entire history, in just one year,” said Wride.</p> 
<p>Voters who backed Trump last November overwhelmingly view the U.S. in a positive light, but subtle differences emerge within his coalition. Eighty-one percent of self-identifying MAGA Trump voters say the U.S. is a positive force in the world overall, compared with 71 percent of non-MAGA Trump voters. Still, 17 percent of non-MAGA Trump voters say the opposite, that the U.S. is a negative force.</p> 
<p><i>POLITICO’s Matt Honeycombe-Foster contributed reporting from the United Kingdom, Victor Goury-Laffont and Laura Kayali contributed from France, Nette Nöstlinger contributed from Germany and Nick Taylor-Vaisey contributed from Canada. Giselle Ruhiyyih Ewing also contributed.</i><br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More than a dozen staffers leave Heritage to join Pence-led nonprofit</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/heritage-staff-join-pence-nonprofit-00703192</link>
      <description>It’s the latest in a string of departures from the embattled organization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-47ad-df0c-a5bb-77ffb8380000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 15:36:32 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/35/af/2b982fe34c8791b50dd05ecf95c9/cheney-funeral-98567.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former Vice President Mike Pence attends ex-Vice President Dick Cheney's funeral at the Washington National Cathedral on Nov. 20.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/35/af/2b982fe34c8791b50dd05ecf95c9/cheney-funeral-98567.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>More than a dozen staffers at The Heritage Foundation are leaving the conservative think tank to join a nonprofit led by former Vice President Mike Pence as the embattled organization continues to reel from ongoing turmoil.</p> 
<p>Advancing American Freedom — founded by Pence in 2021 “to defend liberty and advance policies that build a stronger America” — <a href="https://advancingamericanfreedom.com/advancing-american-freedom-hires-former-heritage-foundation-legal-economic-and-data-directors/" target="_blank">announced Monday</a> that three senior officials who led the legal, economic and data teams at Heritage would be joining the group next year, along with several members of their teams.</p> 
<p>The departures, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elections/top-heritage-officials-flee-to-mike-pences-nonprofit-as-think-tank-fractures-28765f2b?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqcWRThC3x5OjMZyiJ-EWHqZOh48xjVQlICADo_PMYgxHFS3C-BE_hliCGyNfJI%3D&amp;gaa_ts=69498dc6&amp;gaa_sig=2vxAcz6a-QYutN710Zs7HtrLH9cM7ZhPTUxPoGZOegAUzGftuMSG4ZwXCk-SGeVw-VE47zZOspvRP4OV02a1sA%3D%3D" target="_blank">first reported by The Wall Street Journal</a>, mark the latest sign of upheaval at Heritage, which has seen <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/heritage-resigns-robert-george-tucker-00654143" target="_blank">dozens of staffers flee the organization</a> since it became <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/30/heritage-tucker-carlson-nick-fuentes-00631200" target="_blank">engulfed in a scandal</a> involving Holocaust denier Nick Fuentes and the ongoing debate within the conservative movement over antisemitism.</p> 
<p>Heritage Foundation President Kevin Roberts, the architect behind the “Project 2025” blueprint for President Donald Trump’s second administration, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/31/mcconnell-heritage-foundation-tucker-carlson-00631510" target="_blank">drew sharp rebukes</a> from conservative voices, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/03/ben-shapiro-tucker-carlson-nick-fuentes-interview-00633323" target="_blank">commentator Ben Shapiro,</a> after standing by conservative commentator Tucker Carlson’s friendly interview with Fuentes in October.</p> 
<p>In the wake of the initial backlash, Roberts told staffers he’d make a “mistake,” but asked for the chance to “clean it up” during a November all-staff meeting, according to a <a href="https://freebeacon.com/politics/i-made-a-mistake-heritage-foundation-president-apologizes-to-staff-for-video-refusal-to-cancel-tucker-carlson-and-throws-shade-at-former-chief-of-staff/" target="_blank">leaked video</a> first published by the Washington Free Beacon.</p> 
<p>The hires by Advancing American Freedom signal that the organization is looking to position itself as a key player within the broader conservative movement.</p> 
<p>“AAF is honored to welcome these principled conservative scholars to the team,” Pence, who has been the target of Trump’s ire since the former vice president certified the 2020 election results, said in a statement. “They bring a wealth of experience, a love of country, and a deep commitment to the Constitution and Conservative Movement that will further the cause of liberty.”</p> 
<p>Andrew Olivastro, chief advancement officer at The Heritage Foundation, said in a Monday statement that the think tank’s “mission is unchanged, and our leadership is strong and decisive.”</p> 
<p>"Heritage has always welcomed debate, but alignment on mission and loyalty to the institution are non-negotiable. A handful of staff chose a different path — some through disruption, others through disloyalty,” Olivastro said.</p> 
<p>In his statement, Olivastro said several of the departing staffers were “terminated for conduct inconsistent with Heritage's mission and standards” last week, adding that “Their departures clear the way for a stronger, more focused team.”</p> 
<p>Former Heritage Vice President John Malcolm is slated to lead AAF’s new Edwin Meese III Institute for the Rule of Law, which is being relocated from Heritage. Jessica Reinsch, formerly deputy director of programs at the Meese Center, will serve as director of programs, and five other former employees at Heritage will also join AAF’s Meese Institute.</p> 
<p>Five staffers from Heritage’s economic policy institute and its federal budget center will join AAF’s Plymouth Institute for Free Enterprise, and former Heritage’s Chief Statistician Kevin Dayaratna will lead its Center for Statistical Modeling &amp; Scientific Analysis.</p> 
<p>Josh Blackman, a legal scholar who contributed to Project 2025, also resigned his post as senior editor of the Heritage Guide to the Constitution on Sunday. In <a href="https://reason.com/volokh/2025/12/21/my-resignation-from-the-heritage-foundation/" target="_blank">his resignation letter</a>, Blackman wrote that Roberts’ remarks “were a huge unforced blunder, and gave aid and comfort to the rising tide of antisemitism on the right,” in addition to undermining the work of the Meese Center.</p> 
<p>“Your initial remarks were indefensible. Your apology was underwhelming. And the lack of any meaningful followup over the past three months has been telling,” Blackman wrote in his letter to Roberts.</p> 
<p>Still, some Heritage staffers have remained loyal to the organization, with conservative activist Robby Starbuck sharing Monday that he would be extending his stay as a visiting fellow at the think tank. Starbuck <a href="https://x.com/robbystarbuck/status/2003169958172475556?s=46" target="_blank">wrote on social media</a> that “these resignations have a lot more to do with 2028 than it does with anything else,” accusing Blackman and others who stepped down of yearning for “a return to the Pence/Ryan GOP.”</p> 
<p>The shock waves from the infighting at Heritage, once a key player in the MAGA coalition, have continued to reverberate throughout the GOP, with Republican firebrands like Carlson, Shapiro, Vivek Ramaswamy and Steve Bannon <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/maga-infighting-erupts-at-day-one-of-turning-point-usa-conference-00699665?nid=0000018f-3124-de07-a98f-3be4d1400000&amp;nname=politico-toplines&amp;nrid=df9635b8-7d6f-4c86-9d5f-4c7def2c3d10" target="_blank">sparring over Fuentes</a> and whether he had a place in the party this weekend at Turning Point’s AmericaFest in Phoenix.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-22T12:56:51-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump critic George Conway files to run for NY House seat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/george-conway-ny-house-seat-nadler-00702755</link>
      <description>Conway, a sharp critic of President Donald Trump, has filed to run as a Democrat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-46e4-d651-a1ff-7ee424570000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 11:49:45 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/03/53/44279ffe48619edca2d37744668b/trump-hush-money-68572.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ted Shaffrey/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>George Conway, co-founder of The Lincoln Project, has filed to run for Congress as a Democrat.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/03/53/44279ffe48619edca2d37744668b/trump-hush-money-68572.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>George Conway, a conservative lawyer and vocal critic of President Donald Trump, filed paperwork on Monday to run as a Democrat for the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/01/rep-jerry-nadler-to-retire-00539183" target="_blank">seat Rep. Jerry Nadler (D-N.Y.) is vacating</a>.</p> 
<p>News of Conway entering the race began surfacing last month, especially after Conway <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/19/us/politics/george-conway-congressional-run.html?unlocked_article_code=1.2U8.HbBc.yonWJCofFbrJ&amp;smid=url-share" target="_blank">confirmed he had hired a Democratic pollster</a> to weigh his chances.</p> 
<p>Conway was previously married to Kellyanne Conway, who helped manage Trump’s 2016 presidential bid and then served in the White House during Trump’s first term.</p> 
<p>Though George Conway was also offered a position with the administration during Trump’s first term, he declined. The relationship between the president and Conway turned contentious, with Conway often criticizing Trump and the president in turn commenting on the Conways' marriage.</p> 
<p>The feud ultimately culminated in <a href="https://x.com/realDonaldTrump/status/1108335293671845888?s=20" target="_blank">Trump calling Conway</a> a “stone cold LOSER &amp; husband from hell” and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yufAbIeNk0Y" target="_blank">Conway calling Trump a “fascist.”</a> Conway went on to <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2019/10/george-conway-trump-unfit-office/599128/" target="_blank">pen an essay</a> that called Trump “unfit for office.”</p> 
<p>The lawyer eventually co-founded The Lincoln Project, a PAC of former Republicans with a self-described purpose of defeating Trump, and has continued to criticize the president.</p> 
<p>Shortly after Conway filed to run, Councilmember Erik Bottcher <a href="https://x.com/ebottcher/status/2003154217058672737?s=20" target="_blank">announced he is ending his campaign</a> for House of Representatives, choosing instead to run for New York State Senate. </p> 
<p>But Conway will still join an increasingly crowded primary race for Nadler’s seat. At least nine hopefuls — including Jack Schlossberg, the only grandson of John F. Kennedy — have filed to run for the position since <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51541" data-person-id="51541">Nadler</a> announced in September he would not seek reelection.</p> 
<p>March for Our Lives organizer Cameron Kasky, Assemblymen Alex Bores and Micah Lasher have also filed to run for the Manhattan-based seat. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-22T11:34:30-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>CBS pulls ‘60 Minutes’ segment on notorious El Salvador prison</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/22/cbs-pulls-60-minutes-el-salvador-prison-00702617</link>
      <description>The decision, made by editor in chief Bari Weiss, was condemned as "political" by lead correspondent Sharyn Alfonsi.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4665-df0c-a5bb-7677e3340000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 09:38:30 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/0d/b8/151e44d846b3afae9c45ec887346/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/1012221638">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Angela Weiss/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>The Free Press founder Bari Weiss was appointed as CBS News' editor in chief by Paramount owner David Ellison in October.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0d/b8/151e44d846b3afae9c45ec887346/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/1012221638" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>CBS News abruptly pulled a “60 Minutes” investigation featuring Venezuelan men deported to El Salvador’s CECOT prison on Sunday, sparking swift backlash within the newsroom, including from the story’s veteran correspondent.</p> 
<p>The canceled segment, yanked at the behest of newly appointed editor in chief Bari Weiss, focused on the notorious El Salvador prison that President Donald Trump has deported immigrants to despite <a href="https://www.state.gov/reports/2023-country-reports-on-human-rights-practices/el-salvador/" target="_blank">reports of human rights violations within the prison</a>. Several men now released from the prison were featured in the segment describing the conditions they endured within CECOT.</p> 
<p>But Weiss nixed the segment just hours before it was set to air after calling for multiple additions, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/21/business/60-minutes-trump-bari-weiss.html" target="_blank">according to The New York Times</a>, including an interview with top Trump adviser Stephen Miller or another top official in the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>CBS <a href="https://x.com/60Minutes/status/2002854497685582309?s=20" target="_blank">said in a statement</a> that the segment will air at a later date, and Weiss defended the decision to hold the segment in a statement to POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“My job is to make sure that all stories we publish are the best they can be,” Weiss said. “Holding stories that aren’t ready for whatever reason — that they lack sufficient context, say, or that they are missing critical voices — happens every day in every newsroom. I look forward to airing this important piece when it’s ready.”</p> 
<p>But Sharyn Alfonsi, the veteran correspondent on the story, condemned Weiss’ decision.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/grynbaum/status/2002943084322287815?s=20" target="_blank">In an email</a> obtained by The New York Times and later shared on social media by Times reporter Michael M. Grynbaum, Alfonsi told her CBS colleagues that reporters on the segment had requested comment from the White House, the Department of Homeland Security and the State Department. She added that the segment had also already undergone a rigorous review and fact-checking process.</p> 
<p>To pull the story so close to airtime, Alfonsi said, is “not an editorial decision, it is a political one.”</p> 
<p>“Government silence is a statement, not a VETO,” Alfonsi wrote. “Their refusal to be interviewed is a tactical maneuver designed to kill the story.”</p> 
<p>She continued, “If the administration’s refusal to participate becomes a valid reason to spike a story, we have effectively handed them a 'kill switch' for any reporting they find convenient.”</p> 
<p>Alfonsi added that if CBS’ new standard for airing a segment requires government interviews, then the government “effectively gains control over the '60 Minutes' broadcast.”</p> 
<p>“We have been promoting this story on social media for days. Our viewers are expecting it,” Alfonsi wrote. “When it airs without a credible explanation, the public will correctly identify this as corporate censorship. We are trading 50 years of ‘Gold Standard’ reputation for a single week of political quiet.”</p> 
<p>During an editorial call on Monday, Weiss spoke of "trust" between members of the newsroom and the public. </p> 
<p>"The only newsroom I'm interested in running is one in which we are able to have contentious disagreements about the thorniest editorial matters with respect, and, crucially, where we assume the best intent of our colleagues. Anything else is absolutely unacceptable," Weiss said on the call<b>. </b>Multiple news outlets reported on the call and CBS confirmed Weiss' comments to staff to POLITICO. </p> 
<p>She also reiterated that she held "Inside CECOT" because "it was not ready."</p> 
<p>"While the story presented powerful testimony of torture at CECOT, it did not advance the ball — the Times and other outlets have previously done similar work," said Weiss. "The public knows that Venezuelans have been subjected to horrific treatment at this prison. To run a story on this subject two months later, we need to do more. And this is '60 Minutes.' We need to be able to get the principals on the record and on camera."</p> 
<p>The viewers, Weiss added "come first." </p> 
<p>"That's my north star and I hope it's yours, too," she said. </p> 
<p>The cancellation of “Inside CECOT” is the latest in a string of controversial moves made by the media giant this year.</p> 
<p>In July, CBS <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/02/cbs-paramount-donald-trump-settlement-00436989" target="_blank">announced a $16 million settlement with Trump</a>, who sued the company as a private citizen following his own appearance on “60 Minutes.” It was after that settlement that the Trump administration approved Paramount Skydance’s acquisition of CBS.</p> 
<p>Weiss, founder of The Free Press, was appointed as editor in chief by Paramount owner David Ellison in October to overhaul the newsroom.</p> 
<p>Trump has continued to express <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115730908630818072" target="_blank">his displeasure with CBS</a>, but that hasn’t stopped Ellison from courting the administration’s favor as he seeks to acquire Warner Bros. Discovery.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats are united in bashing GOP on Obamacare. Medicare for All could reopen a rift.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/21/democrats-have-been-united-in-bashing-the-gop-on-obamacare-medicare-for-all-could-reopen-a-rift-00701232</link>
      <description>The single-payer health care system is again becoming a rallying cry for progressives in the midterms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3872-d78e-af9f-fc770f0c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 16:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/bf/6b/aa66518944578325dc79ef860cfd/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2242326009">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Sophie Park/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Graham Platner is among the Democratic Senate candidates promoting Medicare for All.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bf/6b/aa66518944578325dc79ef860cfd/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2242326009" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky and Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky and Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Progressives are pushing Medicare for All in some of the Democratic Party's most competitive Senate primaries next year, threatening the unity the party has found on attacking Republicans over expiring Obamacare subsidies.</p> 
<p>In Maine, Graham Platner said he’s making Medicare for All a “core part” of his platform in his race against Gov. Janet Mills, the establishment pick who’s <a href="https://mainemorningstar.com/2025/11/25/mainers-consider-forgoing-health-insurance-due-to-spiking-costs/" target="_blank">called for a universal health care program</a>. In Illinois, Lt. Gov. Juliana Stratton and Rep. Robin Kelly are both championing the concept — and calling out rival Rep. Raja Krishnamoorthi for not fully embracing it.</p> 
<p>In Minnesota, Medicare for All has emerged as a key distinction between progressive Lt. Gov. Peggy Flanagan and moderate Rep. Angie Craig, who supports adding a public option to the Affordable Care Act rather than Medicare for All. Flanagan said she “absolutely” expects the policy to define the primary because “it doesn’t matter if I’m in the urban core, the suburbs or greater Minnesota — when I say I’m a supporter of Medicare for All, the room erupts.”</p> 
<p>And it’s become a flashpoint in Michigan, where physician Abdul El-Sayed, who wrote a book called "Medicare for All: A Citizen’s Guide," is using his signature issue to draw a contrast with Rep. Haley Stevens and state Sen. Mallory McMorrow, who favor other approaches.</p> 
<p>Medicare for All — government-funded health coverage for every American — is “where we need to point to,” El-Sayed said in an interview. “And I think you can galvanize a winning coalition around this issue.”</p> 
<p>But some more moderate Democrats worry that progressives' renewed push for Medicare for All would undermine the party’s recent united front in fighting for an extension of the Obamacare subsidies that are set to expire at the end of the year, leading to a significant spike in insurance costs for millions of Americans. Their effort initially failed in the Senate, but with the help of four vulnerable Republicans who crossed party lines this week, Democrats have now secured a House vote on an extension in January.</p> 
<p>"We have a singular message, which is: ‘Don’t let these tax credits go.’ We have Republicans on the ropes,” said a national Democratic strategist who works on Senate races and was granted anonymity to speak candidly. “I don’t think introducing ‘we need MFA’ is the right strategy right now. I think it would be unhelpful."</p> 
<p>Several Democratic consultants pointed to recent public polling showing Americans like having individual insurance coverage, despite being dissatisfied with health care companies. <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/politics-news/poll-are-satisfied-health-insurance-quarter-report-denials-delays-rcna248908" target="_blank">An NBC News poll</a> found 82 percent of Americans were satisfied with their plans, both private and government-sponsored. Based on that data, these consultants said allowing Americans to buy into a government-offered plan, known as a “public option,” is more politically palatable.</p> 
<p>Centrists have long dismissed Medicare for All as both a policy pipe dream and political albatross for their party — a rallying cry for the left that serves as catnip for Republican ad-makers looking to broad brush Democrats as socialists. They argue that surveys often fail to present voters with the full picture of how Medicare for All would work, and therefore fail to capture its electoral toxicity.</p> 
<p>“What we need to accept is there’s a deeply held skepticism among Americans about going zero to 60 that’s entirely government run, even though they don’t love the current system,” said Adam Jentleson, a Democratic strategist and president of the Searchlight Institute. “In isolation, this thing does okay. But it’s not how it plays out in real life, and the totality will crush us.”</p> 
<p>The once-fringe policy that Sen. Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.) mainstreamed during his presidential campaigns has become a rallying cry for his favored candidates and other progressives across battleground primaries, as Democrats work to make health care costs central to next year’s midterms and as the party base clamors for fighters willing to disrupt the status quo. The push for Medicare for All, which receded during the more moderate Biden era, comes as Democrats have otherwise been unified on their health care messaging, forcing Republicans onto defense over their refusal to extend expiring Affordable Care Act subsidies.</p> 
<p>“Do I think every single swing-seat candidate is going to come out for Medicare for All? No,” said Jess Morales Rocketto, a Democratic strategist and board member for the nonprofit Care in Action. “But if you want to signal that you’re unafraid and bold right now, and you want to say you’re not beholden to the status quo, it’s a perfect position for that.”</p> 
<p>Progressives are <a href="https://www.dataforprogress.org/blog/2025/11/medicare-for-all-is-popular-even-when-put-up-against-attacks" target="_blank">emboldened by partisan</a> and <a href="https://d3nkl3psvxxpe9.cloudfront.net/documents/econTabReport_haeOEK5.pdf" target="_blank">independent polling</a> that shows most Democrats and a majority of independents support Medicare for All. A recent survey commissioned by Rep. Pramila Jayapal’s (D-Wash.) leadership PAC and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/pramila-jayapal-pushes-medicare-for-all-polling-00696301" target="_blank">first reported by POLITICO</a> showed 90 percent of Democrats back Medicare for All and found most independents and one in five Republicans back a “government-provided system.”</p> 
<p>Jayapal, the former chair of the Congressional Progressive Caucus, plans to push her colleagues to start promoting Medicare for All again in the new year. She predicted in an interview that support for the system will be a “defining factor” in the party’s primaries next year and an electoral winner in battleground House seats.</p> 
<p>But proponents of Medicare for All argue that a government-provided system would lessen the pinch of rising health care costs. They say pushing to extend the ACA subsidies and promoting Medicare for All as an end goal are not mutually exclusive. And they point to several 2018 candidates who won tough seats while supporting the measure, including former Rep. Katie Porter in California to retiring Rep. Jared Golden of Maine.</p> 
<p>“You can know that there are short-term stopgaps that must be taken to protect working people while also thinking that long term, we need a better system,” said Platner, who is vying against Mills to unseat GOP Sen. Susan Collins in Maine.</p> 
<p>Platner has been extolling Medicare for All from the start of his campaign and said it gets the “most raucous” response at his events across Maine, where a recent <a href="https://hs-21701012.f.hubspotstarter.net/hubfs/21701012/67th%20Omnibus%20Poll%20December%202025.pdf?utm_medium=email&amp;_hsenc=p2ANqtz-_qWyGL4keanJ5LSdiKL6c5WZV-1bzCKylYwKxtbhhKyeZjebUL8XLBb0fyCN-GbIYvmJH9vOeAAN3J59WkcFJnVG8viQ&amp;_hsmi=393840029&amp;utm_content=393840029&amp;utm_source=hs_email" target="_blank">Pan Atlantic Research poll</a> found 63 percent support for the system (and Platner trailing Mills by 10 points).</p> 
<p>He argued in an interview that Mills isn’t as steadfast in her support for the concept because she “doesn’t talk about it all that often” and uses “vague language” when she does. Mills has said “it is time” for universal health care and that she’s “committed to finding a way to get there” if elected. Her campaign echoed that sentiment in response to a request for comment for this story, and cited her efforts to expand Mainers access to Medicaid.</p> 
<p>In Minnesota, Flanagan said embracing Medicare for All has been a “journey” during her Senate campaign, as she heard from Minnesotans that the “cost of health care is the thing that comes over and over and over again.” Of Craig’s support for a public option, Flanagan said voters don’t want a nominee who “nibbles around the edges” instead of being “bold and audacious.”</p> 
<p>Craig calls the public option a “big, bold reform,” but emphasizes that it’s a policy “we could actually accomplish in this country in a fairly short time period,” she said in a <a href="https://x.com/angiecraigmn/status/2001393940252000258?s=46" target="_blank">video this week</a>.</p> 
<p>In Illinois, Stratton and Kelly, two of the three leading Democrats vying to replace retiring Sen. Dick Durbin, are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IvlTjIoo8n8" target="_blank">jockeying for position</a> as Medicare for All’s biggest champion in the race while their campaigns knock Krishnamoorthi for couching his support for the system. Krishnamoorthi said in a statement that while it’s “a noble goal, and I’m fighting to get us to universal coverage” his focus is on extending the ACA subsidies and reversing Republicans’ cuts to Medicaid.</p> 
<p>And in Michigan, El-Sayed has slammed McMorrow’s call for universal health care with a public option as “incoherent” and ill-informed as the two compete for the same slice of progressive voters. McMorrow has <a href="https://x.com/MalloryMcMorrow/status/1978943351350075534?s=20" target="_blank">knocked the idea</a> of a single-payer system run by President Donald Trump and his controversial health secretary, Robert F. Kennedy Jr. And she’s promoted a public option so people who like their private insurance can keep it. Stevens’ campaign says she supports strengthening Obamacare, including through a public option, without endorsing Medicare for All.</p> 
<p>The issue is also becoming a flash point in Democratic primaries for some of the most competitive House seats in the country, driven in part by Sanders-backed candidates running from California’s Central Valley to Pennsylvania’s Lehigh Valley.</p> 
<p>“There’s immense hostility and anger toward the way the insurance industry functions, doubled up with health care itself being one of the biggest affordability issues,” said Mark Longabaugh, a progressive strategist who worked on Sanders’ 2016 presidential bid. “Progressives are smart to push the case.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vance tries to weather the MAGA storm at Turning Point</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/21/vance-maga-infighting-turning-point-usa-00702396</link>
      <description>The weekend-long gathering has been enveloped in intraparty fighting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-4290-d78e-af9f-fef771e80001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2025 15:42:26 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0f/81/3144db084880a1e2031481a3a658/turning-point-45168.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jon Cherry/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Vice President JD Vance acknowledges supporters during Turning Point USA's AmericaFest on Dec. 21, 2025, in Phoenix.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0f/81/3144db084880a1e2031481a3a658/turning-point-45168.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>PHOENIX — After three straight days of MAGA infighting here at Turning Point’s AmericaFest, top Republicans — including Vice President JD Vance — tried to find agreement on Sunday afternoon, shifting their focus to countering the opposition.</p> 
<p>“President Trump did not build the greatest coalition in politics by running his supporters through endless, self-defeating purity tests,” Vance told the crowd to loud applause, adding later: “We have far more important work to do than canceling each other."</p> 
<p>In his speech, Vance ripped into “far left” Democrats, casting their policies as toxic to Americans and blaming them for <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/11/charlie-kirk-killing-trump-leadership-void-00559167" target="_blank">Charlie Kirk's September killing</a>, which has loomed large over the gathering. He touted the Trump administration’s policies on immigration, vaccines and transgender issues, while calling for the crowd to engage ahead of next year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>“If you miss Charlie Kirk, do you promise to fight what he died for? Do you promise to take the country back from the people who took his life?” Vance asked the crowd.</p> 
<p>His speech at the Phoenix Convention Center is the culmination of a weekend-long festival for 30,000 of President Donald Trump’s most ardent supporters. But until Sunday, much of the weekend was clouded by an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/maga-infighting-erupts-at-day-one-of-turning-point-usa-conference-00699665?nid=0000018f-3124-de07-a98f-3be4d1400000&amp;nname=politico-toplines&amp;nrid=df9635b8-7d6f-4c86-9d5f-4c7def2c3d10" target="_blank">intra-party schism</a> that kicked off during night one on Thursday, when conservative commentator Ben Shapiro ripped into a number of fellow MAGA-verse influencers, especially Tucker Carlson, Candace Owens and Steve Bannon.</p> 
<p>“The conservative movement is in serious danger,” Shapiro said, especially from some “charlatans who claim to speak in the name of principle but actually traffic in conspiracism and dishonesty.”</p> 
<p>Those themes carried through on Friday and Saturday, with presidential-hopeful turned Ohio GOP gubernatorial candidate Vivek Ramaswamy casting the moment as “a time for choosing in the conservative movement.”</p> 
<p>Like Shapiro, Ramasawamy focused significant time on Carlson and his interview with far-right influencer and Holocaust denier Nick Fuentes, <a href="https://x.com/VivekGRamaswamy/status/2002184151680872533?s=20" target="_blank">listing some of his most inflammatory remarks</a> and saying they “have no place in this movement.”</p> 
<p>Then, Bannon hit the stage and reversed course, comparing Shapiro to a “a cancer, and that cancer spreads.”</p> 
<p>“Ben Shapiro is the farthest thing from MAGA,” Bannon told the crowd.</p> 
<p>The sold-out annual meeting is the group’s first since founder Charlie Kirk was gunned down in September. It has featured a broad array of figures from within the conservative movement, including top commentators, elected officials, candidates and religious leaders, culminating with Vance and Speaker Mike Johnson on Sunday.</p> 
<p>Johnson called the weekend an “epic and faithful battle that truly will determine the future of our great republic” while stressing the importance of keeping control of the House ahead of next year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>Vance also spent much of his speech talking about the midterms, bashing Democratic Senate candidates Graham Platner of Maine and Jasmine Crockett of Texas, who are both running in competitive primaries.</p> 
<p>“We are gonna kick their ass next November,” Vance said of Democrats as the crowd immediately burst into “USA” chants. Outside of Johnson and Vance, a number of other speakers on Sunday sought to bridge the divisions that emerged in the prior days.</p> 
<p>"I choose to build a movement, be part of a movement, that stands on principle, on strength, that loves the people in the movement, even sometimes when they piss you off,” said Rep. Byron Donalds (R-Fla.), who is running for governor. "You can't form a winning unit if you can't stay focused on the mission at hand.”</p> 
<p>Donald Trump Jr. also sought to shift the focus to Democrats.</p> 
<p>“The real enemy? It’s not Steve Bannon or Tucker Carlson or Ben Shapiro, it’s the radical left that murdered Charlie and celebrated it on a daily basis,” Trump Jr. told the crowd.</p> 
<p>The political beliefs of alleged Kirk shooter Tyler Robinson, who is facing multiple charges including aggravated murder, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/09/17/how-charlie-kirks-killer-poisoned-everyone-with-meme-slop-00569200" target="_blank">aren’t easily defined</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epstein files put Bill Clinton under scrutiny – and the White House wants him there</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/trump-world-takes-shots-at-favorite-boogeyman-bill-clinton-in-epstein-file-dump-00701780</link>
      <description>The former president is pictured in a swimming pool with Ghislaine Maxwell and an unidentified woman.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3940-d651-a1ff-3f60731f0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 20:08:40 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/aa/c7/f9c4310f42d99a117cf6a407940b/clinton-epstein-grid.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Department of Justice</media:credit>
        <media:title>Undated photographs showing Bill Clinton released by the Justice Department as part of the Jeffrey Epstein files on Dec. 19, 2025. Epstein is pictured with Clinton, top left, redactions of others in the photos are by the DOJ.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/aa/c7/f9c4310f42d99a117cf6a407940b/clinton-epstein-grid.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton and Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton and Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Trump administration, initially wary over the Justice Department’s release of Jeffrey Epstein documents, pounced on go-to villain Bill Clinton’s appearance in Friday’s trove of pictures, emails and interviews.</p> 
<p>“I wonder why the Biden DOJ refused to release the files…,” DOJ spokesperson Chad Gilmartin posted from <a href="https://x.com/ChadGilmartinCA/status/2002136880629043489?s=20" target="_blank"><u>his personal X account</u></a>, alongside one partially-redacted photo of Clinton <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%202/EFTA00003170.pdf" target="_blank"><u>in a pool with an unidentified woman</u></a>. Another swimming pool photo Gilmartin posted shows Clinton with Ghislaine Maxwell, Epstein’s longtime co-conspirator who was convicted of sex trafficking charges in 2021.</p> 
<p>Trump and the DOJ also resisted releasing the files until Congress passed a bill to do so. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/trump-signs-epstein-files-bill-00658418" target="_blank"><u>Trump signed the bill last month</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Clinton has long been linked with Epstein, contributing to his status as MAGA’s favored boogeyman. Some high-profile members of the movement cited him in pushing for the release of the files, and continued that message after the DOJ made public a trove of documents from the government’s investigation into Epstein.</p> 
<p>“Slick Willy! @BillClinton just chillin, without a care in the world. Little did he know…” White House Communications Director Steven Cheung <a href="https://x.com/stevencheung47/status/2002135433933959178?s=12" target="_blank"><u>posted to X</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“Here is Bill Clinton in a hot tub next to someone whose identity has been redacted. Per the Epstein Files Transparency Act, DOJ was specifically instructed only to redact the faces of victims and/or minors. Time for the media to start asking real questions,” White House deputy press secretary Abigail Jackson <a href="https://x.com/abigailmarone/status/2002136727029493885?s=20" target="_blank"><u>posted to her personal X account</u></a>.</p> 
<p>The act also allowed the DOJ to redact material related to active investigations.</p> 
<p>It’s unclear when the <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%202/EFTA00003168.pdf" target="_blank"><u>previously unreleased photo</u></a> was taken and where the pool is located.</p> 
<p>Clinton appears in photos <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%202/EFTA00003177.pdf" target="_blank"><u>posing with Epstein in coordinating shirts</u></a>, interacting with a dancer, sitting with a redacted woman on his lap on what looks like an airplane and with someone who appears to be the late pop icon Michael Jackson. The music legend faced his own child sex abuse allegations as early as 1993, though he was never convicted of any crimes.</p> 
<p>The former president is also seen at a dinner sitting next to rock star Mick Jagger, alongside Maxwell and Epstein.</p> 
<p>Epstein faced state and federal charges over two decades related to the sexual abuse and trafficking of dozens of underage girls as young as 14. He pleaded guilty in Florida to state charges in 2008, one of which was for soliciting prostitution from someone under 18. He was awaiting trial on federal child trafficking charges when he died by suicide in a New York jail in 2019. His connections to the wealthy and powerful, and efforts to keep information related to him from becoming public, has become part of the national political narrative – intensifying bipartisan sniping and deepening fractures in Trump’s base.</p> 
<p>The files were heavily redacted. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/epstein-documents-release-friday-deadline-00699935?utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank"><u>Deputy Attorney General Todd Blanche </u></a><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/epstein-investigation-files-released-00700666" target="_blank"><u>said earlier Friday</u></a><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/19/epstein-documents-release-friday-deadline-00699935?utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank"><u> that the first dissemination would be partial, with as many as hundreds of thousands of more documents </u></a>to follow in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Clinton said the Friday afternoon timing of the document release is “about shielding themselves from what comes next, or from what they’ll try and hide forever.”</p> 
<p>“So they can release as many grainy 20-plus-year-old photos as they want, but this isn’t about Bill Clinton,” Angel Ureña, deputy chief of staff for Clinton, posted in a <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/2002159039183269993?s=46&amp;t=bc4OjMQq3SFcud7QML4uPw" target="_blank"><u>statement</u></a> on X. “There are two types of people here. The first group knew nothing and cut Epstein off before his crimes came to light. The second group continued relationships with him after. We’re in the first. No amount of stalling by people in the second group will change that.”</p> 
<p>Clinton and Epstein have been linked since the early 1990s, having run in the same social circles. They have been photographed together several times. Clinton flew on Epstein’s plane in the early 2000s, taking trips to Europe, Asia and Africa. Ureña <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/1148357927625023490" target="_blank"><u>said</u></a> those trips included stops for work connected to the Clinton Foundation.</p> 
<p>The former president has never been accused of any wrongdoing in connection to Epstein, and said he was not aware of Epstein’s crimes, something a Clinton spokesperson reiterated in a <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/1148357927625023490" target="_blank"><u>social media post six years ago</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Democrats on the House Oversight Committee <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/12/12/politics/epstein-photos-trump-clinton-bannon" target="_blank"><u>this month</u></a> released additional photos from Epstein’s estate that feature Clinton.</p> 
<p>Trump has long suggested that Clinton repeatedly visited Epstein’s private island in the U.S. Virgin Islands, the location of alleged sex trafficking and abuse where the financier hosted high-profile friends. But White House chief of staff Susie Wiles said in a Vanity Fair <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/16/susie-wiles-trump-clinton-epstein-interview-00692570" target="_blank"><u>interview</u></a> published this week that Trump was “wrong” to tie Clinton to Epstein’s criminal activity.</p> 
<p>Trump and Epstein were longtime friends before Trump said they had a falling out several years ago. The president has denied wrongdoing in relation to the Epstein allegations, and no evidence has suggested that he took part in Epstein’s trafficking operation.</p> 
<p><i>Brakkton Booker contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists on the week in politics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2025/12/19/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00698871</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's an offering of the best of this week's crop, picked fresh off the Toonosphere. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-3379-d78e-af9f-ff7f0b6d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2025 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAGA infighting erupts at Turning Point USA Conference</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/maga-infighting-erupts-at-day-one-of-turning-point-usa-conference-00699665</link>
      <description>Two of the night’s headliners — Ben Shapiro and Tucker Carlson — threw jabs at each other in their speeches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-349c-d78e-af9f-fcff36560001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 22:41:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8d/7e/2906bd654b7890e126c0e309610b/arizona-turning-point-conference-21861.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jon Cherry/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Ben Shapiro walks on stage before speaking during Turning Point USA's America Fest 2025 on Dec. 18, 2025, in Phoenix.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8d/7e/2906bd654b7890e126c0e309610b/arizona-turning-point-conference-21861.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>PHOENIX — Members of the MAGA faithful gathered here Thursday to kick off Turning Point USA’s America Fest, the largest meeting for the organization since its founder, Charlie Kirk, was shot to death on a Utah college campus in September.</p> 
<p>Despite that somber backdrop, the event quickly devolved into a spectacle of MAGA infighting.</p> 
<p>Ben Shapiro, the first speaker after widow Erika Kirk, ripped into those who would take the same stage in the coming hours and days. He called out conservative commentators, blasting Candace Owens, Tucker Carlson, Megyn Kelly and Steve Bannon as “frauds and grifters.”</p> 
<p>“The conservative movement is in serious danger,” Shapiro said, arguing the danger is not just on the left, but “from charlatans who claim to speak in the name of principle but actually traffic in conspiracism and dishonesty.”</p> 
<p>He called Bannon “a PR flack for Jeffrey Epstein” ahead of the imminent release of files related to the late convicted sex offender, while praising President Donald Trump and his administration's handling of the issue. Trump pushed to stop Republicans in Congress from voting to release the files, though he signed the legislation once it was passed. Both Bannon and Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/trump-clinton-gates-included-in-epstein-photo-trove-00688628" target="_blank">appear in photos with Epstein that were released by House Democrats</a>.</p> 
<p>Shapiro particularly focused on Carlson — both for elevating Owens’ <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/piers-morgan-confronts-candace-owens-over-charlie-kirk-conspiracy-theories-tense-interview" target="_blank">conspiracy theories about Kirk's murder</a> and for his recent interview with far-right influencer Nick Fuentes, a Holocaust denier who has repeatedly pushed antisemitic tropes. Carlson, a former Fox News host, now hosts his show on X and routinely garners millions of views.</p> 
<p>“The people who refused to condemn Candace’s truly vicious attacks — and some of them are speaking here tonight — are guilty of cowardice,” Shapiro said, adding later: “If you host a Hitler apologist, Nazi-loving, anti-American piece of refuse like Nick Fuentes … you ought to own it.”</p> 
<p>Both the Fuentes interview and Owens’ conspiracies have embroiled the party in recent weeks. On Wednesday, Shapiro called on the Heritage Foundation, the powerful conservative think tank whose president defended the interview, to change its tune about Carlson’s elevation of Fuentes.</p> 
<p>Carlson responded with heat of his own from the stage Thursday.</p> 
<p>“That guy is pompous,” Carlson said, saying he “laughed” while watching clips of Shapiro's speech backstage. “Calls to deplatform at a Charlie Kirk event? That’s hilarious.”</p> 
<p>Carlson went on to rail against cancel culture, and promised the crowd that he was not antisemitic. “Antisemitism is not just naughty, it’s immoral,” he said.</p> 
<p>Erika Kirk addressed the MAGA movement’s fractures, while casting her late husband as a rare unifier and pleading with the crowd to embrace disagreement. “You won’t agree with everyone on this stage this weekend,” she said. “And that's okay. Welcome to America.”</p> 
<p>The event wasn’t entirely heated. Actor Russell Brand — who spoke between Shapiro and Carlson — focused on Christianity, while sprinkling attacks on vaccines and the pharmaceutical industry into his remarks. And earlier in the day, attendees danced to upbeat music, repeatedly chanted “USA” and celebrated Trump’s return to the White House at the Phoenix Convention Center, which is plastered with imagery of Charlie Kirk. More than 30,000 people gathered for the event.</p> 
<p>Kirk’s influence on young people was particularly evident, with thousands of high school and college attendees, some of whom posed for photos in front of a tent that resembled the one Kirk was speaking in front of when he was shot during “The American Comeback Tour.”</p> 
<p>Erika Kirk — who now serves as Turning Point’s CEO — said 80 percent of attendees had never been to America Fest before, and one-third of them were students. More than 140,000 people have submitted requests to join the organization since Kirk’s death, bringing the membership to over 1 million people across 4,000 chapters at high schools and colleges, she added.</p> 
<p>While the group has welcomed speakers from across the conservative movement, it made clear choices about which politicians to welcome to the stage, providing a glimpse into how the organization hopes to shape the future of the GOP. Texas Attorney General Ken Paxton and GOP Rep. Mike Collins, both candidates for Senate, and gubernatorial hopefuls Andy Biggs of Arizona and Byron Donalds of Florida, were given slots on the main stage.</p> 
<p>Erika Kirk also made a point of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/erika-kirk-endorses-jd-vance-president-00699610?utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank">promising to elevate Vice President JD Vance</a> — who will close the event on Sunday — to the White House in 2028. Vance leads early polls of the likely GOP field.</p> 
<p>“We are going to get my husband’s friend JD Vance elected for 48 in the most resounding way possible,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Erika Kirk endorses JD Vance for president</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/erika-kirk-endorses-jd-vance-president-00699610</link>
      <description>Vance was an ally of Turning Point USA before the killing of Charlie Kirk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-346d-dba9-addb-37ffe7970001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 21:43:37 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b1/d8/6db416684ae8aa96daff4c6014db/arizona-turning-point-conference-66841.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jon Cherry/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Erika Kirk speaks during Turning Point USA's AmericaFest 2025, Dec. 18, 2025, in Phoenix.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b1/d8/6db416684ae8aa96daff4c6014db/arizona-turning-point-conference-66841.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>PHOENIX. Arizona — Turning Point USA CEO Erika Kirk has endorsed Vice President JD Vance for president, an early sign of influential support for a likely leading candidate in 2028.</p> 
<p>Kirk, who took over leadership of Turning Point after her husband, Charlie, was killed in September, announced her decision during a speech Thursday at the organization’s America Fest conference in Phoenix.</p> 
<p>Vance is scheduled to speak at the conference on Sunday.</p> 
<p>“We are going to get my husband’s friend JD Vance elected for 48 in the most resounding way possible,” Kirk said.</p> 
<p>Vance has not yet committed to running in 2028, but as vice president he is widely expected to seek the White House. TPUSA — founded by Charlie Kirk — holds major influence for the MAGA movement, particularly among young conservatives, and the early endorsement could give an early lead among the Republican hopefuls.</p> 
<p>“My attitude is the American people elected me to be vice president,” <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/29/jd-vance-marco-rubio-2028-00627286" target="_blank">Vance told the New York Post in October</a>. “I’m going to work as hard as I can to make the president successful over the next three years and three months, and if we get to a point where something else is in the offer, let’s handle it then.”</p> 
<p>Kirk made the endorsement in front of a crowd of thousands of people, many of whom are ardent supporters of President Donald Trump — and they responded with resounding applause.</p> 
<p>Vance and Charlie Kirk were particularly close before Kirk's death.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-term North Carolina Gov. Jim Hunt, a leader in education reform, dies at 88</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/four-term-north-carolina-gov-jim-hunt-a-leader-in-education-reform-dies-at-88-00699172</link>
      <description>Hunt's career, including an unprecedented 16 years in the governor's office, provided a prototype for the modern “education governor.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-33cf-d651-a1ff-3fef8d140000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 18:46:07 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/91/46/19fa83d34e93a36c2f7f71180f89/obit-north-carolina-jim-hunt-22144.jpg">
        <media:title>Former North Carolina Gov. Jim Hunt speaks at the Democratic National Convention, Sept. 5, 2012, in Charlotte, N.C. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite, File)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/91/46/19fa83d34e93a36c2f7f71180f89/obit-north-carolina-jim-hunt-22144.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Associated Press</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Associated Press</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>RALEIGH, N.C. — Four-term <a href="https://apnews.com/general-news-8e99e89aa07942898b7a1ccc8de415d7" target="_blank">North Carolina Gov. Jim Hunt,</a> a towering figure in North Carolina politics in the late 20th century who helped the Democratic Party focus nationally upon public education reform, died Thursday at the age of 88, his <a href="https://apnews.com/article/north-carolina-election-council-appeals-courts-5e73d072749c09276c10d25b753f42ab" target="_blank">daughter Lt. Gov. Rachel Hunt</a> announced.</p> 
<p>Hunt, whose career provided a prototype for the modern “education governor,” served an unprecedented 16 years as governor as the state received the rewards and stings of shifting from textiles and tobacco to a high-tech economy.</p> 
<p>Rachel Hunt’s office said that her father died peacefully Thursday at his Wilson County home.</p> 
<p>“He devoted his life to serving the people of North Carolina, guided by a belief that public service should expand opportunity, strengthen communities, and always put people first,” Rachel Hunt said in a news release that also referenced “my beloved daddy and hero.”</p> 
<p>Considered a business-oriented progressive, Hunt was a giant in state government and influential in the national education reform movement of the late 20th and early 21st centuries. He was first elected governor in 1976 and, after a constitutional change, became the first North Carolina governor elected to successive four-year terms.</p> 
<p>Following an epic U.S. Senate campaign loss to Republican icon Jesse Helms in 1984, Hunt’s political career resumed eight years later with a third term at the Executive Mansion, followed by reelection in 1996.</p> 
<p>Hunt remained active in Democratic politics after leaving office in 2001, particularly as he watched protégés such as former Gov. Roy Cooper and the late U.S. Sen. Kay Hagan achieve higher office. He <a href="https://apnews.com/5938587844b74623ac21a1fd9bdc7846" target="_blank">campaigned for President Barack Obama</a> in 2012 and Hillary Rodham Clinton and Cooper in 2016.</p> 
<p>“I can think of no one who shaped North Carolina’s recent successes as much as Governor Jim Hunt,” current Democratic Gov. Josh Stein said Thursday. And Cooper called Hunt the “greatest Governor in North Carolina history.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://apnews.com/general-news-8e99e89aa07942898b7a1ccc8de415d7" target="_blank">Even entering his 80s</a>, Hunt urged Republicans in charge of the legislature to fund “big things” for public education, rather than pass more income tax cuts.</p> 
<p>“I’m proud of what we’ve done together,” Hunt said in a May 2017 interview. “But I’m far from satisfied about where we are and determined to keep doing my little bit, I guess, to help us keep changing things and improving things in North Carolina. And I know you do it mainly through education.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Relentless on building up public schools</h5> 
<p>Hunt concentrated relentlessly on public schools, talking about the connection between education achievement and competing in the world economy. In the 1970s, while lieutenant governor, he worked with <a href="https://apnews.com/3cc611af23ed4fbe9b01cb54ec4807d0" target="_blank">Republican Gov. Jim Holshouser</a> to make North Carolina the first state with full-day kindergarten.</p> 
<p>In the 1980s, he helped create the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards and pressed for standardized testing for public school students nationwide so that states could compare themselves.</p> 
<p>Returning as governor in the 1990s, he championed the Smart Start early childhood initiative, viewed as a national model to prepare children for school, and higher teacher pay. And after the end of his career in office, the Durham-based Hunt Institute trained up and coming political stars nationwide about public education policy.</p> 
<p>“If there is one person that is responsible for remaking and reforming education in the nation, particularly in the Southeast and starting with North Carolina, it is Jim Hunt,” former Democratic Georgia Gov. Roy Barnes said in a 2009 interview. “We will feel the effect of Jim Hunt’s leadership for generations to come.”</p> 
<p>Hunt was an unabashed lobbyist for his programs and initiatives, often making late-night phone calls to lawmakers to persuade them. If that failed, he would enlist key constituents in a legislator’s district to bombard with them calls all weekend.</p> 
<p>“He really had a way of pushing you to do things you never thought you could do,” said Gary Pearce, a longtime Hunt staffer and later biographer. “He made you feel like that you were genuinely making the world a better place.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Quick rise in North Carolina politics</h5> 
<p>James Baxter Hunt Jr. was born May 16, 1937, in Greensboro, North Carolina. He grew up on the family’s tobacco and dairy farm in Wilson County. After law school graduation, Hunt, his wife, Carolyn, and their young children lived in Nepal for two years while working for the Ford Foundation.</p> 
<p>Hunt rose quickly in Democratic politics, serving as president of the state’s Young Democrats in 1968 and getting elected lieutenant governor four years later.</p> 
<p>In a controversial move during his first term as governor, Hunt commuted the sentences of nine Black men and one white woman convicted of the 1971 firebombing of a Wilmington grocery store during days of violence that included the shooting of a Black teenager by police. Key witnesses in the case had recanted their testimony. Full pardons for the “Wilmington 10” <a href="https://apnews.com/article/raleigh-north-carolina-wilmington-racial-injustice-bombings-516516a170a24535a2a22abe6c8452e0" target="_blank">didn’t come until 2012.</a></p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">After loss to Helms, a rebirth and return to governor</h5> 
<p>His second four-year term closed with his political battle with Helms, the conservative firebrand known as “Senator No” for his opposition to civil rights, gay rights, abortion and the Martin Luther King Jr. holiday. Hunt lost as Helms’ campaign blistered him with ads portraying Hunt as a flip-flopper on the issues.</p> 
<p>A defeated Hunt returned to practicing law but remained in public life. His comeback to state politics in the early 1990s helped delay a growing Republican tide in North Carolina politics.</p> 
<p>Even GOP leaders begrudgingly were impressed with Hunt’s ability to tack with changing political winds. In the mid-1990s, he called a special legislative session to get tough on crime and proposed tax cuts larger than what Republicans initially offered.</p> 
<p>Republican U.S. Sen. Thom Tillis, a former state House speaker in the 2010s, called Hunt on Thursday “one of the most consequential public servants in North Carolina’s history.”</p> 
<p>Rachel Hunt served in the legislature and was elected lieutenant governor in 2024. Jim Hunt was on hand at the Legislative Building in early 2025 when she took as <a href="https://apnews.com/article/north-carolina-legislature-opening-new-speaker-9008424dd87d2aeea84a7ef606e2cf37" target="_blank">a duty of lieutenant governor</a> the gavel as Senate president, following in her father’s footsteps 52 years later.</p> 
<p>Memorial information for Hunt will be announced later.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democratic National Committee blocks release of its 2024 election autopsy</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/dnc-kills-its-own-public-2024-autopsy-00697403</link>
      <description>Despite a pledge from DNC Chair Ken Martin to release the post-election report, the committee announced Thursday it would not share it publicly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-321f-db0e-a9bb-ffff6c2e0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 11:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/04/49/3c8444f0477b8f024e1dcdfa9b9d/election-2026-texas-redistricting-38540.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Erin Hooley/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>DNC Chair Ken Martin speaks during a news conference in Aurora, Illinois, on Aug. 5, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/04/49/3c8444f0477b8f024e1dcdfa9b9d/election-2026-texas-redistricting-38540.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Democratic National Committee is refusing to release its autopsy of the party’s major 2024 losses it announced on Wednesday, breaking Chair Ken Martin’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/01/ken-martin-elected-dnc-party-chair-00201938" target="_blank"><u>public pledge to do so</u></a>. The decision underscores the party’s challenges in grappling with its electoral setbacks as it heads into <a href="https://www.politico.com/interactives/2025/democrats-2026-midterm-flips-redistricting-data/" target="_blank"><u>what is expected to be a stronger midterm year.</u></a></p> 
<p>The DNC’s completed post-election review of the party’s melodramatic and botched campaign cycle is based on hundreds of interviews with operatives in all 50 states. During that process, some Democrats raised concerns about releasing the findings, according to a DNC official granted anonymity to describe the sensitive process.</p> 
<p>The DNC wanted to avoid another public debate over how the party lost the White House to Donald Trump, and instead, turn its focus on its recent successes, according to this official. Democrats have overperformed in special elections across the country this year, and won handily in New Jersey and Virginia last month. The committee <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/dnc-briefs-top-democrats-on-audit-of-2024-white-house-loss-00597998" target="_blank"><u>previewed some initial findings</u></a> from the autopsy to top donors and other Democratic stakeholders in October.</p> 
<p>Former President Joe Biden's decision to run for reelection, despite his advanced age — and his disastrous debate performance — were not mentioned in the some excerpts of the report's findings, which were shared with POLITICO. Democrats are still divided over what contributed to Kamala Harris' loss.</p> 
<p>In a statement, Martin said the committee had “completed a comprehensive review of what happened in 2024” and they are “putting our learnings into motion,” noting the party’s off-year victories.</p> 
<p>“In our conversations with stakeholders from across the Democratic ecosystem, we are aligned on what’s important, and that’s learning from the past and winning the future,” Martin continued. “Here’s our North Star: does this help us win? If the answer is no, it’s a distraction from the core mission.”</p> 
<p>The decision marks an about-face for a coalition that’s at odds over what went wrong last year, and still registering <a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/poll-shock-democrats-congressional-approval-sinks-all-time-low" target="_blank"><u>record-low</u></a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/11/poll-democrats-jobs-economy-00222988" target="_blank"><u>approval</u></a> <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elections/democratic-party-poll-voter-confidence-july-2025-9db38021?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqdN6PgWJ2ORMInFa8bmZ2KaICRsx9G5_TtBfjHFNYA41xiiN4uejhvLgsAwqAw%3D&amp;gaa_ts=69436602&amp;gaa_sig=rtuJCf67rnRXfdBxvgWYp8MJ0OjsVHhKD2e3MpeNUn4OVZdGkIrws8_jK3lPSy1JPgeFwp3Ian4O3rZFCXmNXw%3D%3D" target="_blank"><u>ratings</u></a> even among its own voters. Several outside groups, from <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/204271/why-democrats-lost-2024-election-trump-way-to-win-report" target="_blank"><u>the progressive Way to Win</u></a> to the <a href="https://www.semafor.com/article/10/27/2025/democrats-urged-to-jettison-progressive-rhetoric-favored-by-highly-educated-and-affluent" target="_blank"><u>center-left Welcome nonprofit</u></a>, released their own in-depth audits of the party’s missteps with differing diagnoses for how to fix its problems. Just last week, some DNC members <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/13/dnc-democratic-national-committee-hope-00689938" target="_blank"><u>called on the committee</u></a> to provide more answers.</p> 
<p>The DNC official described some examples of the report’s findings, including the party’s organizing strategies, necessary technological upgrades and its youth voter problem — though the details shared with POLITICO were sparse and incomplete. Excerpts from the review broadly described Democrats as defensive on immigration and public safety — issues that generally favor Republicans — but didn’t name-check a campaign, candidate or entity for its role in this posture, at least not publicly.</p> 
<p>On the party’s organizing efforts, the DNC’s review urged campaigns to incentivize engaging conversations with voters over just the number of doors knocked and phones called. It called for investing more into relational organizing and year-round field infrastructure, efforts Martin championed during his chair’s race last year. Of the party’s data infrastructure, the DNC’s report issued warnings that it was out-of-date and overwhelmed at key moments during the campaign and called for it to be modernized.</p> 
<p>It described the party’s much-reported losses among young voters, citing Republicans’ advantages in communicating through the influencer ecosystem and pressing Democrats to do engage with non-traditional media sources. Back in February, Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/16/democrats-losing-trump-doge-information-battle-00204522" target="_blank"><u>conceded the GOP was “running circles” around them online</u></a>, but in describing its findings, the DNC doesn’t go much further in clarifying its own public recommendations.</p> 
<p>This fall, the DNC <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/dnc-briefs-top-democrats-on-audit-of-2024-white-house-loss-00597998" target="_blank"><u>held briefings with donors and other Democratic stakeholders</u></a> on its initial findings. At the time, one Democrat who attended an October donor event confirmed that Biden’s initial decision to run in spite of his advanced age was not mentioned by DNC officials as a part of the review. It’s not clear whether his decision to run for reelection is discussed in the private review.</p> 
<p>Biden’s age was not mentioned in the excerpts of the review shared with POLITICO on Thursday, nor was it raised <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/dnc-briefs-top-democrats-on-audit-of-2024-white-house-loss-00597998" target="_blank"><u>in other briefings on the report’s initial findings</u></a>. Most Democrats cite the last-minute candidate switch as a core reason for the party’s sweeping losses.</p> 
<p>Martin’s decision to withhold the report doubles back on a pledge he made just hours after he was elected to be the DNC’s chair in February. In comments to reporters, Martin committed to the public release of the 2024 report.</p> 
<p>At the time, he also questioned why the DNC hadn’t released its 2016 autopsy, when he questioned, “what happened with that … was there any utility in doing that?”</p> 
<p>“Of course it will be released,” Martin said in February, referring to a future review on the 2024 election. “There has to be some lessons that we glean on that so we can operationalize it, not just here in DC, but through all of the 57 state parties, and, of course, the county parties, so people have a sense of what we need to do.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pramila Jayapal pushes Medicare for All polling</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/pramila-jayapal-pushes-medicare-for-all-polling-00696301</link>
      <description>The Washington Democrat plans to brief her House Democratic colleagues on the findings in early 2026.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2e78-d369-affb-6ffca18c0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/1c/19/abc0d7d2428ba9aca074ff5980f8/mag-scola-cicilline-jayapal.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Pramila Jayapal arrives for the House Judiciary Committee organizational meeting on Capitol Hill on Feb. 1, 2023.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1c/19/abc0d7d2428ba9aca074ff5980f8/mag-scola-cicilline-jayapal.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) wants Medicare for All back in the health care debate.</p> 
<p>The former Congressional Progressive Caucus chair plans to present polling to her House Democratic colleagues next month as she argues for the electoral merits of Medicare for All — even in battleground districts the party must win to flip the House next fall. The research, paid for by Jayapal’s leadership PAC and shared first with POLITICO, found one in five Republicans support a “government-provided system,” as do most independents. Democrats back Medicare for All by 90 percent.</p> 
<p>Two-thirds of voters said the federal government does “too little” to help people afford health care. Just 18 percent said the government does “too much.”</p> 
<p>Jayapal’s Medicare for All push comes as Democrats have been largely unified on their health care messaging, pushing Republicans on the back foot about extending expiring Obamacare subsidies. Injecting Medicare for All back into the debate could also reopen a long-running intraparty fight that moderate Democrats aren’t keen to have.</p> 
<p>In an interview, Jayapal described swing district voters’ openness to Medicare for All and a desire for “fundamental change” as a “significant shift” in recent years. She cited the rising costs of health care for making the current system less appealing to swing voters who “don't feel like they can afford health care right now” and “don't feel like they have a choice right now.”</p> 
<p>“Whatever tropes they may have had about Medicare for all, those don't really exist today in the public's mind,” Jayapal said, arguing Democrats should now “put forward a very united and universal, comprehensive vision for health care in this country.”</p> 
<p>Democrats are hoping to make health care a central midterm messaging — tying this fall’s federal government shutdown <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/17/congress/brian-fitzpatrick-joins-house-democrats-health-care-discharge-petition-00694688" target="_blank"><u>to a debate within the GOP</u></a> over extending the Affordable Care Act subsidies. Jayapal hopes to nudge her party into not only pushing back on President Donald Trump’s cuts to Medicare, Medicaid and the ACA, but also “be ready with a proactive vision” for voters, she said.</p> 
<p>Jayapal will undoubtedly face pushback from moderate Democrats over championing an issue that’s long divided the party. Medicare for All defined much of the ideological battle of the 2020 presidential primary, serving as the progressives’ flagship policy. After Joe Biden, who didn’t <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2020/03/10/biden-says-he-wouldd-veto-medicare-for-all-as-coronavirus-focuses-attention-on-health.html" target="_blank"><u>back it citing the price tag</u></a>, won the primary, the policy largely fell out of the conversation.</p> 
<p>Over the last five years, Medicare for All has remained popular among Democrats — and Jayapal argues her latest research shows that it’s increasingly intriguing to independents and Republicans, who are feeling the pinch of rising health care costs. Jayapal said she’ll pitch her polling to Republican members, too, though she declined to name them.</p> 
<p>“There’s going to be some internal resistance [to Medicare for All] but it needs to be informed by polling, and in our survey, a majority of voters are in favor of it,” said David Walker, a pollster at GQR Research who conducted the survey. “We didn’t gild the lily [in the survey], we didn’t say it’d all be free.”</p> 
<p>The poll described Medicare for All to participants as a “system [that] would still use the same doctors and hospitals as today, but take the profit motive out of health care by using a government-administered insurance system, like Medicare or Medicaid,” acknowledging “taxes will increase for many Americans,” but added, “those could be offset by not having to pay for health insurance premiums, co-pays or out-of-pocket costs.” The poll found 54 percent of voters nationally and 56 percent in battleground districts back Medicare for All.</p> 
<p>Jaypal acknowledged confusion around the meaning of Medicare for All, and suggested adding “improved” to the slogan, as a nod to Americans’ frustrations with the existing Medicare program.</p> 
<p>Jayapal said she intentionally used a polling firm that works closely with the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee because “we wanted to make it clear this isn’t some fringe poll.” GQR surveyed 1,000 likely 2026 voters from Nov. 5 to Nov. 13, oversampling voters in battleground House seats. The margin of error is 3.1 percentage points.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poll: The economy is fueling political anger in 5 major countries</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/cost-of-living-democracies-poll-00696355</link>
      <description>The international poll illustrates the uphill battle many leaders face in trying to contain the intertwined economic and political backlash.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2e7d-db0e-a9bb-ffff025c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2025 00:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/png" url="https://static.politico.com/99/66/627781b945669ea72039ad28f2a9/europe-afforadbility.png">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Anna Wiederkehr/POLITICO (source images via Getty)</media:credit>
        <media:title>TPP: Europe, Canada, USA affordability</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/99/66/627781b945669ea72039ad28f2a9/europe-afforadbility.png" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The affordability crisis that upended global politics last year continues to ripple across some of the world’s biggest democracies — punishing incumbents and undermining longstanding political alliances.</p> 
<p>New <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-2e9e-d369-affb-6fbe91a20000" target="_blank">international POLITICO polling</a> shows the voter frustration with persistent financial strain remains a deeply potent force today. In five major economies, The POLITICO Poll found ongoing cost-of-living pressures continue to reverberate through politics:<br></p> 
<ul> 
 <li>In the <b>United States</b>, where Donald Trump returned to power on a campaign of economic populism, nearly two-thirds of voters — 65 percent — say the cost of living in the country has gotten worse over the last year.&nbsp;</li> 
 <li>In the <b>United Kingdom</b>, where voters ousted the Conservative Party in 2024 after 14 years of rule, 77 percent say the cost of living has worsened.&nbsp;</li> 
 <li>In <b>France</b>, where President Emmanuel Macron is grappling with <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/emmanuel-macron-approval-rating-drops-historic-low/">historically low favorability ratings</a>, almost half of all adults — 45 percent — say their country is falling behind comparable economies.&nbsp;</li> 
 <li>In <b>Germany</b>, after prolonged infighting over the economy, former Chancellor Olaf Scholz’s governing coalition collapsed last year. There, 78 percent of respondents say the cost of living has gotten worse over the last year.&nbsp;</li> 
 <li>And in <b>Canada</b>, a post-pandemic affordability crisis helped fuel a public backlash against then-Prime Minister Justin Trudeau’s government ahead of his resignation earlier this year. The POLITICO Poll found that 60 percent of adults in the country say the cost of living is the worst they can remember it being.&nbsp;</li> 
</ul> 
<p>The results, from POLITICO and Public First’s first-ever joint international poll, illustrate the uphill battle many leaders face in trying to contain the intertwined economic and political unrest. Five years after the coronavirus pandemic upended the global economy — and as the world contends with competing conflicts and AI rapidly becoming a defining force — meaningful shares of respondents across the U.S., Canada, and Europe’s biggest economies of Germany, the United Kingdom and France view the cost of living as among the biggest issues facing the world right now.</p><p>But as leaders seek to address the affordability concerns, many say that their leaders could be doing a lot more to help on the cost of living, but are choosing not to.<br></p><p>That has left incumbent governments grappling with how to manage the rising economic dread — and control the resulting political backlash. It has also created an opportunity for opposition parties on economic messaging.</p> 
<p>“For incumbents it’s very difficult to run on these platforms,” said Javier Carbonell, a policy analyst at the European Policy Centre. “Today, center-left and center-right parties are seen as incumbents, and as the ones who are to put the blame.”</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Voters are pessimistic about the cost of living</h4> 
<p>There is a pervasive sense in the five countries that their economies are deteriorating.</p> 
<p>In France, 82 percent of adults say the cost of living in the country has worsened over the last year, as do 78 percent of respondents in Germany; 77 percent of adults in the United Kingdom and 79 percent in Canada say the same.</p> 
<p>A majority of people in all five countries go even further, saying the cost of living crisis has never been worse.<br></p><p>In a further sign of the trouble facing leaders, the poll results suggest many view affordability as a systemic problem more than a personal one. Majorities across the countries, for example, say the issue of affordability is the high cost of goods, not that they are not paid too little.</p> 
<p>In the U.K., roughly two-thirds of adults say the country’s economy has deteriorated — greater than the 46 percent who say their own financial situation has worsened over the last year. That same pattern holds for France, Canada and Germany, suggesting the public holds broad concerns about the economy and affordability that go beyond their individual lives.</p> 
<p>While the European Union’s <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/eu-economy-grows-more-than-expected-in-2025-despite-trumps-tariffs/" target="_blank">economy is set to grow</a> by 1.4 percent in 2025, the economy in Germany has weakened over the past two years, and is expected to stagnate this year. In France, a series of government policies aimed at addressing cost-of-living concerns have contributed to an exploding national debt, which currently stands at nearly $4 trillion USD.</p> 
<p>In the United Kingdom, the results come against a backdrop of sluggish economic growth, with incumbent Prime Minister Keir Starmer struggling to convince voters that his center-left Labour Party can drive down the cost of living.</p> 
<p>And in Canada, the country’s deep-seated anxiety is born out by federal inflation data. Statistics Canada <a href="https://www150.statcan.gc.ca/n1/daily-quotidien/251215/dq251215a-eng.htm" target="_blank">reported this week</a> that the consumer price index ticked up 2.2 percent in November compared to the same month in 2024 — nearly a bullseye on the central bank's 2 percent target.</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Negative economic views are shaping politics</h4> 
<p>Voters’ economic concerns are roiling politics.</p> 
<p>In 2024, Trump ran a campaign on economic concerns without having to oversee the economy himself. That dynamic has shifted in recent months, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/04/poll-americans-trump-voters-affordability-crisis-00674747" target="_blank">with voters beginning to sour on his handling of the economy</a>, underscoring the difficulty of convincing voters of economic progress amid stubborn cost-of-living concerns.</p> 
<p>That feeling of falling behind was particularly acute among European respondents in the POLITICO Poll, with nearly half of adults in Germany, France and the United Kingdom saying that their country is “generally falling behind other comparable economies.”<br></p><p>That pessimism has pushed many people out of the political process, Carbonell said, “because there’s no expectation that things are going to change.” For others, it’s fueling a search for political alternatives.</p> 
<p>“There is this increasing demand for a very anti-system politics,” he said.</p> 
<p>In Germany, Chancellor Friedrich Merz made revamping the economy a central campaign promise. But since taking office, he has been preoccupied with geopolitical issues, including the ongoing trade war and the Russia-Ukraine war.</p> 
<p>That has become a successful line of attack for Merz's critics — among them the far-right Alternative for Germany (AfD) party, now polling in first place. The party has accused Merz — whose approval ratings are at an all-time low — of not paying enough attention to the needs of the people in his own country, nicknaming him the “foreign policy chancellor.”</p> 
<p>In France, the government is looking to roll back some of the policies it rolled out in response to cost-of-living concerns, but doing so could prove particularly unpopular with a population laser-focused on high costs. It could also fuel anti-establishment parties on the right and left, which have made the issue a central weapon against France’s crumbling political center.</p> 
<p>David Coletto, a longtime pollster in Canada and CEO of the firm Abacus Data, has for years tracked affordability concerns — and found widespread concern among most survey respondents.</p> 
<p>"This is not a marginal concern or a background anxiety," <a href="https://abacusdata.ca/for-67-of-canadians-the-cost-of-living-feels-as-bad-as-it-ever-has/" target="_blank">he wrote of results</a> from POLITICO’s November poll. "It is a dominant lived experience that continues to shape how Canadians interpret government performance, leadership, and competing policy priorities, alongside concern about Donald Trump, trade, and global instability."</p> 
<h4 class="story-text__heading-large">Affordability messaging will be a central message in upcoming elections</h4> 
<p>Affordability will be a central feature of elections across the globe next year — with some of that messaging already underway. In the U.S., Democratic candidates from New York to Georgia <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/affordability-affordability-affordability-democrats-new-winning-formula-00637023" target="_blank">focused much of their 2025</a> campaigns on lowering the costs of living, and both parties are planning to center the issue in the midterms.</p> 
<p>"For now, the cost of living remains a warning light rather than a red light for the Carney government," Coletto wrote. "But the intensity of feeling, combined with seasonal pressures and fragile household finances, means the issue is unlikely to fade quietly into the background."<br></p><p>Starmer’s government — languishing in the polls and facing local elections in 2026 — has pivoted in recent weeks to a more explicit focus on affordability.</p> 
<p>The U.K. government has also floated freezing train fares, lowering energy bills, and boosting the minimum wage in an attempt to solve the affordability crisis, but a record-high level of taxation confirmed at a government-wide budget last month risks blunting its economic message.</p> 
<p>In Germany, the issue of affordability may gain new momentum when voters in five federal states head to the polls to elect new state parliaments next year. In Berlin, the far-left Left Party, for example, plans to take a playbook from the affordability-centered campaign of New York's Zohran Mamdani as a model for the state elections in September.</p> 
<p>With local elections also taking place across France next year, and a presidential election in 2027, these issues are likely to continue to take center stage, especially in the larger cities where pricing pressures have been particularly acute.</p> 
<p>In Paris, the outgoing center-left administration has been praised for making the city greener and more pedestrian-friendly, but far more needs to be done on affordability, said David Belliard, a member of the outgoing administration and the Green Party’s candidate for mayor.</p> 
<p>“We’ve spent a lot of time fighting against the end of the world,” Belliard said, “but maybe not enough helping people make it to the end of the month.”</p> 
<p><i>POLITICO’s Matt Honeycombe-Foster contributed to this report from the United Kingdom, Victor Goury-Laffont contributed to this report from France, Nette Nöstlinger contributed to this report from Germany and Nick Taylor-Vaisey contributed to this report from Canada.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ramaswamy calls on conservatives to reject Groypers</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/vivek-ramaswamy-groypers-nyt-00694823</link>
      <description>In a New York Times op-ed, the former GOP presidential candidate said Nick Fuentes and his supporters have “no place in the conservative movement.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2d1d-d71a-abff-7fffa3740000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 12:12:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/25/be/a0d8a221454db0ea046de6c697f8/republican-national-convention-41840.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>In a New York Times op-ed, Vivek Ramaswamy said "it is downright unacceptable to spew poison toward Jews, Indians or any other ethnic group."</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/25/be/a0d8a221454db0ea046de6c697f8/republican-national-convention-41840.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Ohio gubernatorial hopeful and former GOP presidential candidate Vivek Ramaswamy urged conservatives to reject "Groyper transgressions," becoming the latest Republican to weigh in on the ongoing debate in the party over antisemitism.</p> 
<p>“If, like Mr. Fuentes, you believe that Hitler was “really f-ing cool,” or if you publicly call Usha Vance a “jeet,” then you have no place in the conservative movement, period,” Ramaswamy wrote <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/17/opinion/republican-identity-divide.html?partner=slack&amp;smid=sl-share" target="_blank">in a New York Times op-ed published Wednesday</a>, referring to a derogatory ethnic slur against South Asians.</p> 
<p>In the quote, Ramaswamy was referencing Nick Fuentes and Vice President JD Vance’s wife Usha Vance, the daughter of Indian immigrant parents.</p> 
<p>Ramaswamy shared that he has been the target of racial slurs and attacks on social media, despite “older Republicans” doubting the rising prevalence white supremacy in right-leaning online circles.</p> 
<p>As the number of “Groypers,” or followers and fans of Fuentes, appears to grow, Ramaswmy said, there is a “real reluctance” from his fellow Republicans to condemn the “new identity politics on the right.”</p> 
<p>“It should be acceptable on the right to criticize U.S. aid to Israel or immigrant visas, but it is downright unacceptable to spew poison toward Jews, Indians or any other ethnic group,” said Ramaswamy, the son of Indian immigrants.</p> 
<p>The Republican Party has been embroiled in an intra-party struggle over whether the party should welcome groups associated with Fuentes, a debate that burst into the open after Tucker Carlson interviewed Fuentes on his podcast. Carlson, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=efBB0D4tf1Y" target="_blank">during his friendly October interview with Fuentes</a>, said GOP backers of Israel have been “seized by this brain virus.” Fuentes said that “organized Jewry” is a major barrier to unifying America.</p> 
<p>While President Donald Trump defended Carlson’s decision to interview Fuentes, House Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/25/mike-johnson-tucker-carlson-nick-fuentes-interview-00668135" target="_blank">called it a “big mistake.”</a> The president of the conservative think tank Heritage Foundation, Kevin Roberts, also initially defended Carlson’s interview, arguing the real enemy was “the vile ideas of the left.” But after immense backlash — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/31/mcconnell-heritage-foundation-tucker-carlson-00631510" target="_blank">including from Sen. Mitch McConnell</a> (R-Ky.) and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/heritage-resigns-robert-george-tucker-00654143" target="_blank">multiple employees quitting</a> — Roberts walked back his comments and condemned Fuentes’ rhetoric.</p> 
<p>In his op-ed, Ramaswamy said that condemning the antisemitism brewing within a faction of the GOP does not need to equate to censorship but “moral clarity instead of indulgence.”</p> 
<p>“The point isn’t to clutch pearls, but to prevent the gradual legitimization of this un-American animus,” he said. “This online edgelording reminds me of toddlers testing their parents’ limits: The job of a real Republican leader is to set firm boundaries for young followers, as a good father does for a transgressive son.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans push mail-in voting for the midterms in defiance of Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/republicans-midterms-mail-in-voting-00693867</link>
      <description>Fearing a turnout slump, Republicans are promoting mail voting to keep Trump’s supporters engaged — even as he tries to end the practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2905-db13-a3fb-efc74bbd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b4/fa/be9e6c9c48c6a1e76b2e76e37284/us-pennsylvania-elections-mail-ballots-12158.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mail-in ballots in Pennsylvania</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b4/fa/be9e6c9c48c6a1e76b2e76e37284/us-pennsylvania-elections-mail-ballots-12158.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republicans are making mail-in voting a core part of their midterm battle plans — a sharp contrast with President Donald Trump’s efforts to abolish the practice as they scramble to turn out his base.</p> 
<p>In Wisconsin, the state party is preparing a full-court press of mailers, emails, phone banks, door knocks and digital ads to get voters to sign up for mail ballots.</p> 
<p>In Michigan, the Monroe County GOP ran a social media campaign ahead of the fall election urging voters to utilize permanent absentee ballots and is planning an even bigger push next year.</p> 
<p>In Pennsylvania, where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/18/trump-mail-voting-attacks-00513875" target="_blank">Republicans poured $16 million into boosting</a> the number of GOP voters using mail ballots in 2024, the state party chair called it “a priority” for 2026. The nonprofit Citizens Alliance, which aided efforts to get Republicans to return their mail ballots in Pennsylvania last year, is planning to knock 750,000 doors ahead of the midterms to encourage infrequent voters to embrace the practice.</p> 
<p>And the Republican National Committee intends to build on the aggressive early mail and in-person voting campaign it ran successfully in 2024, after shying away from the practice in 2020, while also supporting election security efforts including stopping ballots from being counted after Election Day, according to a person granted anonymity to describe the committee’s plans.</p> 
<p>“Democrats have built a pretty massive structural advantage in early voting for a long, long time. And we just can’t keep going into election night 100,000 votes down and expect to make it up in 12 hours,” Wisconsin GOP Chair Brian Schimming said in an interview. “Treating early voting as optional, or something Democrats do, is a losing gamble.”</p> 
<p>Trump has long falsely decried mail voting as rife with fraud. <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/amp/news/trump-ban-mail-in-voting-before-2026-midterm-elections/" target="_blank"><u>Over the summer, he vowed</u></a> that Republicans “are going to do everything possible [to] get rid of mail-in ballots.” In November, and again this week, he called on Senate Republicans to eliminate the filibuster and pass a law to ban mail-in voting.</p> 
<p>But, as has been the case for several years, he and his party are out of sync.</p> 
<p>Rattled by electoral losses across the country this year and fearing a turnout slump in 2026 when control of Congress is on the line, Republican party chairs and operatives in battleground states Trump flipped by razor-thin margins in 2024 are turning to mail-in voting to keep lower-propensity voters engaged when he’s not on the ballot. They’re redoubling the 2024 efforts they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/10/06/trumps-early-voting-00182611" target="_blank"><u>ran successfully despite Trump alternating between promoting and railing against</u></a> the practice — a turnabout after his vilification of mail ballots contributed to GOP losses in 2020.</p> 
<p>Now, back in office, Trump is escalating his war against mail ballots. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/25/trump-signs-sweeping-executive-order-targeting-election-rules-00249891" target="_blank"><u>signed an executive order in March</u></a> that attempted to bar states from counting ballots that arrive after Election Day, along with other election-system overhauls. Judges have blocked most of the order, and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/supreme-court-mail-in-voting-case-00644388" target="_blank"><u>Supreme Court is set to decide</u></a> whether federal law prohibits states from counting late-arriving ballots postmarked by Election Day.</p> 
<p>Despite pledging to “lead a movement” to eliminate “corrupt” voting by mail ahead of the midterms, Trump has yet to issue another executive order on it. State courts have upheld vote-by-mail programs expanded during the pandemic. And presidents have little authority over state-run elections, whose rules are guided by federal and state law rather than presidential decree.</p> 
<p>State and local Republicans, seeing few paths to overturning mail voting programs, are forging ahead — swallowing their own misgivings about ballot security in an effort to cut into a Democratic advantage as early voting options turn Election Day into election season.</p> 
<p>Pressed about their mission appearing antithetical to Trump’s rhetoric, Republican operatives uniformly insisted they’re simply trying to play by the rules they’ve been given and that they support the president trying to change them — even if they’re unsure he’ll succeed.</p> 
<p>“In Michigan, that’s the law of the land unless we can find a U.S. constitutional override, which I doubt that’s going to happen,” said Jim Runestad, a state senator who chairs the Michigan Republican Party. So, he said, “we’ll be fully engaged in early and absentee voting — we have to be.”</p> 
<p>Still, the renewed dispute between Trump and his party over mail-in voting is the latest evidence of cracks forming in the ordinarily unified Republican Party. GOP lawmakers throughout the country, from New Hampshire to Indiana, have been rebuffing the president’s push for an aggressive redistricting effort to shore up his party’s chances of keeping its slim House advantage next year. Democrats need to net just three seats in order to seize control over the lower chamber. And several members of Trump’s base, namely departing Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia, bucked him on the yet-to-be-released Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>The White House did not respond to a request for comment for this story.</p> 
<p>Republicans have already shown some success in convincing their voters to embrace mail voting. In Pennsylvania — where now-Sen. Dave McCormick’s campaign, party committees and outside groups spent millions promoting the practice — GOP voters cast 32.4 percent of mail ballots in 2024, up from 23.7 percent four years earlier, helping Trump narrowly flip the state. Roughly one in five Republican voters who cast ballots in the state that year had not participated in any elections since 2020, suggesting the method worked for some low-propensity voters who the party has to work harder to turn out.</p> 
<p>Nationally, roughly three in 10 ballots in the 2024 general election were cast by mail, according to a <a href="https://www.eac.gov/sites/default/files/2025-07/2024_EAVS_Report_508.pdf" target="_blank"><u>U.S. Election Assistance Commission report</u></a> from June. That was down from 43 percent in 2020, at the pandemic’s peak, but higher than pre-Covid, according to the report.</p> 
<p>“We have to encourage people to embrace mail-in voting and early voting,” Pennsylvania GOP Chair Greg Rothman said in an interview. “That has to be a priority for us in 2026.”</p> 
<p>Rothman won’t be alone in that fight. Citizens Alliance, the nonprofit founded by Pennsylvania-based conservative activist Cliff Maloney that hired over 100 people to chase ballots across roughly 500,000 doors in 2024, is gearing up to knock 750,000 in 2026. The Republican State Leadership Committee, which helped fund mail-ballot programs in Pennsylvania last year, put more than $2 million behind turnout efforts in New Jersey and Virginia this year and said it’s <a href="https://rslc.gop/memo-rslc-launches-project-doorstrike-initiative-for-2025-2026-election-cycle/" target="_blank"><u>“doubling down” on the program in 2026</u></a>.</p> 
<p>“Without Trump on the ballot, the low-propensity problem is an epidemic” and “Republicans have to adapt or die,” Maloney said. “The blessing here is that there’s a solution — and the solution is to actually put dollars, cents, time and energy into the same tactics that the left uses to target low-propensity voters.”</p> 
<p>State and county parties in Wisconsin and Michigan are planning similarly aggressive efforts, though they, like other Republican officials interviewed for this story, declined to share details or put price tags on strategies still taking shape. In Michigan, where voters can sign up for a permanent mail ballot list, Monroe County GOP Chair Todd Gillman sees it as a way to get more people engaged in more under-the-radar local elections.</p> 
<p>But even as they try to make inroads with mail voting, Republicans in other states are <a href="https://www.statenews.org/2025-11-19/ohio-lawmakers-vote-to-eliminate-the-four-day-grace-period-for-mail-in-ballots" target="_blank"><u>attempting to follow Trump in restricting </u></a>the practice. Ohio’s GOP-controlled Legislature last month passed a bill that would invalidate nearly all ballots received after Election Day that were postmarked prior to the deadline. The state’s Republican governor, Mike DeWine, is now <a href="https://www.wlwt.com/article/ohio-bill-mike-dewine-mail-in-balloting-grace-period/69690435" target="_blank"><u>weighing whether to sign it</u></a>. Utah GOP Gov. Spencer Cox <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/03/27/nx-s1-5323797/utah-mail-voting-law" target="_blank"><u>signed a similar bill</u></a> earlier this year. Republican-led Kansas Legislature <a href="https://kansasreflector.com/2025/03/25/kansas-legislature-overrides-governors-veto-of-bill-to-limit-advance-voting/" target="_blank"><u>overrode Democratic Gov. Laura Kelly’s veto</u></a> of another bill eliminating the grace period<b>, </b>which is being challenged in court.</p> 
<p>And Republicans pushing mail-in voting remain somewhat hamstrung by their standard bearer’s scaremongering, which has sown a deep distrust among GOP voters that party officials and activists say they’re still working to reverse.</p> 
<p>Trump made baseless claims of mail-voting fraud the basis for his constellation of stolen-election conspiracy theories in 2020. He piled on in 2024, suggesting scores of Pennsylvania ballots were fraudulent and accusing postal workers of “purposefully” losing some mail ballots — even as his campaign, the RNC and GOP-aligned groups prioritized early voting initiatives. Last month, as Californians voted to approve mid-decade redistricting in response to a GOP-led redraw in Texas, <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115492361756063244" target="_blank"><u>Trump threatened legal action</u></a> that never materialized over ballots cast by mail in a state that sends one to every voter.</p> 
<p>GOP operatives have a script for that, insisting to wary Republicans that they’ve made voting by mail more secure and informing them of the various options they have to ensure their ballots reach election offices, including hand delivery.</p> 
<p>“We don’t necessarily like early voting or absentee ballots,” Gillman said. “But those are the rules we have to play by.”</p> 
<p><i>Jessica Piper contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Michelle Obama pushes back on Trump’s Rob Reiner comments</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/16/michelle-obama-rob-reiner-trump-comments-00692813</link>
      <description>The former first lady said Reiner and his wife were not “deranged or crazed.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2814-d653-afff-6f94f8b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 12:24:43 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ad/fa/0ef7ea4b45a890ec7095b0667d1f/michelle-obama-75560.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Allison Robbert/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Former first lady Michelle Obama speaks about her new book "The Look" during an event at Sixth and I on Nov. 12, 2025, in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ad/fa/0ef7ea4b45a890ec7095b0667d1f/michelle-obama-75560.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former first lady Michelle Obama on Monday appeared to push back on President Donald Trump’s controversial remarks about the death of Hollywood couple Rob Reiner and Michele Singer Reiner.</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IqGNKbXBfPg" target="_blank">an appearance on ABC’s “Jimmy Kimmel Live!”</a> Obama shared that she and her husband, former President Barack Obama, were supposed to see the Reiners on Sunday — the same day their bodies were discovered stabbed to death in their California home.</p> 
<p>While her husband early Monday shared that the two were “heartbroken” to learn of the Reiners’ deaths, Michelle Obama appeared to single out Trump’s statement, which attributed the couple's deaths to “Trump derangement syndrome” and the director's lack of support for the president.</p> 
<p>“Let me just say this, unlike some people: Rob and Michele Reiner are some of the most decent, courageous people you ever want to know,” she told Kimmel. “They’re not deranged or crazed. What they have always been are passionate people. In a time when there’s not a lot of courage going on, they were the kind of people who were ready to put their actions behind what they cared about. And they cared about their family. And they cared about this country.”</p> 
<p>Police are currently investigating the Reiners’ deaths as an “apparent homicide,” and authorities announced Monday that Reiner’s son, Nick Reiner, is in custody as a suspect. He has been booked on murder charges and is being held on $4 million bail.</p> 
<p>The son of legendary comedian Carl Reiner, Rob Reiner was a strong supporter of progressive causes, including LGTBQ+ rights and early childhood education, and often held fundraisers and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/democrats-rob-reiner-react-00690528" target="_blank">campaigned for Democratic issues</a>. He was also a frequent critic of Trump’s.</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115724141568860081" target="_blank">a Monday morning post to Truth Social</a>, Trump said Reiner was “a tortured and struggling, but once very talented movie director and comedy star, has passed away, together with his wife, Michele, reportedly due to the anger he caused others through his massive, unyielding, and incurable affliction with a mind crippling disease known as TRUMP DERANGEMENT SYNDROME, sometimes referred to as TDS.”</p> 
<p>Despite <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/trump-rob-reiner-death-00690682" target="_blank">sharp backlash</a> from Democrats and Republicans alike, Trump doubled down on his comments during a medal presentation Monday afternoon, telling reporters in the Oval Office that he wasn’t a fan of Reiner’s “at all.”</p> 
<p>“He was a deranged person as far as Trump is concerned,” Trump said.</p> 
<p>The White House declined to comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New York Young Republican Club gala draws white nationalist, far-right Germans as elected officials skip out</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/new-york-young-republican-gala-frohnmaier-00690510</link>
      <description>The annual soiree took place as young Republican groups across the country are reeling from POLITICO’s reporting on a racist and antisemitic chat group among prominent leaders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2259-d5ec-abbb-fadfc88e0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 12:22:29 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c3/5c/b078a8fe4ad892dcdeaafb343bf9/main-beefman-younggopgala-lead-new.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Photos by Paola Chapdelaine for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Guests mingle at the New York Young Republican Club gala at Cipriani Wall Street in New York, on Dec. 13, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c3/5c/b078a8fe4ad892dcdeaafb343bf9/main-beefman-younggopgala-lead-new.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jason Beeferman and Caroline McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jason Beeferman and Caroline McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>NEW YORK — Two months after prominent members of a national Young Republican organization were <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/14/private-chat-among-young-gop-club-members-00592146" target="_blank">exposed for their role in a hate-filled, private group chat</a>, the city-based chapter showed it’s willing to welcome almost anyone.</p> 
<p>Inside Cipriani Wall Street, a lavish event space in the financial district, amid the sea of tuxedos and ball gowns, was <a href="https://www.wnycstudios.org/podcasts/otm/segments/what-white-separatist-expects-trump-administration" target="_blank">white nationalist leader</a> Jared Taylor. Across the room sat EmpathChan, an <a href="https://x.com/Emp4thchan/status/2000084514769711542?s=20" target="_blank">influencer</a> who went <a href="https://x.com/emp4thchan/status/1984405716115833112?s=46" target="_blank">viral</a> recently for wearing blackface on Halloween. And appearing on stage was Markus Frohnmaier, a far-right German politician, whose political party the club had <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/03/young-republicans-chapter-plans-to-host-far-right-german-leader-after-i-love-hitler-chat-00671540#:~:text=In%20August%2C%20it%20published%20a%20statement%20calling%20for%20a%20%E2%80%9Cnew%20civic%20order%E2%80%9D%20in%20Germany%20and%20declaring%20%E2%80%9CAfD%20%C3%BCber%20alles%2C%E2%80%9D%20an%20adaptation%20of%20a%20phrase%20associated%20with%20the%20Nazi%20party." target="_blank">cheered with a German-language phrase popularized by the Nazis</a>. At least nineteen other members of the Alternative for Germany (AfD) party joined him.</p> 
<p>Also spotted at the New York Young Republican Club gala: Vish Burra, a club member <a href="https://www.thewrap.com/matt-gaetz-producer-fired-at-oan-over-antisemitic-posts-exclusive/" target="_blank">who lost his job</a> at the conservative One America News Network last month for <a href="https://x.com/jasonahart/status/1989372206166720915?s=20" target="_blank">posting a video depicting Jews as cockroaches</a>.</p> 
<p>Just eight weeks after the city club’s statewide counterpart <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/17/new-york-state-young-republicans-is-done-for-now-after-racist-group-chat-00613576" target="_blank">was disbanded by the New York State GOP</a>, the city-based club showed on Saturday night how a Young Republican organization can throw a party. Its 113th annual gala came as local chapters are still reeling from the racist and antisemitic “I love Hitler” chat — and as the GOP faces a larger reckoning over whether anti-Jewish voices have space within the party.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ba/58/5aa40fed496b8b961e4e2de3f7d4/main-beefman-younggopgala-secondary1.jpg" alt="Amid the sea of tuxedos and ball gowns was white nationalist leader Jared Taylor." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Paola Chapdelaine for Politico" data-title="Amid the sea of tuxedos and ball gowns was white nationalist leader Jared Taylor."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/7e/d1/eaf783d94d8ab77c77c1d954d8a5/main-beefman-younggopgala-secondary2.jpg" alt="The gala took place at Cipriani Wall Street, a lavish event space in the financial district." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Paola Chapdelaine for Politico" data-title="The gala took place at Cipriani Wall Street, a lavish event space in the financial district."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/ab/10/4d430c3f48dabd766ab880fef92b/main-beefman-younggopgala-secondary3.jpg" alt="Markus Frohnmaier, a far-right German politician, was an honored guest and appeared on stage." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Paola Chapdelaine for Politico" data-title="Markus Frohnmaier, a far-right German politician, was an honored guest and appeared on stage."/><p>On Saturday night, the festivities provided a glimpse of what the party’s youth wing looks like amid those conditions. Over the course of the gala, a club member <a href="https://x.com/TimmyFacciola_/status/2000073210453426189?s=20" target="_blank">struck an attendee in the face</a> outside on the sidewalk, President Donald Trump was endorsed for a third term and a protester wearing a Nazi armband and waving a swastika-laden banner popped up from his seat to shout, “I guess we're all Nazis!” in an attempt to disrupt the event, according to two attendees and a <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-2024-d5ec-abbb-f8b63cc70000" target="_blank">release</a> from Goofball, the group behind the protest.</p> 
<p>The sold-out Cipriani served its signature bellini cocktail to attendees upon arrival. Zoltán Mága, a Hungarian violinist whose last name sparked jokes among the GOP faithful, performed during the six-course dinner, which featured baked tagliolini with mushrooms, prime rib and potatoes.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Democratic state senators, assemblymembers and city council members were <a href="https://x.com/JasonBeeferman/status/1999994606776385726?s=20" target="_blank">outside protesting the event</a> at a demonstration hosted by the Manhattan Young Democrats.</p> 
<p>“The people that are in that room, they were calling folks like me watermelon people,” said Assemblymember Jordan Wright, who is Black, referencing a line from the chats exposed by POLITICO. “They were being racist, they were being homophobic, they were idolizing Hitler.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/13/a5/3183b7594502982aa5ea99cbe650/main-beefman-younggopgala-secondary4.jpg" alt="Assemblymember Jordan Wright stands during a protest outside the event." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Paola Chapdelaine for Politico" data-title="Assemblymember Jordan Wright stands during a protest outside the event."/><p>In October, POLITICO reported on a chat with a dozen Young Republicans who held leadership positions in chapters of the organization across the country. Since that initial report, at least seven people involved in the chats lost their jobs, including a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/17/lawmaker-resigns-after-involvement-in-racist-chat-00614823" target="_blank">Vermont state lawmaker who resigned</a>. Two members of the chat apologized for the chats but blamed the rival city group for them coming to light</p> 
<p>Later in the evening, white nationalist Nick Fuentes — whose friendly October interview with Tucker Carlson has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/03/ben-shapiro-tucker-carlson-nick-fuentes-interview-00633323" target="_blank">splintered the GOP</a> — lingered on the sidewalk outside Cipriani after the club’s organizers <a href="https://x.com/TimcastNews/status/2000189193851461721?s=20" target="_blank">banned him</a> from entering.</p> 
<p>“This is the worst event they’ve ever thrown,” the club’s press chairman, Lucian Wintrich, told reporters huddled together in the “press pen” where the media was restricted for much of the event. Wintrich had been expressing frustration that the dozens of outlets he welcomed to the gala were relegated to a distant corner by his fellow organizers.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/19/3d/326612b44d988de0f5792775fdce/main-beefman-younggopgala-secondary5.png" alt="Left: Guests sit for dinner during the gala. Right: Political activist Jack Posobiec, left, holds a rosary before delivering the keynote speech." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="" data-title="Left: Guests sit for dinner during the gala. Right: Political activist Jack Posobiec, left, holds a rosary before delivering the keynote speech."/><p>Conspicuously absent from Saturday night’s event were five GOP elected officials — including one congressman — who the club had announced would be there.</p> 
<p>Rep. Paul Gosar (R-AZ) was advertised as scheduled to attend in an October email, but he didn’t show up. His team did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>Neither did New York City GOP Council Member Inna Vernikov — who was <a href="https://youtu.be/1Qvjt5_apPc?si=mQudYIpMHF1CW9ZX&amp;t=8337" target="_blank">brought on stage by Trump</a> at the 2023 gala while she wore an <a href="https://x.com/InnaVernikov/status/1733678493215453664?s=20" target="_blank">Israeli-flag-themed gown</a>. The local MAGA firebrand and longtime ally of the club skipped its event despite being promoted as an “honored guest” days before. Assemblymember Michael Tannousis and City Council Members David Carr and Frank Morano were also not seen<b>, </b>despite <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-1f92-d7be-a79b-bff752cf0000" target="_blank">promotions</a> touting their participation.</p> 
<p>Vernikov and Tannousis declined to comment. Carr and Morano did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>From the stage, the speakers took an increasingly anti-immigrant bent.</p> 
<p>“If dubiously elected or rather naturalized illegal immigrants are polluting our politics, the new right must have courage to deport them,” said Rep. Andy Ogles (R-Tenn.), in reference to his call to deport Mayor-elect Zohran Mamdani, which he said would “resurrect our nation.”</p> 
<p>Earlier in the night, the club’s president, Stefano Forte, addressed attendees.</p> 
<p>“We all know who the enemy is,” Forte said. “The enemy is who shot President Trump in Butler, Pennsylvania. The enemy is who almost shot him again two weeks [later] in Mar-a-Lago…The enemy slanders us in the media, throws wide open our borders, replaces our native population.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/59/d0/b238485645fca596c3a340aaaec8/main-beefman-younggopgala-secondary6.jpg" alt="New York Young Republican Club President Stefano Forte delivered remarks during the gala." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Paola Chapdelaine for Politico" data-title="New York Young Republican Club President Stefano Forte delivered remarks during the gala."/><p>On Sunday, in the wake of the <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/12-dead-australia-bondi-beach-shooting-gunman-jewish-hannukah-celebration-terrorism/" target="_blank">mass shooting at a Hanukkah celebration in Australia</a>, Vernikov had a blistering message for her fellow Republicans that seemed to reference her absence.</p> 
<p>“For years, antisemitic rhetoric has dominated THE LEFT and has fully infiltrated the Democratic Party,” she <a href="https://x.com/InnaVernikov/status/2000333456304205842?s=20" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>, saying such rhetoric led to the terror seen in Sydney. “Unfortunately, today the same venom has entered corners of the conservative movement and the hard RIGHT WING of the Republican Party. Lunatics like Nick Fuentes, Candace Owens and Tucker Carlson, who spew bigoted, racist and antisemitic rhetoric, should be condemned and excommunicated from the Republican Party never to be welcomed again … I will DISASSOCIATE myself from any event, individual, or organization whether Democrat or Republican, that welcomes these vile bigots into their mist, defends them or amplifies their voices.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/72/1a/8692c1f34ea2a1f55f13a712199f/main-beefman-younggopgala-secondary7.jpg" alt="A band plays inside Cipriani Wall Street." data-portal-copyright="" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Paola Chapdelaine for Politico" data-title="A band plays inside Cipriani Wall Street."/><p>The club had a very different message about the attacks — one which was deleted from social media after POLITICO started asking questions about it.</p> 
<p>“The horrific terror attack in Australia last night is more evidence that Remigration is the only path forward for Western countries,” the club wrote in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019b-2023-d983-affb-e5fb6f8b0000" target="_blank">since-deleted</a> post. “America, Germany, Australia, and the rest of Europe must implement Remigration or more shootings like this will be inevitable.”</p> 
<p><i>Pauline von Pezold contributed to this report. </i></p> 
<p><i>A version of this article first appeared in POLITICO's New York Playbook. </i><a href="https://cms.politico.com/cms/content/edit.jsp?id=0000019b-2259-d5ec-abbb-fadfc88e0001&amp;typeId=a9d449a5-b61d-32fc-b70c-e15227dcdca7" target="_blank"><i>Subscribe here</i></a><i>. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-12-15T12:30:08-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democrats mourn killing of Hollywood star and activist Rob Reiner</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/democrats-rob-reiner-react-00690528</link>
      <description>The director often donated to and advocated for progressive causes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-2256-d983-affb-e7df999d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 10:24:01 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/44/96/79fc545b40948d85994f1cece7fc/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2206443831">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Matt Winkelmeyer/Getty Images for Human Rights Campaign</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rob Reiner (left) was a strong supporter of LGTBQ+ rights and early childhood education. His wife, Michelle Singer Reiner, was a photographer and producer.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/44/96/79fc545b40948d85994f1cece7fc/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2206443831" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are mourning the death of actor and director Rob Reiner and his wife Michele Singer Reiner after they were found dead in their California home on Sunday. The Hollywood star was known not only for classic films like “The Princess Bride” and “When Harry Met Sally,” but for his outspoken support of progressive causes.</p> 
<p>Former President Barack Obama said he and Michelle Obama were “heartbroken” by the news. Former Vice President Kamala Harris said Reiner “fought for America’s democracy.” And former Speaker Nancy Pelosi (D-Calif.) called him “remarkable and excellent” in everything he pursued.</p> 
<p>“Rob’s achievements in film and television gave us some of our most cherished stories on screen,” <a href="https://x.com/barackobama/status/2000442913885712602?s=46" target="_blank">Obama said in a statement</a>. “But beneath all of the stories he produced was a deep belief in the goodness of people — and a lifelong commitment to putting that belief into action. Together, he and his wife lived lives defined by purpose. They will be remembered for the values they championed and the countless people they inspired.”</p> 
<p>Reiner and Singer Reiner’s bodies were discovered in their Los Angeles home on Sunday after the Los Angeles Fire Department responded to a medical aid request shortly after 3:30 p.m., <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/14/2-people-found-dead-in-home-owned-by-rob-reiner-ap-source-says-00690378" target="_blank">according to The Associated Press</a>.</p> 
<p>Authorities are investigating their deaths as an “apparent homicide,” said Capt. Mike Bland of the Los Angeles Police Department. Authorities announced on Monday that Reiner's son, Nick Reiner, is in custody as a suspect in the case. He has been booked for murder and is being held on $4 million bail.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Sen. Chuck Schumer <a href="https://x.com/SenSchumer/status/2000564623326495130?s=20" target="_blank">called the news</a> of the Reiners’ death “horrific.”</p> 
<p>“Not only was Rob an incredibly talented actor &amp; director, he was also a relentless defender of democracy and the values so many of us share,” Schumer said. “He will be missed dearly. My prayers this morning are with the Reiner family and all those who loved his movies and what he and Michele stood for.”</p> 
<p>In her own statement, <a href="https://x.com/speakerpelosi/status/2000423280579064242?s=46" target="_blank">Pelosi reflected on Reiner’s contributions</a> to Democratic causes.</p> 
<p>“Personally, Rob cared deeply about people and demonstrated that in his civic activities — whether by supporting the First 5 initiative or fighting against Prop 8 in California,” said Pelosi, referring to the California Children and Families Commission, which supports programs for children under 5 years old. Proposition 8 was California’s 2008 ballot proposal to ban same-sex marriage.</p> 
<p>Pelosi continued, “Civically, he was a champion for the First Amendment and the creative rights of artists. And professionally, he was an iconic figure in film who made us laugh, cry and think with the movies he created.”</p> 
<p>The son of legendary comedian Carl Reiner, Rob Reiner was a strong supporter of LGTBQ+ rights and early childhood education. Reiner often held fundraisers and campaigned for Democratic issues. In 2008, he co-founded the American Foundation for Equal Rights, which challenged California’s ban on same-sex marriage. In 1998, as chair of the campaign for the state’s Proposition 10, which led to the creation of the First 5 initiative, Reiner advocated for funding early childhood development services with a tax on tobacco products.</p> 
<p>He was also a sharp critic of President Donald Trump, previously <a href="https://thehill.com/blogs/in-the-know/in-the-know/422509-rob-reiner-calls-trump-mentally-unstable-he-is-aiding-and/" target="_blank">accusing the president</a> of “treason” and being “<a href="https://variety.com/video/rob-reiner-trump-mentally-unfit/" target="_blank">mentally unfit</a>” to serve in office. In an October interview with MSNBC, now MS NOW, Reiner compared the current political climate under the Trump administration as “beyond McCarthy era-esque.”</p> 
<p>“Make no mistake: We have a year before this country becomes a full-on autocracy and democracy completely leaves us," <a href="https://www.ms.now/top-stories/latest/trump-rob-reiner-jessica-chastain-delay-savant-apple-rcna235963" target="_blank">Reiner said</a> at the time. “I believe the way to stop it is to educate people who may not understand what democracy is. They may not know what the impact of losing it is. We have to explain it, us storytellers have to explain to them what they’re going to wind up with if an autocrat has his way."</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/kamalaharris/status/2000442127856103609?s=46" target="_blank">Harris on Monday said</a> she was “devastated” to hear of Reiner and his wife’s deaths.</p> 
<p>“Rob Reiner's work has impacted generations of Americans,” she said. “The characters, dialogue, and visuals he brought to life in film and television are woven throughout our culture. Rob loved our country, cared deeply about the future of our nation, and fought for America's democracy.”</p> 
<p>California Democratic Gov. Gavin Newsom praised Reiner — <a href="https://x.com/cagovernor/status/2000433680645537978?s=46" target="_blank">who he called a “big-hearted genius”</a> — for his empathy.</p> 
<p>“His boundless empathy made his stories timeless, teaching generations how to see goodness and righteousness in others — and encouraging us to dream bigger,” said Newsom in a statement. “That empathy extended well beyond his films. Rob was a passionate advocate for children and for civil rights — from taking on Big Tobacco, fighting for marriage equality, to serving as a powerful voice in early education. He made California a better place through his good works.”</p> 
<p>Newsom added that Reiner will be remembered for his “extraordinary contribution to humanity.”</p> 
<p>Los Angeles Mayor Karen Bass called the Reiners’ deaths a “devastating loss” for both the city and the nation.</p> 
<p>“Rob Reiner’s contributions reverberate throughout American culture and society, and he has improved countless lives through his creative work and advocacy fighting for social and economic justice,” <a href="https://x.com/mayorofla/status/2000427445061669125?s=46" target="_blank">Bass said in a post on X</a>.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maryland residents bristle at Wes Moore’s redistricting push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/15/maryland-residents-bristle-at-wes-moores-redistricting-push-00690336</link>
      <description>A recent survey found fewer than one-third of state residents view the push as a leading priority.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1f87-da65-a1bf-ffffacee0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fb/c9/98bd99384b10b898f56b602052d7/maryland-virginia-govs-77907.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Rod Lamkey Jr./AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Maryland Gov. Wes Moore has for months been urging state lawmakers to consider redrawing the state's Congressional maps. He's seen above speaking during a Sept. 18 panel discussion in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fb/c9/98bd99384b10b898f56b602052d7/maryland-virginia-govs-77907.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As President Donald Trump’s mid-decade gerrymandering push in Republican states <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/indiana-republicans-redistricting-vote-trump-00687714?nid=0000018f-3124-de07-a98f-3be4d1400000&amp;nname=politico-toplines&amp;nrid=b833d9b4-a3a9-4256-ac94-718892881680" target="_blank"><u>hit a roadblock in Indiana</u></a> last week, Democrats looking to make up ground in blue states got some unwelcome news: Fewer than one-third of Maryland residents view redrawing the state’s congressional lines as a “high” priority, per a survey out Monday.</p> 
<p>Just 27 percent polled by the University of Maryland, Baltimore County, labeled redistricting a top issue, trailing far behind the cost of health care (77 percent), the quality of K-12 education (75 percent) and reducing crime (73 percent).</p> 
<p>The survey comes as lawmakers in the Old Line State grapple over whether to push forward an effort to redraw congressional lines to give Democrats a chance to flip the state’s lone Republican-held seat. Maryland lawmakers are slated to convene for a special legislative session on Tuesday, though they made clear <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/maryland-redistricting-state-legislature-00687992" target="_blank"><u>redistricting will not be on the agenda</u></a>.</p> 
<p>A similar push Trump championed in Indiana would have eliminated up to two Democratic-held seats; it was soundly rejected by that state’s Republican-led state Senate last week in a sharp rebuke of the president by members of his own party. Their opposition also relieved pressure mounting in some blue states, including Maryland, for state lawmakers to forge ahead with their gerrymandering counteroffensive.</p> 
<p>For several months, Maryland Gov. Wes Moore, a likely 2028 Democratic presidential hopeful, has been urging lawmakers to consider redesigning the state’s maps, but<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/bill-ferguson-wes-moore-00664770" target="_blank"><u> has been stymied by state Senate President Bill Ferguson</u></a>, a fellow Democrat who thinks the move could jeopardize the strength of Maryland Democrats’ congressional dominance. Democrats control seven of the state’s eight congressional seats.</p> 
<p>“This is not a huge priority for Maryland voters,” Mileah Kromer, the director of the university's Institute of Politics, which conducted the survey, said. “Perhaps one of the reasons it hasn't really caught on as a major priority is because over the last year, Maryland voters continue to express concerns about the economic situation in the state.”</p> 
<p>Earlier this year, state lawmakers passed measures raising taxes and fees by $1.6 billion — and are bracing for lingering negative repercussions from the longest federal government shutdown in U.S. history.</p> 
<p>The survey of 801 Maryland adults, the majority of whom were registered voters, found 28 percent of respondents said the Maryland congressional lines were drawn fairly, compared to 41 percent who said they were drawn unfairly. Twenty-nine percent did not have an opinion.</p> 
<p>When broken down by party affiliation, responses show variance in opinion over how Maryland’s maps are currently drawn and whether mid-decade redistricting should be taken up by the state legislature ahead of the 2026 midterms, with control of Congress at stake.</p> 
<p>Among Democrats, 37 percent said the state’s congressional maps are drawn fairly. And among the majority who believe otherwise, 18 percent said the lines favor Democrats and 10 percent said they favor Republicans.</p> 
<p>Just 17 percent of Republicans surveyed said Maryland’s congressional lines are drawn fairly. Among those who view the state’s maps as unfair, 63 percent said the lines favor Democrats, while just 3 percent contend they favor Republicans.</p> 
<p>While high numbers of both parties said they were paying at least some attention to the redistricting debate — 61 percent of Democrats; 71 percent of Republicans — their views of what to do about it also broke along party lines.</p> 
<p>Maryland Democrats’ views of mid-cycle redistricting showed that nearly an equal percentage said they don’t like it and it should not be done — 25 percent — compared to 28 percent who said they don’t like it but believe it is necessary. Just 6 percent of Democrats support it but think it’s the wrong thing to do, compared to 32 percent who said they like it and mid-decade redistricting should be done.</p> 
<p>Among Republicans, 67 percent said they don’t like it and mid-decade redistricting should not be done compared to 9 percent who consider it necessary. Fewer than 10 percent of Maryland Republicans said they like it, but it’s the wrong thing to do or that they like it and lawmakers should move forward with it.</p> 
<p>The poll was funded by the College of Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences at the university. It was conducted between Dec. 2 and 6 and has a 3.5 percent margin of error.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats gather in California feeling sunny once again</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/13/dnc-democratic-national-committee-hope-00689938</link>
      <description>At the Democratic National Committee’s winter meetings in L.A., party leaders are feeling good for the first time in a year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-1508-da65-a1bf-f7f9c4be0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 09:03:07 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b7/7e/276911e9442f8af04cb82ded6168/election-2025-redistricting-california-15534.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ethan Swope/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Gov. Gavin Newsom speaks during a campaign event on Proposition 50, Saturday, Nov. 1, 2025, in Los Angeles.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b7/7e/276911e9442f8af04cb82ded6168/election-2025-redistricting-california-15534.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider, Melanie Mason and Liam Dillon</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider, Melanie Mason and Liam Dillon</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As Democratic Party leaders gathered in Los Angeles for their annual winter meetings this week, for the first time in a long time the mood was warm.</p> 
<p>Optimism coursed through the hotel ballrooms, following a string of double-digit wins in off-year elections last month. Democratic National Committee members <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/newsoms-troll-energy-takes-over-the-dnc-00688472" target="_blank"><u>flocked to California Gov. Gavin Newsom — a likely presidential contender — for selfies</u></a> and major donors are resurfacing after a period of hibernation. Conan O’Brien, Jane Fonda and Shonda Rhimes joined Illinois Governor JB Pritzker for a major donor gathering, according to an invitation obtained by POLITICO. And Nebraska and Utah officials are among those expressing interest in hosting the party's novel midterm mini-convention next year, according to three people briefed on the conversations.</p> 
<p>“The party, broadly, is just feeling like they got their sea legs back,” Newsom told reporters in Los Angeles. “And they’re winning and winning solves a lot of problems.”</p> 
<p>DNC Chair Ken Martin nodded to the vibe shift in his own remarks Friday: "I can tell you, it's a much different feel in this room than a few months ago,” he said.</p> 
<p>But for all the energy at the DNC’s winter meeting, Democrats are still confronting challenges. The committee’s finances are shaky at best, badly trailing their Republican counterparts. The committee has yet to release its 2024 autopsy in full, as Democrats continue to argue over why the party lost so resoundingly last year. A proxy battle looms over the presidential primary calendar, as several states continue to lobby DNC members on the sidelines of this week’s meetings.</p> 
<p>Former Vice President Kamala Harris was warmly received when she addressed the convention Friday night, but her return to the national stage, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/19/kamala-harris-new-book-befuddles-dems-00574304" target="_blank"><u>fresh off a controversial book release</u></a>, is also a reminder of the party’s fractured response to its sweeping losses in 2024, when Donald Trump defeated her in every swing state on his way to becoming president.</p> 
<p>On Friday, Harris <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/kamala-harris-dnc-american-dream-00689951?utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank">gave DNC members a reality check</a> by delivering her most expansive diagnosis yet of what she sees as the country's broken political system. “We must be honest that for so many, the American dream has become more of a myth than reality,” she said.</p> 
<p>Most pressingly, the DNC faces serious financial problems. In October, it <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/20/dnc-loan-elections-fundraising-00663982" target="_blank"><u>took out a $15 million loan</u></a>, framed by the party as a financing investment into the New Jersey and Virginia elections that Democrats ended up dominating. While not unprecedented, it was a larger sum of money earlier in the cycle than is typical. The committee's loan also brings the Republicans' cash advantage into sharp relief — the Republican National Committee has $88 million more in the bank when accounting for the debt, according to November’s Federal Elections Commission filings.</p> 
<p>And some party members still want answers from the committee’s self-diagnosis for what went wrong in 2024.</p> 
<p>The DNC still hasn’t released its long promised post-election report, after earlier saying it wouldn’t come before last November’s elections. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/dnc-briefs-top-democrats-on-audit-of-2024-white-house-loss-00597998" target="_blank"><u>They have so far only shared initial findings with top Democrats at the committee’s national finance meeting</u></a> in October. The preliminary findings, which a DNC aide insisted at the time were incomplete, criticized Democrats for not investing resources early enough, while ignoring discussion of former President Joe Biden’s age. But some DNC members are looking for more answers.</p> 
<p>“It’s very hard for an organization to self criticize, so you need to keep the pressure up to make them do it,” said Eric Croft, the chair of the Alaska Democratic Party. “They said they’d do it. We’re going to make sure that they do.”</p> 
<p>But things of late are looking much rosier. Democrats are cheered by their double-digit victories in New Jersey and Virginia governor’s races last month, as well as a slew of other off-year and special elections in which their candidates outperformed their 2024 margins. They <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/06/mississippi-democrats-appear-to-break-republican-supermajority-in-state-senate-00639455" target="_blank">even denied the GOP</a> its supermajority in the Mississippi state senate. Public polling suggests the wind is at their backs in the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>DNC members estimated the electoral momentum will help with fundraising.</p> 
<p>“People are ready to open their wallets up now that they’ve realized what they’ve voted for,” said Manny Crespin, Jr., a committee member from New Mexico. “Now that they’ve realized it’s actually affecting their pocketbook, they’re going to do everything they can to reverse that.”</p> 
<p>One of the biggest decisions ahead for the DNC will play out in a little-known yet powerful panel, the Rules and Bylaws Committee, which is charged with setting the 2028 presidential primary calendar. States <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/27/democrats-move-forward-2028-calendar-00623836" target="_blank"><u>have until Jan. 16</u></a> to apply to be in the early window, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/25/dnc-2028-primary-states-iowa-new-hampshire-00521488" target="_blank"><u>the behind-the-scenes jockeying for a spot</u></a> has continued, several DNC members said privately.</p> 
<p>“All of the early states are trying to lay their groundwork to get the committee to back them,” said a Democratic operative who attended the DNC meeting. “There’s a bit of a proxy war brewing on this.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indiana GOP’s Trump rebuke could lead to temporary redistricting detente</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/redistricting-indiana-illinois-virginia-florida-maryland-00689748</link>
      <description>It doesn’t mean the redistricting wars are over.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-145f-d5ec-abbb-dcdfebf90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 17:24:12 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/06/9d/858dc0e245a9a374eb1c479cd397/redistricting-indiana-35136.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Michael Conroy/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Annette Groos holds a sign before the start of a rally at the Statehouse in Indianapolis on Sept. 18, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/06/9d/858dc0e245a9a374eb1c479cd397/redistricting-indiana-35136.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Indiana Republicans’ redistricting rejection marks a rare ceasefire in the gerrymandering wars — and could lead to other state leaders backing off their own plans.</p> 
<p>The result gives cover for some Democratic-leaning states to stand down, even as the party’s base is frenzied over the issue. Lawmakers in Illinois and Maryland have for months had internal debates about whether to move forward with redrawing their maps. Indiana’s outcome relieved some of the mounting pressure they anticipated facing had Republicans in Indiana further gerrymandered their maps.</p> 
<p>Illinois Democrats have long said they would only gerrymander if the Indiana GOP bowed to Trump’s demands and redid their own map. In the wake of Hoosier Republicans’ move Thursday, their Democratic neighbors don’t seem eager to change their minds.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile in Maryland, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/bill-ferguson-wes-moore-00664770" target="_blank">one Democratic leader</a> is rebuffing entreaties from top Democrats to eliminate the state’s lone remaining GOP seat.</p> 
<p>Maryland Democratic Senate President Bill Ferguson has exchanged phone calls with Indiana Senate Republican leader Rodric Bray, four people familiar with the two leaders, granted anonymity because they weren't authorized to speak publicly, told POLITICO. Each resisted pressure from top officials in their party to move on redistricting. Bray’s success could now lessen the pressure on Ferguson. Bray's spokesperson, Molly Swigart, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/maryland-redistricting-state-legislature-00687992" target="_blank">said no deal was ever made</a> between Bray and Ferguson on redistricting in their respective states.</p> 
<p>Officials in Virginia, where Democrats gained 13 seats in their House of Delegates in November’s statewide elections, are poised to make drastic changes to their congressional maps that could net the party upwards of four seats. But Democratic Gov.-elect Abigail Spanberger <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/spanberger-redistricting-00683066" target="_blank">sounded reluctant to the idea</a> of making wholesale changes to congressional lines at a POLITICO event earlier this week.</p> 
<p>There are headwinds elsewhere for Trump and his allies. In <a href="https://www.kcur.org/politics-elections-and-government/2025-11-05/kansas-republicans-fail-to-get-support-for-redistricting-but-their-plan-isnt-dead-yet" target="_blank">Kansas</a> and Kentucky Republicans have so far failed to move forward with their redistricting pushes that are complicated by opposition from Democratic governors. Ohio Republicans struck a compromise with Democrats for a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/31/ohio-redistricting-gerrymander-new-map-00631254" target="_blank">less aggressive gerrymander</a> than what some national leaders wanted. And a judge picked a map in Utah that drew <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/29/democrats-seize-on-utah-in-redistricting-war-00535242" target="_blank">a safe Democratic seat</a>; and Republicans are facing <a href="https://apnews.com/article/missouri-redistricting-referendum-trump-gerrymandering-utah-14312a112b6e32d15e5ef36b83cdc6a7" target="_blank">a potential setback for Missouri</a>.</p> 
<p>That doesn’t mean the redistricting wars are over. Lawmakers in a number of other states are still weighing their own maps, with GOP-led Florida and Democratic-controlled Virginia remaining the biggest question marks on the board. Republicans are still eyeing Kentucky and Nebraska as well.</p> 
<p>“We’ve got a lot more states that we can do work on,” one person close to the White House, granted anonymity to speak candidly on a sensitive matter, told POLITICO on Friday, while admitting that “Indiana was definitely frustrating.”</p> 
<p>And if the U.S. Supreme Court issues a ruling <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/15/supreme-court-voting-rights-act-argument-00608340" target="_blank">further gutting the Voting Rights Act</a> in the coming months, a number of states are expected to rush to redraw their lines before their states’ filing deadlines, in a move that could give the GOP a huge boost and potentially put the House out of reach for Democrats.</p> 
<p>“The truth is, I think we're still, we're in the middle of this redistricting war,” said John Bisognano, president of the National Democratic Redistricting Committee. “We're all waiting to hear back from the Supreme Court as to what they're going to do and how they're going to move forward.”</p> 
<p>Here’s what to expect in the coming weeks from states including Maryland, Florida, Illinois and a challenge to the already-passed maps passed in Missouri.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Maryland</h5> 
<p>Perhaps lawmakers breathing the biggest sigh of relief from Indiana bucking Trump’s redistricting push are those in Maryland.</p> 
<p>Ferguson has for months been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/02/bill-ferguson-wes-moore-00664770" target="_blank">facing pressure from Democratic Maryland Gov. Wes Moore and national Democrats</a> to wade into the redistricting fight. That lobbying campaign to net Maryland Democrats an additional seat would have been kicked into hyperdrive if Indiana had drawn new maps.</p> 
<p>Reports of Ferguson <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/2025/11/21/bill-ferguson-will-diminish-his-power-by-opposing-redistricting-analysts-say/" target="_blank">possibly losing his grip on leading the Senate Democrats</a> evaporated this week after he was <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/2025/12/10/bill-ferguson-renominated-legislative-session/?fbclid=IwY2xjawOpOLBleHRuA2FlbQIxMABicmlkETFpNWo2dzNsRFZvdHByOHZrc3J0YwZhcHBfaWQQMjIyMDM5MTc4ODIwMDg5MgABHsvb6X9YnayF_uyDbyjoRCJBqoW_IJKgjHv21HFlMyqvJv9EhuGdfgoGjihO_aem_8OB90-oRdUVSdT3KZ-WpJQ" target="_blank">unanimously renominated as Senate leader</a>. Then on Thursday, just hours before the Indiana Senate cast the vote dooming the redistricting effort, Ferguson put out a statement with Democratic House Delegates Speaker Pro Tem Dana Stein declaring that lawmakers in the special session Moore called for next week <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/11/maryland-redistricting-state-legislature-00687992" target="_blank">will definitively not take up any new maps</a>.</p> 
<p>While that likely closes the door on the redistricting push for this year, Moore still has an opportunity to reignite a pressure campaign aimed at Ferguson to hold a vote on the issue in January, when the legislature returns for regular session. The governor’s <a href="https://redistricting.maryland.gov/Pages/default.aspx" target="_blank">Redistricting Advisory Commission</a> is meeting Friday for its final public hearing to solicit comments from Maryland residents before its members make a recommendation to the governor and the General Assembly on whether to redraw maps.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Illinois</h5> 
<p>For months, Illinois Democrats have suggested they were unlikely to try to squeeze another seat out of their already-gerrymandered state unless Indiana Republicans redrew their seats.</p> 
<p>And while state Democratic leaders didn’t completely rule out redistricting in the wake of the Indiana GOP’s vote, they don’t sound particularly eager for a new map.</p> 
<p>“Our neighbors in Indiana have stood up to Trump’s threats and political pressure, instead choosing to do what’s right for their constituents and our democracy,” Gov. JB Pritzker said in a statement after the result, without saying what Illinois might do.</p> 
<p>A person in Pritzker’s office, granted anonymity because they weren’t authorized to speak publicly, said the governor was less than equivocal in his statement because no one knows what Trump's next move might be.</p> 
<p>State House and Senate Democratic leaders struck similar tones, praising their Hoosier neighbors while pledging to stay vigilant against similar efforts in other states.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Virginia</h5> 
<p>Democrats’ best remaining chance for a multi-seat gerrymander is Old Dominion. But while statehouse leaders seem eager to push forward with a complicated plan for a voter referendum to approve a new gerrymander — much like California’s move — the state’s incoming Democratic governor doesn’t seem quite as eager to lend a hand.</p> 
<p>The Democratic-dominated Virginia legislature is expected to easily pass a procedural measure before putting the issue of redistricting before voters to approve a constitutional Virginia amendment to redraw the state’s maps ahead of the midterms — a move that legislative leaders have teased could lead to a 10-1 map.</p> 
<p>“I feel comfortable that we have an opportunity to do a number of maps here in Virginia to allow for us to level the playing field,” Virginia House Speaker Don Scott <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/virginia-house-speaker-optimism-supreme-court-00684139" target="_blank">said at a POLITICO event this week</a>.</p> 
<p>But at the same event, Spanberger hedged when asked if she supported redrawing maps to achieve the feat.</p> 
<p>“The calendar is tight, and for me, I want to win,” Spanberger said, pointing to Virginia’s first and second congressional districts that are currently held by Republicans. “I want to flip seats in the House of Representatives, and I know that we can because I just won those districts.”</p> 
<p>But when asked directly if redistricting is the way to go, Spanberger said that Virginia should “leave open the option” of new maps but that ultimately voters will decide if the legislature should move forward.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Florida</h5> 
<p>Florida Republicans could deliver their party three to five more seats if they press ahead with mid-decade redistricting. But two factors complicate that effort.</p> 
<p>First, GOP leaders aren’t on the same page. GOP Gov. Ron DeSantis has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/24/desantis-floats-mid-decade-redistricting-for-florida-congressional-seats-00474675" target="_blank">been touting the need to draw new maps since last summer</a>, has suggested waiting until the spring of next year in case the U.S. Supreme Court weakens the Voting Rights Act and bars the consideration of race when drawing lines, a position backed by the state’s GOP Senate president, Ben Albritton.</p> 
<p>But state GOP House Speaker Daniel Perez said this week it is “irresponsible” to wait and that the House is prepared to send a map to the Senate during its regular session that starts next month.</p> 
<p>Second, GOP leaders may be constrained by Florida’s voter-approved constitutional ban on redistricting for partisan gain. Democrats have already asserted that drawing up any new map is “illegal’ and would violate these standards signaling that litigation is likely if state legislators pass a new map. But Florida's conservative-dominated state Supreme Court already ruled in 2022 that legislators can sidestep minority protections when it allowed a previous GOP-drawn map that was muscled into law by DeSantis, weakening its impact. </p> 
<p>Perez <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/florida-gop-house-speaker-insists-white-house-is-not-pushing-redistricting-00684542" target="_blank">insisted that he has not been under pressure from Trump or the White House to move ahead</a> on redistricting. When asked Friday if there was added pressure on the House to act due to the outcome in Indiana he said: “No sir.”</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Missouri</h5> 
<p>Missouri Republicans already passed a map to flip Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51324" data-person-id="51324">Emanuel Cleaver</a>’s (D-Mo.) district red, but Democrats are hoping to undo the GOP-passed map in Missouri via ballot measure. Earlier this week, they <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/missouri-gerrymandering-midterm-elections-00683693?nid=0000014f-1646-d88f-a1cf-5f46b7bd0000&amp;nname=playbook&amp;nrid=e43f4a81-fe4f-4770-8d77-d9774bf5ba97" target="_blank">submitted more than double</a> the 107,000 signatures required to force a statewide vote for the secretary of state.</p> 
<p>If the signatures are validated, the map may not cannot go into effect in time for the midterms, and if voters approve the ballot measure, the map gets tossed. Republicans still have a bit of time, since GOP Secretary of State Denny Hoskins doesn’t have to approve the signatures until July. Plus, it’s unclear when the Republican-controlled Legislature will actually put those signatures up for a vote.</p> 
<p>The timing is causing a bit of chaos. Since candidates need to file by the end of March, prospective members of Congress may have to file in districts that aren’t set for the midterms.</p> 
<p><i>Adam Wren, Andrew Howard, Shia Kapos, Alex Gangitano and Gary Fineout contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
