<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/politics-news.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:31:20 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Donald Trump’s unprecedented political war chest got even bigger in 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/donald-trump-fundraising-midterms-00759005</link>
      <description>Campaign finance disclosures filed late Saturday revealed details of the president’s unmatched political fundraising operation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1796-df17-afbf-7fb7cbb20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 00:31:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b1/b3/56f121c8465b8717682ed2a2177a/trump-19434.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump gestures after stepping off Air Force One, Saturday, Jan. 31, 2026, at Palm Beach International Airport in West Palm Beach, Fla.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b1/b3/56f121c8465b8717682ed2a2177a/trump-19434.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump’s political war chest grew dramatically in the second half of 2025, according to new campaign finance disclosures submitted late Saturday, giving him an unprecedented amount of money for a term-limited president to influence the midterms and beyond.</p> 
<p>Trump raised $26 million through his joint fundraising committee in the back half of last year, and another $8 million directly into his leadership PAC. And a super PAC linked to him has more than $300 million in the bank.</p> 
<p>All together, a web of campaign accounts, some of which he controls directly and others under the care of close allies, within the president’s orbit have $375 million in their coffers.</p> 
<p>The funds far outstrip those of any other political figure — Republican or Democrat — entering 2026, and have no real historical precedent. And Trump could put them to use this year for the midterms, or to shape future elections, even as he cannot run for president again.</p> 
<p>Trump continues to outpace any other Republican in raising money, both from large and small-dollar donors. His joint fundraising committee — Trump National Committee, which pools fundraising for a variety of Trump-aligned groups — accounted for 1 in 8 dollars raised on WinRed, the primary Republican online fundraising platform, during the second half of 2025, according to a POLITICO analysis.</p> 
<p>And no super PAC raised even half as much in 2025 as the $289 million from MAGA Inc., the Trump-aligned super PAC that both the president and Vice President J.D. Vance appeared at fundraisers for last year.</p> 
<p>Trump has given few clues as to how he might put the funds to use. Trump National Committee primarily sends funds to the president’s leadership PAC, Never Surrender, with a bit of money also going to the Republican National Committee and Vance’s leadership PAC, Working For Ohio.</p> 
<p>Candidates cannot use leadership PAC money for their own election efforts. But the accounts — which are common across Washington and have long been derided by anti-money in politics groups as “slush funds” — allow politicians to dole out money to allies or fund political travel.</p> 
<p>Never Surrender spent $6.7 million from July through December, with more than half of that total going toward advertising, digital consulting and direct mail — expenses typically linked to fundraising.</p> 
<p>So far, Trump’s groups have held their powder in Republican primaries. While Trump has endorsed against a handful of Republican incumbents now locked in competitive primaries — including Sen. Bill Cassidy of Louisiana and Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky — and threatened others, he hasn’t used money. A super PAC targeting Massie, MAGA KY, is run by Trump allies but has largely been funded by GOP megadonor Paul Singer.</p> 
<p>MAGA Inc.’s only election-related spending last year was to boost now-Rep. Matt Van Epps in the special election in Tennessee’s 7th District.</p> 
<p>Trump’s massive war chest makes him a political force, independent of the traditional party infrastructure. The RNC — which derives a significant portion of its fundraising from Trump — had $95 million in the bank at the end of the year, roughly a quarter of what the Trump-linked groups have.</p> 
<p>And their rivals at the Democratic National Committee are far worse off — at just over $14 million, while owing more than $17 million in debt.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Houston Democrat wins former Rep. Sylvester Turner’s seat ahead of contested primary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/texas-18-district-run-off-00758972</link>
      <description>Christian Menefee's victory will set up another generational battle for Democrats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1615-df17-afbf-7f37bfe60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 23:11:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/81/83/42f938b64a91b6d78eb446e50546/election-2026-texas-congress-69740.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Karen Warren/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>Democrat Christian Menefee speaks to supporters during his watch party at The Post Houston on Election Day, in Houston, Saturday, Jan. 31, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/81/83/42f938b64a91b6d78eb446e50546/election-2026-texas-congress-69740.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Harris County Attorney Christian Menefee, a Democrat, won a special runoff election on Saturday to serve the remainder of former Texas Rep. Sylvester’s term, who died last year.</p> 
<p>The Associated Press projected that Menefee beat Amanda Edwards, an attorney and former member of the Houston City council, after a protracted process to fill the central Houston seat after Turner's death in March 2025. The process was drawn out by GOP Gov. Greg Abbott’s refusal to quickly schedule a special election following Turner’s death and a crowded field that triggered a runoff following the first round of voting in November.</p> 
<p>But the contest between the pair will continue: Both Menefee, 37, and Edwards, 44, are participating in the March primary for a newly refashioned 18th Congressional District, going up against Rep. Al Green, 78. That winner will be heavily favored to win a full two-year term in November.</p> 
<p>The March primary is the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/texas-18-runoff-dems-00758614" target="_blank"><u>latest example</u></a> of the generational change debate animating the Democratic Party, as the two young Democrats take on progressive icon Green, who has been in Congress for more than two decades. It's a fight that’s taking place nationwide, pitting young and old factions of the party against each other as they both argue they’re better fighters against Republicans.</p> 
<p>Residents in this district have been without consistent representation since former Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee died in 2024. Lee held the seat for three decades.</p> 
<p>Green’s current district was scrambled by the Texas GOP’s redistricting, prompting him to jump into the race to represent a new district that contains many of his constituents.</p> 
<p>Menefee’s victory is a huge boost to his public profile ahead of the primary. Early voting begins in two weeks.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elon Musk pours millions more into helping Republicans keep Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/elon-musk-2026-election-donations-00758992</link>
      <description>The tech billionaire, who once said he had “done enough” political spending, remains a significant benefactor for the Republican Party after patching things up with President Donald Trump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-16be-dbc5-a7bd-1fbe62810001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 20:25:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/1d/af/cf03bb784de5837de753bb120c75/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2216318870">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Elon Musk listens in the Oval Office at the White House on May 21, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/1d/af/cf03bb784de5837de753bb120c75/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2216318870" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tech mogul Elon Musk poured $10 million into two major Republican super PACs at the end of last year, according to campaign finance disclosures submitted Saturday, as he once again <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/elon-musk-gop-comeback-00751572" target="_blank">takes a more active role</a> in GOP politics.</p> 
<p>The Tesla and SpaceX CEO, who had a public falling out with President Donald Trump last spring and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/20/elon-musk-political-spending-00358398" target="_blank">said he was giving up on political spending</a>, gave $5 million in December to each of the Congressional Leadership Fund and Senate Leadership Fund, two groups that aim to help the GOP keep control of Congress this year.</p> 
<p>It was Musk’s second round of donations to both groups this cycle, having <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/31/elon-musk-donations-clf-slf-00487699" target="_blank">previously given in June</a>, amid his feud with Trump. Those contributions came shortly before Musk floated starting his own political party, an initiative that never seemed to gain much headway.</p> 
<p>But Musk and Trump have patched up their differences more recently, with the tech CEO joining Trump for dinner at Mar-a-Lago earlier this month. Musk has also been back to advocating for Republican politics on X, which he owns, pushing for senators to pass a plussed up version of the SAVE Act, a bill that would require states to <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2025/04/14/the-house-passed-the-save-act-what-comes-next-00288458" target="_blank">collect proof of citizenship</a> from people registering to vote.</p> 
<p>Musk has thrown his support behind a version called the SAVE Act Plus, calling for ID requirements and a <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/2013271550636826797?s=20" target="_blank">ban of mail voting</a> for most Americans along with other changes to election administration.</p> 
<p>Musk was the biggest individual donor to political committees during the 2024 election cycle, spending roughly $290 million, mostly through his own super PAC, America PAC, in support of Trump.</p> 
<p>In the first few months of the Trump administration, he played an active role with the Department of Government Efficiency, but <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/03/elon-musk-trump-bill-00382653" target="_blank">began fighting with Trump</a> and Republicans around the president’s One Big Beautiful Bill Act. Musk also threw himself into a Wisconsin Supreme Court election in April where <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/02/elon-musk-wisconsin-loss-reaction-00006129" target="_blank">his preferred candidate lost by 10 points</a>.</p> 
<p>Musk’s funds accounted for just a fraction of total fundraising for both SLF and CLF. SLF raised nearly $77 million in the final six months of 2025 and had $100 million cash on hand, while CLF raised over $38 million over that period and had more than $54 million cash on hand.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-31T14:36:54-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>'There’s something bigger going on': State election chiefs rebuff Trump bid to seize voter rolls</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/democrats-election-trump-voter-rolls-00758940</link>
      <description>Roughly two dozen states have rejected the Trump administration’s request, prompting an unprecedented legal clash between the Justice Department and state election officials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-156e-d1ed-a59e-d77f3b410000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 14:30:18 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/54/7d/f9a2ad7e4cd5953a876add6bfd75/ap22146721014362.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Scott Sonner/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>People wait to vote in-person at Reed High School in Sparks, Nevada, prior to polls closing on Nov. 3, 2020.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/54/7d/f9a2ad7e4cd5953a876add6bfd75/ap22146721014362.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty and Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty and Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic state election officials say the Justice Department’s letter to Minnesota over its voter rolls represents a significant escalation, with several warning that the Trump administration could use immigration enforcement to exert influence over November’s midterm elections.</p> 
<p>The officials are baffled by the Trump administration’s continued demand for access to state voter information and refuse to comply, telling POLITICO they view the requests as part of a broader effort by the administration to insert itself into state election proceedings.</p> 
<p>Minnesota Secretary of State Steve Simon, a Democrat, has been at the center of the push after Attorney General Pam Bondi wrote in <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26508586-bondiwalzltr012426/?q=voter&amp;mode=document#document/p3" target="_blank">a letter</a> to Gov. Tim Walz that one condition of restoring “law and order” in the state amid the administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown would be for Minnesota to turn over its voter rolls to the federal government.</p> 
<p>Minnesota — one of two dozen states, along with the District of Columbia, sued by the administration — has rejected the request, prompting an unprecedented legal clash between the Justice Department and state election officials.</p> 
<p>“To me, [it] seems to be a project in service of the president's longstanding but false view that election systems around the country are rigging elections,” Simon told POLITICO. “And this project seems to be in service of that, and that's the best I can tell.”</p> 
<p>Simon said he has not heard back from the Trump administration since responding to the Bondi letter. “This was already a dispute, but it was a dispute being fought where it belongs, which is in a court of law,” he said.</p> 
<p>Arizona Secretary of State Adrian Fontes, a Democrat running for reelection this year, called the letter to officials in Minnesota “extortion” and echoed the suggestion that the effort was aimed at something beyond voter rolls.</p> 
<p>"The voter roll stuff is not about voter rolls. There’s something bigger going on,” Fontes said in an interview this week, as dozens of secretaries of state gathered in Washington for a meeting of the National Association of Secretaries of State. “They’re bits and pieces, interchangeable in this jigsaw puzzle, and we're being told something that's not true,” he added.</p> 
<p>The highly unusual push for access to states’ voter rolls is part of a yearlong campaign by the Trump administration, which says it is seeking to ensure that states’ voter registration practices comply with federal law and safeguard election integrity. The White House has requested voter records from nearly every state and Washington, D.C. The move comes as Trump frequently <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/trump-2020-election-prosecutions-00738778" target="_blank">repeats his false claim</a> that the 2020 presidential election was “rigged.”</p> 
<p>The White House said it was authorized to make the requests under longstanding laws such as the Civil Rights Act.</p> 
<p>“The Civil Rights Act, National Voting Rights Act, and Help America Vote Act all give the Department of Justice full authority to ensure states comply with federal election laws, which mandate accurate state voter rolls. President Trump is committed to ensuring that Americans have full confidence in the administration of elections, and that includes totally accurate and up-to-date voter rolls free of errors and unlawfully registered non-citizen voters,” said White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department did not immediately respond to POLITICO’s request for comment.</p> 
<p>At least 11 states have complied with the administration’s request, according to the <a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/research-reports/tracker-justice-department-requests-voter-information" target="_blank">Brennan Center</a>.</p> 
<p>Wyoming is one of the states that complied, and its secretary of state, Chuck Gray, a Republican, told reporters on Friday that it has been “very disturbing” to watch Democrats rebuff the administration’s request to engage in what he described as regular upkeep of voter rolls.</p> 
<p>“We've been engaging in routine voter list maintenance that people support in making sure the voter lists are clean,” he said.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department has sued the 24 states — most, but not all, of which are helmed by Democrats — that have refused to comply, with most citing concerns over exposing sensitive voter information.</p> 
<p>“I'm certainly concerned that people may fear that the Department of Justice having access to the voting rolls might make them a target in some way,” said Maine Democratic Secretary of State Shenna Bellows.</p> 
<p>“This Justice Department has weaponized its office to target people based on identity and based on political affiliation,” she said.</p> 
<p>Uzoma Nkwonta, a partner at Elias Law Group, which is representing voters and civic organizations in several states who are also trying to prevent the release of voter rolls, called the effort “another example of overreach by the Department of Justice and the federal government.” “The fact that DOJ officials have stated publicly that they expect to see hundreds of thousands individuals removed from the rolls once they have this data … should set off a red flag,” Nkwonta said, noting that maintaining voter registration lists is a responsibility for the states, not the federal government.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ICE halted its surge in Maine. The state might not be quick to forget.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/maine-senate-ice-campaign-00758811</link>
      <description>Sen. Susan Collins’ announcement of ICE’s drawdown relieved some of the pressure in the blue state. But Democrats still say it’s not enough.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-11e5-dbc5-a7bd-19fdd4120000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/32/15/736b70614c48b37da1cd891552cd/immigration-enforcement-maine-07716.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Robert F. Bukaty/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Attendees hold signs at a news conference held by public officials and faith leaders calling for the abolishment of the U.S. Immigrant and Customs Enforcement, Jan. 30, 2026, in Portland, Maine.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/32/15/736b70614c48b37da1cd891552cd/immigration-enforcement-maine-07716.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>BANGOR, Maine — The federal immigration crackdown in Maine may have ended, but the political fallout could continue to reverberate through the 2026 election.</p> 
<p>Democratic Gov. Janet Mills <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/janet-mills-tv-ad-ice-00756765" target="_blank">launched her first Senate campaign ad on Friday</a> — and it’s focused on attacking Immigration and Customs Enforcement. Political newcomer Graham Platner, competing with Mills for the Democratic nomination, held an anti-ICE protest at Sen. Susan Collins’ offices in Maine on Thursday, calling for her to block funds for the agency.</p> 
<p>The message from both Democrats was clear: Immigration enforcement politics is not going away, and they think it could be a winning issue as they look to unseat the only Republican senator up for reelection this year in a state former Vice President Kamala Harris won in 2024.</p> 
<p>But Collins’ Thursday announcement that ICE was ending its immigration enforcement campaign in Maine — dubbed Operation Catch of the Day by the Department of Homeland Security — released some of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/susan-collins-dhs-ice-shutdown-00751545?utm_content=topic/politics&amp;utm_source=flipboard" target="_blank">pressure that had been building</a> in the state for more than a week, with local leaders expressing an initial sense of relief.</p> 
<p>That campaign had left the state’s immigrant communities hiding in fear and Democrats and activists raging at their treatment. The surge disrupted life for many in southern Maine, with decreased attendance in schools, legal immigrants afraid to go to work and observers trailing ICE agents in the state.</p> 
<p>Now, in the aftermath of an operation that led to more than 200 arrests and prompted widespread protests, lawmakers and community leaders are navigating the upheaval left behind. The political impact continues to ripple.</p> 
<p>Collins' announcement Thursday morning, which implied her conversations with Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem had helped sway the decision, is emblematic of how she wants voters to think of her: a powerful pragmatist who can get results, including by standing up to her own party. And it was a high-profile reminder of her longstanding case that her senior role in Washington helps her deliver for the Pine Street State.</p> 
<p>Still, Democrats and activists, buoyed by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270" target="_blank">rapidly shifting public opinion around immigration enforcement</a> after videos of violent arrests and two fatal shootings in Minneapolis, are redoubling efforts for broader restrictions on ICE and its funding — along with a reckoning on what happened in Maine. Reports of the end of the operation in Maine, they said, are not enough.</p> 
<p>“Senator Collins is going to try to use this moment to trick us. To say that she, somehow, used her power to impose upon ICE,” Platner said in protests at the senator’s Portland and Bangor offices on Thursday, held hours after the end of the surge was announced.</p> 
<p>He mocked what he called a “pinky promise” she received from Noem to cheers from dozens of supporters who had gathered in Bangor in single-digit temperatures. “We all know it’s nonsense. What she is actually doing is trying to justify to us why she is about to try to give them 9 billion more dollars in funding."</p> 
<p>Platner demanded that Collins, the Senate’s top appropriator, cut off funding for ICE entirely, saying the Trump administration could not be trusted to follow the law.</p> 
<p>Collins advocated for passing a DHS funding bill that Democrats blocked this week, citing its funding for body cameras for federal officers as well as de-escalation training. Negotiations are likely to continue in Washington after lawmakers agreed to pass just a two-week stopgap. Failure to pass DHS funding would not stop ICE, as the agency is well-funded from Trump’s major budget bill last summer, but Democrats are hoping to leverage anger at the agency to pressure the GOP for reforms. A Collins spokesperson declined to comment for this story.</p> 
<p>The Maine senator’s positioning still held her somewhat as an outlier. Maine Republicans largely expressed support for federal immigration operations in the state while accusing Mills and Democrats of ginning up conflict with law enforcement. Local Republicans were largely quiet about Collins’ news of the drawdown.</p> 
<p>Mills, in an interview earlier in the week, derided Collins’ calls for retraining ICE officers, telling POLITICO that the “horse was out of the barn already.” On Thursday, she characterized the drawdown of ICE operations as insufficient, calling for Noem’s removal at DHS as well as congressional action to halt ICE funding until measures are in place at the agency to prevent what she characterized as “abuses of power.”</p> 
<p>“Until there are substantive measures and changes in place, no state — including Maine — is protected from the weaponization of Federal law enforcement agencies against its own citizens by the Trump Administration,” she said in a statement on Thursday.</p> 
<p>Mills and Maine Attorney General Aaron Frey, a Democrat, sent a letter to Noem and Acting ICE Director Todd Lyons on Friday demanding information about the immigrants arrested in the state and where they are now.</p> 
<p>Community leaders and lawmakers are also working to understand what the drawdown means in practice, what happened to those detained by ICE and how to begin restoring trust among immigrants who have barely left their homes in weeks.</p> 
<p>“It is welcome news. ICE operations in Maine have failed to improve public safety and have caused lasting damage to our communities,” said Carl Sheline, the mayor of Lewiston, which is home to a large Somali American population and was one of the Maine cities to see significant ICE activity. “We will continue working to ensure that those who were wrongfully detained by ICE are returned to us.”</p> 
<p>Maine House Speaker Ryan Fecteau, a Democrat from Biddeford, said among those detained by ICE was a man named Marcos, whom Fecteau had previously employed as a contractor working on his home. Fecteau said he talked on Thursday to the man’s wife, who said he was at an ICE facility in Arizona two days earlier, but the ICE database was no longer showing his whereabouts.</p> 
<p>“Over the last week and a half there have been people in Maine who have been arrested and detained unlawfully. We want answers for those people. Who they are, where they are, what was the reason for their detention. Those things need to be answered,” Fecteau said. “I hope that Senator Collins, who clearly has some influence here — she spoke with Kristi Noem yesterday — I hope that was part of the conversation as well.”</p> 
<p>In Augusta on Thursday, Maine lawmakers heard testimony over a bill that would require ICE to obtain judicial warrants to search private spaces of schools and health care facilities, among other locations.</p> 
<p>Mills on Thursday threw her weight behind the new bill, citing in part the destabilizing effects of the recent surge. It was a notable move for the former prosecutor, who faced heat from progressives and Platner for not taking a stronger stance last year when she allowed a bill limiting law enforcement cooperation with ICE to go into effect without her signature, rather than signing it outright.</p> 
<p>Activists and observers who had been trailing ICE in Maine noted some agents appeared to be off duty on Thursday, reflecting the drawdown.</p> 
<p>“It's good news. I hope it's true. I hope that we can all find peace and rest in the next coming days,” Eric Nathanson, an activist with Jewish Action Maine who was arrested alongside other faith leaders earlier in the week while protesting at Collins’ Portland office. “If the surge is on pause, we reiterate the goal of no additional funding even more strongly.”</p> 
<p>But the images and experiences from the past week were not easily forgotten.</p> 
<p>“Three people in the past week were abducted in front of my workplace. My coworkers had to watch an ICE agent beat and drag people out of cars,” Nathanson said. “We will stay strong and stay vigilant.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Houston runoff sets up next Democratic generational fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/texas-18-runoff-dems-00758614</link>
      <description>Saturday’s oddly timed runoff is occurring after months of delays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1127-df17-afbf-7d3785d00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 07:01:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a9/3d/516941bd4914876b52948dce09f3/election-2025-congress-texas-28887.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ashley Landis/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Democratic 18th Congressional District candidate Amanda Edwards arrives for an election night watch party on Nov. 4, 2025, in Houston.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a9/3d/516941bd4914876b52948dce09f3/election-2025-congress-texas-28887.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>HOUSTON — House Republicans’ slim majority will be even leaner after Saturday, when Democrats vote to fill the Texas seat left open when Rep. Sylvester Turner unexpectedly died last year.</p> 
<p>But the vote will just be the next step in choosing who ultimately represents Texas’ 18th Congressional District for a full two-year term — and sets up the next generational change debate that has roiled the party nationwide.</p> 
<p>Just five weeks after Saturday’s special election runoff, voters in this Democratic hub of Black political power will return to the polls for a March primary to pick someone to represent the district after the seat was redrawn as part of Texas’ redistricting.</p> 
<p>On Saturday, voters are choosing between Harris County attorney Christian Menefee, 37, or former Houston City Councilmember Amanda Edwards, 44, to fill the current seat. The pair emerged as the top two vote-getters in a crowded 16-person primary in November, with Menefee finishing ahead of Edwards by 3 percentage points.</p> 
<p>The winner will then hold the incumbency for just a few weeks before challenging activist icon Rep. Al Green, 78. That March election, all three candidates argue, is about choosing the best fighter to stand up to House Republicans, the Trump administration and the Texas GOP, which has been encroaching on Houston’s autonomy in recent years as Republicans try to weaken Democrats’ influence in the one of the nation’s largest cities.</p> 
<p>“It’s going to be a fight between generations,” said Marc Campos, a longtime Democratic consultant in Houston, who is unaffiliated with any campaign.</p> 
<p>Saturday’s oddly timed runoff is occurring after months of delays by Gov. Greg Abbott, who didn’t call for the special election to fill the seat until eight months after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/03/05/texas-democrat-sylvester-turner-dies-00213068" target="_blank">Turner's death</a>. Turner, in 2022, revealed he had been recovering from bone cancer and his family said he died from “enduring health complications.” He had been elected to replace former Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/07/20/texas-rep-sheila-jackson-lee-dies-at-age-74-00169909" target="_blank">died in office</a> in 2024 after being diagnosed with pancreatic cancer. She served the district for nearly three decades.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/9f/7f/011bbdc14490b3132df6ffc7fe1d/election-2025-congress-texas-71344.jpg" alt="Democratic 18th Congressional District candidate Christian Menefee greets voters near a polling place on Nov. 4, 2025, in Houston. " data-portal-copyright="Ashley Landis/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25308654371344" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Democratic 18th Congressional District candidate Christian Menefee greets voters near a polling place on Nov. 4, 2025, in Houston. "/><p>Abbott justified the special election hold up by saying he didn’t trust Harris County to conduct a swift and valid election. The governor, who has set his sights on flipping the county in November, has <a href="https://gov.texas.gov/news/post/governor-abbott-calls-for-investigation-of-harris-county-elections" target="_blank">claimed for years</a> that there are widespread problems with electoral administration in Houston.</p> 
<p>Texas Democrats said Abbott’s foot-dragging to fill the seat — which has advantaged House Republicans' paper-thin majority in Washington — is another example of GOP meddling with Democratic power in major cities. Republicans’ off-cycle redistricting last year scrambled Democratic seats in Houston, Dallas and Austin. Green, a towering figure in Houston political circles, jumped into the race for the newly gerrymandered 18th seat after the neighboring district he held for more than 20 years was carved up by the GOP.</p> 
<p>In another sign of how redistricting has muddled campaigns, Menefee and Edwards are running in Saturday’s runoff under different lines from the upcoming March primary — forcing the pair to run simultaneous campaigns with two overlapping but not identical sets of voters. Early voting in the March primary begins in two weeks.</p> 
<p>“This is a microcosm of forced redistricting,” said Odus Evbagharu, a Menefee aide. “It’s something that got forced down our throats, and now we just have to live with that.”</p> 
<p>During the final stretch of the runoff, candidates crisscrossed both the old and new 18th districts, an area of central Houston with a large Black population. About a quarter of the district’s current constituents live within its new iteration.</p> 
<p>At a candidate forum held in a Catholic church on Thursday evening, Green, Menefee, Edwards and a fourth candidate running in the primary with little name recognition, newcomer Gretchen Brown, quickly rattled off their biographies and what they would bring to Washington.</p> 
<p>For Green, it wasn’t an introduction as much as a reminder to the audience that he has represented many of them for two decades. A significant share of Green’s constituents in the new 18th district were shuffled over from Green's old district.</p> 
<p>“It is important for people to understand that I'm not moving into a new congressional district,” Green said while taking the microphone and brandishing his signature gold-capped cane. “I am not. The congressional district moved to me.”</p><img src="https://static.politico.com/ad/40/ec994b5049a8b0500a435bcdb265/supreme-court-voting-rights-73810.jpg" alt="Rep. Al Green (D-Texas) speaks to demonstrators in front of the Supreme Court as the court hearings oral arguments in the Louisiana second majority black Congressional district, in Washington, Oct. 15, 2025. " data-portal-copyright="Cliff Owen/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25288543573810" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Rep. Al Green (D-Texas) speaks to demonstrators in front of the Supreme Court as the court hearings oral arguments in the Louisiana second majority black Congressional district, in Washington, Oct. 15, 2025. "/><p>In this era when Democrats are eager to forcefully counter Republicans, voters here have a choice: Support a trusted figure who can navigate Washington or take a chance on a younger representative seen as the future of the party. It's an urgent debate within the party as Democrats plot their strategy for regaining power, and is playing out in primaries across the country. Some other top Democrats facing generational primaries, including Reps. Nancy Pelosi of California and Steny Hoyer of Maryland, opted not to run again.</p> 
<p>“Al Green has a great name,” said Harris County Commissioner Rodney Ellis, who endorsed Menefee in the runoff but has not weighed in on the primary. “But then, on the other hand, whoever wins [the runoff] will get a bump of celebrity status.”</p> 
<p>Menefee made local history as the youngest elected Harris County attorney — the first Black person in the job — and has built his reputation on going head-to-head with Abbott, suing the governor’s ban on mask mandates and challenging his demands to audit local elections. It’s his first stint in public office after he ran a surprise campaign ousting the three-term incumbent in 2020.</p> 
<p>Menefee — who is <a href="https://www.facebook.com/ChristianDMenefee/videos/1554491595797005/" target="_blank">running ads</a> playing on 90’s millennial nostalgia — has racked up endorsements from organizations like Leaders We Deserve and Houston Black American Democrats, more than a dozen labor groups, and prominent figures like Rep. Jasmine Crockett and former Rep. Beto O’Rourke.</p> 
<p>Edwards draws on broad support from women and from her years as an attorney and at-large member of the city council. She won the endorsement of past opponent Jolanda Jones, a state representative who has served as a main Menefee antagonist, criticizing him for continuing to collect his government salary while campaigning.</p> 
<p>Edwards is also a familiar face on campaign mailers: She ran unsuccessfully for U.S. Senate in 2020, Houston mayor in 2023 and U.S. House in 2024. Her career in politics began when she was a congressional aide for Lee as a recent college graduate.</p> 
<p>Menefee and Edwards dismiss the idea that the primary will be a referendum on age, seeing it instead as an expression of voters’ desire to see broad change in Congress.</p> 
<p>“What I think people want is something new,” Menefee said in an interview. “They want new strategic thinkers who are going to come in and have a plan for opposition against the president.”</p> 
<p>Edwards argues it's also an issue of continuity. A Green victory would mean that some constituents living in the district will have been represented by four lawmakers in three years. “They want to pass that torch forward and this is an opportunity to do that,” she said. “It's not a question of age. It's a question of succession.”</p> 
<p>Green, in an interview, said he expects people will vote for him if they primarily value experience and accomplishments, ticking off his leadership on the Homeland Security and Oversight committees, along with the billions he has steered toward his district and recommendation of three judges confirmed during the Obama administration.</p> 
<p>“I bring to the table traditionally what people have looked for when they were trying to make a decision,” he said. “So we'll find out whether tradition continues or whether we'll have a different circumstance.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘A pretext to rig the election’: Democrats scramble to block ICE crackdowns near polling sites</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/democrats-ice-deployments-midterm-elections-00756490</link>
      <description>Election officials are preparing for the possibility of immigration enforcement activity at or near polling sites in November.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0c46-df8c-a99d-fdf6426f0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 10:01:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/05/cf/e7e58cb9444d8d8371e34fffcf26/imageedit-2-7863109265.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ashlee Rezin/Chicago Sun-Times via AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Federal immigration and border agents walk along West Wacker Drive in the Loop in Chicago on Sept. 28, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/05/cf/e7e58cb9444d8d8371e34fffcf26/imageedit-2-7863109265.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Immigration enforcement is sowing chaos in Minneapolis and across the country. Democrats, elections officials and civil rights groups fear it could interfere with this November’s elections — and are scrambling for a response.</p> 
<p>They’re warning that the White House’s deployments of Immigration and Customs Enforcement and Border Patrol agents could act as a voter suppression tool should armed officers conduct raids at or near polling locations, scaring citizens into staying home.</p> 
<p>“You have to see what's happening: Trump is trying to create a pretext to rig the election,” said Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.). “It stands to reason that this private police [force] that he’s building is, in part, to be used to try to suppress turnout in the election.”</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats considered a requirement banning ICE agents from polling sites as part of their demands in negotiating the Homeland Security funding bill, according to Murphy and Sen. Gary Peters (D-Mich.). But that policy was not included in <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/democrats-dhs-minnesota-shutdown-00753256" target="_blank">Senate Democratic appropriators’ final list of demands</a> to avoid a partial government shutdown, leaving voting rights advocates and Democratic state election officials on edge about what’s to come.</p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson called fears of voter suppression “Democrat conspiracies” with “no basis in reality.”</p> 
<p>“President Trump cares deeply about the integrity of our elections — and so do the millions of Americans who sent him back to office based on his pledge to secure our elections,” Jackson said in a statement. “These Democrat conspiracies have no basis in reality and their claims shouldn’t be amplified uncritically by the mainstream media. ICE is focused on removing criminal illegal aliens from [the] country, who should be nowhere near any polling places because it would be a crime for them to vote.”</p> 
<p>ICE's aggressive crackdowns have already led to citizens hiding at home, and election officials worry that fears of harassment and arrest could keep them from exercising their right to vote.</p> 
<p>“In Maine, we saw people were afraid to leave their homes for groceries, to go to work or to go to school, because of fear of wrongful arrest and imprisonment,” Maine Secretary of State Shenna Bellows, a Democrat who’s running for governor, told POLITICO on Thursday. “If people are too afraid to go to the grocery store because armed ICE agents are patrolling the streets, that may increase fears about going to vote.”</p> 
<p>Bellows said her office is preparing for next month’s special legislative election by ensuring voters are comfortable with absentee voting procedures, especially those in areas with large immigrant populations that have been impacted by ICE’s recent crackdown in the state.</p> 
<p>Immigration enforcement activity near polling locations could dissuade those with noncitizen family members or voters of color, who fear being racially profiled, from turning out. And widespread deployments of immigration officers to battleground districts could cause chaos in key races and swing close elections.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration dispatched about 3,000 federal agents to Minneapolis to apprehend non-citizens in an operation that many in the state and elsewhere consider heavy-handed and excessive. The president and senior officials have indicated that the operation is about more than just law enforcement.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/13/trump-minnesota-reckoning-retribution-warning-00724534" target="_blank">called the Minnesota operation</a> a “day of reckoning and retribution” and has tied the operation to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/12/brace-for-impact-trump-turns-fraud-into-new-weapon-against-blue-states-00719401" target="_blank">welfare fraud</a> in the state. On Saturday, Attorney General Pam Bondi <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26508586-bondiwalzltr012426/" target="_blank">sent a letter</a> to Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz demanding he turn over the state’s voter rolls, an action <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/minnesota-operation-metro-surge-case-00746755" target="_blank">lawyers for the state of Minnesota described</a> as a “shakedown” and a “ransom note.”</p> 
<p>“The demand for the voter rolls tells you what this is really about,” Sen. Alex Padilla (D-Calif.), who oversaw California’s elections for six years as secretary of state, told reporters Wednesday. “It’s about trying to rig the next election, and a desperate attempt to hold onto power.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/USCODE-2011-title18/html/USCODE-2011-title18-partI-chap29-sec592.htm" target="_blank">Federal law is explicit</a> in banning “any troops or armed men at any place where a general or special election is held,” unless to “repel armed enemies of the United States[.]” Many local election officials also take great care to avoid spooking voters by placing law enforcement at polling places, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/10/30/election-threats-violence-00186377" target="_blank">some states even have laws regulating this</a>. Voter intimidation is illegal across the entire country.</p> 
<p>But Trump has falsely and repeatedly claimed for more than a decade <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-migrants-border-voter-fraud-campaign-40bbf5748615a3b1f6087ff920f59278" target="_blank">that millions of illegal immigrants vote</a> in the U.S., arguing that was one factor in his 2020 loss. He also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/08/23/meadows-trump-police-polls-400255" target="_blank">pledged before the 2020 election to send “sheriffs” and “law enforcement”</a> to polling places.</p> 
<p>Some Trump allies have openly described the possibility of deploying immigration enforcement officers to polling sites to ensure non-citizens do not vote.</p> 
<p>“They’re petrified over at MSNBC and CNN that, hey, since we’re taking control of the cities, there’s going to be ICE officers near polling places,” former White House chief strategist Steve Bannon said <a href="https://warroom.org/bannons-warroom-show-clip-roundup-19-august-25-am/" target="_blank">during his show last August</a>. “You’re damn right. … We’re not going to allow any illegal aliens to vote.”</p> 
<p>Civil rights groups are preparing for the possibility that Trump exercises emergency powers to allow such a move.</p> 
<p>Joanna Lydgate, CEO of the States United Democracy Center, told reporters this week that the Trump administration is “using these violent ICE operations as a weapon” for political ends.</p> 
<p>“[Trump] might try to use an executive order or his emergency powers in the 11th hour to interfere with the upcoming election, which is, of course, something that no president in American history has ever done, but something that we need to be prepared for,” Lydgate said Monday during a press briefing.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration has continued its focus on election administration. On Wednesday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/fbi-raid-georgia-elections-trump-2020-00753249" target="_blank">the FBI executed a search warrant</a> at the Fulton County elections office outside Atlanta. Last week, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/20/trump-musk-doge-social-security-00737245" target="_blank">the Justice Department revealed</a> that DOGE employees were secretly communicating with an advocacy group seeking to “overturn election results in certain states” and may have used Social Security data to match voter rolls. Last week in Davos, Trump suggested <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/trump-2020-election-prosecutions-00738778" target="_blank">prosecutions are forthcoming</a> related to the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>State election officials in both parties <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/tulsi-gabbard-2020-election-investigation-00755487" target="_blank">are anxious to see</a> why Director of National Intelligence Tulsi Gabbard, Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem and Attorney General Pam Bondi will address the winter meeting of the National Association of Secretaries of State on Friday. A DHS spokesperson didn’t respond to request for comment for this story.</p> 
<p>Nonprofit legal groups are already gearing up to challenge any efforts to intimidate voters around the November midterms, said Skye Perryman, president and CEO of Democracy Forward.</p> 
<p>“Litigation is going to remain an incredibly important guardrail,” said Perryman, whose nonprofit <a href="https://democracyforward.org/work/legal/stopping-doges-unlawful-seizure-of-americans-social-security-data/" target="_blank">led one of the lawsuits</a> against DOGE’s access to voter information. “And there are many cases that can be swiftly filed on an emergency basis, or even potentially proactively, in order to try to keep the communities as safe as possible.”</p> 
<p>David Becker, the executive director and founder of the nonpartisan Center for Election Innovation &amp; Research, warned that election officials across the country — from secretaries of state to local officers — are seeing “a level of federal interference in their work which is unconstitutional and unprecedented.”</p> 
<p>“I want to stress how unusual this is,” Becker, a former DOJ civil rights attorney, told POLITICO. “County election officials shouldn't have to be thinking about what the president of the United States might say about elections.”</p> 
<p>Those elections officials are working to instill trust in the electoral process, Becker said, and will encourage voters to utilize a variety of alternative ways to cast a ballot, such as early voting or voting by mail, depending on the state.</p> 
<p>An attempt to heighten immigration enforcement before the election could just as easily backfire for Republicans. Trump is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270" target="_blank">now under water on the immigration issue</a>, with polls showing a majority of voters believe his deportation push went too far and want to see it reined in. Justin Levitt, a professor at Loyola Law School who worked in the Biden White House as an adviser on democracy and voting rights, pointed to high turnout in this week’s special elections for Minnesota legislature seats in Democratic-heavy districts, where Democrats romped.</p> 
<p>“In places where there might be disruption, Minnesota is proving that you might well earn yourself a real significant backlash,” Levitt said.</p> 
<p>But even talking about election suppression has a risk of discouraging voters, convincing them there is risk involved or that the elections might be rigged anyway. Conversely, talk of vote-rigging can do the same thing.</p> 
<p>“Our fight right now is both to protect the security of our elections and people's faith in them, because they're deeply intertwined and they're both under attack,” said Michigan Secretary of State Jocelyn Benson.</p> 
<p><i>Andrew Howard contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Janet Mills’ first TV ad hits ICE</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/janet-mills-tv-ad-ice-00756765</link>
      <description>The ad uses footage of the Maine governor criticizing the agency in a speech this week.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0cad-df8c-a99d-fdff7b5a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/df/08/06d605ba41bcbebc5444f67027ad/maine-gov-janet-mills-45569.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Robert F. Bukaty/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Democratic Gov. Janet Mills delivers her State of the State address, Jan. 30, 2024, at the State House in Augusta, Maine.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/df/08/06d605ba41bcbebc5444f67027ad/maine-gov-janet-mills-45569.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Gov. Janet Mills’ first ad buy as she seeks to unseat Sen. Susan Collins features a repudiation of ICE as Democrats nationwide seize on backlash over the agency’s aggressive tactics.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1oC0ffYabwc" target="_blank">new TV spot</a>, shared first with POLITICO, pairs news clippings and videos of ICE agents aggressively detaining people with footage of Mills criticizing the deportation campaign during <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/janet-mills-ice-raids-state-address-00751216" target="_blank">her State of the State address</a> on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>“Our federal government has deployed masked law enforcement onto the streets, including here in Maine, stoking fear in our communities and killing American citizens in Minnesota,” Mills says in the ad. “It’s ridiculous, outrageous and unconstitutional.”</p> 
<p>The six-figure buy goes up statewide on Friday and is running across broadcast and digital for the next two weeks.</p> 
<p>It comes as immigration enforcement has become a national political issue, with voter backlash against ICE raids leading Democrats to talk more about an issue <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270" target="_blank">that had once been favorable for Republicans</a>.</p> 
<p>An ICE surge in Maine, dubbed Operation Catch of the Day by Homeland Security officials, received widespread backlash from Democrats and local leaders, who highlighted cases of Maine residents being detained by the agency despite having legal work permits and no criminal histories. The fatal shooting of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis last weekend further inflamed anger in Maine, too.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/ice-ends-maine-operation-00754382" target="_blank">Collins announced Thursday that ICE would be halting its surge</a> in the Pine Tree State, but the fallout of the heightened enforcement continues to roil the state. Mills’ decision to seize on ICE for her first ad is a sign she believes the issue will have staying power.</p> 
<p>Mills’ main primary opponent, oysterman and political newcomer Graham Platner, has also gone after Collins on ICE this week, holding protests outside her offices in Portland and Bangor on Thursday.</p> 
<p>Platner <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/10/14/graham-platner-janet-mills-maine-senate-tv-ad" target="_blank">ran TV ads skeptical of Mills</a> when the governor first jumped into the Senate race last fall. His campaign recently went up with more biographical spots and has pledged to stay on air through the June primary.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minnesota Dems are trying to walk a tightrope with Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/walz-frey-trump-relationship-00756790</link>
      <description>Dems have struck a fragile and uneasy peace with the president. Everyone’s holding their breath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0ccf-df8c-a99d-fdffc7150001</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e8/72/4e86ba3842d182912d1813c583b6/aptopix-us-conference-of-mayors-74989.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Minneapolis Mayor Jacob Frey steps away from the podium after speaking to the 94th Winter Meeting of the U.S. Conference of Mayors on Thursday in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e8/72/4e86ba3842d182912d1813c583b6/aptopix-us-conference-of-mayors-74989.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider and Madison Fernandez</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider and Madison Fernandez</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Minnesota Democrats are figuring out the delicate art of Trump diplomacy this week.</p> 
<p>First, President Donald Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115962378381121858" target="_blank">had a “very good call”</a> with Gov. Tim Walz, an inflection point after days of heated GOP attacks on the former vice presidential candidate. Then, Trump declared he’d <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115963713974102712" target="_blank">had another “very good” conversation</a>, this time with Minneapolis Mayor Jacob Frey. Both sides had been looking to deescalate, and Trump seemed to be turning a corner on the two Democratic <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115951636521315703" target="_blank">“sanctimonious political fools”</a> he had initially blamed after the shooting of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>Then the mayor accidentally broke the detente.</p> 
<p>After meeting with Trump’s border czar Tom Homan, <a href="https://x.com/MayorFrey/status/2016241048209518736" target="_blank">Frey reiterated on social media</a> that “Minneapolis does not and will not enforce federal immigration laws,” which a person close to Frey said was simply intended as “clarifying what our stance was.” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115972940749866695" target="_blank">But Trump quickly shot back</a>, declaring Frey’s “statement is a very serious violation of the Law” and warning the mayor that “he is PLAYING WITH FIRE.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s response “surprised” the mayor, according to the person close to him, who was granted anonymity to speak about a sensitive issue. This person said city officials saw Trump’s response “as a threat.” Nonetheless, Frey, in recent appearances on CNN and at the National Mayor’s Conference in Washington on Thursday said “the Operation Metro Surge needs to end” while eschewing the kind of combative rhetoric that he had used over the weekend. Homan told reporters on Thursday morning that he’d asked for immigration agencies to work on a “drawdown plan.” After a tense day or two, the fragile peace appeared to be holding.</p> 
<p>The episode illustrates just how delicate the ongoing talks to deescalate the crisis in Minnesota are with a president known for his capricious and erratic negotiating style. As Democrats across the country see a rare political opening on immigration, Minnesota Democrats are first and foremost trying to end the immigration crackdown in their own state. Despite their public confidence, they’re privately on tenterhooks over whether Trump will take the exit ramp.</p> 
<p>“This back and forth [between Trump and Frey] is unhelpful,” said one Minnesota Democratic strategist, granted anonymity to discuss a sensitive situation. “Strategically, I wouldn’t have phrased it that way. It’s not a huge mistake, but it’s not helpful.”</p> 
<p>It’s a lesson foreign leaders are deeply familiar with already: Diplomatic breakthroughs with Trump can come fast, and fall apart just as quickly. European officials have regularly had to scramble to respond to the president’s controversial statements on the war in Ukraine or the ownership of Greenland with highly deferential overtures in both public and private. They’ve had mixed success.</p> 
<p>Throughout Trump’s second term, Democrats have struggled to find their footing in negotiations with the president. Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer drew fury from his own party for voting for a GOP-drafted continuing resolution in March. In October, Democrats forced what would become the longest government shutdown in US history over health care funding, but they emerged from it without any tangible deliverables. But in Minnesota, Democrats appear to hold the political upper hand, as Trump’s polling numbers, particularly his handling of immigration, plummeted in recent weeks — and he signals eagerness to cut a face-saving deal.</p> 
<p>“Everyone needs to give something here to move on from this,” one Minnesota union chief said — adding that it can be difficult to do. A Democratic operative in the state expressed hope that Frey’s post was merely “a bump on the exit ramp.”</p> 
<p>But not all Minnesota Democrats agree that playing ball is the way forward. “Being nice isn’t somehow going to stop Donald Trump when anything can set him off,” said Ron Harris, a Democratic National Committee member from Minnesota. Frey’s post, he said, simply “emphasized what the law is.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Frey said in a statement that “the mayor has been communicating both publicly and privately, including to the president and Tom Homan, that Minneapolis would be happy to partner on criminal investigations, and that’s what we’re focusing our limited law enforcement resources on.”</p> 
<p>It’s unclear when the Trump administration will end its operation in Minnesota, though the president appears motivated to do so. The Trump administration has already pulled back in other states. Republican Maine Sen. Susan Collins said that ICE has “<a href="https://x.com/SenatorCollins/status/2016830738595794944" target="_blank">ended its enhanced activities</a>” in Maine after politicians on both sides of the aisle urged the agency to stop.</p> 
<p>For Democrats studying Trump diplomacy, Walz and Frey may offer a template in some of their tonal differences. Interviews with nearly a dozen Minnesota Democrats said the pair were largely aligned in substance, and the rhetorical daylight, highlighted by the social media scuffle with Trump, reflects their differing constituencies and styles — and political realities.</p> 
<p>Last November, Frey held off a stiff challenge from the left from state Sen. Omar Fateh, a Democratic Socialist, to win reelection. But the progressive wing of the party <a href="https://www.startribune.com/minneapolis-city-council-progressives-dsa-majority/601556625" target="_blank">retook the majority on city council, too</a>. “He’s facing a lot of internal pressure” from the city council to “continue calling out the craziness,” said a Democratic strategist who, like others, was granted anonymity to candidly discuss a sensitive issue.</p> 
<p>“Frey’s constituency is different” than Walz, the strategist said, “and in general, I think he’s been more combative … They’re also just different people with different negotiating styles.”</p> 
<p>The 44-year-old mayor is also seen as a potential statewide candidate, layering in its own political calculations. Minnesota Sen. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/amy-klobuchar-minnesota-governor-00754285" target="_blank">Amy Klobuchar’s gubernatorial run</a> — and departure from the Senate — could likely open up another statewide office after 2026.</p> 
<p>Walz, for his part, is unshackled from an immediate political future. The two-term governor <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/tim-walz-out-minnesota-00710541" target="_blank">dropped his reelection bid earlier this month</a>, after a welfare fraud scandal in the state threatened to engulf his campaign. Walz acknowledged the scandal affected his decision and Republicans were eager to tie him to it, but he has not been accused of any wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Abou Amara, a Minneapolis civil rights attorney, said Frey’s aggressive rhetoric toward the beginning of the federal government’s intervention was "necessary," but now “everyone understands there has to be a ratcheting down.”</p> 
<p>“The mayor is obviously closer to the people, he understands the visceral pain and the trauma that the people are experiencing,” Amara said. “The governor is operating on a level of having a bit more authority here on how the state interacts with the federal government. … Governor Walz is in a position to deliver on things with the federal government in a way that the mayor is not.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nation’s cartoonists on the week in politics</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/gallery/2026/01/30/the-nations-cartoonists-on-the-week-in-politics-00756184</link>
      <description>Every week political cartoonists throughout the country and across the political spectrum apply their ink-stained skills to capture the foibles, memes, hypocrisies and other head-slapping events in the world of politics. The fruits of these labors are hundreds of cartoons that entertain and enrage readers of all political stripes. Here's an offering of the best of this week's crop, picked fresh off the Toonosphere. Edited by Matt Wuerker.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0bd5-d1ed-a59e-dbdd19600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By POLITICO Staff</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By POLITICO Staff</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded />
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sen. Tillis: 'Get the amateurs out of the Oval Office' | The Conversation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/video/2026/01/29/sen-tillis-get-the-amateurs-out-of-the-oval-office-the-conversation-1903672</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0c74-d1ed-a59e-df7db5550000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 23:59:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 class="title">Sen. Tillis: 'Get the amateurs out of the Oval Office' | The Conversation</h3> 
<p><img data-brightcove-id="6388513924112" data-mp4url="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/fd4fc812-1a3b-4110-bbcb-9f4b0f58b7b6/c9f6002e-aec3-414c-815d-61fc12148f4b/main.mp4" src="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/fd4fc812-1a3b-4110-bbcb-9f4b0f58b7b6/3e21fc71-5d99-4f2b-b8a3-c510e39a7d33/1280x720/match/image.jpg">lead image</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Bizarrely and personally lurking’: Gabbard’s appearance at FBI election raid alarms Dems</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/tulsi-gabbard-2020-election-investigation-00755487</link>
      <description>A White House spokesperson defended Gabbard’s involvement, saying she has a “pivotal role in election security.”</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0bbd-df8c-a99d-ffff792d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 19:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5f/8f/e8d3c616460ba0eaf3025a077887/cocaine-seizures-35216.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Rebecca Blackwell/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>As DNI, Tulsi Gabbard has no domestic law enforcement authority and is not typically involved in criminal investigations</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5f/8f/e8d3c616460ba0eaf3025a077887/cocaine-seizures-35216.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By John Sakellariadis and Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By John Sakellariadis and Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats, election experts and even some members of the Trump administration expressed alarm and bewilderment about why Tulsi Gabbard was on the scene as the FBI raided a Georgia election office that has been at the center of Donald Trump’s debunked claims that the 2020 election was stolen.</p> 
<p>Gabbard, the director of national intelligence, <a href="https://x.com/corinne_perkins/status/2016673423708053509" target="_blank">was photographed late Wednesday</a> outside the Fulton County elections office near Atlanta, Georgia, as the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/fbi-raid-georgia-elections-trump-2020-00753249" target="_blank">FBI executed a search warrant</a> to seize ballots and other records related to the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>As DNI, Gabbard has no domestic law enforcement authority and is not typically involved in criminal investigations, a reality that alarmed many Democrats on Capitol Hill — and even puzzled some Trump officials. </p> 
<p>“My constituents in Georgia and I think much of the American public are quite reasonably alarmed in asking questions after the director of national intelligence was spotted bizarrely and personally lurking in an FBI evidence truck in Fulton County, Georgia, yesterday,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/34364" data-person-id="34364">Jon Ossoff</a> (D-Ga.) said during an unrelated Senate hearing Thursday morning.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elections/spy-chief-tulsi-gabbard-is-hunting-for-2020-election-fraud-07ea2383?mod=hp_lead_pos3" target="_blank">The Wall Street Journal reported Thursday</a> that Gabbard was investigating the 2020 election, and has regularly briefed Trump and other administration officials about her search. “President Trump and his entire team are committed to ensuring a U.S. election can never, ever be rigged again. Director Gabbard is playing a key lead role in this important effort,” Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, told The Journal.</p> 
<p>Olivia Coleman, a spokesperson for Gabbard, confirmed the DNI was on the scene in Atlanta. She did not immediately respond to follow-up inquiries about her reported probe of the 2020 vote.</p> 
<p>Despite concerns raised by Democrats, Gabbard appears to be taking on a more expansive public role in American elections. On Thursday, White House aide Jared Borg told a group of election officials that Gabbard — alongside Secretary of Homeland Security Kristi Noem and Attorney General Pam Bondi — is set to address the winter meeting of the National Association of Secretaries of State on Friday.</p> 
<p>Trump has long fixated on unsubstantiated allegations of voter fraud in Georgia in the aftermath of the 2020 election, which he lost to former President Joe Biden. He has continued to falsely suggest that the election was stolen since returning to the White House, including in a speech at the World Economic Forum in Davos last week. </p> 
<p>White House spokesperson Davis Ingle defended Gabbard in an emailed statement. “Director Gabbard has a pivotal role in election security and protecting the integrity of our elections against interference, including operations targeting voting systems, databases and election infrastructure,” he wrote. “She has and will continue to take action on President Trump’s directive to secure our elections and work with our interagency partners to do so.”</p> 
<p>Trump spent much of the morning amplifying claims that the Georgia vote was rigged on Truth Social, and <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115978031218105674" target="_blank">even called attention to Gabbard’s role</a> in Wednesday’s raid. </p> 
<p>Gabbard’s role remains confusing to some in the administration. Two current Justice Department officials and one Trump administration official said they were also puzzled by Gabbard’s presence in Fulton County. “It remains a mystery to me why she would need to be there,” said the administration official, who, like others interviewed, was granted anonymity because they were not authorized to speak publicly on the matter. </p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66837" data-person-id="66837">Mark Warner</a>, (D-Va.), the top Democrat on the Senate Intelligence Committee, <a href="https://x.com/MarkWarner/status/2016722913420845333" target="_blank">argued on X Wednesday</a> that there “are only two explanations” for Gabbard’s presence in the raid.</p> 
<p>“Either Director Gabbard believes there was a legitimate foreign intelligence nexus — in which case she is in clear violation of her obligation under the law to keep the intelligence committees ‘fully and currently informed’ of relevant national security concerns — or she is once again demonstrating her utter lack of fitness for the office that she holds by injecting the nonpartisan intelligence community she is supposed to be leading into a domestic political stunt designed to legitimize conspiracy theories that undermine our democracy,” he wrote.</p> 
<p>Warner and House Intelligence Committee Ranking Member Rep. Jim Himes (D-Conn.) <a href="https://democrats-intelligence.house.gov/uploadedfiles/himes-warner_letter_to_dni_1.29.2026_.pdf" target="_blank">wrote to Gabbard Thursday</a> to request briefings for both panels about the legal basis, scope, and justification of her participation in the raid.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189610" data-person-id="189610">Alex Padilla</a> (D-Calif.), who before entering Congress was California’s chief election official, told a panel at NASS on Thursday that Gabbard’s presence at the raid should be a reminder about “the urgency of the situation.”</p> 
<p>“I guess they’re still searching for 11,000 more votes,” he quipped, referencing a call Trump had with Georgia Secretary of State Brad Raffensperger after losing the 2020 election. “But it should be a reminder — or a wake up — that this can happen at any point once again between now and this coming November.”</p> 
<p>Gabbard’s appearance at the raid led some Democrats to believe she wanted to be there to claim credit for it publicly.</p> 
<p>“When the head of a department participates in something, it's about PR, not about process and the law,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51223" data-person-id="51223">Jack Reed</a> (D-R.I.) told POLITICO. “If they have evidence, they want evidence and they have a valid warrant, and you let the professionals go in and do that.”</p> 
<p>While Gabbard has veered in and out of the good graces of Trump during her tenure as DNI, she appeared to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/23/gabbard-once-scorned-takes-center-stage-with-latest-obama-allegations-00471183" target="_blank">hit a high point last summer</a> when she alleged that senior U.S. intelligence officials under then-President Barack Obama were guilty of treason because they had <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/18/tulsi-gabbard-2016-election-investigation-00463779" target="_blank">fabricated intelligence about Russian meddling in the 2016 election</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump said last week that individuals who played a role in that year’s vote <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/trump-2020-election-prosecutions-00738778?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=substack" target="_blank">will soon be prosecuted</a>.</p> 
<p>David Becker, the executive director of the Center for Election Innovation and Research, told reporters on Thursday that Gabbard’s Georgia appearance only sparks more concerns that the raid “is an attempt to fuel false claims and disinformation.”</p> 
<p>“There is no reason for the director of national intelligence to be in any kind of voting site,” he said. “She has neither the authority nor the competence to assess anything in that voting site. And so it’s incredibly troubling to see something like that.”</p> 
<p>Mo Ivory, a Fulton County commissioner, said Thursday that federal officials took 700 boxes of ballots and “ancillary” materials from the 2020 election. The county’s attorney, she said, is “working with a group of local and national lawyers" to formulate a legal response.</p> 
<p>The first DOJ official said the ballots are now being stored at an FBI facility in Winchester, Virginia.</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for Georgia Secretary of State Brad Raffensperger did not respond to requests for comment. In 2020, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/01/24/raffensperger-georgia-election-misinformation-00137372" target="_blank">Raffensperger famously rebuffed</a> Trump’s pressure campaign to “find” enough votes to flip the state’s election for him.</p> 
<p>The two DOJ officials said the FBI received a heads up that Gabbard would be on site for the raid. They said her participation did not bother FBI Director Kash Patel or other bureau officials.</p> 
<p>Democrats, however, worry more broadly that the raid could have a chilling effect on future elections.</p> 
<p>“The facts are clear, Trump lost, and he has to accept that and move on with his life,” Michigan Secretary of State Jocelyn Benson said in an interview. “And everyone in his administration should do the same, instead of terrorizing election officials and interfering with our work to simply just prepare for the midterm elections.”</p> 
<p><i>Erin Doherty and Andrew Howard contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shapiro dodges on endorsing Fetterman if he runs for reelection</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/shapiro-dodges-on-endorsing-fetterman-if-he-runs-for-reelection-00755851</link>
      <description>It's the latest twist in the long-strained relationship between the top Pennsylvania Democrats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0b82-df17-afbf-7fb3fc630000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 16:19:40 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/11/94/4d00e0de46089b0cab395a2754e0/governor-josh-shapiro-in-conversation-at-92ny-25736.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro was in Washington, D.C., on Thursday as part of his book tour.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/11/94/4d00e0de46089b0cab395a2754e0/governor-josh-shapiro-in-conversation-at-92ny-25736.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pennsylvania Gov. Josh Shapiro on Thursday declined to say whether he would support Sen. John Fetterman if he runs for reelection in 2028, the latest twist in a fraught relationship between Pennnsylvania’s two most prominent Democrats.</p> 
<p>“John will decide if he’s going to run for reelection. I appreciate his service,” Shapiro said before quickly pivoting, when asked whether Fetterman is “someone that you admire and would support for reelection” at a Christian Science Monitor press event in Washington.</p> 
<p>Asked point-blank whether he liked Fetterman, Shapiro replied: “Of course. And we all work together to do good things for the people of Pennsylvania.”</p> 
<p>Fetterman has not yet said whether he will seek reelection in 2028. But progressives are already <a href="https://www.cityandstatepa.com/politics/2025/11/working-families-party-pledges-support-john-fetterman-primary-challenger/409595/" target="_blank"><u>plotting a primary challenge</u></a> to him over his centrist congressional voting record that’s seen him cross party lines to support some of President Donald Trump’s Cabinet picks, give full-throated support for Israel and repeatedly buck Democrats during shutdown fights.</p> 
<p>The relationship between the top Pennsylvania Democrats and stylistic opposites has long been strained, though Fetterman has been much more public about his disdain for Shapiro than the other direction.</p> 
<p>Fetterman, in his 2025 memoir, criticized Shapiro for acting out of “political ambition” and <a href="https://nypost.com/2025/11/12/us-news/sen-john-fetterman-raged-at-fing-ahole-josh-shapiro-reveals-why-their-relationship-never-recovered-in-new-memoir/" target="_blank"><u>wrote that he was caught on a hot mic</u></a> calling Shapiro a “fucking asshole” during a Zoom meeting while serving together on the state’s pardon board. Fetterman wrote he wished Shapiro the best — but claimed the two “no longer speak.”</p> 
<p>Shapiro refuted that Thursday, saying “yes” the two are on speaking terms, adding that they were in a meeting together with Transportation Secretary Sean Duffy “a few weeks ago … working on an important issue in Pennsylvania.”</p> 
<p>Shapiro makes just two mentions of Fetterman in his own memoir, “Where We Keep the Light: Stories from a Life of Service,” which was released this week — both just passing mentions of the two being at the same political events. He notes the two spoke backstage at an Erie Democratic dinner days before Fetterman’s stroke.</p> 
<p>A representative for Fetterman did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>These gov candidates stood up to Trump in 2020. Now they’re betting voters have moved on.</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/secretaries-of-state-governor-candidates-2020-00742615</link>
      <description>Secretaries of state who rose to prominence after the 2020 election are betting voters care more about what comes next.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-e7a4-d1ea-a5df-f7a439510000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/png" url="https://static.politico.com/15/f6/774787e7444483b5ec8ee789a444/main-doherty-sosgovelex-illustration.png">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Jade Cuevas/POLITICO (source images via AP)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.Doherty.SOSGovElex.Illustration.png</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/15/f6/774787e7444483b5ec8ee789a444/main-doherty-sosgovelex-illustration.png" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Erin Doherty</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Erin Doherty</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>State election officials were among the most visible defenders of American democracy after the 2020 election — standing up to President Donald Trump, rejecting false claims and, whether they wanted to or not, becoming national symbols of institutional resistance to his attempts to overturn his election loss.</p> 
<p>But as some run for governor in 2026, they are eager to talk about anything but 2020.</p> 
<p>More than five years after Trump’s attempt to cling to power ignited a political rallying cry on the left and a loyalty test on the right, these Republican and Democratic candidates are betting — and, in some cases, hoping — that voters have moved on.</p> 
<p>A pair of Republican secretaries of state who rejected Trump’s false 2020 election claims and then survived MAGA-fueled 2022 primaries are running for governor. Unsurprisingly, neither is keen to relitigate the issue that linger over their hopes this year.</p> 
<p>“2020 is very far behind us as secretaries of state,” Kansas Republican Secretary of State Scott Schwab said. “We remember it, but we’re moving on, and I think the American public is too.”</p> 
<p>But Trump isn’t ready to move on, complicating these candidates’ hopes of putting 2020 in the rearview mirror. Speaking before an audience of global leaders and business officials in Davos last week, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/trump-2020-election-prosecutions-00738778" target="_blank">Trump repeated his false claim</a> that the 2020 election was “rigged” and promised that “people will soon be prosecuted for what they did.”</p> 
<p>Two Democratic secretaries of state are also running for the governor’s mansion. And while defending democracy and their defiance to Trump on election issues forms a defining part of their political biographies, both candidates lead with pocketbook issues rather than making protecting the vote the centerpiece.</p> 
<p>“This election is about Michigan, and this election is about who is best positioned to lower costs for the people in our state,” Michigan Democratic Secretary of State Jocelyn Benson told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>In many ways, the shift reflects the reality of running for the governor’s mansion. The job description is much broader from the office of the secretary of state — and voters want to hear about what politicians will do for them now.</p> 
<p>But it also underscores the political evolution of one of the most animating aspects of Trump’s first term.</p> 
<p>For Democrats, democracy was a potent force in 2022, when candidates <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/10/24/election-deniers-secretary-of-state-00062383" target="_blank">leaned heavily into running against election deniers</a>. And many Democrats say it’s still effective.</p> 
<p>“They use the issue as an illustration of character,” said Democratic pollster Celinda Lake. “It really communicates integrity, nonpartisanship, commitment to democracy and freedom, standing up for people, and courage.”</p> 
<p>As Democratic candidates’ use of democracy messaging has evolved, strategists say the meaning of “democracy” itself has also shifted since 2020. Then, it was largely about election integrity and the transfer of power. Now, it’s increasingly tied to broader concerns about executive authority, with Democrats arguing they’ll be the ones who can stand up to a president they see as authoritarian.</p> 
<p>“This is the moment where you need a governor who won't bend the knee,” said Benson, who has been outspoken against the Trump administration following back-to-back killings of protestors in Minnesota by federal agents.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/84/77/62a964ca48f79cf2c7810d4e0afe/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2170653219" alt="Michigan Secretary of State Jocelyn Benson speaks during a House Administration Committee hearing on " data-portal-copyright="Bonnie Cash/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2170653219" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Michigan Secretary of State Jocelyn Benson speaks during a House Administration Committee hearing on "/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large is-centered">Jocelyn Benson</h4> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium"></h5> 
<p>Benson was on the front lines of defending her state’s election results after 2020, facing threats and swatting attacks. That period is a part of her messaging: Her campaign launch video showed news footage of her home being surrounded by protesters, and she remains <a href="https://www.ms.now/opinion/msnbc-opinion/trump-2020-election-pardons-michigan-interference-rcna244664" target="_blank">outspoken</a> against false claims related to the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>She has also cast that moment as proof of leadership — and a willingness to stand up to Trump. “We fought back to protect democracy itself and we showed that as state officials, that's how we have to respond to bullies who try to rip away our rights no matter how powerful they may be,” she said.</p> 
<p>But on the campaign trail, Benson has often focused more on bread-and-butter economic issues. Affordability, housing, health care, childcare and energy costs are listed as her top issues on her campaign website.</p> 
<p>“What every resident, every citizen, every voter in this election knows is how important it is to have a governor who will fight for them and who will fight for them in a way that that effectively lowers their cost of living while also protecting the safety of themselves, their families and their communities,” Benson told POLITICO.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/d0/aa/2429e0244afcb5791a7831a19da2/election-2020-georgia-48074.jpg" alt="Georgia Secretary of State Brad Raffensperger speaks during a news conference in Atlanta, on Nov. 11, 2020, after state election officials announced an audit of the presidential election results." data-portal-copyright="Brynn Anderson/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="20316602548074" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Georgia Secretary of State Brad Raffensperger speaks during a news conference in Atlanta, on Nov. 11, 2020, after state election officials announced an audit of the presidential election results."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large is-centered">Brad Raffensperger</h4> 
<p>Secretary of State Brad Raffensperger was one of the most prominent Republicans to reject Trump after the president urged him to “find” more votes in his state. The incident propelled him into the national spotlight — and drew <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/03/28/georgia-secretary-of-state-gop-478251" target="_blank">fury from the president and his MAGA base</a>, leading to death threats. He warded off a Trump-endorsed primary challenge in 2022, in part by <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/02/24/raffensperger-georgia-reelection-conservative-media-00011224" target="_blank">taking his case</a> to conservative media. Now, he’s seeking the governor’s mansion in the state that is in many ways the epicenter of Trump’s bid to hold on to power in 2020.</p> 
<p>Raffensperger does not directly talk about the 2020 incident in his launch video or on his campaign website. Instead, he frames his record as evidence that he is willing to make the "tough decisions.” His launch video focuses on creating jobs in Georgia, lowering property taxes and banning transgender women from women sports, among other issues — issues that are key to voters but not central to his current day job.</p> 
<p>But Georgia’s 2020 election keeps getting pushed back into the spotlight.</p> 
<p>On Wednesday, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/fbi-raid-georgia-elections-trump-2020-00753249" target="_blank">FBI executed a search warrant</a> at the Fulton County elections office outside Atlanta, seizing all ballots from the 2020 election there.</p> 
<p>“He’s trying to talk about other issues, [but] 2020 keeps coming up,” said Buzz Brockway, a former Republican state legislator who lost to Raffensperger in a 2018 primary.</p> 
<p>Brockway said many Republicans have moved on from 2020 — but that there remains a “loud, noisy contingent who are continuing that battle” that Raffensperger will have to contend with, even if most voters’ main focus lies elsewhere.</p> 
<p>Raffensperger has largely sidestepped questions about the 2020 election — in a November <a href="https://www.ajc.com/politics/2025/12/politically-georgia-live-brad-raffensperger-on-passing-the-2020-test/" target="_blank">interview with the Atlanta-Journal Constitution</a>, he said that it showed that he does the “right thing, no matter what.”</p> 
<p>“Other people haven’t been put to that test, but we were at the end of the day," he said.</p> 
<p>Raffensperger’s campaign declined to comment for this story.</p> 
<p>Still, Raffensperger’ opponents in the GOP primary, particularly Lt. Gov. Burt Jones, are eager to keep 2020 alive in the race. Jones, who was a fake elector in the state, has tried to cast his actions during that period as unflinching loyalty to the president.</p> 
<p>“I don’t know that it brings Jones any new voters,” Brockway said, but it may be an effort to “energize his base.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/46/ab/cfad2edd4434b48c8bc762a38219/election-2022-kansas-secretary-of-state-42813.jpg" alt="Kansas Secretary of State Scott Schwab takes the stage for his victory speech after winning reelection during a watch party in Topeka, Kansas, in 2022." data-portal-copyright="Reed Hoffmann/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="22313162342813" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Kansas Secretary of State Scott Schwab takes the stage for his victory speech after winning reelection during a watch party in Topeka, Kansas, in 2022."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large is-centered">Scott Schwab</h4> 
<p>In ruby-red Kansas, Schwab defied some of the loudest voices in his party when he repeatedly rejected false claims about the 2020 election in his role as secretary of state. He has been clear that he does not see that chapter as central to his gubernatorial bid as he runs in a crowded GOP primary.</p> 
<p>“Everybody’s concerned about taxes, especially with cost of living,” Schwab, a past <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/02/16/nass-secretaries-state-election-bipartisanship-00141840" target="_blank">chair of the National Association of Secretaries of State</a>, said in an interview. “Property taxes are a real red-hot button in Kansas.”</p> 
<p>His campaign launch video only briefly mentions election issues, and almost as an afterthought. “As secretary of state, I streamlined business services and cut bureaucratic red tape,” he said. “I secured our elections, too.”</p> 
<p>There remains a segment of the GOP for whom election issues remain salient, said Bob Beatty, a political science professor at Washburn University in Kansas. But for the broader electorate — those most likely to turn out in midterm elections — these issues are still “pretty low down the list.”</p> 
<p>In 2022, Schwab, Raffensperger and Benson all prevailed in their reelections, despite facing Trump-backed challengers or outright election deniers.</p> 
<p>“I would say that most people really believe that we've moved on,” Schwab said.</p><img src="https://static.politico.com/47/81/7b03ade04febac7b9570f38bb14e/trump-elections-commission-46277.jpg" alt="Main Secretary of State Shenna Bellows speaks at the U.S. Election Assistance Commission Standards Board in-person public meeting in Charlotte North Carolina in April 2025." data-portal-copyright="Chris Carlson/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25114535946277" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Main Secretary of State Shenna Bellows speaks at the U.S. Election Assistance Commission Standards Board in-person public meeting in Charlotte North Carolina in April 2025."/><h4 class="story-text__heading-large is-centered">Shenna Bellows</h4> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium"></h5> 
<p>Democrat Secretary of State Shenna Bellows became Maine secretary of state in January 2021 after being chosen by the state legislature, just as Trump was in the middle of his push to overturn his election loss. In 2023, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/12/29/shenna-bellows-maine-trump-ballot-00133332" target="_blank">she ruled that Trump</a> should be barred from the ballot for his conduct during the Jan. 6, 2021 attack on the Capitol, a decision later overturned by the Supreme Court.</p> 
<p>In the blue-leaning state, and facing a crowded primary, Bellows has been more eager to talk about the issue than some of her fellow chief election officials.</p> 
<p>“Leadership is about doing what is right, even when it is hard,” she said in her launch video, which highlighted the threats and harassment she faced as a result of her decision.</p> 
<p>In her bid for governor, she has emphasized that anger over Trump’s actions exists in tandem with persistent anxiety about the economy. Like Benson, she has been vocal in criticizing the killings in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“The economy is the number one issue for most Mainers, there's a lot of economic concern right now, especially in the wake of the tariffs and increasing job losses that we're about to see,” she told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“That being said, I also think it's really important to tell the truth,” she said. “What the Trump decision and my work as secretary and defending democracy tells people about me is that I will do the right thing even when it's hard.”<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The GOP is losing one of its best issues</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/republicans-trump-immigration-midterms-00754270</link>
      <description>Immigration was a solidly winning issue for Republicans. Trump’s deportation campaign is changing that.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-07b0-d1ea-a5de-37b439ec0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 05:55:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d5/65/42ce347d429d8fe7f68db542d9f3/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-75213.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A federal agent stands guard near a hotel during a noise demonstration protest in response to federal immigration enforcement operations in the city Sunday, Jan. 25, 2026, in Minneapolis.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d5/65/42ce347d429d8fe7f68db542d9f3/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-75213.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Adam Wren</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Adam Wren</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For years, Republicans have had some reliable <i>terra firma:</i> If they were talking about immigration and border security, they were winning.</p> 
<p>Even amid the backlash from Donald Trump’s 2016 pledge to ban all Muslim immigrants to his 2024 amplification of baseless claims that migrants in Springfield, Ohio, were eating pets—immigration remained a durable, winning issue for the GOP.</p> 
<p>Now the ground is shifting under them.</p> 
<p>A torrent of viral images from Minnesota and beyond as Trump’s immigration agents stepped up their shambolic interior campaign of enforcement in recent months — and the killing of two people in Minneapolis in two separate incidents this past month — have led to a loud public backlash, soured voters on the GOP’s approach and eroded President Donald Trump’s standing on the issue ahead of the looming midterms.</p> 
<p>The broad sweep of public polling shows Trump fumbling what has historically been his party’s strongest issue, which even Democrats concede paved his path back to the White House. A <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/trumps-immigration-approval-drops-record-low-reutersipsos-poll-finds-2026-01-26/" target="_blank">Reuters/Ipsos poll</a> found this week Trump hit a second-term trough on the issue, with a majority of Americans — 58 percent — saying his crackdown has gone too far. Only 39 percent approve of his handling of immigration, down two points from earlier this month, and an 11-point erosion from last February. What’s more, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/ice-polling-memo-searchlight-00751569" target="_blank">a poll</a> from the Democratic-aligned Searchlight Institute this week found that 58 percent of likely midterm voters want ICE to be reined in.</p> 
<p>"The image that has been created is not a good thing," said Jose Arango, the Republican chair of Hudson County, New Jersey, a heavily Democratic area with a large Hispanic population that shifted rightward in 2024. "We're losing in the public relations campaign."</p> 
<p>Even before Alex Pretti’s killing in Minneapolis, Trump’s own voters were fretting over his agenda. A plurality of Americans said the president’s mass deportation campaign is too aggressive — including 1 in 5 voters who backed Trump in 2024, according to the latest <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/poll-republicans-ice-immigration-deportations-00744668" target="_blank">POLITICO Poll</a>. More than 1 in 3 Trump voters said that while they support his immigration agenda, they disapprove of the way he is implementing it.</p> 
<p>And <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-0762-d9a8-a7be-87e22d550000" target="_blank">another new round of polling</a> on Thursday could give Democrats more ammo as voters move away from Trump’s immigration agenda. The Democratic-aligned Senate Majority PAC’s latest polling, shared exclusively with POLITICO and being sent to lawmakers, donors and campaigns Thursday, shows not only a growing number of likely voters who disapprove of ICE, but also a majority in favor of Democrats’ strategy of demands for reform <i>even if</i> it means a partial government shutdown, with 54 percent also saying they would blame the GOP and Trump for the shutdown and not accepting ICE reforms. These numbers are especially telling as the biggest shifts occur “among moderates, non-MAGA Republicans, and key swing voters,” the polling memo said.</p> 
<p>As former President Joe Biden and his administration officials left themselves electorally exposed on the issue, then-candidate Donald Trump exploited those vulnerabilities with vows to seal the southern border and enact the largest deportation campaign in American history. But his enforcement actions have focused less on the border, which polls show most voters approve of, and more on the nation’s interior, drawing the ire of Trump-curious commentators like the comedian and podcaster Joe Rogan and raising alarm among Republicans.</p> 
<p>“The president can feel, generally, that his policies at the border have been largely supported by a majority of Americans. But what he’s doing inside the border seems to be not working,” <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/republican-mayors-trump-ice-00754195" target="_blank">said Oklahoma City Mayor David Holt</a>, a Republican who runs one of the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/short-reads/2014/08/08/chart-of-the-week-the-most-liberal-and-conservative-big-cities/" target="_blank">most conservative large cities in the nation</a> but backed Kamala Harris in 2024.</p> 
<p>One longtime Republican strategist who worked on presidential campaigns in 2020 and 2024, granted anonymity to candidly assess Republicans’ standing, expressed consternation over ICE’s deployment to a place like Minnesota, far from the southern border.</p> 
<p>“When I think of immigrants broadly, I don’t think of Minnesota,” the strategist said. “People want to see, like, okay, ‘I voted for taking criminal illegal immigrants and getting them out of the country. I want to see criminal illegal immigrants taken out of the country. I want to see more miles of wall being built.’ I feel like we talked about the wall weekly in Trump 1. I don't remember the last time we talked about the wall in Trump 2.”</p> 
<p>All of which raises an uncomfortable question for Republicans: Is the party in danger of ceding one of its best issues back to Democrats?</p> 
<p>“Immigration used to be a winning issue for Democrats back when we made clear we took enforcement seriously,” said Adam Jentleson, the former chief of staff to Sen. John Fetterman (D-Penn.) and top aide to former Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid (D-Nev.), who commissioned the Searchlight polling shared with Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer as he shuttled toward another potential shutdown over the issue. “It can be a winning issue for us again if we are smart about how we handle this.</p> 
<p>Sen. Ruben Gallego (D-Ariz.), a rising Democratic star who won his seat in 2024 at the same time Trump carried his state, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/ruben-gallego-democrats-latino-senator-ab9b48c24fcdbc4eb54bcddc48a82a66" target="_blank">campaigned in key Latino areas</a> for his party in New Jersey, Virginia and Miami’s mayoral elections last year, and who has launched his own <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/12/ruben-gallego-immigration-border-security-plan-00341242" target="_blank">border security and immigration platform</a>, told POLITICO his party has to build trust with swing voters.</p> 
<p>“We have to be the party that talks about professional, legal enforcement of our immigration laws with an understanding that criminals need to be deported and the border needs to be secure, and that we have to move to a sane compromise when it comes to immigration reform,” Gallego said.</p> 
<p>It wasn’t so long ago that was the reality: As recently as 2013, under then-President Barack Obama, <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2013/07/poll-democrats-winning-on-immigration-024052" target="_blank">the majority of Americans</a> said the Democratic Party better represents their feelings on immigration than Republicans did.</p> 
<p>What does the GOP risk ahead of the midterms if it doesn’t find a better message?</p> 
<p>“I think you'll see the numbers continue to suffer,” the longtime GOP strategist said.</p> 
<p>Gallego, who has called for White House Deputy Chief of Staff Stephen Miller to be fired, said that gives Democrats an opportunity.</p> 
<p>“If I was the Republicans right now, I would be very worried about what the future looks like in terms of elections, and Stephen Miller may have basically created a political tsunami among voters, both Latino voters as well as just kind of moderate voters,” Gallego said. “That's going to come back and haunt them, going into the 2026 election.”</p> 
<p><i>Alec Hernández, Lisa Kashinsky and Ali Bianco contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Our cities are no longer safe’: GOP mayors condemn Trump immigration enforcement</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/republican-mayors-trump-ice-00754195</link>
      <description>At a gathering of mayors in Washington on Wednesday, Republicans criticized the White House’s recent immigration crackdown as chaotic and damaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0718-d9a8-a7be-879a57290000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 19:46:57 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5c/1c/f4f80d5d43a4abfd6d63d8a8415e/us-conference-of-mayors-76264.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Kevin Wolf</media:credit>
        <media:title>Oklahoma City Mayor David Holt, right, speaks during a panel discussion with Fresno, Calif. Mayor Jerry Dyer, left, and Omaha, Neb. Mayor John Ewing, Jr. during the 94th Winter Meeting of the U.S. Conference of Mayors on Wednesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5c/1c/f4f80d5d43a4abfd6d63d8a8415e/us-conference-of-mayors-76264.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Lisa Kashinsky and Natalie Fertig</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Lisa Kashinsky and Natalie Fertig</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A number of Republican mayors are condemning the Trump administration’s hardline immigration enforcement tactics in Minnesota, as they call on the president to pull back from Minneapolis and worry their cities might be next.</p> 
<p>“It’s roiling the country,” Oklahoma City Mayor David Holt told POLITICO. “We're all sort of feeling the angst of our residents and the fear that our city will be next and that chaos is going to inevitably creep across the entire country.”</p> 
<p>Fresno, California, Mayor Jerry Dyer said in an interview that “too much damage has been done” with the crackdown and “the trust in communities has been lost.”</p> 
<p>And Burnsville, Minnesota, Mayor Elizabeth Kautz, warned that the agency’s current tactics meant “our cities are no longer safe.”</p> 
<p>The remarks from the trio of moderate-leaning GOP mayors who have broken with Trump in the past came at the annual gathering of the nonpartisan U.S. Conference of Mayors, held blocks from the White House. Holt chairs the conference.</p> 
<p>The Republican leaders’ calls for Trump to deescalate after the fatal shootings of two Minnesotans by federal agents show the GOP’s deepening fissures over the administration’s aggressive immigration agenda, even as the mayors and Republicans broadly offered support for the president’s overall goal. And their alarm comes as ICE ramps up operations in other states, including Arizona and Maine.</p> 
<p>The escalating immigration enforcement crackdown hung over the annual gathering, dominating conversations among leaders who are scrambling to prepare their cities for ICE sweeps and allay anxious and outraged residents.</p> 
<p>Dyer on Wednesday said federal agents need to receive more training in deescalation tactics — a practice that the Fresno mayor, who served in law enforcement for 40 years, including 18 as the city's police chief, said is integral for local police departments. He also said federal agencies should only work in communities where they have the cooperation of local leaders.</p> 
<p>“I don't believe that agencies should be deployed into cities against the will of local government and without the cooperation of local law enforcement,” Dyer said. “That’s a recipe for disaster, and I believe that's somewhat of what we're seeing today.”</p> 
<p>And he urged other Republicans to speak out against federal immigration agents’ recent tactics.</p> 
<p>“The Republican Party in general cannot rubber-stamp everything a party does or this administration does,” Dyer said. “Too many people today are turning a blind eye when they should be speaking out in opposition.”</p> 
<p>It wasn’t just big-city GOP mayors who were concerned with the administration’s response: Kautz’s town of 64,000 people is in Minneapolis’ south suburbs.</p> 
<p>Kautz, who said she now carries her passport in public, called for ICE to use judicial warrants, arguing that while violent criminals need to be off the street, it needs to be done “through proper channels, the rule of law, due process [and rooted] in the Constitution.” In Minnesota, “that is not our experience.”</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/poll-republicans-ice-immigration-deportations-00744668" target="_blank">new POLITICO poll</a> found that more than 1 in 3 Trump voters said that while they support the goals of his immigration agenda, they disapprove of the way he is implementing it.</p> 
<p>Holt, who runs one of the most conservative large cities in the U.S. but backed Kamala Harris over Trump in 2024, warned that Trump’s interior enforcement was a failure.</p> 
<p>“The president can feel, generally, that his policies at the border have been largely supported by a majority of Americans,” Holt said. “But what he's doing inside the border seems to be not working.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats could face an uphill Electoral College after 2030, new projections show</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/2030-electoral-college-projections-00750488</link>
      <description>Two early Electoral College projections show big shifts in the presidential battlefield.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01d0-d452-a99e-69fecdfd0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/eb/62/6f48f00d41689fb9be8a6e277c38/election-2020-protests-philadelphia-89247.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">John Minchillo/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A supporter of President-elect Joe Biden holds up his mobile phone to display the electoral college map outside the Philadelphia Convention Center, Saturday, Nov. 7, 2020, in Philadelphia.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/eb/62/6f48f00d41689fb9be8a6e277c38/election-2020-protests-philadelphia-89247.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats could face a gloomy Electoral College atmosphere next decade, according to new population estimates released Tuesday that show red-leaning states like Texas and Florida making major gains and California as a big loser.</p> 
<p>By combining <a href="https://www.census.gov/newsroom/press-releases/2026/population-growth-slows.html" target="_blank">the census bureau’s new state population estimates</a> for 2025 with previous years’ data, experts quickly projected the number of House seats — and Electoral College votes — states will gain or lose after the 2030 Census in the process known as reapportionment. And while those projections differ slightly, they all had bad news for Democrats: GOP-leaning states will gain electoral power and Democratic-leaning states will lose it if the trends continue.</p> 
<p>While Joe Biden would still have won in 2020 under the estimates, two projected maps show Democrats would no longer be able to win the Electoral College by relying solely on the Rust Belt battleground states.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/RedistrictNet/status/2016161865550659995" target="_blank">One of the estimates from Jonathan Cervas</a>, a redistricting and apportionment expert at Carnegie Mellon University, shows seat changes across the map, with Florida and Texas gaining four seats each, while California, New York and Illinois collectively lose eight.</p> 
<p>Georgia, North Carolina, Arizona, Utah and Idaho would all pick up one more seat, while Oregon, Minnesota, Wisconsin, Pennsylvania and Rhode Island lose one seat.</p> 
<p><a href="https://x.com/amerredistrict/status/2016151110235423153?s=46&amp;t=Gn4QXkIC7rHYnzzbMwY5Vg" target="_blank">Another map</a> from the GOP-aligned American Redistricting Project shows less seats shifting overall, with Texas gaining four seats, Florida gaining two, and Georgia, North Carolina, Arizona, Utah and Idaho gaining one. Under that estimate, California loses four seats, and New York, Illinois, Oregon, Minnesota, Wisconsin, Pennsylvania and Rhode Island all lose one seat.</p> 
<p>In both models, the shifts — which are significant in both projections given the already razor-thin margins in the House — stand to alter the battlefield for the 2032 presidential campaign and the fight for the House down-ballot.</p> 
<p>While the changes are “not going to lock in” GOP wins, the map is certainly shifting in their favor, said Adam Kincaid, president of the National Republican Redistricting Trust.</p> 
<p>“The Rust Belt states and Sun Belt states will continue to be the battleground,” he said. “The difference is that Republicans will be able to win the White House without a single Rust Belt state, whereas Democrats would have to sweep the Rust Belt and win in the Sun Belt.”</p> 
<p>The new maps are mostly in line <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/newsletter/2025/07/an-early-look-at-2030-reapportionment-00438139" target="_blank">with earlier estimates from Democrats</a>, who at the time presented changes to Florida and Texas specifically as the “result of population growth specifically in diverse, metropolitan, Democratic-leaning urban centers.”</p> 
<p>That is leaving the party with some tempered optimism about their fate in the Electoral College and the battle for House control.</p> 
<p>“As these folks are moving, they're bringing their politics with them,” said Marina Jenkins, executive director of the National Democratic Redistricting Committee. “And so I think it's not necessarily safe to assume that those population shifts don't or aren't able to impact statewide results.”</p> 
<p>But not everyone in the party saw good news between the lines. Plus, Democrats have long hoped population shifts in red states like Texas and Florida would lead to gains for the party, but so far that wish has not materialized.</p> 
<p>David Hogg, the former DNC vice chair who has embarked on a mission to primary members of his party that he believes are not doing enough to stand up to President Donald Trump, said the estimates prove that the party must invest further in the South.</p> 
<p>“If we don’t start building infrastructure in the South … we can kiss goodbye any chance of winning the white house in the 2030s,” <a href="https://x.com/davidhogg111/status/2016193134196129843?s=20" target="_blank">Hogg said on X</a>.</p> 
<p>The shifts also amplify fears from Democrats that Republicans will try and gerrymander urban areas and lessen those voters’ impact in House races, something Jenkins said is designed to “dilute the voices of these communities.”</p> 
<p>“We're going to find in states like Texas is that as those communities grow, it's going to become harder and harder for [Republicans] to gerrymander their way out of the fact that those people live there, and they're real people,” she said.</p> 
<p>Jenkins said it’s important to understand the projections “in the context of this effort to gerrymander the country into oblivion,” pointing to the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/the-redistricting-fight-that-dominated-american-politics-in-2025-00703193" target="_blank">White House-initiated mid-cycle redistricting effort</a> that swept the country last year.</p> 
<p>But both parties acknowledge there’s still plenty of time for populations to shift even more before the numbers are locked in during the 2030 Census.</p> 
<p>Ahead of the 2020 Census, reapportionment projections were dire for Democratic-controlled states. But the shifts ended up <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/04/26/census-house-apportionment-for-next-decade-484653" target="_blank">being less dramatic than anticipated</a> — in part due to an undercount of Black, Hispanic and Native American people, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/03/10/2020-census-undercount-black-people-hispanics-native-americans-00016138" target="_blank">the Census Bureau acknowledged</a>, that was partially triggered by the extraordinarily difficult task of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/04/27/census-latinos-count-484846" target="_blank">counting every American during a pandemic</a>.</p> 
<p>“It's basically halftime,” Kincaid said. “We've got 5 years to go. A lot can change.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Third ‘No Kings’ nationwide protest planned for March</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/no-kings-protest-march-00750265</link>
      <description>“This lawless police force is committing crimes all across the country,” said Ezra Levin, co-founder of Indivisible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0110-d9a8-a7be-8792d2370000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/31/d6/fa91ba07469abfc7420ae049a441/us-protests-portland-94609.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jenny Kane/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>People prepare to march during a "No Kings" protest in Portland, Oregon, on Saturday, Oct. 18, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/31/d6/fa91ba07469abfc7420ae049a441/us-protests-portland-94609.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The group behind the nationwide “No Kings” protests are planning their fourth demonstration of President Donald Trump’s second term — and are anticipating even greater turnout than their earlier rallies.</p> 
<p>Ezra Levin, a rally organizer and the co-founder of the progressive group Indivisible, said in an interview that the planned third “No Kings” protest on March 28 is in response to a “secret police force terrorizing American communities.”</p> 
<p>“It is unfortunately not a surprise to us that this lawless police force is committing crimes all across the country and that people are standing up to it,” said Levin. “Our goal is safeguarding American democracy, protecting our communities and the people who are under threat by this regime.”</p> 
<p>Nationwide protests have become a staple of both of President Donald Trump’s terms. Indivisible estimated 3 million protesters turned out for its “Hands Off” rally in April 2025, while 5 million showed up in June as part of the first “No Kings” protest and 7 million for the second “No Kings” demonstration in October.</p> 
<p>Organizers said they are aiming for nearly 9 million people to turn out in March.</p> 
<p>Levin said that Indivisible had been planning the upcoming protest since before Renee Good was shot and killed by an immigration officer in Minnesota earlier this month, calling <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-trump-administration-dueling-accounts-minneapolis-shooting-00745811?utm_campaign=mb&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_source=morning_brew" target="_blank">what is unfolding in the Midwestern state</a> is “tragic and horrific.” A second person, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">Alex Pretti, was killed by Border Patrol agents</a> on Saturday not far from where Good died.</p> 
<p>Still, Levin said, it is “inspiring and gives me hope that while this regime and many political leaders even outside this regime are cowards or fascist sympathizers, people on the ground aren't putting up with it.”</p> 
<p>Trump and his GOP allies have not been fans of the demonstrations. Ahead of the October marches — which took place amid the government shutdown — Speaker Mike Johnson called <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/10/no-kings-protest-mike-johnson-00602705" target="_blank">them “hate America” rallies</a>, and Trump’s “war room” account posted a mocking picture of the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/18/no-kings-rallies-trump-washington-00613973" target="_blank">president wearing a crown</a>.</p> 
<p>Levin said the organizers are taking safety precautions, including holding de-escalation training sessions. On Monday, the group held a session on non-violent documentation techniques for the public. And at the last “No Kings” protest, Levin said Indivisible trained thousands of volunteer marshals, emphasizing non-violent principles.</p> 
<p>The tactics have a proven track record, Levin argued, with <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/10/20/arrests-no-kings-new-york-austin-chicago-dc-san-diego-trump-administration-police" target="_blank">major cities reporting zero arrests</a> during the last “No Kings” demonstration.</p> 
<p>Still, Levin said, he can’t guarantee there aren’t risks to participating.</p> 
<p>“Based on how the regime is behaving, the fact of the matter is, everybody should worry about it,” he said. “I can't guarantee that there isn’t a risk involved to show up and exercise your constitutional rights. It's a terrible thing to have to say in 2026 in America, but it's the truth.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New polling memo urges Senate Dems to ‘play hardball’ on ICE</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/ice-polling-memo-searchlight-00751569</link>
      <description>The memo from the Searchlight Institute think tank, which was circulating among Senate Democrats, emphasizes reforming the agency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0285-d1ea-a5de-3285bb820000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c9/5d/04671d94432f9aa58c995d3abf6f/u-s-congress-84192.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.) calls on a reporter during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 13, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c9/5d/04671d94432f9aa58c995d3abf6f/u-s-congress-84192.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Adam Wren</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Adam Wren</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats should “play hardball” ahead of a looming partial government shutdown and use their “leverage to reform ICE,” according to a new <a href="https://www.searchlightinstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Memo-Play-Hardball-and-Use-Your-Leverage-to-Reform-ICE.pdf" target="_blank">polling memo</a> circulating among Democratic senators Tuesday.</p> 
<p>The polling, in the field January 23 to 26 during the height of public backlash to Alex Pretti’s killing in Minneapolis, found that 58 percent of likely midterm voters want ICE to be reined in. More voters prefer reforming ICE than the number who prefer eliminating the agency entirely by 30 percent to 19 percent, according to the survey shared first with POLITICO.</p> 
<p>“Voters want ICE to follow the law, and focus enforcement on people who pose a threat to public safety. They want to see tangible changes to ICE operations and oppose letting ICE detain U.S. citizens, enter homes without warrants, or fail to wear identifying uniforms,” according to the memo. “There is a desire for immigration enforcement that is lawful, reasonable, and effective. “</p> 
<p>The memo was written by Adam Jentleson, the former chief of staff to Sen. John Fetterman (D-Penn.) and top aide to former Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid (D-Nev.), for his organization the Searchlight Institute, which conducted the 1,502-person online survey alongside Tavern Research.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/03/dems-are-quietly-forming-a-think-tank-to-help-them-win-again-00381601" target="_blank">The influential new think tank</a> seeks to push the Democratic Party toward broadly popular positions, regardless of ideology. In the case of ICE, Jentleson writes, Democrats should embrace reforming, not abolishing, the agency.</p> 
<p>“Democrats should use their leverage to demand commonsense reforms to ICE that have the backing of broad bipartisan majorities of Americans,” Jentleson writes in the memo, which came across the desk of aides to Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer Tuesday and continued to make the rounds among Senate Democrats early Wednesday.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Schumer did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Searchlight’s latest survey finds that “bipartisan majorities of voters oppose ICE’s lawless tactics, including detaining U.S. citizens (73 percent), entering people’s homes without warrants (79 percent), and failing to wear clearly identifying uniforms (70 percent)”, according to the memo.</p> 
<p>The polling comes as Senate Democrats are <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/cuellar-dhs-blank-check-00749995" target="_blank">demanding to re-negotiate</a> a hulking DHS funding bill ahead of a Friday midnight deadline for a partial government shutdown, carving it off from a six-bill appropriations package.</p> 
<p>“This is likely to be their last major leverage point for several months at least if not for the rest of the year” to curtail the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown, Jentleson told POLITICO. “But there’s a larger reason, which is that the tragic events that have unfolded in Minneapolis have shocked the conscience of Americans and brought their attention to the horrible shit that ICE is doing. Those two things combined give them a lot of leverage at this moment.”</p> 
<p>Democratic likely midterm voters were split in the poll over how to change ICE, with 34 percent favoring reforming ICE and 33 percent wanting to get rid of it as an agency — meaning that it’s “a coin flip among Democrats,” Jentleson said. That indicates that in contested Democratic primaries, it’s not clear which side of that debate will have the edge with base voters.</p> 
<p>What’s clearer, he wrote in the memo, is that voters do support some degree of immigration enforcement. The memo notes that the view that “immigrants living in the U.S. illegally should not be deported” receives no more than 30 percent support among Democrats and young people, and even less among other groups.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats have embraced this push.</p> 
<p>Speaking on the Senate floor Tuesday, Schumer seemed to set the predicate for the partial shutdown, saying any administrative actions on ICE wouldn’t be enough and that “any fix should come from Congress. The public can’t trust the administration to do the right thing on its own and the Republicans and Democrats must work together to make that happen.”</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans face a Friday midnight deadline to avert a shutdown. GOP Sens. Thom Tillis and Lisa Murkowski have said that Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem should be fired. President Donald Trump acknowledged shaking up his border security leadership team Tuesday.</p> 
<p>“Senate Democrats should embrace this reality and use their leverage to achieve meaningful changes that rein in ICE’s abuses and refocus the agency on its critical law enforcement mission,” Jentleson writes.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RNC pushed Bovino’s false claims as talking points hours before his removal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/rnc-bovino-ice-talking-points-memo-00751117</link>
      <description>A new memo from the RNC reveals how the party wanted to frame the fallout over a second fatal shooting in Minnesota — but shows how quickly the messaging is changing in real time</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01e7-d1ea-a5de-31e71acc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:47:29 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/23/69/5c83203d48a4a561ee35d2e77a82/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-95123.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Angelina Katsanis/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>U.S. Border Patrol Cmdr. Gregory Bovino walks with federal agents outside a convenience store on Jan. 21, 2026, in Minneapolis.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/23/69/5c83203d48a4a561ee35d2e77a82/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-95123.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The RNC distributed talking points highlighting Border Patrol commander Greg Bovino’s false statements about the killing of Alex Pretti just hours before he was sidelined by President Donald Trump — a sign of how quickly the party’s messaging has shifted on the events in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-01f7-d9a8-a7be-87f729550001" target="_blank">The memo</a>, sent to party surrogates midday on Monday and obtained by POLITICO, encouraged Republicans to cast blame for the shooting on Democrats for “inciting protestors to attack and aggressively confront law enforcement in Minneapolis.” The talking points also delve into administration officials’ account of how the shooting took place, including Bovino’s Saturday comments that the U.S. citizen killed by immigration agents “wanted to do maximum damage and massacre law enforcement." The government’s initial account has been called into question by videos shot by witnesses as well as analyses conducted by The <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-federal-agents-video.html" target="_blank">New York Times</a>, The <a href="https://www.wsj.com/livecoverage/minneapolis-shooting-alex-pretti/card/wsj-visual-investigation-videos-contradict-u-s-account-of-minneapolis-shooting-lrNpSm80hhnrxVxEy7kO?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqeMfXHa-r5f_coUtyWU2TDX_pUwGzct7ciQYXf_QuPsBeDX-5YqhaQBv69a5x8%3D&amp;gaa_ts=69793983&amp;gaa_sig=DSspyLz-8HCs-CWTnsRr3TjzrIBrFPt1TzRmBugZwzesss81GIE8xUHvg0x1nkczT8b97u7hD1yc8-EZ9pRSsg%3D%3D" target="_blank">Wall Street Journal</a>, and others.</p> 
<p>The memo includes the talking point that “Agents attempted to disarm the individual as he violently resisted. Fearing for his life and the lives and safety of fellow officers, a Border Patrol agent fired defensive shots.” Video from the scene appears to contradict that statement.</p> 
<p>The whiplash between the RNC’s promotion of Bovino’s comments and his sudden removal shortly afterward from the federal operation in Minneapolis shows how the administration and other Republicans scrambled to contain the fallout from the shooting. A significant number of elected GOP officials have called for an official investigation into the matter, a rare and notable break with the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Immediately following the shooting on Saturday, high-profile administration officials like Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem publicly described Pretti, a 37-year-old nurse, as a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/leavitt-briefing-minneapolis-trump-walz-alex-pretti-00747495" target="_blank">“domestic terrorist.”</a></p> 
<p>By that evening, however, Trump was already more cautious in his description of what had transpired. <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/policy/trump-says-administration-is-reviewing-everything-about-minneapolis-shooting-a501f48e?gaa_at=eafs&amp;gaa_n=AWEtsqcZVoLjAgLS_LENGeVH-NWCqZFB9zgFqjGu85ixp9xYdgMDpDSXuPw2gtxFkd8%3D&amp;gaa_ts=69792383&amp;gaa_sig=nUi-HJXipOVQ2Rgqh7-IB_Dhu-dAq4sY2s6SwobYlLst1e3NtzUYThMdV4gHRtW4R2uldBGkMhRutTfX9moJxA%3D%3D" target="_blank">In an interview that day with The Wall Street Journal</a>, the president did not answer directly when asked whether the officer involved in the shooting did the right thing and said his administration is “reviewing everything.”</p> 
<p>Speaking at a restaurant in Iowa on Tuesday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/trump-pretti-shouldnt-have-been-carrying-a-gun-00750241" target="_blank">Trump said that he hadn’t heard the assessment</a> from Noem and others in his administration, such as deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller, that Pretti was a “domestic terrorist” or assassin, but said that “certainly he shouldn’t have been carrying a gun.” Pretti had a permit to carry a firearm, according to Minnesota officials.</p> 
<p>Monday’s talking points memo notably omits reference to any comments made by Noem since the shooting took place. While the White House has publicly stood behind Noem, administration allies have <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/kristi-noem-scrutiny-minneapolis-shootings-00748618" target="_blank">increasingly placed blame on the secretary’s handling of the chaotic crackdown in Minnesota</a> as calls among Democrats for her impeachment have grown. <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/thom-tillis-kristi-noem-fired-00750580" target="_blank">On Tuesday evening</a>, Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said Noem should be “out of a job,” while Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said she “should go.”</p> 
<p>Trump announced on Monday morning that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">border czar Tom Homan would go to Minneapolis</a> to oversee the administration’s immigration operation there, a move seen as an acknowledgement that DHS’s leadership had mishandled the situation. Hours later, Bovino had been removed from his post as commander at large, <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/2026/01/greg-bovino-demoted-minneapolis-border-patrol/685770/" target="_blank">according to The Atlantic</a>.</p> 
<p>Kiersten Pels, a spokesperson for the RNC, would not confirm the authenticity of the memo but echoed its overall sentiment in a written statement. “Democrats incited this violence by encouraging protesters to confront law enforcement,” she wrote. “Democrats are demonizing ICE and threatening to defund DHS instead of condemning attacks on officers – while President Trump and Republicans stand with law enforcement and public safety.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s approval rating on immigration has dropped significantly since he first came into office, with only 39% of Americans now approving of the president’s handling of immigration, according to a <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/trumps-immigration-approval-drops-record-low-reutersipsos-poll-finds-2026-01-26/" target="_blank">recent Reuters/Ipsos poll</a>. The high-profile shooting in Minneapolis, following the fatal shooting earlier this month of Renée Good in the city, has only brought more attention to the administration’s goal of a mass deportation.</p> 
<p>Democrats in the Senate have pledged to vote against funding DHS in a crucial vote later this week unless the bill is amended to add guardrails for the agency — and the RNC’s talking points seize on the potential for a partial government shutdown as well.</p> 
<p>“Now, Democrats are threatening to defund law enforcement later this week by refusing to pass a DHS funding bill,” the memo concludes.</p> 
<p>“While Democrats will stand in the way of ICE and law enforcement to defend terrorists and criminal aliens, President Trump and Republicans are working to keep our communities safe.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T20:48:09-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Janet Mills: Maine ‘will not be intimidated’ amid ongoing ICE surge</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/janet-mills-ice-raids-state-address-00751216</link>
      <description>The Maine governor delivered her annual address as immigrant enforcement surges in the state and she gears up for a Senate run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01fa-dabb-ad9c-3fffe7d00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:28:03 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d4/04/c7bfa20b481c83eedd260ece2fbf/20260127-janet-mills-sots.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jessica Piper/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Maine Gov. Janet Mills speaks during her State of the State address at the State House in Augusta, Maine, on Jan. 27, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d4/04/c7bfa20b481c83eedd260ece2fbf/20260127-janet-mills-sots.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper and Lisa Kashinsky</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>AUGUSTA, Maine — Gov. Janet Mills issued a dire warning in her annual address to state lawmakers Tuesday night: The federal immigration raids sweeping the state are part of an ongoing nationwide attack on democracy.</p> 
<p>The speech from Mills, who is a leading Democratic challenger to Republican Sen. Susan Collins, marks perhaps the most prominent example of how the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration raids have upended communities — and potentially electoral politics — around the country. The crackdown has become a political crisis for the White House in recent days following two fatal shootings by federal officers in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“Today, I say to the people of Maine: We will not be intimidated. We will not be silenced,” Mills said, to cheers from the Democratic side of the chamber. “And to anyone outside these halls, including any federal officials, I say: If you seek to harm Maine people, you will have to go through me first.”</p> 
<p>The Democratic governor’s defiant State of the State address on Tuesday came as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/ice-maine-dhs-trump-00740138" target="_blank">a sweeping ICE operation in Maine</a> has prompted widespread protests throughout the state since it began last week. The killing of a protester in Minneapolis by federal immigration officers this weekend has amplified those pressures — and the political stakes.</p> 
<p>Mills addressed the ICE operation directly in the opening of her speech, commending the “moral clarity” of Mainers who had risen to “protect their neighbors and their communities against federal agents who seek to intimidate and silence us.”</p> 
<p>Federal officials indicated Monday that <a href="https://www.mainepublic.org/immigration/2026-01-26/ice-says-its-arrested-more-than-200-people-since-last-week-in-maine-operation" target="_blank">more than 200 people had been arrested</a> in the immigrant enforcement action in Maine they’re calling Operation Catch of the Day. That effort has followed a pattern of surges in other localities under President Donald Trump’s aggressive revamped enforcement operations.</p> 
<p>Mills, who has made opposition to Trump a centerpiece of her Senate campaign, cast the immigration enforcement operation as part of a broader federal overreach that threatens American democracy in Tuesday’s speech — warning “the very idea of America is in peril.” She accused federal officials of arresting people not on “public safety grounds but based on quotas, on skin color, on accents, and religion and ethnic origin.”</p> 
<p>“For those who may be unconcerned by the federal government’s abuses of today, affecting our state, I only ask you to consider this — what happens when the federal government finds you to be the problem tomorrow?” Mills said, her voice rising and cracking with emotion in a departure from the more soft-spoken tone she had adopted while ticking through the policy points of her speech.</p> 
<p>Much of Mills’ speech was met with partisan reaction in the House chamber in Augusta, with some Republican lawmakers audibly pushing back at Mills’ notion that ICE activities amounted to an abuse of power. Earlier in her speech, Republican state Rep. Jim Thorne interrupted Mills’ call for the federal government to enact universal health care, suggesting it was out of place for a State of the State speech.</p> 
<p>Mills’ address to the legislature came days after <a href="https://www.maine.gov/governor/mills/news/governor-janet-mills-statement-following-another-killing-minnesota-hands-federal-agents-2026" target="_blank">she asked for a meeting with Trump</a> to call for a withdrawal of ICE agents from Maine. The Maine governor famously confronted Trump at the Oval Office last year over his administration’s intent to withhold federal funding from Maine over the state’s allowance of transgender students’ participation in youth sports.</p> 
<p>The politics of Trump’s deportation campaign have rapidly evolved in the wake of two shootings in Minnesota, putting ICE at the forefront of both the Democratic primary between Mills and political newcomer Graham Platner, and their efforts to unseat Collins.</p> 
<p>Collins — who has conflicted with the Trump administration more than most Republicans — <a href="https://www.mainepublic.org/politics/2026-01-27/susan-collins-asks-dhs-to-pause-immigration-enforcement-surge-in-maine-and-minnesota" target="_blank">told Maine Public</a> on Tuesday that she had asked Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem to pause the immigration enforcement surge in both Maine and Minnesota, calling it sweeping and indiscriminate. Those detained in Maine have included a corrections officer trainee who the Cumberland County sheriff <a href="https://www.mainepublic.org/courts-and-crime/2026-01-22/cumberland-county-sheriff-kevin-joyce-denounces-actions-by-ice-agents-in-maine" target="_blank">said had a legal work permit</a>.</p> 
<p>Mills has called on Collins to join with Democrats in holding up DHS funding until ICE changes course. Minutes before her speech, she <a href="https://x.com/JanetMillsforME/status/2016278711759253867?s=20" target="_blank">castigated Collins</a> on social media for <a href="https://x.com/JanetMillsforME/status/2016299356584890596?s=20" target="_blank">not calling for Noem’s ouster</a> and for “pushing to give the agency more funding without any accountability.” Collins oversees ICE’s purse strings as the Senate’s top appropriator, and she has advocated for passing the DHS funding bill as a Saturday shutdown deadline looms, saying it includes new guardrails for ICE such as body cameras and training and would fund other key agencies such as FEMA and the Coast Guard.</p> 
<p>The Democratic governor has also faced criticism from her left, with Platner attacking her Monday for her handling of a bill last year that sought to limit law enforcement cooperation with federal immigration authorities.</p> 
<p>Platner blasted Mills in an interview Monday for letting the bill idle, saying the governor “stymied the state’s ability to prepare” for the surge of federal immigration agents that “many in the immigrant rights community and the immigrant community knew … was coming” by preventing the law from taking effect sooner.</p> 
<p>Mills allowed the bill to become law without her signature in December, which means it does not officially take effect until after the end of this year’s legislative session. However, the Portland Press Herald <a href="https://www.pressherald.com/2026/01/21/a-new-anti-ice-law-isnt-in-effect-yet-maine-state-police-are-already-following-it/" target="_blank">reported earlier this month</a> that Maine’s public safety commissioner had implemented a directive to immediately comply with the law’s provisions.</p> 
<p>Platner dismissed her escalating rhetoric against ICE as politically convenient.</p> 
<p>“For the governor now to kind of just read the tea leaves and realize that people are actually really angry about this and want to see action, and then suddenly be like ‘I’m fighting this tooth and nail’ while not even fighting tooth and nail … yeah, that’s going to be a pretty clear distinction for the voters of Maine,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T18:32:33-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Virginia state court blocks Democrats’ redistricting push</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/virginia-redistricting-blocked-court-ruling-00750060</link>
      <description>The ruling is a major setback for Democrats’ efforts to redraw the lines in the state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0152-d452-a99e-69fea57c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:19:44 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b1/27/17417f2b4032af94d8236dd2b98a/election-2019-redistricting-45464.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Matthew Barakat/AP Photo</media:credit>
        <media:title>A mobile billboard urges voters to cast ballots for Democrats outside Centreville High School in Clifton, Va. on Nov. 5, 2019.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b1/27/17417f2b4032af94d8236dd2b98a/election-2019-redistricting-45464.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Andrew Howard and Brakkton Booker</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Andrew Howard and Brakkton Booker</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A Virginia state court blocked Democrats’ plans to redistrict this year, a blow to the party’s hopes of redrawing the state’s congressional lines ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>Jack Hurley Jr., a judge on the Tazewell County circuit court, ruled that Democrats did <a href="https://www.virginiascope.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/CL25001582-00-PO-95_Certified.pdf?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email" target="_blank"><u>not follow the right procedure</u></a> to approve the proposed constitutional amendment that would allow for the last-minute redraw of the state’s lines.</p> 
<p>Democrats are expected to appeal the decision. But the ruling is still a major loss for the party in the ongoing mid-decade redistricting fight, and one that could — if ultimately upheld — block the party from picking up as many as four seats in next year’s midterms.</p> 
<p>Democrats in the Legislature first passed a measure to take up redistricting <a href="https://virginiamercury.com/2025/10/31/virginia-senate-approves-mid-decade-redistricting-amendment-in-party-line-vote/" target="_blank"><u>in October of last year</u></a>, utilizing a special session left open by then-Gov. Glenn Youngkin. Lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/virginia-redistricting-legislature-00733644" target="_blank"><u>took up the issue again in January</u></a>, finalizing the plan to put the issue before voters ahead of the midterms.</p> 
<p>But Hurley said using the still-open special session was not allowed because early voting in last year’s elections had already begun, and state law requires the Legislature to pass proposed constitutional amendments both before and after an election. Hurley also ruled that the proposed constitutional amendment was not properly noticed in state courts.</p> 
<p>The judge also noted that lawmakers in the special session passed a procedural resolution along party lines, with the Democrat-controlled legislature delivering the decisive votes for the resolution’s passage. Because lawmakers did not vote unanimously, as is required under the Legislature’s own rules, and did not pass it by a two-thirds Senate majority, it was a violation of the rules governing a special session.</p> 
<p>“Certinaly, both houses of the Commonwealth’s legislature are required to follow their own rules and resolutions,” Hurley wrote.</p> 
<p>The Republican plaintiffs in the suit issued a statement praising the court’s ruling, calling it a “decisive victory for the rule of law” but also noting this legal challenge was not about partisanship, rather the process the majority used in attempting to rewrite Virginia’s Constitution.</p> 
<p>"The court confirmed that Democrat legislative leaders unlawfully expanded a Special Session, violated their own rules, and attempted to force through a redistricting constitutional amendment while Virginians were already voting,” said Del. Terry Kilgore, the top Republican in the Virginia House, state Sen. Minority Leader Ryan McDougle and former Rep. Eric Cantor (R-Va.) said in a joint statement Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Virginia had been seen as the crown jewel in Democrats' redistricting fight, especially as state Republicans in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/desantis-florida-redistricting-special-session-00713882" target="_blank"><u>GOP-led Florida eye midcycle redistricting</u></a> later this year. Currently in Virginia, Democrats control six congressional seats and Republicans hold five. Virginia Democrats, had been forging ahead with their plans to unveil a proposed map by their self-imposed deadline of Jan. 31, with the goal of holding a special election to approve the maps in spring.</p> 
<p>Democrats strongly criticized Hurley’s ruling.</p> 
<p>“This is a clear attempt to confuse voters and block them from having a say,” said Kéren Charles Dongo, who is heading Virginians for Fair Elections, the Democrat-affiliated group that launched this month to urge the state's voters to pass a pending ballot measure. “We’re prepared for what comes next, and Virginians deserve both the right to vote and the chance to level the playing field.”</p> 
<p>Spokespeople for the top Democrats in the Virginia legislature, state Sen. Majority Leader Scott Surovell and state House Speaker Don Scott, did not respond to requests for comment on whether the ruling will impact the release of their proposed maps.</p> 
<p>But in a joint statement along with other top Virginia Democrats on Tuesday, the group struck a defiant tone and promised to continue with plans to redraw maps, suggesting the ruling was but a minor blip in their quest to deliver what could be a 10-1 map that favors their party.</p> 
<p>“Nothing that happened today will dissuade us from continuing to move forward and put this matter directly to the voters,” the Democratic lawmakers said. “We will be appealing this ruling immediately and we expect to prevail.”</p> 
<p>Julie Merz, who heads up the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, suggested the court overreached. </p> 
<p>"This rogue decision is a disappointing, but temporary setback issued by a lower court that will be immediately appealed — where we're confident it will be overturned," Merz said in a statement. "The order issued today has no constitutional basis, but is instead a desperate attempt to keep electoral power out of the hands of Virginia voters."<br></p>CORRECTION: This story has been updated to correct the spelling of Kéren Charles Dongo's name.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T13:35:55-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Philip Glass pulls new symphony from Kennedy Center</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/philip-glass-symphony-kennedy-center-00749464</link>
      <description>He joins a growing list of artists who have canceled performances at the beleaguered institution this year.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-008d-d452-a99e-69ff067f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:15:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/47/2d/49940ec34b348b47795ef035ec08/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2041954554">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Ilya S. Savenok/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Bowen Yang, left, and Philip Glass are seen backstage during the 37th Annual Tibet House US Benefit Concert at Carnegie Hall on Feb. 26, 2024, in New York City.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/47/2d/49940ec34b348b47795ef035ec08/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2041954554" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Famed American composer Philip Glass on Tuesday announced he is pulling the premiere of his newest symphony, titled “Lincoln,” from the Kennedy Center, becoming the latest performer to cut ties with the beleaguered institution since its takeover by President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>“Symphony No. 15 is a portrait of Abraham Lincoln, and the values of the Kennedy Center today are in direct conflict with the message of the Symphony,” Glass said <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DUBSBMejT_5/?igsh=MTM5NGVmcXh4YnYzZg==" target="_blank">in a post on social media</a>. “Therefore, I feel an obligation to withdraw this Symphony premiere from the Kennedy Center under its current leadership.”</p> 
<p>He joins a growing list of artists who have canceled performances at the Kennedy Center since Trump’s overhaul of Washington’s premier arts center. Grammy winner Renee Fleming canceled performances set for May, <a href="https://www.kennedy-center.org/nso/home/2025-2026/gaffigan/" target="_blank">the institution announced on its website</a>. More performers, including banjo player Béla Fleck and singer Sonia De Los Santos, as well as groups such as the Martha Graham Dance Company and the Seattle Children’s Theater, have also canceled planned shows.</p> 
<p>Trump has made rebranding the Kennedy Center a priority since returning to the White House early last year. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/07/donald-trump-kennedy-center-014498" target="_blank">axed several members from the center’s board</a> and installed himself as chair in February 2025, later bringing on longtime ally Richard <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/10/trump-ric-grenell-kennedy-center-00203484" target="_blank">Grenell to serve as interim executive director</a>.</p> 
<p>In December, the newly reformed Kennedy Center’s board voted to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/trump-kennedy-center-00698140" target="_blank">add the president’s name</a> to the building. One lawmaker, Rep. Joyce Beatty (D-Ohio), an ex officio member of the board, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/23/kennedy-center-lawsuit-trump-00704327" target="_blank">sued in protest</a>.</p> 
<p>Trump has also taken a personal interest in a refurbishment of the Center, including overseeing details <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115787817857959030" target="_blank">down to the theater’s armrests</a>.</p> 
<p>Glass, 88, is one of the country’s most celebrated living composers, <a href="https://www.eno.org/discover-opera/articles/the-beginners-guide-to-philip-glass/" target="_blank">an early pioneer of minimalism</a> in classical music and famous in part for scores in films such as 2002’s "The Hours" and "The Truman Show," starring Jim Carrey.</p> 
<p>“We have no place for politics in the arts, and those calling for boycotts based on politics are making the wrong decision," Roma Daravi, the institution's vice president of public relations, said in a statement. "We have not cancelled a single show. Leftist activists are pushing artists to cancel but the public wants artists to perform and create—not cancel under pressure from political insiders that benefit from creating division.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How a Democratic heavyweight is using AI in the midterms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/american-bridge-opposition-research-ai-00747243</link>
      <description>American Bridge 21st Century is publishing its research for everyone to see ahead of the midterms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc04-d452-a99b-fdfea31b0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/da/1f/59b5d43848958d4f1d12f634434c/gettyimages-1230110704-1.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Al Drago/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>American Bridge released opposition research on President Donald Trump online in 2020. They have bigger plans for the midterms.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/da/1f/59b5d43848958d4f1d12f634434c/gettyimages-1230110704-1.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A Democratic opposition research powerhouse is putting massive troves of its work product online ahead of the midterms. And it’s using artificial intelligence to help everyone from campaigns to podcasters figure out how to navigate it.</p> 
<p>The project from American Bridge 21st Century, shared first with POLITICO, reflects an expansion of its efforts ahead of the 2026 midterms — as well as the evolving nature of political campaigning, including oppo research, in an increasingly fragmented media environment.</p> 
<p>“Swing voters are generally speaking getting their information very ambiently,” American Bridge President Pat Dennis said in an interview. </p> 
<p>A challenge in recent election cycles, he said, has not been a lack of opposition research, but rather how to best convey it when more voters are getting political news from podcasts, social media influencers or group chats. “If people can’t find it or read it, it’s no good,” Dennis said.</p> 
<p>The new tool, <a href="https://research-books.com/" target="_blank">titled Research Books</a>, is a public-facing website featuring opposition research on dozens of Republican candidates in races that American Bridge has identified as crucial to deciding control of Congress. It also includes select statewide candidates.</p> 
<p>Pages for each candidate feature messaging around key votes, candidate-specific research and — in some races — videos from Democratic trackers and sample media based on the oppo that closely resemble campaign ads.</p> 
<p>It also includes an AI-powered search tool that aims to bring together different sources about a candidate into cohesive messaging. (The AI agent only probes the super PAC’s internal database, not external sources or the wider internet.) </p> 
<p>Results from the search link back to original sources, which include news articles, videos and public records. The tool also integrates with other external large language model platforms such as ChatGPT.</p> 
<p>The notion of publishing opposition research files online, rather than keeping them closely held by party operatives for strategic deployment, is not entirely new for American Bridge. Ahead of the 2020 election, the group <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/08/07/american-bridge-trump-oppo-book-392536" target="_blank">posted 1,043 pages of opposition research</a> about President Donald Trump online for use by other Democratic groups. </p> 
<p>Sharing such research publicly is a way for super PACs to avoid running afoul of campaign finance laws that prohibit direction coordination.</p> 
<p>Because the new research tool is publicly available online, it could similarly be used by Democratic campaigns or other outside groups — though American Bridge hopes the uptake is broader than that, including among influencers and voters.</p> 
<p>For its initial public rollout, Research Books includes 15 GOP House incumbents in seats Democrats are hoping to flip this year, along with Republican Senate candidates in four seats Democrats are trying to flip, as well as Georgia, where Democratic Sen. Jon Ossoff is seeking reelection.</p> 
<p>The initial list also includes 15 candidates for governor or attorney general in key states like Arizona, Michigan, Nevada, Pennsylvania, Georgia, New Hampshire and Iowa.</p> 
<p>The inclusion of attorney general candidates, newer territory for American Bridge, reflects in part the greater role that they have played in suing the Trump administration, Dennis said. He expects the tool to include more races and candidates as the midterms near, with the super PAC seeking to help Democrats cast a broad net.</p> 
<p>“There are times where opposition research can fundamentally reshape a race, so we prefer to take an expansive view on this,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klobuchar delays governor campaign launch as Border Patrol killing upends Minnesota</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/klobuchar-delays-governor-campaign-launch-as-border-patrol-killing-upends-minnesota-00748621</link>
      <description>Before Alex Pretti’s death, Sen. Amy Klobuchar had planned to launch her gubernatorial campaign Monday, two people tell POLITICO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fcd5-d452-a99b-fdff189d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:40:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e2/4c/fc15baf64402b42605584a2ec926/u-s-congress-36790.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Amy Klobuchar (D-Minn.) speaks during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol on Dec. 11, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e2/4c/fc15baf64402b42605584a2ec926/u-s-congress-36790.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Amy Klobuchar planned to officially launch her gubernatorial campaign on Monday, but has delayed it in the wake of the fatal shooting of a protester by immigration agents in Minneapolis over the weekend, according to two people familiar with the Minnesota Democrat’s plans.</p> 
<p>The senator instead spent Monday morning speaking to White House officials, urging deescalation and pushing to get the administration to end its immigration crackdown in her state, according to a third person, who is close to the senator and, like the others, was granted anonymity to describe private conversations.</p> 
<p>Her decision to wait on her campaign launch comes amid weeks of turmoil in Minnesota that further escalated over the weekend when Border Patrol agents on Saturday fatally shot Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old intensive care unit nurse and American citizen.</p> 
<p>Over the last two days, Klobuchar has been meeting with city and state leaders, strategizing with Senate colleagues over Department of Homeland Security funding and calling Trump administration officials, according to the third person, who said Klobuchar’s “focus is on de-escalating the situation and getting ICE out of Minnesota. There's not time for politics today.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar’s nascent gubernatorial campaign has run headlong into a national crisis, another twist for a campaign that started under unusual circumstances. Earlier this month, Democratic Gov. Tim Walz unexpectedly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/tim-walz-out-minnesota-00710541" target="_blank"><u>dropped his reelection bid</u></a> for a third term, as a swirling fraud scandal threatened to engulf his campaign, and met with Klobuchar about running for the office herself. Since then, two American citizens have been killed by federal immigration agents, thrusting Klobuchar into the center of a battle on an issue for which she’s traditionally cut a moderate profile.</p> 
<p>“Regardless of what [campaign] Klobuchar is considering, this is what I’d expect from her, she’s been the leader in this state,” said Democratic Minnesota state Sen. Grant Hauschild. “We’re facing unprecedented circumstances of federal overreach and harm to our communities, and she’s stepped up, being present on the ground and fighting in Congress.”</p> 
<p>The two people who described her changed launch plans said they expect the senator to formally launch before next Tuesday, when the state’s party precinct caucus kicks off. Klobuchar <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/klobuchar-files-paperwork-minnesota-governor-00741649" target="_blank"><u>already filed paperwork with the state’s campaign finance board</u></a> last week, allowing her to begin raising funds ahead of an expected bid.</p> 
<p>Pretti’s killing also shook up the GOP side of the Minnesota governors’ race. Chris Madel, an attorney who launched his campaign as a Republican late last year, announced on Monday he would be dropping out, calling the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement tactics “wrong” and “an unmitigated disaster.”</p> 
<p>“I cannot support the national Republican-stated retribution on the citizens of our state, nor can I count myself a member of a party that would do so,” he said <a href="https://x.com/CWMadel/status/2015783448091283559?s=20" target="_blank"><u>in a video posted to social media</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Klobuchar is not expected to face a serious Democratic opponent when she enters the gubernatorial race, giving her some breathing room on both her announcement timeline and on her stance on immigration. Minnesota Attorney General Keith Ellison, a well-known progressive who was considered a potential candidate, confirmed he would not be running for the job last week.</p> 
<p>“What you hear from Klobuchar is, ‘ICE needs to get out of here,’ and I don’t think she needs to say more than that [because] without a primary challenger, I don’t think she’ll have to change her position on it,” said a Minnesota Democratic strategist, granted anonymity to discuss the issue candidly. “She’s smart, she’s careful and she’s cautious, and she knows how to win suburban and independent voters.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar has always cut a moderate profile. She rose up in Hennepin County as its prosecutor before running for Senate. During her presidential campaign in 2020, Klobuchar rejected calls for “abolishing ICE,” drawing fire from immigration rights advocates groups in that race, and instead called for reforms of the agency.</p> 
<p>When asked during <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/video/amy-klobuchar-says-ice-is-making-us-less-safe-after-another-fatal-mn-shooting-full-interview-256544325570" target="_blank"><u>an interview on NBC’s “Meet the Press”</u></a> on Sunday whether she supported abolishing ICE, Klobuchar said “we’re always going to have some immigration enforcement in this country, and border control.” But she called for the ICE operation to leave the state because “this agency has been functioning is completely against every tenet of law enforcement.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar ticked through several reforms she supports: “New leadership. Stopping these surges across the country, not just in my state. Training them like they were supposed to be trained. ... Mandatory body cameras. Stopping ramming into people's houses without a judicial warrant.”</p> 
<p>Those specifics could become part of Senate Democrats’ demands to give enough votes to pass a bill to fund the Department of Homeland Security and other parts of the government.</p> 
<p>Other Democrats have called for more aggressive policies, including abolishing ICE altogether. Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn) <a href="https://x.com/IlhanMN/status/2015544841405350257" target="_blank"><u>posted on X</u></a> that “voting NO on the DHS funding bill is the bare minimum,” adding that ICE is “beyond reform” and to “abolish it.”</p> 
<p>Klobuchar’s approach is once again drawing criticism from some immigrant-rights advocates. “I do not believe that's far enough,” said George Escobar, executive director of CASA, an immigration advocacy organization. “Unless we deal with the cancer that is causing this, which is ICE itself, and unless we have a comprehensive reform of that agency, which to us, means abolishing it, then honestly, this cycle is just going to repeat over and over again.”One Democratic consultant who has worked on Minnesota races warned that Klobuchar’s deliberative approach could hurt her. “She’s incredibly cautious, and this is not a cautious moment,” they said. “So far, she has not put her foot in it by being too moderate, but she’s also not been under a huge spotlight — and that will change with the gubernatorial run.”</p> 
<p>Nonetheless, Klobuchar’s messaging earned her praise from even some progressives. "I think she’s spot on,” said Mark Longabaugh, a former adviser to Sen Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.). “If you're going to step up and say that this organization needs to be restructured, or shut down and restructured, you also have to tie that to, ‘Listen, there is a legitimate law enforcement need here, both for customs and for border control.’”</p> 
<p>Most Minnesota Democrats don’t think Klobuchar will suddenly center anti-ICE messaging in her gubernatorial campaign. Interviews with a half dozen operatives and elected officials found they still expected the campaign to largely revolve around the economy. “Affordability is still going to be central to her work, along with protecting her state,” said the person close to Klobuchar. “She will always stand up for Minnesota on both.”</p> 
<p>“Who knows if, in 10 months, it will specifically be a part of the narrative or messaging,” said a Minnesota Democratic donor adviser. “But this isn’t going to go away any time soon … because we’re traumatized here.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T19:27:31-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Former Trail Blazer Chris Dudley to run again for governor of Oregon</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/chris-dudley-oregon-governor-00747694</link>
      <description>He came within 2 points when he ran in 2010.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fc31-d1ea-a5df-fcb566ec0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:02:30 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/64/fa/df60895a4d47ab770da0232758e1/oregon-governor.JPEG">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Greg Wahl-Stephens/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Oregon Republican gubernatorial candidate Chris Dudley, center, thanks supporters as his family, from left, Charles Dudley, Emma Dudley, Sam Dudley, and his wife, Chris Love Dudley, listen at his election night gathering in Portland, Oregon, on Nov. 2, 2010.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/64/fa/df60895a4d47ab770da0232758e1/oregon-governor.JPEG" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Natalie Fertig</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Natalie Fertig</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Portland Trail Blazer center Chris Dudley has launched a second attempt to run for governor of Oregon as a Republican, a long-shot bid in a blue state even as the incumbent has struggled in polls.</p> 
<p>Dudley, who played six seasons for the Trail Blazers and 16 for the NBA overall, said in an announcement video Monday that he would ease divisiveness and focus on public safety, affordability and education in a state where support for Democratic Gov. Tina Kotek has been low for her entire tenure.</p> 
<p>“The empty promises, the name calling, the finger pointing and fear mongering that has solved nothing must stop,” said in <a href="https://www.dudley4oregon.com/" target="_blank">his election announcement</a>. “There are real solutions, and I have a plan.”</p> 
<p>Dudley is one of the most successful Republicans of the last 25 years in Oregon, coming within 2 points of defeating Democratic Gov. John Kitzhaber in 2010.</p> 
<p>“I think it’s imperative that we get somebody from outside of Salem who’s away from the partisan politics, away from the name calling, the finger pointing,” Dudley <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2026/01/former-blazer-chris-dudley-will-run-for-oregon-governor-setting-up-heated-republican-primary.html" target="_blank">told The Oregonian</a>. “Who has the expertise and background and the ability to bring people together to solve these issues.”</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://www.dudley4oregon.com/" target="_blank">his election announcement,</a> Dudley spoke about his love of the state and frustration people have with the current state of politics. He mentioned education, safety and affordability as key issues he plans to address but did not give any key policy specifics.</p> 
<p>Dudley is a Yale graduate who worked in finance after leaving the NBA. A diabetic, he also founded a foundation focused on children with Type 1 diabetes.</p> 
<p>In the GOP primary, Dudley faces a field that includes state Sen. Christine Drazan, who lost to Kotek by nearly 4 percentage points in 2022.</p> 
<p>Other candidates include another state lawmaker, a county commissioner and <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2026/01/this-jan-6-rioter-who-was-pardoned-by-trump-is-now-running-for-oregon-governor.html" target="_blank">a conservative influencer</a> who was pardoned by President Donald Trump for his involvement in the Jan. 6, 2021, riot at the U.S. Capitol.</p> 
<p>Kotek is a relatively unpopular governor. Her approval rating has consistently remained under 50 percent her entire term in office, <a href="https://pro.morningconsult.com/trackers/governor-approval-ratings" target="_blank">according to polling analysis by Morning Consult</a>. In December, she announced her intention to seek reelection.</p> 
<p>Despite expectations that Democrats will do well in the midterms, a number of Oregon Republicans have become more involved in state politics since the last election. Phil Knight, a co-founder of Nike, donated $3 million to an Oregon Republican PAC focused on gaining seats in the state Legislature in October. It was his largest political donation to date, <a href="https://www.wweek.com/news/state/2025/11/24/phil-knight-writes-record-check-to-republican-legislative-pac/?utm_source=chatgpt.com" target="_blank">according to the Willamette Week</a>.</p> 
<p>Dudley received <a href="https://www.oregonlive.com/politics/2025/11/former-blazer-and-republican-is-testing-the-waters-for-a-2026-run-for-oregon-governor.html" target="_blank">significant backing from Knight</a> in his 2010 race, but it’s unclear if he will get the same level of support this time around.</p> 
<p>Any Republican faces an uphill battle for governor in Oregon, where a GOP candidate has not won since 1982 and where Democrats have a registration edge of about 8 percentage points.</p>CORRECTION: A previous version incorrectly reported that Gov. Kotek had not announced plans to seek reelection.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pence calls images of Minnesota shooting ‘deeply troubling’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/mike-pence-minnesota-shooting-00746688</link>
      <description>The former vice president called for a “transparent” investigation into the deadly incident.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-fb35-d9a8-a7bf-ffb74c3d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 13:26:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/97/9b/a6bd161946a6a6450d588cfd6cb6/cheney-funeral-04016.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Mark Schiefelbein/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>“The American people deserve to have safe streets, our laws enforced and our constitutional rights of Freedom of Speech, peaceable assembly and the right to keep and bear Arms respected and preserved all at the same time,” former Vice President Mike Pence said.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/97/9b/a6bd161946a6a6450d588cfd6cb6/cheney-funeral-04016.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Vice President Mike Pence on Monday called video footage of the shooting of Alex Pretti in Minnesota “deeply troubling” as he urged a full investigation into the deadly incident.</p> 
<p>“In the wake of the tragic shooting that claimed the life of Alex Pretti this weekend, our prayers are with his family, the citizens of Minneapolis and local, state and federal law enforcement officers serving there,” <a href="https://x.com/Mike_Pence/status/2015813964605636760?s=20" target="_blank">Pence said in a post on X</a>. “The images of this incident are deeply troubling and a full and transparent investigation of this officer involved shooting must take place immediately.”</p> 
<p>Pretti, a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident, was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">shot and killed</a> by Border Patrol agents on Saturday. The incident, which occurred about 2 miles from where Renee Good was shot and killed by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement officer on Jan. 7, has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-trump-administration-dueling-accounts-minneapolis-shooting-00745811" target="_blank">ignited a heated debate</a> between the Trump administration and Minnesota officials amid intense scrutiny of the tactics of the president's immigration crackdown. </p> 
<p>Protesters have flooded the streets of Minnesota in the aftermath of Pretti’s killing.</p> 
<p>State leaders have <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/state-watch/5705051-alex-pretti-federal-shooting-investigation/" target="_blank">alleged federal officials have blocked them</a> from being involved in an investigation into the shooting. Administration officials have accused Minnesota authorities of refusing to collaborate with immigration authorities on deportations.</p> 
<p>But Pence on Monday called for law enforcement at all levels to work together on investigating the latest shooting.</p> 
<p>“The focus now should be to bring together law enforcement at every level to address the concerns in the community even while ensuring that dangerous illegal aliens are apprehended and no longer a threat to families in Minneapolis,” Pence said.</p> 
<p>The former vice president is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707" target="_blank">the latest high-profile Republican to express concerns</a> over the events unfolding in Minnesota. Like Pence, some of the party’s top voices have called for a full investigation into the shooting. </p> 
<p>Others have disputed the administration's justification that Pretti’s carrying of a gun was legal justification for his killing, which Pence echoed on Monday.</p> 
<p>“The American people deserve to have safe streets, our laws enforced and our constitutional rights of Freedom of Speech, peaceable assembly and the right to keep and bear Arms respected and preserved all at the same time,” said Pence. “That’s how Law and Order and Freedom work together in America.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-26T16:28:20-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans go all-in on 'Sharia law' attacks ahead of Texas primary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/republicans-go-all-in-on-sharia-law-attacks-ahead-of-texas-primary-00745647</link>
      <description>From the Senate primary to local races, Republicans are pledging to fight the supposed spread of radical Islam</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f583-dabb-ad9f-ffefb6820001</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:08:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/81/4b/29b73c1f4abb994bc07a4ac543ab/u-s-congress-21753.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. John Cornyn (R-Texas) walks to a Senate Republican Conference luncheon at the U.S. Capitol in Washington, on Dec. 3, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/81/4b/29b73c1f4abb994bc07a4ac543ab/u-s-congress-21753.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Liz Crampton and Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Liz Crampton and Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Anti-Muslim rhetoric has emerged as a potent ingredient in the looming Texas Republican primary while candidates compete to raise fears about the spread of Sharia law in the state and portray themselves as the toughest option to stand against it.</p> 
<p>From the state’s white-hot GOP Senate primary down to local races, Republican candidates are pledging to fight the hardest against a proposed residential development of 1,000 homes centered around a Mosque north of Dallas, while issuing dire warnings about the supposed threat of Islam and questioning their opponents’ commitment to the cause.</p> 
<p>Sen. John Cornyn (R-Texas) and his top primary opponent, Texas Attorney General Ken Paxton, have sparred in attack ads and on the trail over that project and Afghan refugee resettlement program, at times veering into inflammatory anti-Islamic rhetoric. Cornyn called for a federal investigation into the project; Paxton launched several probes and in December sued the development over alleged securities fraud.</p> 
<p>Texas is a heavily diverse state, with non-Hispanic whites representing less than two fifths of its total population — a flashpoint for years on the right. The state’s relatively small but fast-growing Muslim population has become a charged issue for Republicans seeking to distinguish themselves in competitive races. This year’s GOP ads – which vary from condemning terror attacks to burning the Quran – represent an escalation of rhetoric the party has long used to rally its voters.</p> 
<p>“The Muslim community is the boogeyman for this cycle,” said Texas GOP consultant Vinny Minchillo. “One hundred percent this message works — there's no question about it. This has been polled up one side and down the other, and with Texas Republican primary voters, it works. It is a thing they are legitimately scared of.”</p> 
<p>Muslim advocacy organizations and Democrats decry the ads as racist and grossly inaccurate characterizations of those communities.</p> 
<p>“The Texas GOP has declared war on Islam in Texas, claiming that Islamic leaders in the state are implementing Sharia law and using it in court,” said Joel Montfort, a north Texas-based Democratic strategist. “None of it is true, it is just fearmongering and racism to stir up the GOP base and get them to vote.”</p> 
<p>A POLITICO review identified ads in half a dozen races since the start of 2025 that highlighted “Sharia law,” according to data from AdImpact, which tracks political advertising. All were from or backing Republican candidates touting their fights against it, and most were common in Texas.</p> 
<p>Last week, Cornyn launched a seven-figure <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0vD6gujdRfE" target="_blank"><u>ad</u></a> buy titled “Evil Face” that declares “radical Islam is a bloodthirsty ideology,” referencing the Oct. 7 Hamas attack against Israel and December Bondi Beach shooting in Australia. The ad also references his bill to revoke the tax-exempt status of Council on American-Islamic Relations, a Muslim advocacy organization.</p> 
<p>Paxton has <a href="https://x.com/KenPaxtonTX/status/2014344216508498073?s=20" target="_blank"><u>gone after</u></a> Cornyn’s past support of an Afghan refugee resettlement program. And in his capacity as attorney general, Paxton <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2025/12/05/texas-ken-paxton-epic-city-lawsuit/" target="_blank"><u>said</u></a> the project is an “illegal land development scheme” and its leaders are “engaged in a radical plot to destroy hundreds of acres of beautiful Texas land and line their own pockets.”</p> 
<p>In the four-way GOP race for Texas attorney general, candidate Aaron Reitz says in an <a href="https://x.com/bwaltens/status/2013978366030864753" target="_blank"><u>ad</u></a> out this week that “Islam is not compatible with Western civilization” and vows to “stop the invasion” of Muslims. Reitz served less than a year in the Justice Department before launching his bid for attorney general. His opponent, state Sen. Mayes Middleton, also has an <a href="https://pdfweb.s3.amazonaws.com/scraped-ads/CR17061108716880789505.mp4" target="_blank"><u>ad</u></a> boasting that he’s running to “stop Sharia law” in Texas.</p> 
<p>And, most provocatively, Valentina Gomez <a href="https://www.fox26houston.com/isiah-factor-uncensored/texas-congressional-candidate-sparks-controversy-quran-burning-video" target="_blank"><u>launched</u></a> her candidacy in Texas’ 31st Congressional District last year with a video showing her burning a Quran and declaring that “your daughters will be raped and your sons beheaded, unless we stop Islam once and for all.” Gomez, who is challenging President Donald Trump-endorsed Rep. John Carter (R-Texas), is a known conservative activist and provocateur who won just 8 percent of the primary vote when she ran for Missouri secretary of state last year.</p> 
<p>Anti-muslim sentiment in the U.S. grew out of the 9/11 terror attacks, which some Republicans used to rally their base for political gain. False rumors on the right that Barack Hussein Obama was a secret Muslim persisted <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2007/10/untraceable-e-mails-spread-obama-rumor-006314" target="_blank"><u>from his rise to the White House </u></a>and for years after. The planned construction of a mosque blocks from Ground Zero became a right-wing cause celebre early in his presidency, with multiple national Republican figures rallying against it.</p> 
<p>Trump intensified those feelings, first by elevating conspiracy theories that Obama wasn’t born in the U.S., then by repeatedly disparaging Muslims, pledging in his 2016 campaign to ban Muslims from entering the country and once he became president implementing travel bans against majority-Muslim countries. On Tuesday, Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115928297468422986" target="_blank"><u>reposted</u></a> a comment calling Islam a “cult.”</p> 
<p>But in recent years Islam hasn’t been as much of a focus within GOP campaigns — until now.</p> 
<p>The Texas ads come as Republicans nationwide have placed heightened scrutiny on CAIR, the largest Muslim advocacy group in the U.S. Sameeha Rizvi, CAIR Action Texas Policy and Advocacy Coordinator, called Cornyn’s ad “defamatory and despicable” and borne out of “desperation to compete with Ken Paxton’s anti-Muslim bigotry.”</p> 
<p>“CAIR is not going anywhere, American Muslims are not going anywhere, and our community will show its strength at the ballot box, God willing,” Rizvi said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Cornyn has introduced legislation seeking to revoke CAIR’s tax-exempt status. U.S. Rep Chip Roy, who is also in the Texas attorney general race, introduced a similar bill last year.</p> 
<p>When a super PAC on behalf of Cornyn launched an <a href="https://x.com/bradj_TX/status/2014319896671199443" target="_blank"><u>attack</u></a> against Paxton on Thursday, calling him “weird” and highlighting his divorce and alleged extramarital affairs, Paxton <a href="https://x.com/KenPaxtonTX/status/2014344216508498073" target="_blank"><u>shot back</u></a> on X : “This desperate hail mary can't erase the fact that he [Cornyn] helped radical Islamic Afghans invade Texas and that his family's making a fortune securing visas for foreigners.”</p> 
<p>Paxton was referencing Cornyn’s past support for increasing the number of Special Immigrant Visas available to Afghans following the Taliban’s 2021 takeover of the country. Cornyn, who had once been supportive of the program,<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/18/republicans-drop-support-afghans-asylum-00697430" target="_blank"><u> reversed course</u></a> along with other Republicans late last year following the shooting of two National Guard members by an Afghan who’d been granted asylum in the U.S., on the basis that the vetting of applicants was inadequate.</p> 
<p>Cornyn has responded to Paxton’s attacks with a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xZSeyNhSbPY" target="_blank"><u>digital ad</u></a> stating that Paxton talks tough but he’s actually “soft on radical Islam,” claiming that Paxton directed $2.5 million to resettle Afghan refugees in Texas, and his former attorney who defended him during impeachment proceedings now represents the East Plano Islamic Center.</p> 
<p>Several ads from different candidates in Texas use footage of the project from the East Plano Islamic Center, which would also feature a K-12 school and retail. Texas leaders, including Gov. Greg Abbott, have said that the presence of the planned Muslim community raises national security concerns. The East Plano Islamic Center did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>“Texans overwhelmingly care about this – they're looking at their communities transform in radical ways,” said Reitz, the attorney general candidate.</p> 
<p>“You look at the number of mosques that have been built in Texas in just the last 10 to 20 years, and it's explosive,” he said. “It’s alarming for good reason, and I think that Republican voters in particular are looking for their public office holders to address it, and so it's such a pressing issue that I chose to really lean into this.”</p> 
<p>Cornyn’s ad declares that “Sharia law has no place in American courts or communities,” a reference to the development. Trump’s Justice Department also launched a civil rights investigation into the project last year after Cornyn requested the federal government to investigate “religious discrimination.”</p> 
<p>The project was already on the radar of Paxton, who had opened his first of several probes into its construction. In December, Paxton — whose candidacy is boosted by his reputation as an aggressive attorney general who frequently files lawsuits on behalf of MAGA causes — <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2025/12/05/texas-ken-paxton-epic-city-lawsuit/" target="_blank"><u>sued</u></a> the development for alleged securities fraud.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department quietly <a href="https://www.keranews.org/news/2025-06-25/department-justice-ends-federal-probe-epic-city-mosque" target="_blank"><u>closed</u></a> its investigation last summer without filing any charges. But Abbott still went forward and signed multiple laws last year that banned “Sharia compounds” and designating CAIR and Muslim Brotherhood as terrorist organizations. CAIR sued Texas in response, arguing the action was unconstitutional and defamatory.</p> 
<p>Paxton, in his official capacity as attorney general, <a href="https://x.com/KenPaxtonTX/status/2015160530848121149" target="_blank"><u>said</u></a> last week that the state comptroller can exclude private schools from the school voucher program if they violate the recently signed anti-terror laws, declaring that “Texans’ tax dollars should never fund Islamic terrorists or America’s enemies.”</p> 
<p><i>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misstated John Cornyn's level of involvement in legislation to revoke CAIR's tax-exempt status. He introduced it.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A battle over the truth erupts after deadly Minneapolis shooting</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-trump-administration-dueling-accounts-minneapolis-shooting-00745811</link>
      <description>Federal and local leaders are sharply divided over what happened and who is to blame.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-f77a-d9a8-a7bf-f7faaf830000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 19:29:50 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/50/46/b239cb1548d0be8872d389b3e16f/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-40005.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Adam Gray/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>A makeshift memorial is placed where Alex Pretti was fatally shot by a U.S. Border Patrol agent the previous day, in Minneapolis, on Jan. 25, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/50/46/b239cb1548d0be8872d389b3e16f/immigration-enforcement-minnesota-40005.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels and Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels and Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the wake of another fatal shooting involving immigration agents, Trump administration and Minnesota officials are locked in a heated dispute over what exactly transpired and who’s to blame for the death of 37-year-old Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p>And they don’t just disagree in their interpretation of the events — they fundamentally differ on what exactly took place and what triggered it.</p> 
<p>Border Patrol agents <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">shot and killed</a> Pretti on Saturday during a tense encounter between observers and federal agents, a dynamic that has led to several violent interactions as the Trump administration escalates its nationwide immigration crackdown. His death comes less than a month after an Immigration and Customs Enforcement officer <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/minneapolis-immigration-crackdown-shooting-00714034" target="_blank">fatally shot 37-year-old Renee Good</a>. The scenes of the shootings were roughly two miles apart, and protesters flooded the streets after both.</p> 
<p>Amid conflicting accounts over the incident — including whether Pretti’s hand at any point during the incident was near his gun — video verified and analyzed by several media outlets, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-federal-agents-video.html" target="_blank">including The New York Times</a>, show the item Pretti appeared to be holding was a phone he was using to film the scene before he attempted to help a woman who had been pushed to the ground by Border Patrol agents. According to a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/investigations/2026/01/25/minneapolis-shooting-video-gun/" target="_blank">Washington Post analysis</a> of video footage, federal agents appear to have secured Pretti's gun just moments before an agent shot him.</p> 
<p>“What you see is someone brandishing a cellphone who is simply there with a cellphone helping someone up, a woman up, as his parents point out, when she had slipped,” Sen. Amy Klobuchar (D-Minn.) <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/video/amy-klobuchar-says-ice-is-making-us-less-safe-after-another-fatal-mn-shooting-full-interview-256544325570" target="_blank">told NBC’s “Meet the Press.”</a> “And so when I hear these officials from the Trump administration describe this video in ways that simply aren’t true, I just keep thinking, ‘Your eyes don’t lie.’”</p> 
<p>Border Patrol commander Gregory Bovino on Sunday <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/bovino-border-patrol-agents-minneapolis-victims-00745702" target="_blank">accused Pretti of having “injected” himself</a> into a law enforcement investigation. Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said Pretti had committed a “felony” by impeding law enforcement. And Deputy Attorney General Todd Blanche blamed local state officials for what he called an “entirely avoidable” event.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/1f/1a/db0193cf4a55a6c5a4e24bf5d77b/ap26024812004514-edit.jpg" alt="People gather at the intersection of 27th Street and Nicollet Avenue, a block from the shooting." data-portal-copyright="Ben Hovland/Minnesota Public Radio via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26024812004514" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="People gather at the intersection of 27th Street and Nicollet Avenue, a block from the shooting."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/5d/ef/38ac589b42c58a09cdf599421d97/gettyimages-2258037569-edit.jpg" alt="A person is tackled by a federal agent amid protests following the shooting." data-portal-copyright="Brandon Bell/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2258037569" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="A person is tackled by a federal agent amid protests following the shooting."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/26/92/d47baebe4fc3a3966708e045f536/ap26024793513012-edit.jpg" alt="Protesters react in the street along Nicollet Avenue on Jan 24." data-portal-copyright="Aaron Lavinsky/Minneapolis Star Tribune via AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26024793513012" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Protesters react in the street along Nicollet Avenue on Jan 24."/><p>But Minnesota officials see a different story in the footage. Minneapolis Police Chief Brian O’Hara said Pretti was lawfully armed and exercising his constitutional rights, and Klobuchar told NBC’s “Meet the Press” that the video shows him holding a cellphone and helping a woman up, not acting aggressively toward agents.</p> 
<p>Shortly after Saturday’s shooting, Noem offered one account of the incident: She said Pretti “approached U.S. Border Patrol officers with a 9mm semi-automatic handgun” and that he “violently resisted” when the officers attempted to disarm him.</p> 
<p>Noem then <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=91s4Iwa3K6Q" target="_blank">told Fox News on Sunday</a> that agents on Saturday “clearly feared for their lives” before shooting Pretti. She and other federal officials have claimed that Pretti was approaching agents with a gun.</p> 
<p>“We do know that he came to that scene and impeded a law enforcement operation, which is against federal law. It's a felony. When he did that, interacting with those agents when they tried to get him to disengage, he became aggressive and resisted them throughout that process,” Noem said. “These officers used their training, followed their protocols and were in fear of their lives and the people around them.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/a6/b1/0e9ee652414ebde1e7edfc87edda/gettyimages-2258012002-edit.jpg" alt="Shortly after Saturday’s shooting, Kristi Noem offered one account of the incident: She said Pretti “approached U.S. Border Patrol officers with a 9mm semi-automatic handgun” and that he “violently resisted” when the officers attempted to disarm him." data-portal-copyright="Al Drago/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2258012002" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="Shortly after Saturday’s shooting, Kristi Noem offered one account of the incident: She said Pretti “approached U.S. Border Patrol officers with a 9mm semi-automatic handgun” and that he “violently resisted” when the officers attempted to disarm him."/><img src="https://static.politico.com/77/a1/33171be6435c9da3fae973e1d3e3/ap26010606785601-edit.jpg" alt="Minneapolis Police Chief Brian O’Hara said Pretti was lawfully armed and exercising his constitutional rights." data-portal-copyright="Jen Golbeck/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26010606785601" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Minneapolis Police Chief Brian O’Hara said Pretti was lawfully armed and exercising his constitutional rights."/><p>Despite Noem’s claim that the agents feared for their lives, O’Hara, <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/video/minneapolis-police-chief-brian-ohara-says-people-have-had-enough-after-border-patrol-shooting/" target="_blank">speaking on CBS’ “Face the Nation”</a> on Sunday morning, said he had seen no evidence Pretti brandished a weapon during the encounter.</p> 
<p>“You have a Second Amendment right in the United States to possess a firearm,” O’Hara said during an interview with host Margaret Brennan. “And there are some restrictions around that in Minnesota, and everything that we see that we are aware of shows that he did not violate any of those restrictions.”</p> 
<p>But in an interview with CNN’s “State of the Union” on Sunday, Bovino said a person’s Second Amendment rights “don’t count when you riot and assault, delay, obstruct and impede law enforcement officers.”</p> 
<p>Noem seemingly suggested the fact that Pretti possessed “a gun and ammunition, rather than a sign” meant the scene was a “violent riot.”</p> 
<p>“We have someone showing up with weapons and are using them to assault law enforcement officers,” she said Saturday of the situation.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/c8/10/53fe7d5b41e899cafe21b2fa719e/ap26025601602125-edit.jpg" alt="Bureau of Criminal Apprehension officers stand over a memorial at the scene where Pretti was fatally shot." data-portal-copyright="Adam Gray/AP" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="26025601602125" data-licensor-name="AP" data-title="Bureau of Criminal Apprehension officers stand over a memorial at the scene where Pretti was fatally shot."/><p><a href="https://x.com/kylegriffin1/status/2015481050248470580" target="_blank">Former President Barack Obama also said</a> the Trump administration’s explanations “appear to be directly contradicted by video evidence.” And Pretti’s family members have accused the White House of <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/01/24/us/alex-pretti-minneapolis-ice-shooting-invs" target="_blank">spreading “sickening lies.”</a></p> 
<p>Just as in the aftermath of Good’s shooting, federal and state officials disagree about who bears responsibility — and how to manage the fallout.</p> 
<p>Blanche on Sunday told NBC’s “Meet the Press” that Pretti’s shooting was a “tragedy” but added that “this was entirely avoidable if we had a governor, if we had a mayor, if we had leadership in Washington and over in Minnesota that actually cared about their citizens.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/e6/6c/85fae6f54bde8e3ef57befd2ed87/gettyimages-2257466650-edit.jpg" alt="A person carries an American flag on Nicollet Avenue in Minneapolis on Jan. 24." data-portal-copyright="Stephen Maturen/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="2257466650" data-licensor-name="Getty Images" data-title="A person carries an American flag on Nicollet Avenue in Minneapolis on Jan. 24."/><p>But Gov. Tim Walz and local officials say it’s the Trump administration that has sown chaos. Walz deployed the state’s National Guard to Minneapolis in the aftermath of Pretti’s killing, which he called “sickening.”</p> 
<p>“I just spoke with the White House after another horrific shooting by federal agents this morning. Minnesota has had it. This is sickening,” <a href="https://x.com/GovTimWalz/status/2015093164999119352?s=20" target="_blank">Walz posted on X</a>. “The President must end this operation. Pull the thousands of violent, untrained officers out of Minnesota. Now.”</p> 
<p>“This administration and everyone involved in this operation should be reflecting. They should be reflecting right now and asking themselves, what exactly are you accomplishing?” Minneapolis Mayor Jacob Frey, a Democrat, said at a Saturday press conference. “If the goal was to achieve peace and safety, this is doing exactly the opposite. If the goal was to achieve calm and prosperity, this is doing exactly the opposite.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rift over generational change roils the Congressional Black Caucus</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/congressional-black-caucus-2026-midterms-00741618</link>
      <description>“You cannot be a part of the system for 40 years and also be the one who's going to change it for the next 40,” said Tennessee state Rep. Justin Pearson.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ec66-d452-a99b-edfecbd70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/e5/5a/a5d72a90427bad4a6421fcb980e0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2241490328">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jan Sonnenmair/Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Tennessee state Rep. Justin Pearson takes a selfie with rallygoers at the "No Kings" protest on Oct. 18, 2025 in Memphis, Tennessee.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e5/5a/a5d72a90427bad4a6421fcb980e0/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2241490328" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A new generation of Black Democrats is running in the midterms, aiming to inject a younger vision into an aging Congressional Black Caucus. And in some cases, that means primarying incumbents.</p> 
<p>The wave of new candidates comes amid an identity crisis for the Democratic Party, which has splintered along generational and ideological lines as the party searches for new leaders in the second Trump era, both for this November and the open presidential race in two years.</p> 
<p>“This is a new moment that requires different ideas, requires new energy and new perspectives and you cannot be a part of the system for 40 years and also be the one who's going to change it for the next 40,” said Tennessee state Rep. Justin Pearson, 31, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/08/justin-j-pearson-to-challenge-tennessee-rep-steve-cohen-in-dem-primary-00597567" target="_blank">who launched his primary challenge</a> to 76-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51856" data-person-id="51856">Steve Cohen</a> (D-Tenn.) last year. “You've done the best that you could, and it's time for other folks to be able to do the best that they can for the present and for the future.”</p> 
<p>Young Black candidates say they’re motivated to run due to rising racial tensions, redistricting and the possibility of <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-nightly/2025/08/08/its-been-60-years-since-the-voting-rights-act-was-signed-will-it-make-it-to-61-00500390" target="_blank">an end to the Voting Rights Act</a> — and what they describe as an inadequate response from older generations that are fighting past battles.</p> 
<p>“Our generation recognizes the fierce urgency of now,” Pearson said.</p> 
<p>The CBC has grown exponentially since its establishment in 1971, currently boasting a historic 62 members — the largest of any of the affinity caucuses. But the average age of CBC members is 60 years old, and some of the oldest House Democrats are members.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51325" data-person-id="51325">Jim Clyburn</a>, 85, has represented South Carolina for more than 30 years and plans on running again. At 88 years old, D.C. Del. Eleanor Holmes Norton has not ruled out running for reelection, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/10/congress/eleanor-holmes-norton-reelection-00397248" target="_blank">despite growing concerns about her age</a>. And 87-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51664" data-person-id="51664">Maxine Waters</a> (D-Calif.), who was first elected in 1990, said she <a href="https://www.axios.com/2025/05/15/house-democrats-age-members-reelection-biden" target="_blank">also plans on running for reelection</a> this year.</p> 
<p>These long tenures have started to worry some new candidates, they said in interviews.</p> 
<p>“When I was born in 1992, this was the poorest district in the poorest state in the country,” said Evan Turnage, who is primarying 77-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51647" data-person-id="51647">Bennie Thompson</a> (D-Miss.). “Congressman Thompson was elected in ’93 and now today, I'm 33, and this is still the poorest district in the poorest state in the country.”</p> 
<p>Turnage — a former senior staffer to Sens. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> of New York and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/140963" data-person-id="140963">Elizabeth Warren</a> of Massachusetts — said these long-serving members have “failed” younger generations for too long.</p> 
<p>“Just because you've been around the block for 30 years doesn't mean you're delivering results for the district, doesn't mean you're delivering results for your constituents,” Turnage said.</p> 
<p>In a statement, Thompson said he has spent his entire career encouraging young people “to make a difference in the world.”</p> 
<p>“If this is how Mr. Turnage chooses to make a difference in Mississippi’s 2nd Congressional District, that's his choice," Thompson said.</p> 
<p>The younger Black candidates — and current lawmakers — have generally pushed more progressive policies in their campaigns than CBC members who have served for decades. They've had a heavy focus on issues they say are of most concern to those in their generations, such as the cost of living and education.</p> 
<p>"The Democratic Party has to adapt in order to survive. That work starts right now," said Pearson, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/04/12/second-tennessee-state-lawmaker-reinstated-00091715" target="_blank">gained nationwide fame in 2023 as a member of the "Tennessee Three”</a> after he was expelled from, and then reelected to, the state Legislature for leading a gun safety protest on the state House floor.</p> 
<p>"Black folks in this country are still suffering disproportionately in every single category, and without leadership to elevate those concerns, those worries, those issues in a meaningful way, we're never going to see that change," Pearson added.</p> 
<p>He is challenging Cohen, who is white, in a majority-Black district based in Memphis that Cohen has represented for decades. During his 2007 campaign, Cohen expressed interest in joining the CBC, <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2007/01/black-caucus-whites-not-allowed-002389" target="_blank">but caucus members quickly shut that down</a>.</p> 
<p>Cohen said in an interview that his tenure in Congress is actually a strength.</p> 
<p>“I know the issues and I know the problems, I know the people,” said Cohen. “The way you get legislation passed hasn't changed, really, in the 40 years I've been here. Some people think it's about getting a megaphone and hollering or making some kind of a fuss, and I've done some of that in my younger days, and I still like to occasionally … but it's a matter of having friends, having relationships, and being able to get the majority of votes to pass the bills. And I've done that all my life.”</p> 
<p>The CBC has begun to see younger legislators enter their ranks in recent years. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/461974" data-person-id="461974">Gabe Amo</a>, 38, made history in 2023 when he was elected as Rhode Island’s first Black representative. And in 2022, at the age of 25, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/411928" data-person-id="411928">Maxwell Frost </a>became the first Gen Z CBC member elected to Congress.</p> 
<p>“Our movement — from the civil rights era to the birth of the CBC itself — was born from the energy and courage of young people to stand up and do the right thing,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51521" data-person-id="51521">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.), chair of the CBC’s political arm, in a statement. “Our caucus today represents the breadth and depth of our community — from every corner of America — and folks whose families have been here for generations, those who are immigrants, queer, disabled, and more women and young people than ever before.”</p> 
<p>The CBC PAC has already endorsed some young candidates this cycle, including California’s Lauren Babb and Arkansas’ Chris Jones. It’s likely the PAC will also endorse Adrian Boafo, 31, according to a person familiar with the matter who was granted anonymity to discuss private matters, who is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/steny-hoyer-retirement-00715790" target="_blank">running to succeed</a> 86-year-old Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51438" data-person-id="51438">Steny Hoyer</a>. </p> 
<p>But the PAC this year also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/congressional-black-caucus-espaillat-primary-00728543?utm_source=dlvr.it&amp;utm_medium=twitter" target="_blank">endorsed 71-year-old incumbent</a> Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/193043" data-person-id="193043">Adriano Espaillat </a>(D-N.Y.) — who identifies as Afro Latino, currently chairs the Congressional Hispanic Caucus and has had a bumpy relationship with the CBC — over his 32-year-old primary challenger, Darializa Avila Chevalier.</p> 
<p>As the age gap between caucus members and voters grows, an influx of fresh faces will be vital to regaining voters’ support for Democrats ahead of the 2026 midterms, said 25-year-old Courtney McClain, who is running for a red House seat in South Carolina.</p> 
<p>“Within the party in general, we've had an issue of connecting with younger voters, and especially with young men,” said McClain, referring to the <a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2025/06/26/behind-trumps-2024-victory-a-more-racially-and-ethnically-diverse-voter-coalition/" target="_blank">15 percent of Black men</a> who supported President Donald Trump in the 2024 presidential election. “I really think a lot of people are more apt to vote if they can see themselves in the candidate as opposed to someone who has been there for many years.”</p> 
<p>But these young Black candidates still hold a deep appreciation for the caucus, despite their concerns around age.</p> 
<p>Turnage said he’d “love” to be a member of the CBC. Pearson called the caucus an "extraordinary institution.” And McClain — a onetime CBC Foundation intern and a fellow with the CBC Institute last year — said she would “definitely” like to be a member.</p> 
<p>Ultimately, McClain said, the CBC needs young members if they hope to actually address the challenges facing the next generation.</p> 
<p>“The legislation that's being passed, a lot of the people that are currently in office won't even be impacted by it, say, in the next 20 years,” McClain said. “But my generation will.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
