<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 21:20:53 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Senate expected to repeal law allowing lawmakers to sue over data seizures</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-poised-to-repeal-payout-provision-00756723</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0ca5-df17-afbf-7db72bc60001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 21:20:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate is expected to swallow a House-passed provision that would nix a law that allows senators to receive cash payouts if they had their phone records seized by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader John Thune said in an interview Thursday night he currently anticipates the repeal language to remain a part of the government funding package the Senate hopes to pass in the coming hours, but which has not yet been unveiled.</p> 
<p>A second person granted anonymity to disclose private discussions confirmed that the House provision is likely to be preserved. A third person, a Senate aide, also said the expectation is that the House language stays in.</p> 
<p>It goes back to the spending agreement Congress cleared last November to end the record-breaking government shutdown. At that time, the Senate quietly inserted a new policy into the legislation which would have the effect of allowing certain Republican senators to sue the federal government for hundreds of thousands of dollars if they had their electronic records seized without prior notification during Smith’s 2021 probe of President Donald Trump’s attempts to subvert the results of the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>House members of both parties <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-votes-to-overturn-thunes-controversial-subpoena-measure-00661169" target="_blank">were horrified</a> by the language, which they learned about only after the fact, and quickly passed legislation unanimously to undo it. They took steps last week to tuck that repeal into a separate, six-bill government funding package the Senate will need to pass before the end of the day Friday to avoid a partial government shutdown.</p> 
<p>But now the chamber is preparing to strip out the Homeland Security appropriations bill to negotiate new provisions around immigration enforcement activities and pass the other five, and it has been an open question throughout the day Thursday whether the repeal provision would remain intact.</p> 
<p>While the funding agreement hasn’t been announced yet on the Senate floor — meaning it could still change as leaders try to wrangle holdouts, whose blessing they need in order to speed up a passage vote before the shutdown deadline — senators were sending signals that there was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">a bipartisan appetite to keep it.</a></p> 
<p>“I think it was politically tone deaf to put a monetary penalty in there,” said Sen. Ron Johnson (R-Wis.), who has been leading the charge to re-investigate the work of Smith’s office.</p> 
<p>Sen. Martin Heinrich (D-N.M.), who had expressed frustration that he was not consulted on the initial measure as ranking member of the relevant appropriations subcommittee, said he would advocate for the repeal provision to be included in any funding bill the Senate considers this week.</p> 
<p>“I think it should be part of anything we vote on,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-29T23:47:33-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump-blessed deal to keep government funded gets snagged in Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/shutdown-spending-deal-trump-00756372</link>
      <description>The agreement would allow for passage of full-year funding for most federal agencies while extending DHS for two weeks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0c16-df8c-a99d-fdf6e0810000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 18:29:48 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/3b/73/7329851f4654a687ed4a7303b78f/2026-0128-congress-francis-7-1-86155.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.), followed by Sens. Patty Murray (D-Wash.) and Alex Padilla (D-Calif.), arrives for a press conference at the U.S. Capitol, on Jan. 28, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/3b/73/7329851f4654a687ed4a7303b78f/2026-0128-congress-francis-7-1-86155.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump and Senate Democrats reached an agreement to fund the federal government as a Friday midnight deadline for a partial shutdown approaches.</p> 
<p>But the Senate’s hopes of quickly passing the deal, text of which is yet to be unveiled, ran into a snag Thursday night, with leadership sending senators home around 11 p.m. Senators hope to pass the deal Friday, but votes aren’t yet scheduled.</p> 
<p>“Hopefully by sometime tomorrow we’ll be in a better spot,” Majority Leader John Thune said as he left the Capitol. “Tomorrow’s another day, and hopefully people will be in a spirit to try and get this done tomorrow.”</p> 
<p>Minority Leader Chuck Schumer was more blunt: “Republicans need to get their act together.”</p> 
<p>Thune said there were unresolved issues on both sides of the aisle. But the main sticking point appears to be Sen. Lindsey Graham’s decision to block a quick vote on the deal because it includes a House-passed provision undoing a law that allows senators to receive cash payouts if they had their phone records seized by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>The provision’s inclusion in the Senate funding agreement <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-poised-to-repeal-payout-provision-00756723" target="_blank">was first reported by POLITICO</a>.</p> 
<p>Graham (R-S.C.), who was among the senators who had records subpoenaed, said Thursday night his interest was not personal: “It’s not about me — 190 private groups had their phone records messed with. I want notification.” Graham’s objection comes even after Trump urged support for the agreement.</p> 
<p>"I am working hard with Congress to ensure that we are able to fully fund the Government, without delay," Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115980912926614287" target="_blank">posted on Truth Social</a>. "Hopefully, both Republicans and Democrats will give a very much needed Bipartisan 'YES' Vote."</p> 
<p>Even if the Senate passes the deal Friday, a partial government shutdown could still happen early Saturday morning, since the House is in recess and not scheduled to return until Monday. Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://x.com/ZachSchermele/status/2017028033408897052" target="_blank">said at an event Thursday night</a> that is the earliest the House could vote, though House Republicans will hold a conference call Friday morning where leaders could recalibrate.</p> 
<p>Leadership aides reiterated after Trump’s announcement that they still expect the earliest they will be able to hold votes on the agreement is next week, which would guarantee a brief partial shutdown.</p> 
<p>Stripping the full-year DHS bill out of the larger six-bill package is a victory for Senate Democrats, who are unified behind demands for enforcement policy changes after federal agents deployed to Minnesota fatally shot 37-year-old Alex Pretti last week.</p> 
<p>But Democratic leaders are still in negotiations with the White House over exactly what <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/democrats-dhs-minnesota-shutdown-00753256" target="_blank">policy changes</a> they want signed into law in return for their support for a long-term bill. Though Republicans have signaled they are open to some of the ideas Democrats have proposed, including requiring independent investigations, some in the GOP are raising warning flags about a fight to come.</p> 
<p>Graham told reporters Thursday that while he was “willing to entertain some reforms … the cancer that we're dealing with is sanctuary-city policy.” He wants a vote on legislation cracking down on those jurisdictions that don’t comply with federal immigration laws, an idea Trump also backed this month.</p> 
<p>Republicans are already bracing for the possibility of another weeks-long stopgap for DHS if a deal isn’t reached by mid-February. Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) went further, predicting that after the two-week stopgap “part of the government is just going to stay shut down.”</p> 
<p>If Thursday’s deal is enacted, Congress will have approved full-year funding for more than 95 percent of the agencies it funds on an annual basis — leaving unfinished only the DHS spending measure.</p> 
<p>If the package isn’t enacted before the Friday night deadline, a shutdown will hit all federal agencies that weren’t covered in the six funding bills Congress already enacted for the current fiscal year.</p> 
<p>Agencies already funded include the departments of Agriculture, Veterans Affairs, Justice, Interior, Commerce and Energy, as well as the EPA, water programs, federal science initiatives, the FDA and the operations of Congress itself.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clinton contempt votes will hit the House floor next Wednesday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/bill-hillary-clinton-contempt-of-congress-vote-00755863</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0ba9-d1ed-a59e-dbfd1cd30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 17:17:46 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders are planning votes next Wednesday on a pair of contempt of Congress resolutions against former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss private planning. </p> 
<p>The Rules Committee will meet at 4 p.m. Monday to consider the resolutions for the floor. </p> 
<p>The Oversight Committee <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/21/9-democrats-vote-to-hold-bill-clinton-in-contempt-of-congress-for-evading-epstein-testimony-00739940" target="_blank">advanced the resolutions last week</a>, with several Democrats breaking from their party to support the measure after the Clintons defied a subpoena to testify as part of the panel’s investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>POLITICO <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/01/27/no-shutdown-deal-in-sight-00748757" target="_blank">previously reported</a> the votes were expected some time next week. </p> 
<p><i>Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Ethics finds 'substantial evidence' of fraud charges against Florida Democrat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/house-ethics-fraud-evidence-sheila-cherfilus-mccormick-00755641</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0b6b-dbc5-a7bd-1bff266a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 15:29:31 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A panel of House lawmakers found “substantial evidence” that Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/314122" data-person-id="314122">Sheila Cherfilus-McCormick</a>, who's facing federal fraud charges, committed conduct outlined in the indictment against her.</p> 
<p>The investigative subcommittee under House Ethics found violations of campaign finance laws and regulations; criminal laws; the Ethics in Government Act; the Code of Ethics for Government Service; and House rules. The Florida Democrat <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/florida-democrat-indicted-on-federal-fraud-charges-00661162" target="_blank">has already been indicted</a> for siphoning FEMA funds for her campaign, taking part in a straw donor scheme and tax fraud.</p> 
<p>“The ISC’s investigation has revealed substantial evidence of conduct consistent with the allegations in the indictment, as well as more extensive misconduct as laid out in the following Statement of Facts in Support of Alleged Violations related to violations of federal laws and regulations, as well as ethical standards,” a report from the investigative subcommittee stated.</p> 
<p>A lawyer for Cherfilus-McCormick, Michael Stroud, responded to panel lawmakers by requesting that they pause their proceedings while the criminal case plays out and dismiss the investigation that began in June.</p> 
<p>“Representative Cherfilus-McCormick disputes and refutes the allegations and report of the Ethics Committee’s Investigative Subcommittee,” Stroud wrote to the panel.</p> 
<p>Stroud did not immediately return a request for comment. </p> 
<p>The subcommittee reviewed over 33,000 documents, conducted dozens of interviews, issued 59 subpoenas and met 12 times. Although initially cooperative, Cherfilus-McCormick ultimately invoked her Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination.</p> 
<p>An adjudicatory subcommittee will hold a hearing in her case in March.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amy Klobuchar’s governor run sets up Senate leadership shakeup</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/amy-klobuchar-senate-leadership-00755417</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0b4a-df17-afbf-7f7bed960000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 14:49:33 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Amy Klobuchar, the No. 3 Democratic Party leader, made her <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/amy-klobuchar-minnesota-governor-00754285" target="_blank">bid for Minnesota governor</a> official Thursday morning, presaging a leadership shakeup in the caucus.</p> 
<p>Klobuchar was viewed as a potential contender to succeed Illinois Sen. Dick Durbin as Democratic whip after Durbin — who has held the No. 2 position for two decades — <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/23/dick-durbin-retiring-from-senate-illinois-00305833" target="_blank">announced his retirement</a> last year.</p> 
<p>But Sen. Brian Schatz of Hawaii moved quickly to lock down support to succeed Durbin, and Klobuchar never threw her name in. Even so, she was seen as a credible successor to Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, who is planning to run again for leader but has faced calls to step down from outside the caucus.</p> 
<p>Klobuchar’s announcement comes amid a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/senators-block-funding-package-amid-dhs-standoff-00754927" target="_blank">fight on Capitol Hill</a> about President Donald Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement agenda in her home state. The killing of two U.S. citizens at the hands of federal agents in Minneapolis has thrown federal funding for the Department of Homeland Security into question ahead of a Friday midnight shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>With the funding fight in full swing and the internal leadership election not taking place until after the November elections, other Democratic leaders aren’t yet jumping to declare their interest in moving up the ranks.</p> 
<p>“Let’s talk about it after,” Sen. Cory Booker of New Jersey, the No. 4 Democratic leader, told reporters Thursday. “I am really just focused on an agency out of control.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Chris Murphy of Connecticut, another member of Senate leadership and the top Democrat on the Homeland Security funding panel, said he isn’t focused on how leadership ranks will shift.</p> 
<p>“We got other big things we’re doing today,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-29T15:53:17-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Feds charge man accused of attacking Ilhan Omar at town hall with assault</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/omar-attack-00755404</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0b37-dbc5-a7bd-1bbf99f90000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 14:31:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Federal authorities charged a man who allegedly attacked Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) this week at a town hall in Minnesota with assaulting or impeding a federal employee.</p> 
<p>Minneapolis resident Anthony Kazmierczak, 55, allegedly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540" target="_blank">charged at Omar</a> on Tuesday night and sprayed her with a liquid after she called for the abolishment of Immigration and Customs Enforcement and the removal of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem, addressing constituents at a town hall amid <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">unrest in the city</a> following the fatal shootings of two Minneapolis residents this month.</p> 
<p>Kazmierczak apparently responded, “She’s not resigning. You’re splitting Minnesotans apart,” according to video evidence reviewed by the FBI.</p> 
<p>Kazmierczak was tackled by two security guards and later arrested by the Minneapolis Police Department. During his initial court appearance on Thursday, Kazmierczak was ordered detained pending a detention hearing on Feb. 3.</p> 
<p>A hazardous materials specialist later identified the substance from the syringe as water and apple cider vinegar, with Kazmierczak allegedly admitting to squirting Omar with vinegar at the time of his arrest, according to <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.mnd.231039/gov.uscourts.mnd.231039.1.1.pdf" target="_blank">an affidavit</a>.</p> 
<p>At a Wednesday press conference, Omar — who has been a frequent target of Donald Trump's criticism — blamed the president for threats against her.</p> 
<p>“Every time the president of the United States has chosen to use hateful rhetoric to talk about me and the community that I represent, my death threats skyrocket,” she said.</p> 
<p>The attack came less than a week after Trump wrote in <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/115941130299210878" target="_blank">a social media post</a> that Omar “should be investigated for Financial and Political Crimes, and that investigation should start, NOW!” Trump has criticized her many times on social media.</p> 
<p>Shortly after the incident, Trump reiterated his criticism of the Minnesota Democrat, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/trump-hints-relaxed-federal-tactics-minnesota-after-shootings/story?id=129626425" target="_blank">telling ABC News</a>: “I think she's a fraud.” He also alleged, without evidence, that Omar may have “had her herself sprayed.”</p> 
<p>Kazmierczak, who has been arrested twice for driving under the influence and was convicted of felony auto theft in 1989, apparently told a close associate that “someone should kill” Omar several years ago, per the affidavit.</p> 
<p>He also has a history of pro-Trump social media activity. In one October 2021 Facebook post, he shared a political cartoon depicting Omar holding a sign that reads “Defund police” and saying: “Security for me, none for thee.” The cartoon also depicts a security officer holding a bag of money that reads: “Omar and the squad spent a combined $100,000 on security last quarter,” an apparent reference to the young progressive group of House Democrats.</p> 
<p>Kazmierczak also repeatedly posted in defense of Kyle Rittenhouse, the man who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2021/11/19/rittenhouse-not-guilty-in-kenosha-murder-case-523049" target="_blank">shot three people</a> — killing two — at a 2020 Black Lives Matter protest in Kenosha, Wisconsin.</p> 
<p><i>Josh Gerstein contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-29T12:39:41-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Senators block funding package amid DHS standoff</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/senators-block-funding-package-amid-dhs-standoff-00754927</link>
      <description>There will be a partial government shutdown if lawmakers cannot reach a deal by Saturday morning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0ad2-df8c-a99d-fff6c7e60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 12:35:41 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/59/57/1330ecee4532b29bee41a699f9df/2026-0128-congress-francis-8-1-92741.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.) hands a document to an aide during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 28, 2026. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/59/57/1330ecee4532b29bee41a699f9df/2026-0128-congress-francis-8-1-92741.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus, Jordain Carney and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus, Jordain Carney and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Eight Republicans joined every Senate Democrat to block sweeping government funding legislation from advancing Thursday amid ongoing negotiations around a potential offramp to avert a lengthy shutdown of several agencies.</p> 
<p>The Senate voted 55-45 against moving forward with a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill package</a> that would fund, among other things, the departments of Homeland Security, State and Health and Human Services, as well as the Pentagon.</p> 
<p>The measure accounts for more than 75 percent of discretionary spending across the federal government, and programs relying on this money will shutter if Congress cannot reach a deal by 12:01 a.m. Saturday.</p> 
<p>The House already passed these bills, then left town for recess. The Senate was on track to clear them without much drama. But then came last weekend’s killing in Minneapolis of Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old U.S. citizen, at the hands of Border Patrol agents.</p> 
<p>The incident has fueled new scrutiny of the administration’s immigration enforcement activities, including from some of President Donald Trump’s more reliable GOP allies on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Democrats now say they will oppose advancing the funding measure as long as <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">funding for DHS</a> is included — or until Republicans agree to legislation that would put new guardrails around ICE.</p> 
<p>The current DHS bill would reduce the agency’s budget for enforcement and removal efforts but also hand ICE $10 billion for the remainder of the fiscal year. It would require DHS to use $20 million to outfit immigration enforcement agents with body cameras, direct the department to give officers more training on defusing conflict while interacting with the public and provide a separate $20 million for independent oversight of DHS detention facilities.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said ahead of the vote Thursday that Democrats remain ready to pass the other five funding bills included in the package as he engages in discussions with the White House on what further changes could be made to the DHS bill to address Democrats’ concerns.</p> 
<p>The New York Democrat said “strong legislation to rein in ICE” is necessary.</p> 
<p>“Congress has to step up to the plate,” Schumer added. “The Republican majority must step up to the plate.”</p> 
<p>Democrats across Congress want rules tightened around the use of warrants and identification of DHS agents conducting immigration enforcement operations, among other things.</p> 
<p>Many of Democrats' requests for changing the DHS bill were pursued earlier in the process at the committee level, but didn’t have the support to make it into the bipartisan and bicameral compromise package.</p> 
<p>Republicans and Democrats are talking, according to a person granted anonymity to speak freely, but a deal is not done.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said in an interview Thursday before the doomed procedural vote that he believed the negotiations were “trending in the right direction.”</p> 
<p>After the vote went down, Thune moved to lay the groundwork to quickly bring the package back up if Democrats and the White House can reach a deal. He voted “no” to give himself the option to force reconsideration later.</p> 
<p>Republican Sens. Ted Budd of North Carolina, Ron Johnson of Wisconsin, Tommy Tuberville of Alabama, Mike Lee of Utah, Rand Paul of Kentucky and Rick Scott and Ashley Moody of Florida were the other GOP lawmakers who voted “no.” Some are seeking a potential opportunity to reshape the Department of Homeland Security funding bill; others are looking to secure further spending cuts.</p> 
<p>Ultimately, Congress appears likely to barrel over the shutdown cliff for at least some amount of time, as the House is out of town until Monday and hard-liners in that chamber have already vowed to complicate leadership’s ability to pass the funding bills a second time. House GOP leaders are set to meet later Thursday to discuss options, two people familiar with the private deliberations said.</p> 
<p>The other person granted anonymity to share details of private party dynamics said Democrats could be willing to shore up the votes for a short-term spending patch — as long as it is very brief for the sole purpose of allowing more time to close out negotiations on a new DHS bill.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans believe the administration is open to making changes to the House-passed DHS measure in the wake of the backlash over Pretti’s death. Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins also announced Thursday morning that Homeland Security Secretary Krisi Noem had informed her that ICE had ended its enhanced operations in Maine at the Republican lawmaker’s request — another sign the White House could be ready to cooperate.</p> 
<p>Members of both parties want to move quickly. Though the congressional fight has been focused on immigration enforcement activities, the DHS bill also would fund the Coast Guard, FEMA, TSA and other critical agencies through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats had raised concerns in particular about FEMA funding as a significant swath of the country continues to recover from a widespread winter storm from this past weekend.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Ag advances crypto bill along party lines</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-ag-advances-crypto-bill-00754586</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0a9e-dabb-ad9c-3fff0b0e0004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 11:38:34 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate Agriculture Committee voted along party lines Thursday to advance a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_DRAFT19" target="_blank">landmark cryptocurrency bill</a>, sending the measure to the Senate floor without bipartisan backing.</p> 
<p>The committee voted 12-11 to advance so-called crypto market structure legislation, which would create new rules governing how digital tokens are regulated. The bill that the Ag panel approved Thursday, which would grant new crypto regulatory authority to the Commodity Futures Trading Commission, would need to eventually be merged with a second part of the bill dealing with the Securities and Exchange Commission that falls under the Senate Banking Committee’s jurisdiction.</p> 
<p>The party-line vote came after months of negotiations between Ag Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51287" data-person-id="51287">John Boozman</a> (R-Ark.) and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/211545" data-person-id="211545">Cory Booker</a> (D-N.J.) failed to yield a bipartisan deal. Boozman plowed ahead with a GOP-only bill, saying “there were fundamental policy disagreements” between the two sides and it is now “time to move this process forward.”</p> 
<p>“The CFTC is the right agency to regulate the spot trading of digital commodities,” he said in an opening statement. “At a high level, this bill provides a clear definition of a digital commodity, protects innovation and technology, establishes consumer protection safeguards, and equips the agency with the necessary resources to take on this new responsibility.”</p> 
<p>Booker, who is a member of a Senate Democratic working group that is negotiating with Republicans on the market structure bill, said Republicans were “walking away from the bipartisan process that produced” <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/11/senate-ag-releases-long-awaited-crypto-bill-draft-00641759" target="_blank">a Boozman-Booker discussion draft</a> last year.</p> 
<p>“That frustrates me because I see a bipartisan glide path to land this plane, to punch through the end zone,” Booker said.</p> 
<p>Boozman said that he remains “committed to continue working with” Democrats on the bill as it moves toward the floor, adding that “what we want is a bipartisan bill.”</p> 
<p>The panel voted down several amendments offered by Democrats along party lines, including a provision from Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/69394" data-person-id="69394">Michael Bennet</a> (D-Colo.) that would ban federal officials and their families from issuing or endorsing digital assets. Ethics issues have been a major sticking point in market structure negotiations, as Democrats have pressed for language targeting the Trump family’s crypto businesses.</p> 
<p>Republicans also voted to reject a pair of amendments from Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.) that would seek to crack down on crypto ATM fraud and ban some crypto firms from receiving a federal bailout, respectively.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-29T12:34:49-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House infighting will complicate brewing Senate spending deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/shutdown-house-dhs-stopgap-00754590</link>
      <description>Some Republicans are skeptical of a plan to split off and renegotiate Homeland Security funding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0a93-d452-a99e-6bff5cd70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 11:27:24 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/3f/cb/6630e8a64206b866af814ab564ca/u-s-congress-65837.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Speaker Mike Johnson's GOP majority is set to further narrow over the weekend.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/3f/cb/6630e8a64206b866af814ab564ca/u-s-congress-65837.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Nicholas Wu and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Nicholas Wu and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As White House officials and Senate Democrats scramble to nail down a last-minute deal to salvage a massive spending package, an internal GOP battle is brewing in the House over whether to accept any compromise.</p> 
<p>At stake is whether a partial government shutdown set to kick off early Saturday morning would last just a few days or much longer. The House is in recess and currently not expected to reconvene until Monday.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders expect President Donald Trump will have to lean heavily on House Republicans to get any Senate-approved agreement through the other chamber. Earlier this week, conservative hard-liners <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/freedom-caucus-dhs-ultimatum-00749816" target="_blank">threatened to oppose</a> the potential plan — suggesting a shutdown could drag on for weeks if leaders aren’t careful.</p> 
<p>The Senate talks have revolved around splitting off Homeland Security funding from a larger six-bill package the House sent across the Capitol last week and passing a stopgap measure to keep DHS agencies open while additional strictures on immigration enforcement are negotiated.</p> 
<p>A White House official granted anonymity to comment on the pending negotiations said Trump “wants the government to remain open” and confirmed the administration is “working with both parties to ensure the American people don’t have to endure another shutdown.”</p> 
<p>Privately, some GOP hard-liners are open to the possibility of a DHS stopgap, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal conversations, with one saying it was “not an automatic no.”</p> 
<p>But their support would depend on the length of the stopgap and whether any Democratic policies are included as part of the agreement. That person added that a two-week punt negotiators are discussing would be “ridiculous.” Ultra-conservatives would prefer one lasting six weeks or longer.</p> 
<p>Democrats want to move in the opposite direction, with Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/282320" data-person-id="282320">Tina Smith </a>of Minnesota <a href="https://x.com/SenTinaSmith/status/2016873883559686445" target="_blank">calling for a negotiation</a> of “days, not weeks.”</p> 
<p>In any scenario, GOP leaders will likely need Trump’s involvement to get the DHS stopgap and the remaining five bills passed in the House and signed into law, which would keep the vast majority of federal agencies — including the Pentagon — open through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson already is dealing with a razor-thin margin, and a special election in Texas over the weekend is expected to complicate matters. If the Democratic nominee wins as expected, Johnson could spare only a single defection on a party-line vote.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders are set to discuss their plans Thursday afternoon, including whether they would need to call the House back earlier than currently planned Monday night, according to two other people granted anonymity to describe private deliberations. But that will depend on how quickly the Senate can pass any agreement.</p> 
<p>Another complication is that a huge swath of House Democrats would likely oppose stopgap funding for DHS, which would keep ICE and Border Patrol funded at current levels without immediate new restrictions. That could prevent GOP leaders from trying to pass the spending legislation on a bipartisan basis under suspension of the rules, which requires a two-thirds majority vote.</p> 
<p>On a caucus call Wednesday night, House Democrats aired concerns their Senate counterparts might accept a deal that does not put real guardrails on DHS agents, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the private meeting. Their leaders haven’t been included in the talks with the White House so far.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries told reporters Thursday his caucus would "evaluate" whatever emerged out of the Senate on DHS funding and signaled they might settle for a stopgap funding bill for the agency while broader negotiations come together.</p> 
<p>"If we're on a path to a dramatic, immediate, transformative change, then I'm sure that will be a part of what heavily weighs into our discussion," he said.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a>, asked Thursday about how soon a potential agreement could get final House approval, said his “hope and expectation” is that the other chamber will do “what's necessary to keep the government funded.” He added that the House plan would be up to Johnson, whom he has spoken with, while acknowledging that having to abandon the six-bill package was “not ideal, for sure.”</p> 
<p>“We'd hoped to process all the six bills and send it to the White House, but we are where we are, and so we got to try and sort it out and get the best possible outcome given the hand we've been dealt,” Thune added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-29T11:51:04-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Democrats and White House in last-ditch talks to avert extended shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/shutdown-deadline-dhs-funding-vote-ice-00754278</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-07bf-d9a8-a7be-87bf98230000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 07:54:40 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats and the White House are in intensive negotiations over how to avert an extended partial shutdown of the federal government that is set to start early Saturday morning.</p> 
<p>The two sides haven’t yet reached an agreement, according to a person granted anonymity to describe the private discussions.</p> 
<p>Even if Democrats and the White House reach an agreement, Congress is still expected to blow past the Friday midnight shutdown deadline, since the House is in recess until Monday and is not expected to reconvene earlier to ratify any changes to the six-bill funding package it sent to the Senate last week.</p> 
<p>The person with knowledge of the discussions characterized them as “ongoing and moving in Democrats’ direction.” A White House official granted anonymity to comment on the pending negotiations said Trump “wants the government to remain open” and confirmed the administration is “working with both parties to ensure the American people don’t have to endure another shutdown.”</p> 
<p>Democrats have unified behind a demand that Republicans agree to remove Department of Homeland Security funding from the six-bill package following the killing of Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old Minneapolis man, by federal agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>The Senate is set to vote on that package Thursday morning, with Democrats expected to block it absent an agreement with the White House. Were the Senate to agree on splitting apart the bills, it’s unclear if or how quickly the House could act to send them to President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Democrats want to renegotiate the DHS bill to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/democrats-dhs-minnesota-shutdown-00753256" target="_blank">include new restrictions and rules</a> for immigration enforcement activities, including tightening rules for warrants and requiring independent investigations.</p> 
<p>But Democrats are open to a “very-short term extension” of DHS funding in order to give Congress and the White House time to renegotiate the bill, the person added.</p> 
<p>White House border czar Tom Homan, who has been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/white-house-banks-on-homan-to-help-avert-shutdown-00754083" target="_blank">tasked by Trump with overseeing the DHS enforcement operation</a> in Minnesota, is set to address reporters Thursday morning in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>Separately, Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) announced early Thursday that ICE has ended its “enhanced activities” in Maine, citing a conversation with Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem.</p> 
<p>“There are currently no ongoing or planned large-scale ICE operations here,” Collins said.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Key crypto markup: </b>The Senate Agriculture Committee will mark up landmark cryptocurrency legislation at 10:30 a.m. The big question is whether any Democrats will back the so-called crypto market structure bill coming out of committee.</p> 
<p>Chair John Boozman (R-Ark.) negotiated for months over the proposal with Sen. Cory Booker (D-N.J.), but is moving forward with a GOP-only bill that doesn’t currently have any bipartisan backing. That could set the stage for a party-line vote Thursday — or Democrats could vote for it and push for further changes before it hits the floor.</p> 
<p><i>Jasper Goodman contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Who can you kill?’: Minnesota crisis collides with Rand Paul’s ideological crusade</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/rand-paul-dhs-alex-pretti-00754259</link>
      <description>As Homeland Security chair, the Kentucky Republican has significant power to shape Congress’ response to the deaths of Alex Pretti and Renee Good.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0774-d9a8-a7be-87f60dae0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d0/89/b742392840ec966b74e78d109bfe/unlimiteduse-01-28-2025-rubio-congress-0011-30492.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>"It’s something I’ve been concerned with the whole time I’ve been here," Sen. Rand Paul said Wednesday about federal overreach.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d0/89/b742392840ec966b74e78d109bfe/unlimiteduse-01-28-2025-rubio-congress-0011-30492.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rand Paul made his name as a gadfly preaching about the dangers of a tyrannical federal government. Now, after the killings of two Minnesota residents at the hands of Homeland Security agents, the Kentucky Republican has a chance to do something about it.</p> 
<p>The 63-year-old, who spent years on the outskirts of the party, is now at the center of the Senate’s response to the deaths of Renee Good and Alex Pretti, which have sparked new criticism of the administration’s immigration enforcement policies and raised <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/democrats-trump-administration-dueling-accounts-minneapolis-shooting-00745811?utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank">many of the same civil liberties</a> questions Paul has long been asking.</p> 
<p>As chair of the Senate Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee, he’s already forced a trio of top immigration officials to agree to testify, publicly criticized the administration’s response to the Pretti shooting and even raised the possibility Congress might step in if the administration refuses to conduct an independent investigation of that incident.</p> 
<p>“For people to have confidence in government and confidence in law enforcement … we have to be very honest,” Paul told reporters. “I don’t think anybody in America believes he was assaulting those officers, so we have to tell the truth.”</p> 
<p>But Paul — who is already in President Donald Trump’s doghouse as an inconsistent GOP ally — is still walking a fine line.</p> 
<p>He repeatedly refused this week to weigh in on if Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem should leave the administration, saying he was “reserving judgment for now.” And he has also taken pains to separate himself from some of DHS’s most aggressive Democratic critics, telling reporters he is “for restoring trust in ICE” — not abolishing it.</p> 
<p>Were Noem to depart, Paul could find himself in an especially precarious position. As chair of the Homeland Security panel, he would essentially serve as gatekeeper for the confirmation of any replacement. A single Republican defection on the committee could block any Trump nominee who does not have Democratic support.</p> 
<p>Speaking to reporters, he connected his skepticism about the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement practices to his longstanding ideological crusade.</p> 
<p>“I mean, it's something I've been concerned with the whole time I've been here,” he said. “What are the rights of individuals? Who can you kill? When can you kill them? What is war? What is not war? What is due process? When do you have Fourth Amendment protections? So all these things are incredibly important.”</p> 
<p>For now, it’s an open question as to how far he is willing to risk his political career to push back against Trump’s historically aggressive agenda — with GOP colleagues skeptical he would block a Cabinet pick.</p> 
<p>He might not have to go to such extremes. After Paul publicly questioned why the DHS agents involved in the Pretti shooting were still on the job Tuesday, the department announced Wednesday they had been <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/minnesota-shooting-agents-leave-00753083" target="_blank">placed on leave</a> — though no steps have been publicly taken toward the independent probe the senator is seeking.</p> 
<p>While Paul’s skepticism of federal power, both domestically and abroad, has long made him suspect in the eyes of Trump loyalists, his decision to use his committee gavel to seek answers from DHS is earning support from fellow Republicans — many of whom are uneasy over the administration’s enforcement surge in Minnesota, even if they aren’t willing to go as far as Paul.</p> 
<p>“Terrible — I mean, this is why there needs to be a full investigation as the president said,” Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.), a member of the Homeland Security panel, told reporters earlier this week. “I’m a firm believer in qualified immunity for law enforcement, but qualified immunity isn’t total immunity.”</p> 
<p>Hawley added that the Feb. 12 hearing, under Paul’s direction, would be “thorough.”</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who has disagreed plenty with his libertarian-leaning GOP colleague, also backed up Paul’s decision to have the hearing with the heads of ICE, Customs and Border Protection, and Citizenship and Immigration Services.</p> 
<p>“I think it's important,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>Underscoring the unusual role Paul occupies in the Senate, Democrats also view him as a potential ally who might help them force answers out of top administration leaders. While the Kentucky Republican frequently clashes with Democrats, especially on fiscal matters, he’s teamed up in recent weeks on bipartisan efforts to check the president’s war and tariff powers.</p> 
<p>Sen. Andy Kim (D-N.J.), another member of the Homeland panel, praised Paul’s decision to call in the administration officials to testify.</p> 
<p>“We've had a number of other experiences where there have been issues that are very much on the people's minds, and Congress and colleagues have not called in the administration,” he said in an interview. “This is a good sign from his proactive nature.”</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer also praised Paul as an example of a Republican who understands that “the American people demand truth and accountability right now.”</p> 
<p>Paul, however, is making clear his concerns about the administration’s response to Saturday’s shooting aren’t personal against Trump. And there are signs his orbit is treading lightly around the Minnesota crisis.</p> 
<p>After Pretti’s killing Saturday, Doug Stafford — Paul’s longtime chief strategist — <a href="https://x.com/adamwren/status/2015192154528731585" target="_blank">posted on X</a>, questioning why Border Patrol officers were in a city nowhere near the border and “when did it become illegal to carry a gun in America.” </p> 
<p>He later deleted the post. A spokesperson for Paul’s office did not respond to a request for comment on that decision.</p> 
<p>“[Paul is] not a partisan voice,” said Brian Darling, a lobbyist who previously worked for Paul in the Senate. “He’s somebody who is going to look at the issue and look at it from a conservative perspective. And look at it from the perspective of preserving liberty. That’s the way he analyzes issues.”</p> 
<p>In the case of the Minnesota shooting, Darling said Paul would not simply look the other way because of his Republican colleagues.</p> 
<p>“He’s not going to play team ball on an issue where he sees important issues like the Fourth Amendment, the Second Amendment at risk,” he added.</p> 
<p>Often a maverick among the Senate GOP, Paul was cast aside as the party crafted Trump’s landmark domestic policy bill last year. As Homeland chair, Paul had jurisdiction over one of the legislation’s central pillars — a surge in new spending on border security.</p> 
<p>But he clashed with the Trump administration and Senate leadership over how much to give the agencies in question. Members of his panel, at the time, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/20/rand-paul-trump-republican-border-00414101" target="_blank">suggested Paul was operating</a> without consulting his peers.</p> 
<p>His legislative text was rejected. Budget Committee Chair Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), who has a history of butting heads with Paul, instead led the drafting of the language.</p> 
<p>As the fury mounted over Pretti’s killing Monday and Democrats started uniting around blocking funding for ICE, Paul offered a public reminder of how much funding the agency already had.</p> 
<p>“The Senate is debating another $10B for ICE. But Congress already locked in nearly $19B a year for four years,” he <a href="https://x.com/RandPaul/status/2015890857241579689" target="_blank">wrote on X</a>. “Even if this fails, ICE will still have about 87% more funding than last year.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Democrats float DHS changes in shutdown stalemate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/democrats-dhs-minnesota-shutdown-00753256</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-064e-d1ea-a5de-36ced07d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 15:48:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Democrats on Wednesday revealed the DHS restrictions they need in exchange for helping Republicans avert a shutdown Friday night, including the tightening of rules on warrants.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer outlined the asks after a closed-door caucus meeting, telling reporters that Democrats were united around “common sense and necessary policy goals.”</p> 
<p>The list – featuring several demands previously <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">reported by POLITICO</a> — also included a prohibition on agents using masks, mandates for body cameras and IDs and a “uniform code of conduct and accountability,” including requiring independent investigations of incidents like Saturday’s fatal shooting of Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p>“Republicans must work with Democrats to find legislative solutions,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Wednesday’s caucus meeting was the first time Senate Democrats had gathered in person and talked strategy since the killing of Pretti by federal agents in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>The shooting and the initial response by top administration officials have fueled widespread calls for changes to the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement strategy. On Capitol Hill, it has upended the debate over government funding ahead of Friday’s midnight shutdown deadline.</p> 
<p>The Senate will vote Thursday on a six-bill package that would fund several departments, including DHS. But Democrats have demanded that Senate Majority Leader John Thune strip out the DHS bill and negotiate new policy changes for immigration agencies. Senators are widely expecting the bill to fail to advance Thursday, which would force them to pivot to a Plan B. </p> 
<p>“There has to be accountability,” Sen. Tina Smith (D-Minn.) said. “This is not like some wish list. This is like really practical, common sense stuff that would actually go a long way towards minimizing the harm that we’re seeing in Minnesota right now.”</p> 
<p>Republicans are loath to strip out the Department of Homeland Security bill because any changes to the funding package would require it to go back to the House, where GOP hardliners are already vowing to throw up roadblocks.</p> 
<p>Though talks have been ongoing between Senate Republicans, Democrats and the White House, Republicans have been waiting for Schumer to outline specifically what Democrats want.</p> 
<p>“There's been overtures and attempts to try to connect on what they want and then see if it's something the administration could accommodate without having to change the language of the bill,” Senate Majority Leader John Thune told reporters.</p> 
<p>But Schumer said the “White House has had no specific, concrete ideas.”</p> 
<p>Without a deal to pass the funding package as is, a partial government shutdown will start Saturday. Privately, Republicans are hoping if there is a partial shutdown that they would be able to negotiate an off-ramp by Monday or early next week.</p> 
<p>Republicans have floated that the administration could take executive actions to address some of Democrats' concerns.</p> 
<p>But Smith dismissed that Wednesday, adding, “If you believe that I’ve got a bridge.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Republicans set to make ‘best and final’ Obamacare offer, Moreno says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/republicans-set-to-make-best-and-final-obamacare-offer-moreno-says-00752843</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-05d1-d452-a99e-6dff53160005</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:16:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>GOP Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> said that Republicans will make their “best and final” offer after weeks of bipartisan talks to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/senate-deal-obamacare-subsidies-00714048" target="_blank">revive lapsed Obamacare subsidies</a>.</p> 
<p>“It’s going to be in the hands of the Democrats very shortly. … Here’s the exact thing that we think is the maximum we can sell our conference,” Moreno told reporters.</p> 
<p>“This would be it,” the Ohioan added. “This is the best and final” offer.</p> 
<p>Moreno is one of the lead GOP negotiators involved in months of talks about a potential two-year revival of the enhanced Obamacare tax credits that lapsed Jan. 1. The senators involved have discussed immediate new restrictions such as an income limit, as well as more sweeping changes kicking in the second year, including expanding the use of health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>Moreno separately told reporters the group is proposing to maintain the status quo on the Hyde amendment, which restricts the use of federal dollars on abortion services.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/197755" data-person-id="197755">Angus King</a> (I-Maine), who has been involved with the talks, appeared optimistic about the chances of a deal, telling reporters Wednesday he expected to receive text later in the day. The health care discussions have been largely back-burnered as Congress has spent recent weeks dealing with an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">approaching government shutdown deadline</a>.</p> 
<p>“I think we’re very close,” said King, who caucuses with Democrats. “We have a solid bipartisan group, and hopefully we can move the bill once we get through this budget situation.”</p> 
<p>But others involved in the negotiations have been surprised by Moreno’s comments about the impending release of a bill, noting that Democrats had not seen or signed off on anything yet, according to two people granted anonymity to speak candidly about the talks.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-28T13:43:37-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Rubio digs in on cooperation with Venezuela’s Rodríguez, lack of immediate elections</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/rubio-venezuela-hearing-00752750</link>
      <description>Democrats lashed Rubio for the administration’s lack of transparency about the Jan. 3 operation to capture ousted Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-05b0-dabb-ad9c-3ffdd1260000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:49:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c8/ae/fc02637e4d878ddc67890e35a3fe/unlimiteduse-01-28-2025-rubio-congress-0007-47495.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Secretary of State Marco Rubio testifies before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee on Capitol Hill in Washington, on Jan. 28, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c8/ae/fc02637e4d878ddc67890e35a3fe/unlimiteduse-01-28-2025-rubio-congress-0007-47495.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Secretary of State Marco Rubio defended the Trump administration’s decision to work with the remnants of ousted Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro’s regime on Wednesday, as Democrats raise questions about the timeline for elections and a transition to democracy in the South American petrostate.</p> 
<p>Testifying before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Rubio reiterated previous statements that the ultimate goal in Venezuela is to restore democracy, but emphasized that the country needs to stabilize so that the opposition can actually participate in free and fair elections.</p> 
<p>“You can have elections, you have elections all day, but if the opposition has no access to the media, if opposition candidates are routinely dismissed and unable to be on the ballot because of the government, those aren't free and fair elections,” Rubio said. “That's the end state that we want: a free, fair, prosperous and friendly Venezuela. We're not going to get there in three weeks. It's going to take some time.”</p> 
<p>Rubio has consistently pushed the need for elections in Venezuela, though without giving a timeline. His comments suggest that a ballot could be well into the future. Some others inside the administration have argued that elections aren’t needed, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/trump-demands-venezuela-leader-00711728" target="_blank">as POLITICO has reported</a>.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump’s comments around U.S. access to Venezuela’s vast oil reserves and his praise of acting Venezuelan leader Delcy Rodriguez have raised questions about how much democracy in Venezuela is a priority for the administration.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Rodriguez, long an ally of Maduro who rose up the ranks in Caracas, has in recent days said her country will not take orders from Washington. Her comments have rankled the Venezuelan opposition and their friends in Washington, who already see the longtime regime official as an untrustworthy partner for the United States.</p> 
<p>Rubio’s comments Wednesday make clear the administration’s view that a pragmatic course is necessary to restore democracy in Venezuela. Rubio, who noted he’s meeting later Wednesday with Venezuelan opposition leader Maria Corina Machado, said that the administration does want to see more progress towards stabilizing the country over the next few months.</p> 
<p>But Rubio reiterated that more steps need to be taken, including reopening the U.S. embassy in Caracas.</p> 
<p>“One thing is for me to pick up the phone and talk to Delcy Rodriguez three times a week,” Rubio said. “Another thing is to have someone on the ground on a daily basis that's following these events, is talking to civil society, but also engaging with interim authorities.”</p> 
<p>In the face of sharp questions from Democrats — who’ve argued Rodriguez staying in power reflects an impediment to a transition to democracy — Rubio also insisted that working with Rodriguez is a necessary step.</p> 
<p>“No one here is telling you this is what we want to see in the long term,” Rubio said. “Whether we like it or not, the elements of control in that country — the people with the guns, the people that control the guns and the institutions of government there — are in the hands of this regime.”</p> 
<p>It was the first time the secretary of State and acting national security adviser had spoken to lawmakers in a public hearing since the campaign against Venezuela began months ago. Republicans largely praised the operation and focused questions on the structures to open up access to Venezuela’s oil reserves.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Democrats used that setting to criticize the administration for a lack of transparency around the military operations in Venezuela. Democrats had protested that only Republicans were directly briefed by Rubio in the immediate aftermath of the Jan. 3 operation to capture Maduro — and that all briefings occurred after the operation had begun.</p> 
<p>“Consulting with Congress is not just some high-minded principle, not some abstract thing, not a nice-to-have. It's a got-to have,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151823" data-person-id="151823">Chris Coons</a> (D-Del.).</p> 
<p>Democrats and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/175586" data-person-id="175586">Rick Scott</a> (R-Fla.) also raised questions about the timeline for future elections in Venezuela. The administration has not committed to a hard plan to see elections in the South American petrostate, but worries have mounted on both sides of the aisle that a long wait for elections may allow Rodriguez and the remnants of the Maduro regime to entrench their grip on power.</p> 
<p>The secretary of State, who served in the Senate for over a decade before his appointment, received a friendly welcome from Republicans, many of whom took pains to praise the operation and Rubio’s contributions to the administration. Senate Foreign Relations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66832" data-person-id="66832">Jim Risch</a> (R-Idaho) said Americans were “lucky” to have Rubio as secretary of State. Others, meanwhile, focused their questions on efforts to expand U.S. access to Venezuela’s vast oil reserves.</p> 
<p>Still, Rubio faced some tough questioning from his former Republican colleagues. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151828" data-person-id="151828">Rand Paul</a> (R-Ky.), critical of the campaign against Venezuela since the U.S. began striking alleged drug boats off Venezuelan waters, needled the secretary on the legal basis of the operation and whether Congress should have authorized it.</p> 
<p>Rubio responded that the short duration of the actual capture of Maduro, coupled with the fact that Maduro faced federal indictment in U.S. courts and was seen as the illegitimate leader of Venezuela, meant the operation did not reflect an act of war such that it would require congressional authorization.</p> 
<p>That answer did not satisfy Paul.</p> 
<p>“We’re in violation of both the spirit and the law of the constitution by bombing a capital, blockading a country and removing elected officials. And we certainly wouldn’t tolerate it, not would I, if someone did it to us,” Paul said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol police report spike in threats made toward lawmakers in 2025</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/congress-threats-rise-2025-00752137</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0551-dabb-ad9c-3ffdfce30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:22:48 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Threats toward members of Congress, their families, staff and the Capitol complex surged in 2025, according to the U.S. Capitol Police, with over 5,000 more incidents reported than the previous year.</p> 
<p>The police force’s Threat Assessment Section investigated 14,938 “concerning” statements, behaviors and communications, the agency <a href="https://www.uscp.gov/media-center/press-releases/uscp-threat-assessment-cases-2025" target="_blank">said in a news release this week</a>.</p> 
<p>It’s a sharp increase from 2024, when 9,474 threats were investigated by USCP. These threats — which include everything from social media posts to more direct targeting of lawmakers — mark the third year in a row that USCP has seen an increase in the number of threats made.</p> 
<p>As the number of incidents continues to rise, Capitol Police Chief Michael Sullivan said in a statement that USCP has been “strengthening” its partnerships with law enforcement agencies across the country so members can remain safe when they are away from Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>“We want to make sure agencies have the resources they need to be able to enhance protection, which is critical to the democratic process,” Sullivan said.</p> 
<p>In recent years, the nation has seen <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/09/12/charlie-kirk-political-violence-expert-analysis-00558638" target="_blank">an increase in political violence</a>, with some targeting members of Congress.</p> 
<p>On Tuesday, a man was arrested after charging Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) and spraying her with an unknown substance <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540" target="_blank">during a town hall</a>.</p> 
<p>In September, conservative activist Charlie Kirk was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/10/charlie-kirk-tpusa-shot-00555826" target="_blank">killed while speaking at a college campus</a>. Last summer, a gunman <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/14/minnesota-lawmakers-targeted-shooting-00406125" target="_blank">shot two Minnesota state lawmakers,</a> killing one. Two months before that, an arsonist <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/14/josh-shapiro-pennsylvania-arson-attack-00288601" target="_blank">set fire to the Pennsylvania governor’s mansion</a> while Democratic Gov. Josh Shapiro and his family slept inside. And during the 2024 presidential campaign, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2024/09/15/trump-gunshots-florida-golf-club-00179228" target="_blank">a gunman shot President Donald Trump</a> at a political rally during an attempted assassination.</p> 
<p>USCP on Wednesday said one of the best ways to combat the number of threats facing legislators around the country is to decrease violent political rhetoric — a sentiment both Democrats and Republicans have been urging their counterparts to do each time violence breaks out.</p> 
<p>As Capitol Police continue to monitor threat assessments, the department has expanded its Protective Intelligence Operations Center, which launched in 2024 as a way to process reports regarding the safety of the legislators. The 24/7 center works with the House and Senate Sergeant at Arms to monitor members’ safety, the agency says.</p> 
<p>“We, and both Sergeant at Arms, are seeing an increase of reporting through our outreach efforts with the Congressional Community,” said Jeanita Mitchell, acting assistant chief of police for protective and intelligence operations.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump dings Murkowski, Tillis after their Noem criticism, calls them ‘losers’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/trump-attacks-tillis-murkowski-00752089</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-053b-d9a8-a7be-87bbb1210000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:45:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump took a swing at Sens. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) and Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) after they called for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem to be fired, dismissing both as “losers.”</p> 
<p>“They’re terrible senators. One is gone, and the other should be gone,” Trump said in an interview with <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/trump-hints-relaxed-federal-tactics-minnesota-after-shootings/story?id=129626425" target="_blank">ABC News posted Wednesday</a>. “What Murkowski says — she’s always against the Republicans anyway. And Tillis decided to drop out. So you know, he lost his voice once he did that.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski and Tillis became <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/thom-tillis-kristi-noem-fired-00750580" target="_blank">the first Republicans in Congress to publicly state</a> that Noem should lose her job after her response to a second highly publicized shooting in Minnesota involving federal immigration agents.</p> 
<p>“I think what she’s done in Minnesota should be disqualifying,” Tillis, who is not seeking reelection, told reporters Tuesday. “It’s just amateurish. It’s terrible. It’s making the president look bad.”</p> 
<p>Murkowski told reporters separately that “she should go,” adding to mounting pressure for Trump to fire Noem following the killing of 37-year-old nurse Alex Pretti on Saturday.</p> 
<p>Trump has remained supportive of Noem, telling reporters at the White House on Tuesday, “I think she’s doing a very good job.” When asked if Noem would step down, he replied, “No.”</p> 
<p>Noem faced backlash for her comments soon after Pretti’s shooting, <a href="https://youtu.be/bocDdL_a-IM?si=xtETRzUjjy6gSYKk" target="_blank">in which she labeled him a “domestic terrorist”</a> and claimed without evidence that he intended to kill law enforcement.</p> 
<p>While a growing number of Democrats in Congress have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/democratic-house-leaders-kristi-noem-impeachment-00749643" target="_blank">called for Noem’s impeachment</a>, Trump signaled that he has little patience for Republicans joining in that narrative.</p> 
<p>Trump also took a jab at Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540" target="_blank">she was attacked by a man and sprayed</a> with an unknown substance Tuesday while she spoke at a Minnesota town hall. The man, later identified by local police as 55-year-old Anthony Kazmierczak, was tackled to the ground and detained.</p> 
<p>When asked for his thoughts on Omar’s attack, Trump told ABC News, “I don’t think about her. I think she’s a fraud. I don’t really think about that.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Shutdown threat weighs on Senate lunches</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/shutdown-senate-lunches-dhs-funding-00751643</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-02de-d452-a99e-6bfe7dbf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans and Democrats will head into separate lunches Wednesday for their first in-person conference meetings on how to avoid a partial shutdown at the end of the week.</p> 
<p>No one wants to see the vast majority of federal agency funding lapse at 12:01 a.m. Saturday. But partisan divisions over the Homeland Security bill are reaching the brink amid a weather-shortened week.</p> 
<p>Senators have a few days to turn the tide.</p> 
<p><b>— Democratic demands:</b> Democrats expect to come out of lunch with a firmer wish list of policy changes they want incorporated into the Homeland bill.</p> 
<p>“The things that we care most about are getting an independent investigation and ending these roving patrols that are terrorizing Minneapolis,” said Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.), the top Democrat on the Homeland funding panel. “And solving these problems [with] secret police and getting some identification of body cams.”</p> 
<p>A new <a href="https://www.searchlightinstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Memo-Play-Hardball-and-Use-Your-Leverage-to-Reform-ICE.pdf" target="_blank">polling memo</a> circulating among senators, obtained by POLITICO, is <a href="http://politico.com/news/2026/01/28/ice-polling-memo-searchlight-00751569" target="_blank">providing some encouragement for Democrats</a>. The Searchlight Institute found that “bipartisan majorities of voters oppose ICE’s lawless tactics, including detaining U.S. citizens (73 percent), entering people’s homes without warrants (79 percent), and failing to wear clearly identifying uniforms (70 percent).”</p> 
<p><b>— GOP looks to the White House:&nbsp;</b>Republicans are trying to come up with alternative solutions to address frustrations with President Donald Trump’s aggressive immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader John Thune told reporters he’s encouraging dialogue between the administration and Senate Democrats to reach “some mechanism whereby you don’t have to change the bill or split it out and have to send something back to the House.” He acknowledged members of his own conference would block any attempt to strip DHS funding from the six-bill appropriations package.</p> 
<p>Appropriations Chair Susan Collins said Tuesday she’s also hoping for an off-ramp via executive action. The Maine Republican is in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/susan-collins-dhs-ice-shutdown-00751545" target="_blank">middle of the fight</a> to hold the funding package together as she navigates a DHS enforcement surge in her own state and a likely reelection campaign.</p> 
<p><b>— Will the House return? </b>Democrats want House leaders to bring the chamber back from recess to be ready to pass amended legislation — but Republicans say they have no plans to do so. One senior House Democrat told POLITICO it “seems inevitable at this point the House will be involved” and doubted the administration could do anything to convince Senate Democrats to pass the bill in its current form.</p> 
<p>“I know the House loves recess — they do,” Murphy said. “The House does not like doing their jobs, but sometimes they might actually have to show up when the country is exploding.”</p> 
<p>The Senate will vote Thursday on advancing the six-bill package as is. Thune said it’s “to be determined” what happens if that vote fails.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Rubio testifies on Venezuela: </b>Secretary of State Marco Rubio will appear before Senate Foreign Relations at 10 a.m. to give his first public testimony to Congress since the capture of Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro. Expect questions from lawmakers in both parties about the administration’s plan to get to democracy in Venezuela and who will profit from Venezuelan oil.</p> 
<p><b>— ACA compromise? </b>Sen. Angus King (I-Maine) said Tuesday he’s expecting the bipartisan group of senators working to revive expired Affordable Care Act subsidies to release bill text “hopefully in the next day or so.” It comes after lead GOP negotiator Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio) spoke with senators on the floor Tuesday evening about the health care framework.</p> 
<p>Democrats in the negotiating group were initially caught off guard by Moreno’s apparent prediction of text, since they had neither seen nor signed off on anything, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss the private talks. Other lawmakers were pessimistic Tuesday about the state of the discussions, which have been overshadowed by the fight over DHS funding after Saturday’s fatal shooting of Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Katherine Tully-McManus, Jennifer Scholtes, Adam Wren and Benjamin Guggenheim contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top Hunt aide charged taxpayers $44,000 in hotel expenses</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/top-hunt-aide-charged-taxpayers-44-000-in-hotel-expenses-00750033</link>
      <description>The Texas Republican’s top aide, James Kyrkanides, racked up the tab over three years, with an average nightly stay costing four times the federal benchmark rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-013f-d1ea-a5de-31bf8c7f0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/43/22/4879d4a24d57a308f907a55309f3/ap24179069272208-edit.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Gerald Herbert/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>James Kyrkanides, right, is seen with Rep. Wesley Hunt (R-Texas), left, at an event in Fairburn, Georgia, on June 26, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/43/22/4879d4a24d57a308f907a55309f3/ap24179069272208-edit.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Lippman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Lippman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The travel expenses of a Republican campaign manager in the crowded Texas Senate race have raised eyebrows for their seemingly exorbitant amount.</p> 
<p>James Kyrkanides, the campaign manager for Senate candidate Wesley Hunt, charged taxpayers more than $44,000 in hotel expenses over three years as Hunt’s congressional chief of staff. The charges average $457 per night, four times the <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/about-us/newsroom/news-releases/gsa-releases-fy-2025-conus-per-diem-rates-for-federal-travelers-08162024" target="_blank">national standard rate set by General Services Administration rate</a> for many federal employees, according to a POLITICO analysis of House expense records.</p> 
<p>That total accrued over 97 nights during 49 different stays. For instance, on Jan. 3, 2025, when Congress was being sworn in, Kyrkanides expensed a one-night hotel bill of $805. For May 20 to 22, 2024, he submitted a hotel bill of $1,692. And for a stay starting Aug. 6, 2024, he expensed two nights for a total of $1,321.</p> 
<p>The expense records do not require the hotels or the city in which they’re located to be listed, and Kyrkanides declined to name the hotels.</p> 
<p>Kyrkanides said all of the expenses were reviewed and approved by the House finance office, which handles disbursements of member money. He said less than half of the money that was reimbursed went to him personally and the remainder covered travel expenses for other Hunt staffers. He declined to provide receipts to verify that claim.</p> 
<p>Kyrkanides confirmed Washington was his primary workplace during that period of time. He said a number of the reimbursements were in Hunt’s hometown of Houston, where the GSA’s <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/travel/plan-book/per-diem-rates" target="_blank">recommended federal lodging rate</a> is $128 per night. Krykanides said expenses also included stays in Washington, San Diego and New York, which have had average GSA rates of $234, $205 and $277 over the last year, respectively. Krykanides said the hotel stays in those cities were expensed on behalf of Hunt staffers for work travel, including a district director conference in San Diego and communications staffers going to New York for Fox News interviews related to policy.</p> 
<p>Kyrkanides also noted that costs of food, beverage and parking aren’t included in the GSA rates, but his reimbursements folded in those items. He said subtracting them brings his average nightly lodging costs, excluding taxes, to $269. He also pointed to GSA policy that allows federal employees to be reimbursed up to 300 percent of the recommended rate if <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/travel/plan-a-trip/per-diem-rates/faqs" target="_blank">no other rooms</a> are available.</p> 
<p>Asked for comment about the expenses, a Hunt spokesperson said in a statement: “All transactions in this office are approved by the chief administrative officer, made public, and carried out in accordance with the highest ethical guidelines.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for the chief administrative officer which oversees House finance declined to comment.</p> 
<p>House members are given broad discretion in how they use their office budget. But some members and committees abide by GSA hotel rates, which serve as a reference point for the federal government. Senate staffers have to limit their hotel expenses to $165 per night but can obtain waivers for additional reimbursement in line with GSA hotel rates.</p> 
<p>Hunt is now in a fiercely contested Senate primary against Sen. John Cornyn and Texas Attorney General Ken Paxton and, according to a <a href="https://share.google/W09eP2hI5HkEqTDmv" target="_blank">RealClearPolitics average</a> of recent polls, is running in third place. Trump hasn’t weighed in with an endorsement and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/14/trump-endorsements-senate-races-republicans-00724042" target="_blank">has no plans to endorse</a> in the race.</p> 
<p>When briefed about the expenses, Donald Sherman, the president and CEO of Citizens for Responsibility and Ethics in Washington, said the pattern of expenses appeared to be “excessive” and that instances like these show “there needs to be more robust independent oversight of Congress and how it spends taxpayer dollars.”</p> 
<p>“The expenses themselves certainly suggest that there should be more scrutiny on Congressman Hunt and his staff about how they are spending taxpayer funds,” he said in an interview. “Costs aren’t getting real oversight. People [who approve such expenses] are simply checking boxes and giving deference to members.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elon Musk is flexing his political muscle again — and the GOP is responding</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/28/elon-musk-gop-comeback-00751572</link>
      <description>His recent footprint includes a $10 million investment in the Kentucky Senate race and an all-out influence campaign targeting Senate Republicans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-028a-d9a8-a7be-868aa6e30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/29/44/3c8a7d5148d7b35c8ac647043014/main-congress-elon.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Bill Kuchman/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images, iStock, Creative Commons)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Main.Congress.Elon.jpg</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/29/44/3c8a7d5148d7b35c8ac647043014/main-congress-elon.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Just six months ago, most congressional Republicans kept their distance from Elon Musk after the tech mogul’s messy political breakup with President Donald Trump and his feverish attempt to kill their signature megabill.</p> 
<p>Musk is persona non grata no longer, thanks to his mega checkbook and mega platform — both of which he is now using to influence the future of the GOP.</p> 
<p>Republicans see his recent donation to a Kentucky Senate candidate as an encouraging sign that Musk will make good on his promises to back the GOP, and top House leaders are elated — especially those in charge of defending their razor-thin majority. Musk spent more than $260 million in the last election helping to elect Trump and Republicans.</p> 
<p>“It's definitely a positive development for us,” NRCC Chair Richard Hudson said in an interview.</p> 
<p>He added, “By the way, when they had their rift, I told you all this would happen.”</p> 
<p>That rift seemed unlikely to heal early on, with Musk accusing the president of covering up the Jeffrey Epstein files because Trump was named in the documents, then threatening to start his own political party.</p> 
<p>But just six months later, Musk is back having dinners with Trump and attempting to steer GOP policy again — and he is making his presence felt in key offices on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Musk, who <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/2006832891024781722" target="_blank">posted on New Year’s Day</a> that “America is toast if the radical left wins,” did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>Recently he has used his 233-million-follower X account to push Senate Republicans to pass the SAVE Act — a <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2025/04/14/the-house-passed-the-save-act-what-comes-next-00288458" target="_blank">bill meant to tighten election laws</a> to prevent noncitizens from voting, in part by imposing new proof-of-citizenship requirements and restricting mail voting.</p> 
<p>The campaign has driven a huge volume of calls to member offices, according to two aides granted anonymity to discuss internal matters, forcing Republican after Republican to publicly state their support for the legislation. It has no Democratic support and has not been called up for a vote because it cannot overcome the Senate’s 60-vote filibuster hurdle.</p> 
<p>Two of the Senate’s most endangered Republican incumbents — Sens. Bill Cassidy and John Cornyn — have leaned into Musk’s push to hold a vote on the bill, often reposting his messages on their accounts. Cornyn also spoke privately with Thune about the bill last week.</p> 
<p>When Sen. John Boozman of Arkansas announced on X Saturday he was “reviewing” the bill, Musk <a href="https://x.com/JohnBoozman/status/2015097398951911921" target="_blank">reposted the message</a> with a pair of American flag emojis.</p> 
<p>Asked about the bill, Senate Majority Leader John Thune said in an interview Tuesday night that he was sure it would come up for a vote “at some point” but “we’ll have to figure out where we can get it done.”</p> 
<p>“We’ve got a lot of interest in it, and I’m supportive of it,” Thune said, noting he has co-sponsored the bill previously.</p> 
<p>The public pressure campaign appears to have caught some Republicans by surprise given that there’s been little internal rush to formally sign onto the bill since it’s currently not moving and can’t pass the Senate.</p> 
<p>Congressional Republicans, who have fresh memories of the trail of destruction he has often left on Capitol Hill, see Musk’s re-emergence as a mixed blessing. He blew up a carefully negotiated bipartisan government funding deal in December 2024 and almost sunk the GOP megabill in the final stages of passage over his personal objections to the cancellation of electric vehicle subsidies and other policies.</p> 
<p>“He’s a big voice,” said Rep. Blake Moore (R-Utah), a member of House GOP leadership, who recalled how Musk was “really antagonistic” about the huge Republican policy bill last year.</p> 
<p>But, he added, “I think if he's willing to be accurate, yeah, then I then totally want him on board.”</p> 
<p>That’s especially true when it comes to Musk’s money. Even amid his feuding with Trump, he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/31/elon-musk-donations-clf-slf-00487699" target="_blank">cut $10 million worth of checks</a> to the GOP super PACs charged with preserving the House and Senate majorities.</p> 
<p>But with Musk dropping another $10 million into Kentucky Senate candidate Nate Morris’ campaign effort — and ending his dalliance with a third party — the expectation is that more checks will now be on the way.</p> 
<p>Hudson said he hasn’t talked to Musk yet about any future financial commitments to helping House Republicans. But members are straining to get in his good graces as Republicans face huge midterm challenges without Trump on the ballot.</p> 
<p>“History is not on our side,” Rep. Carlos Gimenez (R-Fla.) said, referring to the typical midterm losses suffered by the president’s party. “We'll take any and all help possible to reverse that trend in history, because I think it's important for the Republican Party.”</p> 
<p>Whether they want Musk as a presence on the campaign trail is a more complicated question. His Department of Government Efficiency initiative is widely seen as a bust nearly a year later, and his post-2024 election efforts to vocally back conservatives — like a Wisconsin Supreme Court candidate — backfired at the ballot box.</p> 
<p>Rep. Ralph Norman (R-S.C.), a hard-liner who is running for governor of South Carolina, said Musk “did an unbelievable job in identifying waste, fraud and abuse” and would be welcome both on the campaign trail and in his potential administration as an efficiency consultant.</p> 
<p>But Republicans in swingier territory are cooler to the idea of a large Musk presence in their races this fall.</p> 
<p>Rep. Rob Bresnahan (R-Pa.), one of the most vulnerable Republicans in the House, said he was pleased to see Trump and Musk patch up their rift — that “obviously we are better when we are united and as a team.”</p> 
<p>Asked if he wanted Musk to campaign in his district, Bresnahan was more equivocal.</p> 
<p>“I’m not really sure — I’m impartial,” Bresnahan said. “We look at whoever's going to be supportive of what we're trying to do for northeastern Pennsylvania, and if their mission aligns with our mission, then we're going to embrace it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T21:33:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Ilhan Omar sprayed with liquid at Minneapolis town hall</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/ilhan-omar-sprayed-minneapolis-00751540</link>
      <description>The attack on the progressive lawmaker briefly interrupted her remarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0258-d1ea-a5de-32dc80180000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:29:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/2b/64/9fac20b44870aed536fea3bfcd0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2257991042">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Octavio Jones/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Ilhan Omar reacts after being sprayed with an unknown substance by a man as she hosted a town hall in Minneapolis, Minnesota, on Jan. 27.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/2b/64/9fac20b44870aed536fea3bfcd0b/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2257991042" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Minnesota Rep. Ilhan Omar was attacked by a man who sprayed a liquid while lunging at her before being detained at a town hall in Minneapolis on Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Omar was speaking to constituents in her district, which includes much of Minneapolis, about the turmoil in the city in the wake of federal immigration agents shooting Alex Pretti, the second U.S. citizen killed by federal agents in the city in less than a month.</p> 
<p>As she spoke, a man charged at Omar and sprayed her with an unknown substance before being detained by security. She did not appear to be injured and, after a pause, continued the town hall despite a security officer’s advice to halt the event, asking him to “please not let them have the show.”</p> 
<p>“Here’s the reality that people like this ugly man don’t understand,” Omar said. “We are Minnesota strong and we will stay resilient in the face of whatever they might throw at us.”</p> 
<p>The lawmaker's office later said <a href="https://x.com/ilhan/status/2016334654949777714?s=46" target="_blank">on social media</a> that the man who threw the liquid is in custody. "The Congresswoman is okay," it said. "She continued with her town hall because she doesn’t let bullies win.” </p> 
<p>Omar has been the subject of frequent rhetorical attacks from Republicans, including President Donald Trump, who have sought to tie the lawmaker to investigations into public benefits fraud linked with Minnesota’s Somali community. On Tuesday, Trump said the Department of Justice is investigating her personal finances while suggesting she illegally profited from her service in Congress.</p> 
<p>The incident heightens the tensions in Minneapolis, where anti-Trump protests continue to embroil the city in response to a surge of federal immigration enforcement. Two Minneapolis residents, Pretti and Renee Good, were killed by immigration officers, sparking further backlash to the Trump administration’s immigration policies from protesters around the city.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The DHS crisis is squeezing Susan Collins</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/susan-collins-dhs-ice-shutdown-00751545</link>
      <description>The Maine Republican is under immense pressure as a huge funding package hangs by a thread and federal agents swarm her state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0268-dabb-ad9c-3fed275e0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 21:24:04 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fc/66/b90a782b4c13ad7fd81507163c69/2026-0127-congress-francis-44-2-50610.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine) is seen at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 27, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fc/66/b90a782b4c13ad7fd81507163c69/2026-0127-congress-francis-44-2-50610.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> is stuck in the middle of an ICE storm.</p> 
<p>The Maine Republican and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/16/susan-collins-reelection-appropriations-00455206" target="_blank">Senate Appropriations Committee chair</a> is working overtime to salvage a package of <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">six funding bills hanging by a thread</a> after the Saturday killing of a Minnesota man by federal agents. The scramble follows months of work to put the appropriations process back on track in the wake of a record government shutdown.</p> 
<p>How Collins navigates the fight will have reverberations far beyond whether or not Congress manages to avoid falling over the shutdown cliff for the second time in four months. The 73-year-old — who intends to seek a sixth term this November — is already under a microscope from Democrats back home after the Trump administration launched an immigration enforcement operation in her state.</p> 
<p>Collins, who said earlier this month she didn’t “see the rationale for a large number of ICE agents” in Maine, spoke with Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem on Monday, later telling reporters Tuesday <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/susan-collins-speaks-with-noem-about-immigration-enforcement-00747915" target="_blank">she urged Noem</a> to pause “this surge of enforcement” in Minnesota and Maine “until we can get far better focus.”</p> 
<p>On Capitol Hill, she’s part of a group of senators who are trying to defuse the shutdown fight, including by exploring actions President Donald Trump could have his agencies take without needing to strip DHS funding out of the pending spending package as Democrats are demanding.</p> 
<p>“We are having conversations with all the parties,” Collins said in an interview Tuesday, referring to the White House and Democrats.</p> 
<p>As to whether or not a shutdown is inevitable, she separately told reporters “it depends on whether people look at the consequences.”</p> 
<p>She pointed to Trump’s decision to send <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis</a> as a sign that the administration is willing to make policy changes in the wake of Saturday’s shooting. But just sending in Homan won’t be enough to appease Democrats.</p> 
<p>Republicans, including Collins, are loath to do that because any changes to the six-bill package would virtually guarantee a partial shutdown starting 12:01 a.m. Saturday. The House would need to approve any changes to the package, and the chamber is in recess until Monday.</p> 
<p>Republican leaders are also wary of an internal backlash to any revised bill, with the ultra-conservative Freedom Caucus warning Monday that they would oppose any measure that did not include money for DHS.</p> 
<p>Democrats say the deployment of DHS agents in Collins’ home state is justification enough for pulling apart the funding package she’s trying to salvage this week.</p> 
<p>“All you have to do is look at what's happening in Minnesota, look at what's happening in Maine,” Maryland Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51658" data-person-id="51658">Chris Van Hollen</a>, a senior Democratic appropriator, told reporters. “And I think that this is why everyone's got to vote to rein in Trump's ICE operation.”</p> 
<p>Collins acknowledged on the Senate floor Monday that the killing of Alex Pretti in Minnesota Saturday refocused attention on Homeland Security funding and whether more guardrails are needed for the immigration agencies under its purview.</p> 
<p>“I recognize that and share the concerns,” she said.</p> 
<p>But she noted that the funding package includes “many safeguards” on DHS funding and that the majority of the department’s budget covers work unrelated to immigration enforcement, including TSA, the Coast Guard and FEMA.</p> 
<p>The political backdrop could hardly be more fraught for Collins. She was already dealing with a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/09/susan-collins-trump-reelection-00719283" target="_blank">complicated relationship with Trump</a>, with the president attacking her and several other GOP senators just this month for supporting an effort to rein in military action in Venezuela. They “should never be elected to office again,” Trump announced — with Collins the only in-cycle Republican among those targeted.</p> 
<p>Collins also voted against the Trump-backed “Big, Beautiful Bill” last year and a separate $9 billion funding clawback pushed by the White House. Still, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and other GOP colleagues have publicly defended Collins as essential to keeping the Maine seat in Republican hands.</p> 
<p>But her well-documented willingness to break from her party has done little to stop Democrats back home from linking her to Trump’s immigration enforcement policies. The Maine Democratic Party <a href="https://www.mainedems.org/media/susan-collins-slammed-refusing-hold-trump-accountable-ice" target="_blank">accused Collins</a> of “choosing Donald Trump over the people of Maine” and “<a href="https://www.mainedems.org/media/collins-call-out-collins-pushing-bill-fund-ice-no-reforms-or-accountability" target="_blank">leading the charge</a> to pass more funding for ICE.”</p> 
<p>One of her aspiring Democratic challengers, Gov. Janet Mills, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/janet-mills-ice-raids-state-address-00751216" target="_blank">leaned into the immigration fight</a> during her State of the State speech Tuesday night — the latest indication of how it is potentially reorienting midterm politics.</p> 
<p>“Tonight, I say to the people of Maine: We will not be intimidated. We will not be silenced,” Mills said.</p> 
<p>Back in Washington, Collins is speaking with Democrats on the Appropriations Committee and members of the Trump administration, as well as fellow Republicans including Thune and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a>, the top Homeland Security appropriator.</p> 
<p>Whether Collins can hold the funding package together and avoid a partial shutdown, most Hill Republicans believe, will ultimately come down to what Trump and congressional Democrats can agree to.</p> 
<p>Thune cited “good conversations” involving Collins and Britt, before adding: “The other thing too is making sure that they’re engaged in the White House.”</p> 
<p>Democrats believe Republicans are open to immigration enforcement changes — and are speaking out about Saturday’s shooting — in large part because of the potential electoral ramifications coming in November.</p> 
<p>Oregon Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66836" data-person-id="66836">Jeff Merkley</a>, another Democratic appropriator, said Republicans are only concerned about the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement actions “in the context of elections right now.”</p> 
<p>“So they talk about Maine — there's a reason that there's extra attention to Maine,” Merkley said in an interview. “I'd like to see some actual principles exhorted by the Republican leadership in both houses — to stand up.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alex Pretti was shot by 2 CBP agents, not just 1, report finds</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/pretti-shot-by-two-cbp-agents-00751207</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01f7-d9a8-a7be-87f78d8a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:34:43 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Authorities believe two federal officers fired their weapons in the shooting that killed Alex Pretti as he was wrestled to the ground in Minneapolis, according to a preliminary Homeland Security report to Congress.</p> 
<p>The report obtained by POLITICO provides the government’s most detailed account yet of the killing of the 37-year-old Pretti, whose death has sparked widespread outrage and prompted the government to modify its immigration enforcement campaign in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>U.S. Customs and Border Protection’s Office of Professional Responsibility said in the report that two of its officers fired after another officer on the scene yelled “He’s got a gun” while restraining Pretti on the snowy street.</p> 
<p>Video from bystanders showed officers had already taken the gun from Pretti, an ICU nurse with a permit to carry a concealed weapon, when he was shot. He appeared to be attempting to intercede in a confrontation between agents and a woman who was protesting immigration operations when the officers grabbed him and forced him to the ground.</p> 
<p>The new details come as the Trump administration scrambles to respond to intense blowback over the killings of Pretti and Renee Good, a Minneapolis woman who was killed by a federal immigration officer earlier in January. Some Republican lawmakers have <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/john-thune-kristi-noem-minnesota-00750451" target="_blank">declined to offer their support</a> for Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem’s handling of the shootings.</p> 
<p>Earlier on Tuesday, President Donald Trump suggested Pretti shouldn’t have been armed when confronting immigration agents. Other administration officials have indicated that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/27/trump-pretti-shouldnt-have-been-carrying-a-gun-00750241" target="_blank">Pretti risked provoking the officers</a> by carrying a weapon.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tillis, Murkowski say Noem should be fired</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/thom-tillis-kristi-noem-fired-00750580</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-01bd-d9a8-a7be-87bfe06d0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:16:44 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican Sens. Thom Tillis and Lisa Murkowski said Tuesday that Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem should be fired given her response to the killing of a 37-year-old Minneapolis man by DHS agents Saturday.</p> 
<p>Tillis, of North Carolina, said Noem should be "out of a job." Murkowski, of Alaska, said separately that "she should go."</p> 
<p>“I think what she’s done in Minnesota should be disqualifying,” Tillis told reporters. “It’s just amateurish. It’s terrible. It’s making the president look bad.”</p> 
<p>Tillis and Murkowski are the first two Republican lawmakers to say outright that Noem should lose her Cabinet job. Trump is facing intense pressure to fire Noem in the wake of Saturday’s shooting, as well as calls from Democrats for her to be impeached.</p> 
<p>In addition to Noem, Tillis faulted deputy White House chief of staff Stephen Miller for castigating victim Alex Pretti in the immediate aftermath of his shooting: “Those two people told the president before they even had any incident report whatsoever that the person who died was a terrorist. I mean that is amateur hour at its worst.”</p> 
<p>Tillis also signaled he is open to operational changes at DHS in the wake of the shooting, including requiring an independent investigation. And he said he would be OK with a Democratic demand to split off DHS funding from a six-bill package up for debate in the Senate this week, with a stopgap measure in place while funding for the department is renegotiated. </p> 
<p>“I wouldn’t have a problem with its absence,” Tillis said about the DHS bill.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Thune declines chance to back Noem after Minnesota killing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/john-thune-kristi-noem-minnesota-00750451</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-019c-dabb-ad9c-3ffde9330000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:40:47 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> declined to say Tuesday whether he had confidence in Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem as President Donald Trump faces calls to fire her and Democrats push for her impeachment.</p> 
<p>“That's the president's judgment call,” Thune told reporters when asked about Noem, a fellow South Dakota native who previously served with him in the state’s congressional delegation.</p> 
<p>Noem has been at the center of intense scrutiny over the administration’s immigration enforcement tactics after federal agents killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti during a street skirmish on Minneapolis Saturday. Trump said Tuesday he was standing by the embattled secretary.</p> 
<p>While Thune’s comments fell well short of an endorsement of Noem’s performance, he has similarly withheld comment on other embattled Trump officials in recent months, including Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth in December.</p> 
<p>Thune said Tuesday he backs an impartial investigation of the Pretti killing, including probes by state and local officials, as well as a federal investigation outside of DHS.</p> 
<p>“Clearly, there a lot of questions that have to be answered,” he said, adding that investigations are “necessary … any time there's a shooting like that and lives lost.”</p> 
<p>He doubled down on praise for Trump’s decision to send White House border czar Tom Homan to Minnesota to oversee immigration enforcement operations there, calling him “an experienced pro” and calling the moment an “opportunity to evaluate and to really assess the policies and the procedure.”</p> 
<p>Thune’s GOP counterpart across the Capitol, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, has been silent since the shooting, with the House out of session for a one-week break.</p> 
<p>The fallout from Pretti’s killing has upended the Senate’s plan to pass a six-bill spending package by the Friday midnight deadline to avoid a partial government shutdown. Democrats want DHS funding stripped out of the bill and renegotiated, but Republicans are hoping that they can appease Democrats with other actions.</p> 
<p>Thune said Democrats should make their policy demands “clear and known and see to what degree the administration will be able to address that,” adding that he “would prefer that there be a way that we keep the package together.”</p> 
<p>If Democrats block the six-bill package, as they have vowed to do, Thune said the Senate would move to “Plan B,” which is “to be determined.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Henry Cuellar warns against shutdown, handing DHS ‘blank check’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/cuellar-dhs-blank-check-00749995</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0125-d1ea-a5de-31a5a4f50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:30:54 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a>, who helped craft and backed the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">Homeland Security funding bill</a> now fueling a standoff in the Senate, said in an interview Tuesday that he supports putting more guardrails on federal immigration enforcement agencies but urged senators to pass the legislation the House approved last week.</p> 
<p>The partial government shutdown senators are barreling toward after Saturday’s DHS-involved killing of a Minneapolis man, he warned, would be “the worst situation,” leaving the controversial agencies operating with “a blank check.”</p> 
<p>“If you have a government shutdown, what really happens? ICE got $75 billion in the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/26/trump-megabills-name-not-good-for-explaining-what-it-does-00527379" target="_blank">big-beautiful-slash-ugly bill</a>. [But] you shut down FEMA, you shut down TSA, you shut down the Coast Guard, you shut down CISA,” the moderate Texas lawmaker said. “I don't think that's a good alternative.”</p> 
<p>Cuellar, the ranking Democrat on the Homeland Security Appropriations Subcommittee, said he supports many strictures that got left on the cutting room floor in the House, including banning agents from wearing masks and requiring identification, codifying parts of the agency’s use of force policy and notifying Congress about large surges in ICE activity.</p> 
<p>But he suggested those could be revisited in the next yearly funding cycle if Democrats are unable to secure commitments from Republicans before the shutdown deadline. And he said there are steps the Trump administration could take now to defuse tensions, such as increasing training and enforcing ICE’s internal use-of-force policy.</p> 
<p>“I sense an opening where I think we can get more Republicans to work with us,” Cuellar said.</p> 
<p>Amid <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/republicans-concern-minneapolis-shooting-00745707'" target="_blank">bipartisan backlash</a> to Alex Pretti’s killing, Senate Democrats are seeking to strip the DHS funding bill from a larger <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">six-bill appropriations packag</a>e and renegotiate it. They’re seeking a raft of new provisions, including requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests, mandating federal agents identify themselves and compelling DHS to cooperate with state and local investigations.</p> 
<p>But Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">scrambling to avoid making changes</a> to the massive bill as the Friday midnight deadline for a partial government shutdown approaches. With the House out till next week, passing the funding package intact is the only viable path to avoiding a shutdown.</p> 
<p>Cuellar joined his fellow Democrats and many Republicans in calling for independent investigations into the shootings of both Pretti and Renee Good, who was also killed in a confrontation with a DHS officer. And he didn’t rule out joining House Democrats’ push to impeach DHS Secretary Kristi Noem if President Donald Trump doesn’t fire her first.</p> 
<p>“I’ll wait until a later time” to weigh in, Cuellar said. “But I’m certainly looking at everything that’s going on, and [Trump and his team] definitely need to change course on it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ICE, Border Patrol leaders to testify in House, Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/ice-border-officials-hearing-00749840</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00f3-d1ea-a5de-30f760b00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:53:36 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Top officials from ICE and U.S. Customs and Border Protection will testify before the House and Senate Homeland Security committees next month, as lawmakers ramp up scrutiny of the Trump administration's immigration crackdown after the killing of Alex Pretti.</p> 
<p>ICE acting director Todd Lyons, Customs and Border Protection Commissioner Rodney Scott and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services Director Joseph Edlow have agreed to appear in the House on Feb. 10 and in the Senate on Feb. 12.</p> 
<p>House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) and Senate Homeland Security Chair Rand Paul (R-Ky.) called for the oversight hearings after federal agents shot and killed Pretti in Minneapolis Saturday.</p> 
<p>“Transparency and communication are needed to turn the temperature down,” Garbarino said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem, who has overseen the Minneapolis operation, isn't set to testify on Capitol Hill until March 3. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freedom Caucus pushes to fund DHS amid funding fight</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/freedom-caucus-dhs-ultimatum-00749816</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00f3-d1ea-a5de-30f774530000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:36:10 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Freedom Caucus leaders are warning they will oppose a proposal favored by Senate Democrats to send an amended spending package back across the Capitol without <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">Department of Homeland Security funding</a>.</p> 
<p>The ultimatum from the hard-right group comes as top leaders try to find a way to avoid a partial government shutdown late this week after Saturday's DHS-involved shooting in Minneapolis threw the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">massive funding package</a> passed by the House last week into jeopardy. Members of the group could potentially tank procedural votes required to advance any alternative funding package.</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://x.com/freedomcaucus/status/2016223256445956146" target="_blank">letter to President Donald Trump</a> sent Tuesday, senior members of the group said they would "not allow Democrats to strip [DHS] funding out to pass other appropriations separately."</p> 
<p>"We cannot support giving Democrats the ability to control the funding of our Department of Homeland Security," they added.</p> 
<p>Senate Democrats want to break up the six-bill package sent over from the House, stripping out the DHS funding to renegotiate terms following the killing of 37-year-old Alex Pretti. But House GOP leaders privately believe that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">would open a new "hellscape"</a> in the funding talks within the divided House Republican conference.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T15:41:18-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Democratic House leaders join push to impeach Kristi Noem</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/democratic-house-leaders-kristi-noem-impeachment-00749643</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-00c1-d1ea-a5de-30c5adef0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:02:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The leaders of the House Democratic caucus vowed on Tuesday to impeach Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem if President Donald Trump does not fire her, citing a “DHS killing spree unleashed in Minnesota.”</p> 
<p>The threat comes as Noem <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/kristi-noem-scrutiny-minneapolis-shootings-00748618?can_id=bb0274a7e273dbe000778c447d392e4c&amp;email_referrer=email_3071138&amp;email_subject=tuesday-minnesota-update-add-your-name-if-you-agree-impeach-secretary-of-homeland-security-kristi-noem&amp;link_id=8&amp;source=email-tuesday-minnesota-update-add-your-name-if-you-agree-impeach-secretary-of-homeland-security-kristi-noem" target="_blank">faces heightened scrutiny</a> over her response to the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by Customs and Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis on Saturday, the second killing by federal immigration agents in the city this month.</p> 
<p>Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, whip Katherine Clark (D-Mass.) and caucus Chair Pete Aguilar (D-Calif.) in a joint statement called for “dramatic changes” at DHS and criminal prosecution of federal agents who have broken the law.</p> 
<p>“Taxpayer dollars are being weaponized by the Trump administration to kill American citizens, brutalize communities and violently target law-abiding immigrant families,” the leaders wrote. “The country is disgusted by what the Department of Homeland Security has done.”</p> 
<p>More than 140 House Democrats have signed on to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/krist-noem-democrats-00746865" target="_blank">an impeachment resolution</a> against Noem, who is <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/noem-to-testify-to-senate-judiciary-00747610" target="_blank">set to testify</a> before the Senate Judiciary Committee in March. GOP lawmakers and influential MAGA commentators have also <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/john-curtis-kristi-noem-minnesota-investigation-00747397" target="_blank">publicly rebuked the Homeland Security secretary</a> in recent days, saying her department’s aggressive immigration operation in Minnesota has overstepped.</p> 
<p>“If Democrats cared this much about deporting violent, criminal illegal aliens, the American people would be much safer," White House spokesperson Abigail Jackson said in response to the statement. </p> 
<p>DHS spokesperson Tricia McLaughlin said in a statement that Democrats should "focus on protecting the American people," which the DHS does "every day under Secretary Noem's leadership."</p> 
<p>"DHS enforces the laws Congress passes, period. If certain members don’t like those laws, changing them is literally their job," McLaughlin said.</p> 
<p>The Trump administration signaled a possible shift in strategy on Monday, with the president sending border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis and announcing that Homan “will report directly to me.” The White House also <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">pulled Border Patrol Commander Gregory Bovino</a>, a close ally of Noem’s whose response to the shooting also drew backlash, from his assignment in the city.</p> 
<p>Still, White House press secretary Karoline Leavitt said Monday that Noem retains “the utmost confidence and trust of the president of the United States,” and Trump told reporters Tuesday that “she's done a very good job” and will not step down.</p> 
<p>The Democratic leaders wrote in their statement that “the violence unleashed on the American people by the Department of Homeland Security must end forthwith,” adding: “We can do this the easy way or the hard way.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eleanor Holmes Norton confirms her retirement as DC delegate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-statement-00749099</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-003d-dabb-ad9c-3ffdeff70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:32:11 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Eleanor Holmes Norton, Washington's nonvoting House delegate for 35 years, confirmed Tuesday she is retiring from office — more than 48 hours after a public filing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/25/eleanor-holmes-norton-retires-dc-delegate-00731986" target="_blank">terminating her reelection campaign</a>.</p> 
<p>“With pride in our accomplishments, gratitude to DC, and confidence in the next generation, I announced I'll retire at the end of this term,” she said in a statement. </p> 
<p>Norton, who is 88 and has faced serious questions about her fitness for office, said she would complete her 18th term.</p> 
<p>“Although I’ve decided not to seek reelection, I will never falter in my commitment to the residents I have long championed,” she said, touting her success in securing the transfer of federal lands to local government control and the establishment of a federally funded college tuition assistance program for D.C. residents.</p> 
<p>Norton stayed silent for days after her campaign filed termination paperwork Sunday morning — even as local politicians and dignitaries paid public tribute to Norton and her service to the city.</p> 
<p>Norton has made limited public appearances in the past year, even as President Donald Trump targeted the city for a police takeover and immigration enforcement surge. She insisted for months she would run for reelection but raised barely any campaign cash as pressure to retire mounted and challengers began to line up against her. </p> 
<p>Among the Democrats already vying to succeed her are D.C. Council members Brooke Pinto and Robert White, political strategist Kinney Zalesne and former Norton aide Trent Holbrook. The June 16 primary is all but certain to decide the next delegate in a city that hasn’t given a Republican presidential nominee more than 10 percent of the vote since 1988.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-27T17:08:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Florida Republican Vern Buchanan won’t seek reelection</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/27/congress/vern-buchanan-florida-retirement-00748961</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0016-d9a8-a7be-869687cf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:35:02 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Florida Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51853" data-person-id="51853">Vern Buchanan</a> announced Tuesday that he will be retiring from Congress after 20 years in office, the latest Republican to forgo seeking reelection amid a challenging midterm environment for the party.</p> 
<p>Buchanan, who represents the red 16th District that includes some of Tampa’s suburbs along the Gulf Coast, is a longtime member of the House Ways and Means Committee.</p> 
<p>“Serving the people of Southwest Florida has been the honor of my lifetime,” Buchanan said in a statement. “After 20 years of service, I believe it’s the right time to pass the torch and begin a new chapter in my life.”</p> 
<p>First elected in 2006, Buchanan became a key player on tax, trade and health care policy.</p> 
<p>His decision to step aside has sparked chatter among Republicans over potential successors. Shortly after news of Buchanan’s retirement broke, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260192" data-person-id="260192">Randy Fine</a> (R-Fla.) voiced support for Republican National Committee Chair Joe Gruters, writing <a href="https://x.com/VoteRandyFine/status/2016170411755462822?s=20" target="_blank"><u>“Run, Joe, run!” in a post on X</u></a>.</p> 
<p>But Gruters is not interested in running to replace Buchanan in the Florida district, according to two people with direct knowledge of the matter granted anonymity to discuss his thinking, and is instead interested in remaining the RNC chair. </p> 
<p>But another person close to Gruters, similarly granted anonymity, said he “wouldn’t shut any doors just yet” over whether Gruters might run, despite him being elected to lead the RNC in August. The person added that Gruters would be a “significant frontrunner should he do it.”</p> 
<p>Christian Ziegler, a former Florida GOP chair, floated other possible names for the seat, including Buchanan’s son, Florida state Rep. James Buchanan, who is running for the state Senate; Manatee County Commissioner Mike Rahn; former state Senate President Bill Galvano; state Rep. Fiona McFarland; and former state Rep. Tommy Gregory.</p> 
<p>Ziegler added there was “always a chance” wealthy self-funders could also enter the race.</p> 
<p>Buchanan’s early years in Congress drew scrutiny after he was <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2011/10/report-doj-investigating-buchanan-066301" target="_blank"><u>investigated by the Justice Department in 2011</u></a> over allegations that he asked a former associate in the auto industry to improperly reimburse his employees for their contributions to his campaign. Buchanan denied any wrongdoing, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2012/09/doj-drops-case-against-rep-buchanan-081069" target="_blank"><u>the case was dropped in 2012</u></a>.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Kimberly Leonard contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
