<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 20:46:52 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers resign themselves to lengthy DHS shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/congress-shutdown-dhs-ice-00779881</link>
      <description>Negotiations will keep going but Democrats and the White House are far apart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-54ad-d0f8-adde-feffb3a80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 20:46:52 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7c/47/e91ee91d43858abdfb9c45234517/2026-0129-congress-francis-12-1-83379.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.) speaks during a press conference at the U.S. Capitol Jan. 30, 2026. He is standing near a sign listing demands relating to U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE). (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7c/47/e91ee91d43858abdfb9c45234517/2026-0129-congress-francis-12-1-83379.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawmakers left Washington for a week-long recess Thursday, showing no urgency to avert a shutdown at the Department of Homeland Security that will take effect Saturday morning.</p> 
<p>The overwhelming sense of resignation reflected the reality that neither Republicans nor Democrats saw an obvious path forward to resolving their differences over President Donald Trump’s immigration crackdown and whether to rein it in as part of legislation to fund DHS.</p> 
<p>Though negotiations between the White House and Senate Democrats continue, the trajectory of talks suggest DHS funding will be lapsed for at least 10 days — meaning the soonest any resolution would be reached is in the political hothouse around Trump’s State of the Union address on Feb. 24. The lack of progress has even raised the prospect that Trump’s speech to Congress might be postponed, and some Democrats are mulling a boycott.</p> 
<p><b>“</b>This ‘nyah nyah’ is going to go on for a while,” Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) said Thursday.</p> 
<p>Even if a deal were struck, Kennedy added, “I’m not entirely convinced that anybody would vote for it. I can’t see the Dems voting for anything because they’re not going to get pounded for funding ICE. And the Republicans on my side are not going to get pounded for hurting ICE.”</p> 
<p>Negotiations between Democrats and White House officials were ongoing as of Thursday evening. Democrats, who have floated a series of guardrails on immigration enforcement agencies in exchange for funding DHS, were expected to formally respond to the latest White House offer over the weekend after Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries bashed it Thursday without disclosing specifics on what was contained within.</p> 
<p>The absence of leaked bill text in the exchanges between Democrats and the White House was one subtle sign of encouragement for those watching the negotiations that both sides were taking the talks seriously.</p> 
<p>As they prepared to leave Washington, Republicans continued to knock key demands from Democrats, including a proposal that immigration enforcement agents seek judicial warrants before entering private property.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said that Republicans and Democrats were “not close.” A senior White House official granted anonymity during a call with reporters warned that the administration wouldn’t “accept concessions that meaningfully affect its ability to carry out its immigration enforcement agenda.”</p> 
<p>Even if a compromise emerges, some Democrats worry that Republicans will insist on so many qualifications that any of their proposed guardrails would be rendered toothless.</p> 
<p>“We can't pass reform that has exceptions and caveats — ‘you can't wear masks, except for seven different situations where you can. You can't bust into people's homes, except 20 different situations where you can,’” said Sen. Chris Murphy of Connecticut, the top Democrat on the subcommittee overseeing DHS appropriations. “The offers we've gotten are just not serious.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) said it was paramount that both sides “sit down with each other face to face and talk about what you’re doing.” But there were no plans for an in-person meeting<b>.</b></p> 
<p>It will likely take weeks for the public to start feeling pain from a lapse in DHS funding, meaning each side will feel limited political pressure to give in right away. TSA screeners are not set to miss paychecks until March, and FEMA coffers are likely full enough to respond to natural disasters for the near future.</p> 
<p>After the Senate failed to pass DHS funding legislation Thursday, lawmakers in both chambers left Washington with guidance to be ready to come back in a matter of days if Democrats and the White House were able to strike a deal – something that members didn’t see as a realistic possibility before the end of next week.</p> 
<p>“Both sides could dig in and just let this thing drag on,” Thune said. “I don’t think that’s in anybody’s best interest.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes, Mia McCarthy, Myah Ward contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bipartisan congressional delegation saves US-Mexico joint military exercise</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/bipartisan-congressional-delegation-us-mexico-military-exercise-00779598</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5418-d3b5-addf-f4dc3f0b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 18:13:20 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bipartisan congressional pressure helped push Mexico’s legislature to approve a joint military exercise between the U.S. and Mexican militaries, according to two people familiar with a U.S. delegation to the country.</p> 
<p>The U.S. and Mexico had been considering a joint exercise for which 19 U.S. Marines would train with the Mexican Navy in the city of Campeche along the Gulf of Mexico (the U.S. calls it the “Gulf of America”). But Mexican lawmakers balked at approving the exercise after the U.S. conducted a Jan. 3 operation to capture former Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>The plan got back on track following a visit from a congressional delegation led by Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51507" data-person-id="51507">Michael McCaul</a> (R-Texas), according to two people familiar with the visit who were granted anonymity to discuss sensitive conversations. U.S. lawmakers raised the issue with their counterparts in the Mexican Senate, urging them to approve the exercise and telling Mexican lawmakers they would closely track the matter, the people said.</p> 
<p>Mexican President Claudia Sheinbaum <a href="https://www.infobae.com/mexico/2026/02/11/sheinbaum-solicita-al-senado-el-ingreso-de-19-navy-seals-estadounidenses-para-adiestramiento-en-mexico/" target="_blank">officially requested the Marines’ entry earlier this week</a> for the exercises, which will run from Feb. 15 to April 16. The nudge from Congress apparently helped, and Mexico’s Senate unanimously approved the Marines’ entry on Wednesday.</p> 
<p>The involvement of the congressional delegation in securing the approval of the exercise has not been previously reported.</p> 
<p>McCaul, who chairs the Mexico-United States Interparliamentary Group, and Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51338" data-person-id="51338">Henry Cuellar</a> of Texas, the top Democrat for the group, said in a joint statement that they “welcome the approval” and said it was a “key objective of our bipartisan delegation to Mexico this past weekend.”</p> 
<p>“We are grateful for the Mexican Senate’s commitment to shared security, which will enable our countries to enhance intelligence-sharing and naval capabilities, intercept dangerous shipments before they reach our shores, and better protect communities on both sides of the border,” McCaul and Cuellar said.</p> 
<p>U.S. Ambassador to Mexico Ronald Johnson said in his own statement that the delegation “in its meetings with Mexican authorities and Senate counterparts, reflects the profound depth of our bilateral cooperation.” He added it was also part of the embassy’s round-the-clock efforts “to work alongside the Government of Mexico and deliver greater security and prosperity for the American and Mexican peoples.”</p> 
<p>At least in this case, the episode underscores that lawmakers still have some ability to sway foreign policy.</p> 
<p>And the approval of the exercise comes at a critical juncture for the bilateral security relationship between Mexico City and Washington. President Donald Trump has previously warned he might consider using military force against Mexico’s drug cartels in the name of combating fentanyl trafficking.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, drug cartels, which control an increasing amount of territory in Mexico, have continued to expand their technological capabilities. On Wednesday, the U.S. abruptly closed the airspace around El Paso International Airport, saying that a Mexican cartel’s drone had breached U.S. airspace and counter-drone operations around the airport could have endangered commercial flights.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-12T15:05:55-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>DHS shutdown all but certain after failed Senate vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/dhs-shutdown-all-but-certain-00778721</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5339-d0f8-adde-fb7bcf6e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 14:01:38 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Lawmakers are heading for the exits following a failed Senate vote Thursday, all but guaranteeing the Department of Homeland Security shuts down early Saturday morning.</p> 
<p>The funding lapse, which will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499" target="_blank">hit parts of DHS harder than others</a>, comes as the White House and congressional Democrats have failed to move closer to a deal after trading proposals to rein in immigration enforcement practices in the wake of two high-profile shootings in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>Democrats called the latest offer from the White House insufficient Thursday and are expected to send a counteroffer.</p> 
<p>“Democrats have been very clear: We will not support an extension of the status quo,” Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> said on the Senate floor ahead of the vote.</p> 
<p>Democrats went on to block progress on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7147" target="_blank">DHS funding bill</a> the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/22/house-approves-homeland-security-funding-amid-ice-uproar-00742402" target="_blank">House passed last month</a>, which would have been the vehicle for a short-term funding punt or a larger immigration agreement. The procedural vote was 52-47, well short of the needed 60 votes.</p> 
<p>Prior to the vote, Trump’s border czar, Tom Homan, announced that ICE would be ending its enhanced immigration enforcement, a step Democrats have called for. But Schumer said Thursday that “ICE’s abuses cannot be solved merely through executive fiat alone — we first and foremost need legislation.”</p> 
<p>Republicans attempted to pass a two-week-long stopgap for DHS Thursday afternoon. But every senator needed to agree to quick passage, and Democrats blocked it on the Senate floor, saying a durable agreement to rein in the department was necessary.</p> 
<p>While the negotiations have centered on ICE and Customs and Border Protection, a shutdown will affect a wider variety of agencies including TSA, FEMA and the Coast Guard.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> told reporters he thought the White House offer went “a long ways” toward an agreement, adding: “There are a couple of issues obviously that they’re going to have to work through and work out [with Democrats], and lines that neither side is probably going to be able to cross.”</p> 
<p>Thune added that Democrats are “posturing right now” but that “progress has been real.”</p> 
<p>With no deal close at hand, the Senate is on track to adjourn Thursday for a previously scheduled one-week recess. The House also adjourned Thursday for its previously scheduled recess, though members are on call to return within 48 hours if an agreement is reached. Thune said Thursday if a deal is struck, senators will need to get back to the Capitol within 24 hours.</p> 
<p>Some GOP senators publicly pushed to stay in session in the event of a DHS shutdown, but many others pleaded with their colleagues during a closed-door lunch earlier this week to let them go back home and campaign.</p> 
<p>Others are scheduled to leave Thursday to go on international trips, including a bipartisan group heading to the Munich Security Conference. House Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> has barred members from traveling to Munich or going on other government-funded trips over the break.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-12T14:45:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Mike Johnson chides DOJ for tracking lawmakers’ perusal of unredacted Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/member-backlash-to-doj-tracking-00778751</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5325-d647-addc-fbe7135b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 13:44:14 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said Thursday he disapproves of the Justice Department surveilling lawmakers who come to agency headquarters to review the unredacted Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>“I don't think it's appropriate for anybody to be tracking that,” Johnson told reporters. “So I will echo that to anybody involved with DOJ, and I'm sure it was an oversight. That's my guess.”</p> 
<p>This week, members of Congress have been invited to a DOJ office building to read materials related to the federal case against Epstein that have not been scrubbed for public consumption.</p> 
<p>“Members should obviously have the right to peruse those at their own speed and with their own discretion,” Johnson said.</p> 
<p>But revelations came to light Wednesday, when Attorney General Pam Bondi was testifying before the House Judiciary Committee, that the department might be keeping tabs on which documents lawmakers are viewing on official computers. During Bondi’s appearance on Capitol Hill, a <a href="https://www.gettyimages.com/detail/news-photo/attorney-general-pam-bondi-takes-her-seat-before-testifying-news-photo/2260529263?adppopup=true" target="_blank"><u>photo was taken of her research binder</u></a> that revealed a print-out page of the “Search History” for Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.).</p> 
<p>“It is an outrage that DOJ is tracking Members’ investigative steps undertaken to ensure that DOJ is complying with the Epstein File Transparency Act and using this information for the Attorney General’s embarrassing polemical purposes,” said Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the Judiciary Committee, in a statement.</p> 
<p>Jayapal said <a href="https://x.com/NPRinskeep/status/2021934199020601409" target="_blank"><u>in an interview</u></a> with NPR that she had also raised her concerns with Johnson.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries, at his weekly news conference Thursday, said he would follow up to ensure Johnson is pressing the matter with the DOJ directly and “make clear to him that his job is to defend this institution.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries continued, “it does violate the principles of separate and co-equal branches of government. And of course, my Republican colleagues should be denouncing it, but they will not, because they simply are reckless rubber stamps for Donald Trump's extreme behavior.”</p> 
<p>It's not clear what will come from the complaints. A Justice Department spokesperson, in a statement, said the agency "has extended Congress the opportunity to review unredacted documents in the Epstein files. As a part of that review, DOJ logs all searches made on its systems to protect against the release of victim information."</p> 
<p>Asked whether Democrats would seek reprisal for the DOJ tracking, Jeffries said “accountability can either happen right now” or “in the aftermath of the November midterm elections,” when the New Yorker is bullish that his party will retake control of the House.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utah Sen. John Curtis is sinking Jeremy Carl's nomination for a State Department post</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/carl-hearing-00778566</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5316-d0f8-adde-fb5ef17a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 13:31:43 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Utah Sen. John Curtis will vote against Jeremy Carl's nomination for a top post at the State Department — dealing a crippling blow to the Trump nominee's chances of ascending to the job of assistant secretary of state for International Organizations.</p> 
<p>"After reviewing his record and participating in today’s hearing, I do not believe that Jeremy Carl is the right person to represent our nation’s best interests in international forums, and I find his anti-Israel views and insensitive remarks about the Jewish people unbecoming of the position for which he has been nominated,” Curtis said in a statement Thursday.</p> 
<p>The first-term senator's announcement came after Carl told the Senate Foreign Relations Committee at a confirmation hearing on Thursday he would not stop making posts and statements as he waits for congressional confirmation.</p> 
<p>Members from both parties on the committee grilled Carl over a string of comments Democrats call antisemitic and racist that have surfaced in recent months.</p> 
<p>“I greatly understand the importance of restraint and conduct,” said Carl, a senior fellow at the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/05/how-the-claremont-institute-became-a-power-center-in-trumps-washington-00700147" target="_blank">Claremont Institute</a>, a conservative think tank with members dispersed throughout Washington. “I unfortunately have to balance that with my current job, which involves advocacy and I can’t, as I’ve explained, just totally put away my day job. I’m not being offered a job here yet.“</p> 
<p>Assuming all Democrats in the Foreign Relations Committee join Curtis in voting to reject his nomination, Carl will not have enough votes to advance to the Senate floor. Carl previously served as Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Interior during Trump's first term.</p> 
<p>In the past, Carl has appeared to endorse the “great replacement theory,” slammed the Juneteenth holiday and called for the execution of American Federation of Teachers President Randi Weingarten, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/09/25/politics/kfile-jeremy-carl-state-department-deleted-tweets" target="_blank">according to CNN</a>. He deleted nearly 5,000 social media posts since before his nomination, the outlet reported in September.</p> 
<p>“We are essentially moving,” he told conservative media commentator Tucker Carlson in April 2024, “to what is effectively, a post-White America.”</p> 
<p>Democrats also hit out at Carl, who grew up Jewish before converting to Christianity, for what they say are derisive comments he’s made about Jewish Americans, including statements that diminish the effects of the Holocaust.</p> 
<p>“No person who thinks Jews should get over the Holocaust and spreads pernicious Jewish stereotypes can claim to have the character or judgment necessary to serve as a diplomat for this country,” Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, who is Jewish, <a href="https://www.democrats.senate.gov/newsroom/press-releases/leader-schumer-floor-remarks-opposing-the-nomination-of-jeremy-carl-following-his-record-of-racist-and-antisemitic-rhetoric" target="_blank">said in a statement this week</a>.</p> 
<p>Democrats on the foreign relations committee, including ranking member Sen. Jeanne Shaheen (D-N.H.) and Jacky Rosen (D-Nev.), a former synagogue president, panned Carl for his past statements.</p> 
<p>A vote for Carl "tells Americans you're willing to use your sacred vote, not just to ignore but to endorse the hateful statements,” Rosen implored her colleagues.</p> 
<p>“It tells Jewish Americans they simply don't matter," she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Billy Long calls Iceland ‘52nd state’ joke ‘totally inappropriate’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/billy-long-on-greenland-00778409</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-52e9-de8a-a1fc-fbe9aa2c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 13:00:32 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Finya Swai</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Finya Swai</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Former Rep. Billy Long apologized to lawmakers for a private joke he made to former House colleagues saying Iceland would be the “52nd state” with him as its governor.</p> 
<p>Appearing Thursday before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, President Donald Trump’s pick to serve as ambassador to the Arctic nation moved to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/15/congress/billy-long-apologizes-to-iceland-00732007" target="_blank">clean up a diplomatic mess</a> of his own making.</p> 
<p>“It was totally inappropriate,” Long told senators, describing the remark as an attempt at humor that did not land well. “I just hope that the people in Iceland will give me a second chance to make a first impression.”</p> 
<p>Long’s private joke on the House floor, <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/inside-congress/2026/01/14/more-floor-meltdowns-threaten-funding-bills-00727023" target="_blank">first reported by POLITICO</a>, prompted minor diplomatic issues amid tense relations between the U.S. and Iceland as Trump seeks to take control of nearby Greenland, a Danish territory. Icelanders also <a href="https://island.is/undirskriftalistar/915fdb39-dad8-4b98-86a1-da6db479775c" target="_blank">launched a petition</a> to their foreign minister, Katrín Gunnarsdóttir, to reject Long as ambassador.</p> 
<p>“We want [Gunnarsdóttir] to reject Billy Long as ambassador to Iceland and call for the United States to nominate another man, who will show Iceland and Icelanders more respect,” the petition read, garnering thousands of signatures.</p> 
<p>Long later apologized for the remark, telling Alaska-based news site <a href="https://www.arctictoday.com/trumps-iceland-ambassador-pick-apologizes-for-52nd-state-comment/" target="_blank">Arctic Today</a> that he was aware of the reaction in Iceland.</p> 
<p>“There was nothing serious about that, I was with some people, who I hadn’t met for three years, and they were kidding about Jeff Landry being governor of Greenland and they started joking about me and if anyone took offense to it, then I apologize,” Long said.</p> 
<p>The president has also mused about making Canada the 51st state.</p> 
<p>Trump nominated Long to replace former Ambassador Carrin Patman. Long represented Missouri’s 7th Congressional District for six terms and briefly served as IRS commissioner last year.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minnesota AG: Feds still not cooperating on Pretti and Good investigations</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/minnesota-keith-ellison-good-pretti-investigation-00778112</link>
      <description>The comments come as White House border czar Tom Homan announced an end to the surge in immigration operations in Minneapolis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-52ab-d3b5-addf-f2ef5baf0006</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 11:39:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4b/84/3788d74d40d8a36482f17410c1d0/congress-homeland-security-69767.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Tom Brenner/AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Minnesota Attorney General Keith Ellison speaks during a Senate Homeland Committee hearing on Capitol Hill in Washington, Thursday, Feb. 12, 2026, in Washington.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4b/84/3788d74d40d8a36482f17410c1d0/congress-homeland-security-69767.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Eric Bazail-Eimil</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Minnesota Attorney General Keith Ellison told senators Thursday that federal law enforcement agencies are still blocking state and local authorities from participating in the investigations into the shootings of two U.S. citizens by immigration agents in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>“We haven’t had any cooperation up until now, which is very unusual, because in prior cases where there’s been a federal and state interest in a crime, we’ve seen collaboration between federal and state authorities,” Ellison told lawmakers on the Senate Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs Committee. </p> 
<p>Federal agents shot and killed two Americans — Renee Good and Alex Pretti — just days apart amid public protests over a major expansion of federal immigration enforcement in Minneapolis in December and January.</p> 
<p>Ellison said that in the case of the shooting of 37-year-old Good in early January, state officials still haven’t had any access to the car she was driving when ICE officers shot and killed her, or the bullet casings.</p> 
<p>Ellison said federal officials are not investigating the shootings and added: “We still haven’t received any access to the evidence that is involved in that case. ... But we’re with good faith hoping that things will change.”</p> 
<p>The FBI declined to comment. The Justice and Homeland Security Departments did not respond to requests for comment.</p> 
<p>Ellison’s comments Thursday follow <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/minneapolis-republicans-democrats-dig-in-heels-00721471" target="_blank">earlier protests from Minnesota officials</a> that they were not being included in the federal investigations that followed the Good shooting. In the immediate aftermath of the killing, prosecutors had begun investigating Good’s widow as opposed to the officers, though that <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/antoniopequenoiv/2026/01/13/at-least-6-minnesota-doj-prosecutors-resign-after-request-for-probe-into-renee-goods-widow/" target="_blank">probe appears to have stopped</a> after federal prosecutors resigned in protest.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, White House border czar Tom Homan said Thursday that the surge of thousands of immigration officers into Minneapolis will soon come to an end.</p> 
<p>Democrats on the Homeland Security Committee said federal investigators need to be more transparent.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151824" data-person-id="151824">Richard Blumenthal</a> (D-Conn.) said he was “really concerned that the failure to provide this evidence” and collaborate with local law enforcement “in fact, amounts to a cover up.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate Democrat aims to put members on record opposing Maxwell pardon</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/dem-wants-vote-opposing-maxwell-pardon-00777989</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5246-d647-addc-fbc7b3ff0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 09:38:10 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Jacky Rosen will introduce a resolution Thursday designed to put the Senate on record opposing the prospect of President Donald Trump granting a pardon or clemency to Ghislaine Maxwell, the longtime associate of convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein who is currently in prison.</p> 
<p>The Nevada Democrat, in a statement first shared with POLITICO, said she wanted to “make sure the U.S. Senate sends a clear message to the White House that a convicted sex trafficker of minors should not receive any clemency.”</p> 
<p>“If Leader Thune won’t bring this up for a recorded vote, I'll do everything I can to try to bring this up for unanimous consent, as it’s my sincere hope we can all agree Ghislaine Maxwell should serve out her full sentence,” Rosen added.</p> 
<p>Absent getting Republicans to allow a vote on her resolution, Rosen is discussing whether to try to approve it through a unanimous consent agreement after the Senate returns from next week’s scheduled recess.</p> 
<p>Adoption would require an agreement from all 100 senators, however. And while there are Republicans who have clamored for more transparency in the Epstein case and accountability for Epstein’s co-conspirators, the measure would likely face at least one GOP objection. Though the Senate quickly cleared legislation last year to force the release of the Epstein files, Senate Republicans have batted down related follow-up efforts on the floor.</p> 
<p>Though the resolution would be nonbinding, it would make the Senate’s official position against a pardon or clemency for Maxwell, which Republicans could see as boxing in Trump if he chooses that route.</p> 
<p>The president has not ruled it out, and Rosen’s forthcoming resolution is expected to note that the president has refused to rule it out. It also is likely to quote Trump saying, in 2025, he is “allowed to do it, but it’s something [he has] not thought about.”</p> 
<p>Maxwell’s attorneys have said his client will only testify under oath in exchange for clemency. Making good on that position, Maxwell invoked her Fifth Amendment right earlier this month when she appeared over video in a deposition, in compliance with a congressional subpoena, before the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justice Democrats endorse Kat Abughazaleh in Illinois primary</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/justice-dems-endorse-abughazaleh-00777652</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4fb1-de8a-a1fc-fff102270000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 09:30:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Elena Schneider</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Elena Schneider</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Justice Democrats and the Peace, Accountability, and Leadership PAC, or PAL PAC, have jointly endorsed progressive influencer Kat Abughazaleh in the hotly contested Democratic primary to replace Rep. Jan Schakowsky in Illinois.</p> 
<p>In a statement, Justice Democrats executive director Alexandra Rojas described Abughazaleh as “the type of progressive leadership we need in Congress — leadership that isn't too afraid to take on AIPAC or corporate PACs to defeat right-wing fascism or corporate corruption in the Democratic Party.”</p> 
<p>Abughazaleh faces more than a dozen opponents in a March primary that’s turned into a national proxy fight. Last week, a newly formed super PAC, Elect Chicago Women, started airing ads backing state Sen. Laura Fine, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/centrist-democrats-are-livid-with-aipac-after-primary-meddling-00769461?utm_medium=email&amp;utm_source=substack" target="_blank">some of Fine’s opponents have accused</a> the PAC of being funded by AIPAC.</p> 
<p>Abughazaleh, who is Palestinian American, has frequently criticized AIPAC and <a href="https://x.com/KatAbughazaleh/status/1967945971914117481" target="_blank">called Israel’s military operations in Gaza a genocide</a>.<br></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House member trips to Munich, elsewhere at risk due to likely DHS shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/house-codels-dhs-shutdown-00777978</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-522d-d0f8-adde-fa7f04dc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 09:08:37 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two dozen House members could miss a major national security gathering in Munich this weekend, thanks to the Senate's struggles to strike a deal that would avert a shutdown of the Department of Homeland Security.</p> 
<p>With DHS funding past Friday in doubt, Speaker Mike Johnson told members this week they will not be allowed to travel with official funding during the upcoming recess. That includes military flights, which are frequently arranged for congressional delegations overseas.</p> 
<p>House members could arrange commercial flights, but it's unclear whether they could seek House reimbursement for them.</p> 
<p>Among the trips in doubt is the Munich Security Conference, which some members were hoping to depart for Thursday, according to four people granted anonymity to describe private discussions. The Senate is not affected by Johnson's prohibition and multiple senators have indicated they plan to attend the conference regardless of whether DHS is funded or not.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Koch-backed group posts 7-figure ad buy in North Carolina Senate race</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/koch-backed-group-posts-7-figure-ad-buy-in-n-c-senate-race-00776363</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e14-de8a-a1fc-ff543b730000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 08:05:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Alec Hernandez</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alec Hernandez</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Americans for Prosperity Action, the political arm of the powerful conservative Koch network, has placed a 7-figure ad buy for former RNC Chair Michael Whatley’s Senate campaign in North Carolina, banking an early investment in a must-win seat for the GOP in what's expected to be one of the most expensive races in the country.</p> 
<p>The total spend in the Tarheel State will amount to over $1 million and will run on cable, marking the organization’s first TV ad buy of the 2026 midterms cycle. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k9dS0IlGjHE" target="_blank">The 30-second spot</a>, shared first with POLITICO, hits on perennial Koch priorities, casting Whatley as the candidate who will “stop wasteful spending, drive down prices and cut taxes.” The package of ads will also run on internet connected TV services and Meta platforms.</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis’ (R-N.C.) retirement announcement last year <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/29/thom-tillis-retires-00432045" target="_blank">following a barrage of attacks from President Donald Trump</a> opened a top-priority race for both parties in the swing state. Democrats haven’t won a Senate race or carried the state at the presidential level since 2008 — but Democrats have been inching closer to cinching a statewide federal win in past cycles after posting two consecutive Democrats to the governor’s mansion and maintaining a longtime hold on the attorney general’s office in Raleigh.</p> 
<p>Whatley, the Trump-endorsed front-runner in the GOP primary, raised <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/senate-fundraising-campaign-finance-fec-00759078" target="_blank">$3.8 million in 2025’s final FEC filing period</a>, which amounted to about half of the $7 million haul posted by former Gov. Roy Cooper, his likely Democratic challenger. AFP Action’s support will likely amount to just a drop in the bucket, though, as operatives in both parties have estimated that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/06/roy-cooper-raises-14-5-million-last-quarter-shattering-records-00594563" target="_blank">spending in the race could reach $650 million</a> by Election Day.</p> 
<p>The ad campaign is coupled with a grassroots door-knocking effort helmed by AFP Action, which began in North Carolina earlier this year. Whatley is set to join one of those outreach efforts himself in the Charlotte area later this month.</p> 
<p>The significant spend in North Carolina comes as the group has made similar, albeit smaller, 6-figure digital investments in the open Senate races in Michigan and New Hampshire for Mike Rogers and John Sununu, respectively — a sign of where they might invest more down the line.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Senate heads into doomed DHS votes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/12/congress/dhs-vote-stopgap-ice-shutdown-impacts-00777784</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-5035-d647-addc-fbf75ce80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A DHS shutdown is coming Friday night, and there’s no telling how long it could last.</p> 
<p>The White House on Wednesday night sent Congress the legislative text of its immigration enforcement counterproposal, a White House official and two people granted anonymity to disclose the private action told POLITICO. But key Democrats have already said they don’t believe the administration is serious enough about reining in the immigration agencies, all but guaranteeing a funding lapse despite the text exchange.</p> 
<p><b>— State of play: </b>Senators are headed into doomed DHS appropriations votes Thursday. Majority Leader John Thune teed up a vote to advance the House-passed DHS bill. Once that inevitably fails, Republicans plan to try to pass at least one continuing resolution, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss unannounced plans.</p> 
<p>“It doesn’t look like we’re going to stick the landing … so we’ll have to go to Plan B,” Thune told reporters Wednesday evening.</p> 
<p>Republicans want another stopgap that lasts between four to six weeks, but haven’t made a final decision about what they will try to clear Thursday. But they’d need Senate Democrats to advance any such measure, and the minority party said Wednesday they had no interest in cooperating on a stopgap.</p> 
<p>Minority Leader Chuck Schumer declared Democrats won’t support a CR after refusing to rule one out throughout the week. Other Democrats whose votes would likely be necessary — Catherine Cortez Masto and Jacky Rosen of Nevada — told POLITICO Wednesday they won’t back a funding patch either.</p> 
<p>“ICE is shutting down until we put guardrails,” Rosen said. “ICE should be acting with the same rules, uniform code of conduct, like the FBI and our state and local police … We are just asking what every other law enforcement agency abides by.”</p> 
<p>ICE is among the DHS agencies that would be least affected by a shutdown. That’s because it receives a combination of mandatory funds, revenue from fees and billions of dollars from the GOP megabill President Donald Trump signed into law in 2025.</p> 
<p><b>— Why a shutdown could drag: </b>Congress is in recess next week, and several senators are eager to get out of town today to make it to the Munich Security Conference or to campaign in their home states — regardless of the state of DHS talks.</p> 
<p>“I’m going to go home and I’m packing for Munich and I’m packing for Alaska,” Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) said. “That’s my plan and I’m sticking to it.”</p> 
<p>Once the shutdown starts, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499" target="_blank">it could take weeks</a> for the public to notice, giving lawmakers time before public pressure ramps up to end the standoff.</p> 
<p>TSA screeners, for example, would miss their first full paychecks mid-March, leading to a gradual increase in wait times for travelers during the peak of spring break. FEMA has enough funds — about $7 billion — to buoy the agency for at least a month or two during a shutdown.</p> 
<p>DHS officials could also pay active-duty Coast Guard members for several months using a pot of money from the 2025 megabill, which was replenished after last year’s shutdown ended. The Secret Service also received money from the legislation that it could tap in the event of a shutdown.</p> 
<p>“It does take the public a longer time to figure it out,” Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.) told POLITICO Wednesday. “[But] I don’t know that the length of this, if there is a shutdown, is going to be based on how long it takes people to feel the effect. I think it’s more going to be governed by when we can find the reforms that are sufficient to people’s concerns.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Rosen’s Epstein resolution: </b>Rosen is introducing a resolution Thursday that would force senators to go on the record over whether President Donald Trump should grant clemency to Ghislaine Maxwell, convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein’s longtime associate.</p> 
<p>If the resolution passes, it would be nonbinding but symbolically significant in declaring the Senate’s official position against a pardon or clemency for Maxwell, even as her attorney has dangled such a step in exchange for her testimony.</p> 
<p><b>— Notable hearings: </b>It’s the Senate Homeland Security panel's turn to hear testimony from DHS officials, including Todd Lyons, acting director for ICE, at 9 a.m. The Senate Armed Services Committee will hear testimony from Defense Department officials on American drones at 9:30 a.m. And at 10 a.m., the crypto world will tune into <a href="https://www.politico.com/morningmoney" target="_blank">SEC Chair Paul Atkins’ testimony</a> in front of the Senate Banking Committee as the industry pushes for a revamp of financial regulations.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Myah Ward, Mia McCarthy and Declan Harty contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tariff votes hand Republicans an unwanted referendum on affordability</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/12/house-tariff-votes-republicans-affordability-00777567</link>
      <description>House GOP leaders shielded their most vulnerable members from politically explosive votes for more than a year. Now the fallout is reverberating.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4f9a-d0f8-adde-ffda4f420000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/5d/ed/bf0db45c45729d2d7e2a8fe6de05/u-s-congress-73014.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“My job is to defend my district and my Constitution at the same time,” Rep. Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) said after voting to nix Trump's Canada tariffs.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/5d/ed/bf0db45c45729d2d7e2a8fe6de05/u-s-congress-73014.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy, Daniel Desrochers and Samuel Benson</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy, Daniel Desrochers and Samuel Benson</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A small GOP rebellion is unleashing a flood of House votes on President Donald Trump’s tariff policies in the coming weeks — handing Democrats a powerful tool to hammer Republicans on <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/05/affordability-affordability-affordability-democrats-new-winning-formula-00637023" target="_blank">affordability issues</a> ahead of the November midterms.</p> 
<p>House leaders had shielded their most vulnerable Republicans from politically explosive <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HJRES_72" target="_blank">votes on tariffs</a> for more than a year, but now the fallout is reverberating on Capitol Hill and in tough battleground races around the country.</p> 
<p>Six Republicans broke ranks and joined Democrats on Wednesday to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/house-rebukes-trumps-canada-tariffs-00776898" target="_blank">overturn Trump’s Canada tariffs</a> — a vote that took place only after three of those GOP members bucked Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> and voted Tuesday to reject a provision that would have blocked it. The move is likely to force a Trump veto.</p> 
<p>More votes are coming: Senior House Democrats plan to call up at least three more resolutions that will force many Republicans to choose between protecting their tariff-hit districts and pleasing their MAGA voter bases — not to mention their loyalties to a president who has, up until this week, not tolerated any House GOP dissent on the matter.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198811" data-person-id="198811">Suzan DelBene</a> of Washington, who leads the House Democratic campaign arm, said in an interview that her group would “continue to hold every single vulnerable Republican responsible for their broken promise to lower prices.”</p> 
<p>“If Republicans think this is such a great idea, then they can vote to support the tariffs,” she added. “But … we're going to make sure that they're accountable for their votes.”</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HJRES_72" target="_blank">tariff votes</a> — brought to the House floor under special expedited procedures that Johnson and other GOP leaders cannot easily block — are already making some farm-state Republicans squirm. Trump’s tariff wars have weighed heavily on agricultural exports, and many committed free-traders have long since had to make their peace with Trump’s policies.</p> 
<p>“I've been critical of the tariffs,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/495840" data-person-id="495840">Derek Schmidt</a> (R-Kan.). “But having said that, we've come this far.” He echoed a leadership argument — that Trump’s sweeping tariff powers could be confirmed or curtailed in a Supreme Court ruling expected sometime before July.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51185" data-person-id="51185">Adrian Smith</a> (R-Neb.), another tariff skeptic who chairs the Ways and Means subcommittee on trade, painted the Democratic effort to reject the tariffs as a political stunt. Like Schmidt, he voted to support the Canada tariffs Wednesday.</p> 
<p>“I welcome a sincere discussion on trade policy and the role in the legislative branch — any time, any place,” Smith said. “I'm not sensing that this is one that is intended to be a good discussion.”</p> 
<p>But those in more vulnerable districts and seeking other offices weren’t so eager to chat about the tough vote. Many have been uneasy with the president’s slash-and-burn trade policy and skeptical of the White House’s pleas for patience as Trump pursues trade deals. A recent POLITICO poll showed that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/10/poll-affordability-cost-of-living-00678076?nid=00000150-1596-d4ac-a1d4-179e288b0000&amp;nname=illinois-playbook&amp;nrid=a2f62cc8-609d-4f42-8611-136f942576cf" target="_blank">more Americans oppose Trump’s tariffs</a> than support them.</p> 
<p>One of the six Republicans opposing the Canada tariffs Wednesday, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/476519" data-person-id="476519">Jeff Hurd</a> of Colorado, cited congressional powers, not political concerns, in explaining his vote, while also noting the steep impact tariffs have had on farmers and manufacturers in his district.</p> 
<p>“My job is to defend my district and my Constitution at the same time,” he said in an interview. “This is not a partisan issue for me.”</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151736" data-person-id="151736">David Schweikert</a>, a longtime free-trade advocate who is running for governor of Arizona in a heavily contested GOP primary, said he was on the fence ahead of the Canada vote but ultimately came to a different conclusion.</p> 
<p>“Part of my angst is, it's a taxing authority. Taxing authority belongs with Congress. So in some ways, it's a classic, you know, do I defend the Constitution?”</p> 
<p>Democrats are now preparing to move ahead with multiple additional resolutions overturning Trump’s tariffs in Mexico and Brazil, as well as the president’s global “Liberation Day” tariffs. They see them as up-or-down referendums on a key policy driving up costs for Americans as recent special and off-year elections show voters turning against the GOP.</p> 
<p>“Those folks are starting to speak out,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51521" data-person-id="51521">Gregory Meeks</a> of New York, the top Democrat on the House Foreign Affairs Committee and the lead proponent of the tariff votes. “Those are warning signs to them that they need to do what the right thing is, and not just follow the president and his wayward ways.”</p> 
<p>Tariff politics are already making their mark on a number of campaigns — especially in districts and states where manufacturing or agriculture have been adversely impacted. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307607" data-person-id="307607">Haley Stevens</a>, who is running in a competitive Democratic primary for a Michigan Senate seat, has hammered the Trump levies as part of her affordability message.</p> 
<p>“Erratic, shoot-by-the-hip tariffs are causing Michiganders an incredible cost. They're raising the cost of groceries and everyday goods,” Stevens told reporters after a United Auto Workers candidate forum held Wednesday in Washington. “We can't withstand this level of uncertainty and chaos.”</p> 
<p>The tariff votes were unlocked by a trio of House Republicans who are unusually immune to intraparty pressure. One, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/198835" data-person-id="198835">Thomas Massie</a> of Kentucky, is a libertarian rebel who has clashed with Trump for months. Another, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260571" data-person-id="260571">Kevin Kiley</a> of California, had his district redrawn by Democrats last year and is less eager to toe the party line.</p> 
<p>The third, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227109" data-person-id="227109">Don Bacon</a> (R-Neb.), is retiring after repeated disagreements with the White House on tariffs, foreign policy and other matters. He said in an interview Wednesday the levies have simply been bad for his Omaha-centered district and that it was time to take a stand.</p> 
<p>“There's so many companies struggling against tariffs, and that's what the president needs to hear,” he said. “Our farmers are struggling.”</p> 
<p>White House officials and House GOP leaders unleashed an all-out pressure campaign to try to force the rebels to fall in line, calling around to other House Republicans and staffers asking “what buttons to push” with the holdouts, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the covert effort.</p> 
<p>Bacon said that after he voted against the procedural measure and left the floor Tuesday night, GOP leaders tried to persuade him to come back and negotiate, offering tariff carve-outs and other incentives for businesses in his district.</p> 
<p>“They were shocked,” Bacon recounted. “They said, ‘Why don't you stick around?’ I said, ‘I'm not planning on negotiating.’”</p> 
<p>After the tariff votes were unleashed, the Trump administration pivoted its lobbying campaign, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/white-house-substantial-gop-defections-canada-tariff-00776381" target="_blank">according to one White House official</a>, and is now focused on maintaining enough GOP support to prevent veto overrides. More than 70 Republicans would have to break ranks to meet the two-thirds majority for an override.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats expected a major GOP jailbreak Wednesday, thinking Republicans would not want to threaten their reelection chances by voting to sustain the tariffs.</p> 
<p>“[Republicans] have been remarkably loyal to a bad policy,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51324" data-person-id="51324">Emanuel Cleaver</a> (D-Mo.). “They were thinking about the president as this term began and as this push on tariffs was launched. And now they’re thinking about themselves.”</p> 
<p>But as House members were voting Wednesday, Trump publicly threatened any turncoats.</p> 
<p>“Any Republican, in the House or the Senate, that votes against TARIFFS will seriously suffer the consequences come Election time, and that includes Primaries!” he <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116054542648712986" target="_blank">wrote on Truth Social</a>.</p> 
<p>When the gavel fell, only Hurd and two other Republicans — Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/254452" data-person-id="254452">Brian Fitzpatrick</a> of Pennsylvania and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227706" data-person-id="227706">Dan Newhouse</a> of Washington — had joined Bacon, Kiley and Massie. The tight margin all but guaranteed that the House will fail to override a Trump veto.</p> 
<p><i>Elena Schneider contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Democrats think Pam Bondi just helped them in the midterms</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-judiciary-epstein-trump-00777293</link>
      <description>Tensions flared between Democrats and the Attorney General during a House Judiciary Committee hearing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4ef1-d0f8-adde-fefbedc70001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 19:17:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/88/21/eb64ddd74c0fbbb4fa8eeeca05f6/congress-bondi-55791.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Attorney General Pam Bondi testifies before a House Judiciary Committee oversight hearing on Capitol Hill in Washington, Wednesday, Feb. 11, 2026, in Washington, as Jeffrey Epstein survivors, stand left. (AP Photo/Tom Brenner)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/88/21/eb64ddd74c0fbbb4fa8eeeca05f6/congress-bondi-55791.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats walked into the House Judiciary Committee hearing with Attorney General Pam Bondi Wednesday expecting her to be nonresponsive and combative. They walked out with what they believe to be a more compelling argument for winning back the majority.</p> 
<p>For four hours, the nation’s top law enforcement officer largely refused to answer questions from Democrats about the Justice Department’s handling of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>In some moments, Bondi deflected queries by asking members if they cared about crimes or violence in their districts, flipping through a massive binder of research Rep. Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) derided as her “burn book.”</p> 
<p>In others, she responded by lashing out at committee members in personal terms, at one point calling Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the panel’s top Democrat, a “washed-up, loser lawyer — not even a lawyer.”</p> 
<p>“If we had the power, we would subpoena her, and we would require her to answer our questions,” Raskin, a former constitutional law professor, told reporters following the hearing. “So that is the importance of who's going to be in control in Congress after the 2026 elections because we would like the subpoena power, so we don't see this kind of phenomenal disrespect of Congress.”</p> 
<p>Even if Democrats reclaim the gavel of the House Judiciary Committee, Bondi could still drag her feet. And her aggressive posture in attacking lawmakers during a regular oversight hearing of the DOJ — the purported purpose of Wednesday’s proceedings — suggests she will not cooperate easily.</p> 
<p>“The questions I’ve asked … are not trick questions, they’re not gotcha questions, they’re actually basic questions about how the Department of Justice functions,” said Rep. Joe Neguse (D-Colo.), who said the hearing lacked “some modicum of resembling something that has typically been fairly conventional: an oversight hearing of the Department of Justice.”</p> 
<p>The only relevant, new information that Bondi provided to lawmakers was in response to a question from a Republican, Rep. Chip Roy of Texas, who asked <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/doj-epstein-investigations-00776455" target="_blank"><u>whether people would be indicted</u></a> for ties to Epstein’s crimes.</p> 
<p>Bondi said vaguely, “We have pending investigations in our office.” It was not clear whether she was referring to investigations into prominent Democratic officials, which had come after a directive from President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Still, Democrats think Bondi’s hostile performance throughout the hearing will help their cause in the midterms as they make a case for a return to normalcy. At times, even House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan had to interrupt to ensure lawmakers could ask their questions.</p> 
<p>"I can't believe that the Attorney General of the United States of America would appear before hundreds of millions of Americans this way and then have a book of insults that she's ready to lob at members of Congress ... we've got to get back to the America that we had before they dragged us down into the mud like this,” Raskin said following the hearing.</p> 
<p>Rep. Steve Cohen (D-Tenn.), a member of the Judiciary panel, also said the events Wednesday boost Democrats’ case in the midterm elections.</p> 
<p>“She did an excellent job in appealing to Donald Trump, and it was [for] … one person audience: Donald Trump,” said Cohen, adding that the hearing “gave the public some information about what the Justice Department's not doing correctly.”</p> 
<p>In many ways, Bondi played directly into Democrats’ hands, and not only by trash-talking lawmakers whose questions she didn’t want to answer — similar to the maneuver she deployed when <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/07/congress/bondi-goes-after-schiff-00596375" target="_blank"><u>testifying before the Senate Judiciary Committee</u></a> back in October.</p> 
<p>Democrats coordinated with the victims of Epstein’s abuse so that roughly ten could sit in the hearing room behind Bondi. Lawmakers offered her the opportunity to engage with them directly and apologize for the department’s conduct or meet with the victims.</p> 
<p>Bondi, in her opening remarks, said she was “deeply sorry for what any victim … has been through” but otherwise refused to take the bait. At one point, when Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/dems-challenge-bondi-on-epstein-00775809" target="_blank"><u>asked Bondi to apologize to the victims</u></a> for what the Justice Department has put them through, Bondi declined: “I’m not going to get in the gutter for her theatrics.”</p> 
<p>Democrats also headed into Wednesday’s high-profile hearing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-house-judiciary-tesitmony-00775441" target="_blank"><u>prepared to draw a contrast</u></a> between their interest in asking hard questions about events that have captured the public’s attention — namely justice for Epstein’s victims and accountability for any potential accomplices — and Republicans’ more politically accommodating approach.</p> 
<p>Jordan said on Wednesday evening he thought Bondi “handled herself very well” and expected Democrats to be aggressive. At one point, Rep. Dan Goldman (D-N.Y.) yelled at Bondi to be “quiet” as he fought to be heard, while Rep. Chuy Garcia (D-Ill.) called her “one of the worst” attorneys generals “in our history.”</p> 
<p>“I think it went great — I mean, the bottom line is … under the leadership of the Attorney General and the president, crime is down,” Jordan said.</p> 
<p>The only <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/massie-vs-bondi-00775966" target="_blank"><u>Republican who challenged Bondi</u></a> was Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky, who led the charge to release the Epstein files in DOJ’s possession and picked enough fights with Trump that the president and his allies are now seeking to oust him in a primary.</p> 
<p>Accusing Bondi of failing to comply with the law he shepherded through Congress with sloppy redactions — or lack thereof — of both victims and the name of one powerful man in the Epstein files, Bondi called Massie a “failed politician” and a “hypocrite.”</p> 
<p>Massie, in an interview Wednesday evening, said it took Bondi “a long time to find my insult card.”</p> 
<p>“I think she was crashing the whole time,” he said. “There was no effort really to answer any of the difficult questions.”</p> 
<p>Asked about being the only Republican to ask a tough question at the hearing, Massie replied, “Nobody wants to get on the bad side of Trump … That’ll change once we get past our primaries.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House passes GOP elections overhaul</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/save-america-act-passes-house-00777405</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4f12-de8a-a1fc-ff523bba0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 18:44:56 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House passed a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499" target="_blank">major GOP elections overhaul</a> Wednesday after intense pressure from President Donald Trump, tech mogul Elon Musk and hard-right influencers. But the legislation still has no clear path forward in the Senate, where Republicans privately acknowledge there is not enough GOP support to skirt a Democratic filibuster as Trump is demanding.</p> 
<p>The SAVE America Act, an updated version of a bill tightening voter registration standards that the House passed last year, was approved on a 218-213 vote. One Democrat, Rep. Henry Cuellar of Texas, voted for it — down from the four who backed the earlier effort.</p> 
<p>Conservative hard-liners wanted the bill attached to a massive government funding package this month, threatening to extend a four-day partial government shutdown until Trump intervened and ordered House Republicans to pass the bill without it.</p> 
<p>The legislation would trigger major changes to how Americans vote, including requiring voters to present proof of citizenship to register, eliminating mail-only registrations, and requiring photo ID in every state for the first time. It would also require states to take new steps to remove noncitizens from existing voter rolls.</p> 
<p>The GOP’s hope is that the focus on election integrity and Trump’s false claims that the 2020 election was “rigged” will help drive turnout among MAGA voters when Trump isn’t on the ballot this November, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal strategy. The vote is also meant to satisfy the president’s demands for a voting crackdown as he mulls bigger overhauls many Republicans oppose, like “federalizing” America’s election system and ending mail voting.</p> 
<p>But the House vote hands a hot potato to Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who has ruled out changing Senate rules to weaken the 60-voter supermajority threshold to pass the bill and has reacted coolly to suggestions a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/senate-filibuster-gop-save-act-00775393" target="_blank">“talking filibuster” approach could work instead</a>.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders deployed a procedural feint, using a Senate-passed shell bill to try to fast-track consideration in the other chamber — part of the Trump-backed push to try to force a reckoning on the filibuster.</p> 
<p>Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska) poured cold water on House Republicans' celebratory mood this week.</p> 
<p>Even before the House vote Wednesday, Murkowski announced she would oppose it — lambasting the bill as “federal overreach.” Her move sparked an onslaught of recriminations from House Republicans, who are still pushing Thune and Speaker Mike Johnson to find a way to send the bill to Trump’s desk.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bondi dodges questions about Lutnick’s connections with Epstein</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/pam-bondi-howard-lutnick-00776491</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e46-d3b5-addf-eec634520000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 15:04:11 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Josh Gerstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Josh Gerstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi gave no direct answer Wednesday when pressed by Rep. Becca Balint (D-Vt.) on whether the Justice Department has made any effort to question Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick about his interactions with Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“Secretary Lutnick has addressed those ties himself,” Bondi replied.</p> 
<p>Lutnick said on a podcast last year that he was disgusted by Epstein’s conduct and vowed in 2005 to never to be in the same room with him again. However, documents the Justice Department released last month show continued interactions between the two men in the ensuing years.</p> 
<p>In addition, Lutnick acknowledged at a Senate hearing Tuesday that he and his family traveled in 2012 to the Caribbean island Epstein owned. Lutnick <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/lutnick-grilled-over-epstein-links-at-commerce-appropriations-hearing-00773002" target="_blank">described a lunch with the financier</a>, who pleaded guilty in 2008 to soliciting a minor for prostitution in Florida and who died by suicide in 2019 in a New York jail while awaiting trial on federal sex-trafficking charges.</p> 
<p>Lutnick, despite the latest revelations, has faced <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/main-wh-lutnick-00774844" target="_blank">few recriminations from Trump world</a> over his connections with the late financier.</p> 
<p>As Balint demanded that Bondi explain whether prosecutors or the FBI have talked with Lutnick or other Trump administration officials who had “ties” with Epstein, the attorney general challenged the lawmaker’s terminology.</p> 
<p>“What does ‘ties’ mean?” Bondi replied. “Can you define that? Can you define ‘ties’?"</p> 
<p>“I think Americans would be shocked to learn that you are not interested in talking with these officials who have ties to Jeffrey Epstein,” Balint replied as the attorney general tried to change the subject to the shooting of a Border Patrol agent in Vermont last month. “We now know that Lutnick went to Epstein's island in 2012. How was that not a dealbreaker for the president?” the Democratic lawmaker asked.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bondi says DOJ is investigating possible Epstein conspirators</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/doj-epstein-investigations-00776455</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e30-d3b5-addf-eef43f4f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 15:03:06 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Erica Orden</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Erica Orden</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi said Wednesday her department is actively probing individuals who might have conspired with convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>“We have pending investigations in our office," she said during her testimony before the House Judiciary Committee, when asked by Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) if people would be indicted for ties to Epstein's crimes.</p> 
<p>It was not clear if Bondi was referring to work by the U.S. Attorney's Office in the Southern District of New York, where Bondi has directed U.S. Attorney Jay Clayton to oversee investigations into connections between Epstein and prominent Democrats. </p> 
<p>But members of both parties are clamoring for justice for Epstein's victims, with many lawmakers counting on the release of the DOJ's Epstein files to reveal more information about who should be implicated in wrongdoing.</p> 
<p>Republicans have repeatedly suggested former President Bill Clinton should be further scrutinized, pointing to his long-standing relationship with Epstein as captured in photos Bondi's agency made public in compliance with the law Congress passed last fall. Democrats, meanwhile, continue to scrutinize Trump's relationship with the disgraced financier. </p> 
<p>Neither man has been accused of wrongdoing in connection with Epstein's crimes.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rep. Jason Crow asks Pirro to preserve evidence related to failed indictment</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/rep-jason-crow-asks-pirro-to-preserve-evidence-related-to-failed-indictment-00776376</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e1e-d3b5-addf-eede3ce50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 14:19:05 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Jason Crow (D-Colo.) on Wednesday demanded U.S. Attorney for the District of Columbia Jeanine Pirro preserve all evidence related to her unsuccessful effort to bring charges against him and five other Democratic lawmakers.</p> 
<p>The request comes a day after Pirro’s office <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/lawmakers-military-orders-grand-jury-indictment-00775504" target="_blank"><u>failed to obtain a criminal indictment</u></a> against the lawmakers for putting out a video last year urging military personnel not to carry out illegal orders.</p> 
<p>In a letter sent Wednesday to Pirro’s office, Abbe Lowell, Crow’s attorney, called the effort to indict Crow and the other Democrats involved in the video “a breathtaking and unprecedented level of prosecutorial overreach and misuse of power.” Lowell, who has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/27/trump-retribution-lawyer-abbe-lowell-lisa-cook-00529290" target="_blank"><u>represented a wide swath of President Donald Trump’s enemies</u></a> in the last year, also put Pirro and other federal prosecutors “on notice” of the possible legal ramifications for failing to preserve evidence in the case or taking further action to pursue the case.</p> 
<p>“Donald Trump’s abuse of America’s justice system is chilling and indefensible,” Lowell wrote <a href="https://www.politico.com/document/crow-lowell-pirro-letter" target="_blank">in the letter</a>. “What’s perhaps most surprising is not that your effort to secure a grand jury indictment failed, but that you even tried. Americans are paying attention to your gross abuses of power and demanding accountability."</p> 
<p>Pirro's office did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Pirro and other prosecutors in the Trump administration have on several occasions struggled to secure indictments against several of the president’s political foes, including <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/letitia-james-indictment-third-charge-00697148" target="_blank"><u>New York Attorney General Letitia James</u></a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/19/james-comey-case-lindsey-halligan-hearing-00659479" target="_blank"><u>former FBI Director James Comey</u></a>. A grand jury rejecting indictments is an exceedingly rare outcome in federal cases, as they are tasked only with determining whether the Justice Department has brought a plausible case, although the Trump administration has faced an unusual number of failures in liberal areas like New York and the D.C. area.</p> 
<p>Sens. Mark Kelly of Arizona and Elissa Slotkin of Michigan, whom federal prosecutors also attempted to indict in relation to the video, decried the move from Pirro’s office at a Wednesday press conference, with Kelly, calling it an effort “to abuse power in order to silence and intimidate anyone who disagrees with them.”</p> 
<p>“The baseless and absurd allegations by Donald Trump, followed by your carrying out of the President’s political retribution campaign has already gone too far, and are evidence of yet another abuse of power directed at those who dare speak out and criticize this Administration,” Lowell wrote in the letter, which was <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/jason-crow-letter-jeanine-pirro-illegal-orders-video-records-lawsuit/" target="_blank"><u>first reported by CBS News</u></a>.</p> 
<p>Trump, in the wake of the video’s release in November 2025, repeatedly called for the lawmakers to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank"><u>face arrest and trial</u></a> for what he called “SEDITIOUS BEHAVIOR, punishable by DEATH!” The president later clarified that he was “not threatening death” against the Democrats.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Johnson says he has urged Florida Republican to stay in Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/neal-dunn-resignation-johnson-00776216</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4e11-de8a-a1fc-ff517add0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 13:59:40 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> says he has asked retiring Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/259506" data-person-id="259506">Neal Dunn</a> to serve out his term amid concerns the Florida Republican might resign early.</p> 
<p>An early exit from Dunn, 72, would deal Johnson another massive blow as he tries to maintain his narrow majority. Currently, Republicans can afford to lose no more than one GOP vote on party-line measures, though they are expected to pick up a vote in a March special election.</p> 
<p>Senior House Republicans believe Dunn intends to step down in the coming months despite an effort to get him to stay, according to three people granted anonymity to describe the private discussions.</p> 
<p>“Neal Dunn is a beloved member of Congress and a great man, and you know, he's informed us he's <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/13/congress/neal-dunn-florida-retirement-00724395" target="_blank">not going to run for reelection</a>," Johnson told reporters Wednesday. As for what Dunn does beyond that, he added, "I'm not sure — you need to ask him about it. But I've encouraged him to stay and be a part of this, and I think he wants to do that.”</p> 
<p>Dunn, who represents a heavily Republican seat in northern Florida, declined to discuss his intentions in an interview Wednesday: "No comment," he said. </p> 
<p>Dunn has worn a mask on the House floor at times in recent weeks, and some of his colleagues said they believe his health is a factor in his decision. Asked about those concerns, Dunn replied, "Don't I look good?"</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massie becomes first Republican to spar with Bondi during House Judiciary hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/massie-vs-bondi-00775966</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4dc6-de8a-a1fc-fdc617370000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 12:57:34 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Thomas Massie was the first and so far only Republican to spar with Attorney General Pam Bondi during her hearing Wednesday before the House Judiciary Committee.</p> 
<p>The Kentucky lawmaker asked Bondi about redactions in the Jeffrey Epstein files that failed to comply with the law Massie helped shepherd to passage last year. He pointed to instances where the names of victims are not shielded but the name of Les Wexner, a businessman and client of the convicted sex offender, is blacked out.</p> 
<p>“Who’s responsible?" Massie asked. "Are you able to track who in the organization made this massive failure and released the victims’ names?"</p> 
<p>Bondi replied that Massie, who has become a vocal critic of President Donald Trump, was a "failed politician" and a "hypocrite."</p> 
<p>“Within 40 minutes, Wexner’s name was added back in,” Bondi said.</p> 
<p>“Within 40 minutes of me catching you red-handed,” Massie responded.</p> 
<p>Bondi then accused Massie of having “Trump derangement syndrome" and refusing to press for justice for Epstein's victims during previous administrations.</p> 
<p>“This is bigger than Watergate,” Massie told Bondi. “This cover-up spans decades, and you are responsible for this portion of it.”</p> 
<p>Wexner has said he severed ties with Epstein in the aughts, around the time of an earlier investigation against the late financier and when Wexner realized that Epstein has illicitly taken money from him.</p> 
<p>“The Assistant U.S. Attorney told Mr. Wexner’s legal counsel in 2019 that Mr. Wexner was being viewed as source of information about Epstein and was not a target in any respect," a legal representative for Wexner said in a recent statement. "Mr. Wexner cooperated fully by providing background information on Epstein and was never contacted again.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP senators rail at FDA after closed-door briefing on abortion drug</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/bitter-pills-00775740</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d3e-d0f8-adde-ff7e39600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:57:18 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Alice Miranda Ollstein</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some Senate Republicans emerged disappointed from a closed-door briefing Tuesday with FDA Commissioner Marty Makary, saying the agency is not taking a safety review of the abortion pill mifepristone seriously and calling for congressional action to curb access to the drug.</p> 
<p>Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said in an interview Makary failed to give a timeline for completion of the review, explain what the audit will involve and disclose whether it was even underway.</p> 
<p>“I think that this safety study is a dead end,” Hawley said. “I just think that FDA is not serious about it. I don't think that they're proceeding with any sense of urgency whatsoever. If they're really proceeding at all. I frankly, can't tell.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Bill Cassidy (R-La.), the chair of the Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions Committee who organized the briefing for select GOP senators, in a statement also blasted “the lack of progress on HHS and FDA’s promised safety study on these dangerous drugs” as “disappointing,” and complained the review was “moving too slowly.”</p> 
<p>It's not clear what comes next. Republicans have previously tried and failed to impose restrictions on mifepristone, which is used in more than two-thirds of abortions, through government funding legislation. Hawley said he has not yet decided whether to attempt to place guardrails on the drug as part of the next appropriations process or introduce a standalone bill, but that he will roll out his plans in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p><br>“I don't have confidence [the FDA review] is going to amount to anything,” he said. “My view is Congress now needs to get involved.”</p> 
<p><br>Reached for comment, HHS spokesperson Andrew Nixon referred POLITICO to a<a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/questions-and-answers-mifepristone-medical-termination-pregnancy-through-ten-weeks-gestation" target="_blank">&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/postmarket-drug-safety-information-patients-and-providers/questions-and-answers-mifepristone-medical-termination-pregnancy-through-ten-weeks-gestation" target="_blank">previous agency statement</a> asserting the FDA “is taking care to do this study properly and in the right way.”</p> 
<p>“We are planning to complete the study as soon as possible while ensuring we are not cutting any corners from a scientific research standpoint,” the statement reads, adding that such reviews “often take approximately a year or more to conduct.”</p> 
<p>Conservative anger with the Trump administration has boiled over in recent months over its decision to leave in place Biden-era rules that<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/01/03/justice-department-postal-abortion-drugs-00076274" target="_blank">&nbsp;</a><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/01/03/justice-department-postal-abortion-drugs-00076274" target="_blank">expanded access to abortion pills via mail</a> and telemedicine, and for approving a new generic version of the drug. Administration officials took narrower steps in January to roll back access to mifepristone at retail pharmacies, but the anti-abortion movement and its allies in Congress are pressuring the FDA to abolish telemedicine prescription of the pills or ban them altogether.</p> 
<p>At the same time, several GOP states are suing the agency, including Cassidy’s Louisiana and Hawley’s Missouri. The administration has tried to rebuff these lawsuits, asking judges to wait until FDA’s ongoing study is completed before issuing a ruling. Anti-abortion activists, tired of waiting, have threatened to withhold resources from the GOP in the upcoming midterm elections if they don’t see action on the drugs.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dems challenge Pam Bondi to address Epstein's victims at House Judiciary hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/dems-challenge-bondi-on-epstein-00775809</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d50-d647-addc-efd783a70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:53:05 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democrats are challenging Attorney General Pam Bondi to address the victims of Jeffrey Epstein, who are seated behind her during a House Judiciary Committee oversight hearing of the Justice Department.</p> 
<p>The panel's top Democrat, Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, used his opening remarks to introduce Bondi to Epstein's victims, setting the tone for the tough questions she's expected to face for her handling of the case against the convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>“To promote justice for the people, you’ve got to listen to the victims, like the women seated behind you today,” said Raskin. “Those are just some of the hundreds of survivors of Jeffrey Epstein's global sex trafficking ring who are demanding that the truth be told and are demanding accountability for the abusers who trafficked and raped them.”</p> 
<p>Raskin added that Bondi had not yet met with those victims.</p> 
<p>In her own opening remarks, Bondi defended her handling of the Epstein files and maintained that if victims’ names were inadvertently released, her department has moved swiftly to correct those mistakes.</p> 
<p>She opted to directly address the victims seated behind her.</p> 
<p>“I’m a career prosecutor and despite what the ranking member said, I have spent my entire career fighting for victims, and I will continue to do so," Bondi said. "I am deeply sorry for what any victim, any victim, has been through, especially as a result of that monster.”</p> 
<p>She added that the FBI was waiting to hear from those with information.</p> 
<p>But when asked by Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) to turn around and directly address the victims and apologize for what the Justice Department has put them through, Bondi refused.</p> 
<p>"I am not going to get in the gutter for her theatrics," Bondi said of Jayapal.</p> 
<p>Jayapal also asked the Epstein victims seated in the hearing room to stand and raise their hands if they have not been able to meet with the Justice Department to share their stories. Everyone did.</p> 
<p>Bondi has faced criticism for months for reneging on her commitment to bring transparency in the Epstein case, starting with when <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/02/25/lawmakers-pressure-pam-bondi-release-epstein[…]ref_fark&amp;utm_content=link&amp;utm_medium=website&amp;utm_source=fark" target="_blank">she told Fox News</a>last year that Epstein-related materials were “on [her] desk right now to review" but then in July announced no such files would be released.</p> 
<p>Since Congress passed legislation compelling the Justice Department to release the Epstein files in their near-entirety, the administration has blown past statutory deadlines to do so. A bipartisan group of lawmakers has complained in recent days that some redactions were overly broad, while other materials appeared to jeopardize the privacy of Epstein’s victims.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tillis pans ‘political lawfare’ after grand jury declines to indict Democratic lawmakers</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/tillis-on-lawfare-00775810</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d52-d0f8-adde-ff5a9b510000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:31:50 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republican Sen. Thom Tillis slammed the Justice Department’s push to criminally charge Democratic lawmakers who last November urged military servicemembers to disobey illegal orders in a video, calling it “political lawfare” in a post on X on Wednesday.</p> 
<p>A Washington, D.C., <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/lawmakers-military-orders-grand-jury-indictment-00775504" target="_blank">grand jury on Tuesday declined to</a> indict the six lawmakers, who include battleground state Sens. Mark Kelly (D-Ariz.) and Elissa Slotkin (D-Mich.). It marked another instance of U.S. Attorney Jeanine Pirro failing to clinch a high-profile federal indictment since taking over as the top prosecutor in D.C.</p> 
<p>“Political lawfare waged by either side undermines America's criminal justice system, which is the gold standard of the world,” <a href="https://x.com/SenThomTillis/status/2021577817868095796" target="_blank">Tillis wrote</a>. “Thankfully in this instance, a jury saw the attempted indictments for what they really were. Political lawfare is not normal, not acceptable, and needs to stop.”</p> 
<p>The White House referred POLITICO to the Department of Justice, which did not immediately respond to a request for comment on the North Carolina Republican’s social media post.</p> 
<p>Kelly and Slotkin were joined in the video by Pennsylvania Democratic Reps. Chris Deluzio and Chrissy Houlahan, and also Reps. Jason Crow of Colorado and Maggie Goodlander of New Hampshire.</p> 
<p>“Like us, you all swore an oath to protect and defend this Constitution,” they said. “Right now, the threats to our Constitution aren’t just coming from abroad, but from right here at home. Our laws are clear, you can refuse illegal orders.”</p> 
<p>In a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/20/congress/trump-democratic-lawmakers-sedition-00661504" target="_blank">Truth Social spree that followed</a>, President Donald Trump called for the lawmakers to face trial for “seditious behavior” and reshared a post that advocated for hanging the Democrats.</p> 
<p>The two-term senator has been a thorn in Trump’s side even before he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/29/thom-tillis-retires-00432045" target="_blank">declared he wouldn’t seek reelection last June</a>. Tillis <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/06/28/congress/donald-trump-threatens-thom-tillis-00431472" target="_blank">voted against the Big Beautiful Bill</a>, Trump's signature domestic policy package, last year after expressing major concerns with its effects on Medicaid. He’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/blogs/politico-press/2026/01/30/full-transcript-sen-thom-tillis-on-the-conversation-with-dasha-burns-00757104" target="_blank">called for the sacking</a> of Department of Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem and White House deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller. And he’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/16/greenland-trump-republicans-congress-00732945" target="_blank">called for greater congressional cooperation</a> in the wake of Trump’s ambitions to expand into Greenland.</p> 
<p>This isn’t the first time Pirro has struggled to persuade a grand jury to indict subjects who draw the ire of the Trump administration. After a panel last August declined to grant a felony indictment against a former DOJ employee who threw a hoagie at a federal officer in Washington, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/31/pirro-washington-crime-sandwich-thrower-00538780" target="_blank">she lamented that DC residents</a> “were so used to crime” and “don’t even care about whether or not the law is violated” in an interview with Fox News.</p> 
<p>“My office has been instructed to move for the highest crime possible, consistent with the law, the statute, and the evidence. And in that one case, in that particular article, we were on point,” she said. “But the grand jurors don’t take it so seriously. They’re like, ‘Ah, you know, whatever.’”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>US debt forecast to hit $64T in a decade as Trump policies widen deficit  </title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/us-debt-forecast-to-hit-64t-in-a-decade-as-trump-policies-widen-deficit-00775726</link>
      <description>Congress’ nonpartisan scorekeeper predicts that the annual deficit will grow to $3.1 trillion by 2036.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4d19-d3b5-addf-eddd7fa30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 10:00:22 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/a7/d1/ab32a83f41ef81a799606189abd1/u-s-congress-88781.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>The U.S. Capitol building is seen Jan. 12, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/a7/d1/ab32a83f41ef81a799606189abd1/u-s-congress-88781.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The U.S. national debt is on track to reach $64 trillion within a decade as the federal government continues its trend of red-ink balances under President Donald Trump and Republican control of Congress.</p> 
<p>The Congressional Budget Office released its <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019c-4d22-d3b5-addf-ede6923c0000" target="_blank">marquee report</a> Wednesday on the U.S. fiscal outlook, estimating that the tax and spending package Republicans enacted last summer — along with Trump’s immigration policies — will increase deficits by trillions of dollars over the next decade. That budget gap would essentially cancel out the roughly $3 trillion in deficit reduction Trump’s tariffs are expected to produce.</p> 
<p>Congress’ nonpartisan scorekeeper predicts that the U.S. will run a $1.9 trillion deficit during the current fiscal year as the national debt currently exceeds $38 trillion. The annual deficit is then forecast to grow to $3.1 trillion by 2036.</p> 
<p>Growing interest costs and spending on safety-net programs drives the expanding gap between how much money flows into federal coffers each year and how much is doled out.</p> 
<p>Debt compared to economic output is also on track to soar in the coming years. CBO predicts that federal debt held by the public will rise from 101 percent of gross domestic product this year to 120 percent in a decade, exceeding the previous high of 106 percent of GDP in 1946.</p> 
<p>As the CBO <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/12/cbo-economic-growth-estimate-trump-00560730" target="_blank">predicted last summer</a>, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/house-passes-gop-megabill-00438206" target="_blank">Republican megabill Trump signed into law in July</a> will help boost economic growth this year. But that will be partially offset by the economic effects of Trump’s tariffs and increased immigration enforcement.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: House set to rebuke Trump’s tariffs</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/11/congress/house-votes-trump-tariffs-resolution-canada-00775520</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4b4e-d3b5-addf-ebce31e10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House is set to rebuke Donald Trump’s signature economic policy Wednesday following Speaker Mike Johnson’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/gop-revolt-sinks-effort-to-block-votes-on-trumps-tariffs-00775107" target="_blank">failure late last night</a> to contain GOP unrest over the administration’s trade war.</p> 
<p>The chamber will vote on a resolution offered by Democratic Rep. Gregory Meeks (N.Y.) to overturn the president’s Canadian tariffs. It comes after GOP Reps. Kevin Kiley of California, Don Bacon of Nebraska and Thomas Massie of Kentucky sided with Democrats to tank a procedural rule, which contained a provision GOP leaders have relied upon for months to prevent members from voting to undermine Trump’s trade agenda.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think that the House should be limiting the authority of members and enlarging the power of leadership at the expense of our members,” Kiley told POLITICO.</p> 
<p>Now the House will vote Wednesday afternoon on the Meeks resolution. And thanks to a combination of Johnson’s razor-thin majority, Democratic unity and expected Republican defections, that measure is expected to be approved — it’s only a question of, by how much.</p> 
<p>Besides Kiley, Bacon and Massie, keep an eye on Republican Reps. Dan Newhouse (Wash.) and Zach Nunn (Iowa), who held out on voting for the rule Tuesday night before eventually folding. Newhouse in particular was subject to a full-court press on the House floor from House Majority Leader Steve Scalise and Majority Whip Tom Emmer. Reps. Tom McClintock (R-Calif.) and Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) have also been uneasy about the tariffs.</p> 
<p>No longer held back, Democrats can and likely will continue to force votes on other resolutions to overturn Trump’s tariffs on goods from Mexico and Brazil, following the example of senators who have successfully voted across party lines to curb the administration’s trade activities.</p> 
<p>“What we want to show is that really this should be a bipartisan issue,” Meeks told reporters Tuesday. “The American people are watching to see what we do in this issue.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— DHS negotiations: </b>Senate Majority Leader John Thune took the first procedural step Tuesday toward allowing the Senate to vote on another DHS funding punt. But Democratic support will be necessary to get a continuing resolution for the agency over the finish line. A DHS shutdown at the end of the week is near certain, with no deal in sight.</p> 
<p><b>— Schumer seeks Venezuela probe: </b>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer and Sen. Adam Schiff (D-Calif.) are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/schumer-pressure-trump-venezuela-oil-fund-00775358" target="_blank">rolling out legislation Wednesday</a> that would direct the Government Accountability Office to investigate the Trump administration’s handling of proceedings from Venezuelan oil sales. Their bill, shared first with POLITICO, would require GAO to launch the audit within 30 days and report its findings to Congress within 90 days of completion.</p> 
<p><b>— Bondi in the hot seat: </b>Attorney General Pam Bondi will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-house-judiciary-tesitmony-00775441" target="_blank">testify before the House Judiciary Committee</a> Wednesday as the Department of Justice faces scrutiny over its handling of the Jeffrey Epstein files, prosecution of former Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro and response to the fatal shootings by federal agents of two U.S. citizens in Minnesota.</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor, James Bikales and Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump keeps driving online fundraising — for both parties</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/political-donations-trump-fundraising-00774862</link>
      <description>The GOP president is dominating his own party’s online fundraising and proving a major driver for Democrats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4993-d3b5-addf-e9d75cb70001</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 05:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f3/17/05cb869f497d9f77436aa363ef2b/main-piper-onlinefundraising-illustration.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Illustration by Jade Cuevas/POLITICO (source images via Getty Images and iStock)</media:credit>
        <media:title>Donald Trump continues to best Republicans' best online fundraiser, even as he is constitutionally barred from running for office again.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f3/17/05cb869f497d9f77436aa363ef2b/main-piper-onlinefundraising-illustration.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jessica Piper</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jessica Piper</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump still raises far more money online than any other GOP figure.</p> 
<p>Democrats get major fundraising boosts when they clash with him.</p> 
<p>And the Democratic money machine continues to churn — a sign of hope for a party seeking to regroup from brutal losses the year prior.</p> 
<p>Those are among the key patterns that appeared in a POLITICO analysis of online fundraising across 2025, as both parties began to gear up for highly competitive midterms.</p> 
<p>The sweeping POLITICO analysis of data from ActBlue and WinRed — the primary fundraising platforms for each party — revealed how Trump, who is constitutionally barred from seeking reelection, is still at the center of the GOP’s digital and financial universe. And while Democrats continue to debate how much they should focus on opposing Trump in their broader campaign messaging, the data shows just how strongly the GOP president motivates liberal donors.</p> 
<p>Major surges in online Democratic fundraising were fueled by members of the party standing up to — or being attacked by — the president. Democratic candidates’ biggest fundraising days on ActBlue were all driven by conflict with Trump, with those days accounting for millions of dollars raised from tens of thousands of donors giving online for the first time this cycle.</p> 
<p>Among Republicans, Trump’s own joint fundraising committee, Trump National Committee, continued to raise the most money out of anyone on WinRed in 2025, bringing more over the course of the year than the next two biggest GOP groups combined. Trump’s political operation accounted for more than 1 in 5 total dollars raised federally through WinRed last year.<br></p><p>ActBlue and WinRed report all donations made to federal campaigns and committees through their platforms, providing a detailed picture of small-dollar giving. The platforms are so dominant that they include the vast majority, though not all, of online donations for both parties.</p> 
<p>The data provides insight not only into who raised the most but the specific moments that drove donors to give.</p> 
<p>Leading the way was Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/211545" data-person-id="211545">Cory Booker</a> (D-N.J.), who saw a massive surge in donations when he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/04/01/cory-booker-record-breaking-senate-speech-00265142" target="_blank">broke records with a 25-hour quasi-filibuster speech</a> protesting the Trump administration’s policies.</p> 
<p>Booker’s campaign committee received nearly 92,000 donations totaling $2.5 million on ActBlue on April 2, the day after his speech finished. It was the highest single-day total for any federal committee on the platform in 2025. For roughly a third of those donors, it was their first donation of the year on ActBlue.</p> 
<p>The New Jersey senator was not the only Democrat to get a donation boost off of standing up to Trump. California Gov. Gavin Newsom’s joint fundraising committee saw a massive surge in donations in early June after he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/11/california-national-guard-deployment-lawsuit-00400503" target="_blank">sued the Trump administration</a> to block the deployment of the National Guard to Los Angeles and Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/09/donald-trump-on-arresting-gavin-newsom-id-do-it-00394530" target="_blank">suggested arresting</a> the governor. The group, Campaign for Democracy, recorded more than 47,000 donations on June 11, for a total of $1.3 million.</p> 
<p>That was the start of a three-day surge that accounted for nearly one-third of all online donations to the Newsom joint fundraising committee in 2025.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/163882" data-person-id="163882">Mark Kelly</a> (D-Ariz.) saw nearly 43,000 donations for a total of nearly $1.3 million to his campaign committee Nov. 25 after Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/24/pentagon-to-investigate-sen-mark-kelly-for-anti-trump-video-00666894" target="_blank">ordered the Pentagon to investigate</a> whether a video that featured Kelly and others advising troops not to follow illegal orders was itself unlawful. Roughly 1 in 5 donations on the platform that day went to Kelly’s campaign.</p> 
<p>Kelly then remained the top fundraiser nearly every day for three weeks after that, bringing in donations from about 278,000 unique donors in November and December. That surge set Kelly apart from other Democratic figures last year for both its intensity and duration. The POLITICO analysis found that more than three-quarters of donors in that time period had not given to Kelly previously in the year. For 1 in 5 of his donors, it was the first time they’d given to any Democrat through ActBlue in the entire year.</p> 
<p>Kelly’s strong preexisting brand helped him leverage the attack from Trump into a fundraising bonanza, said Mike Nellis, a democratic digital strategist and founder of the firm Authentic.</p> 
<p>“You can raise a ton of money by just opposing Trump,” Nellis said. “But if you want to elevate yourself into that stratosphere of becoming a household name that people believe in, with Democratic donors who are going to give you $5, $10, $25, over and over and over, you’ve got to go a little bit deeper.”</p> 
<p>Democrats’ dream of flipping the Senate also fueled massive contributions. A handful of Senate candidates — Roy Cooper in North Carolina, Sherrod Brown in Ohio, Janet Mills in Maine and both James Talarico and Jasmine Crockett in Texas — were the top Democratic online fundraisers when they launched their respective campaigns.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/34364" data-person-id="34364">Jon Ossoff</a> (D-Ga.), the only incumbent Democratic senator seeking reelection in a state Trump won in 2024, brought in $32.5 million through ActBlue in 2025, more than any other candidate on the platform. Democrats running in competitive Senate races this year were consistently among the top overall fundraisers on ActBlue, as was the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee itself.</p> 
<p>The online fundraising landscape for Democrats looking to take back the House was more muddled, with the top fundraising numbers coming more often from progressive stars than candidates in competitive races.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/304452" data-person-id="304452">Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez</a> (D-N.Y.), long a fundraising powerhouse, raised $22.8 million on ActBlue in 2025, the most of any House Democrat, followed by House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>, who raised just shy of $11 million through his campaign and joint fundraising committee, then Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/482861" data-person-id="482861">Eugene Vindman</a> (D-Va.) and Eileen Laubacher, one of the Democrats seeking to challenge Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/356900" data-person-id="356900">Lauren Boebert</a> (R-Colo.) in a heavily Republican district.</p> 
<p>Those House candidates reflect a few of the different ways that virality can help online fundraising. More than 400,000 donors gave to Ocasio-Cortez’s campaign more than once in 2025, reflecting her strength with returning donors. Laubacher’s numbers reflect how running in a district represented by a high-profile Republican can attract Democratic donors — even as she still has to get through a primary to face Boebert.</p> 
<p>But vulnerable Democratic House incumbents and candidates running in some of the most competitive battlegrounds were not represented among those with the best online fundraising numbers — a challenge for party strategists as they fight for the resources to flip the House.</p> 
<p>“The things that work to raise money from small donors are the opposite of the things that work to beat MAGA,” said Liam Kerr, co-founder of the centrist Democratic group WelcomePAC.</p> 
<p>At the same time, Kerr said that there was enough variety in the candidates who put up strong online fundraising numbers to suggest that more moderate candidates can make inroads.</p> 
<p>Donors give, Kerr said, because they want to “feel like they're part of something.” If candidates in key races can start to capture the attention of donors across the country, then, he said, “the base of the raged donor class would start to shift to what they thought could beat Trump.”</p> 
<p><i>Methodology: Donations and monetary totals are based on ActBlue and WinRed receipts, not reports from campaigns. Donations that were later refunded are still included in the totals.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Here's where — and when — a DHS shutdown would cause pain for the public</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/dhs-shutdown-impact-furloughs-00775499</link>
      <description>Immigration and border security agencies wouldn’t be as affected in a funding lapse as other parts of the department.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4ab0-d0f8-adde-fafaec2a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/af/01/f9a850184d2ca3d20c735aedb33f/u-s-congress-37856.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem could find creative ways to lessen the pain of a shutdown.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/af/01/f9a850184d2ca3d20c735aedb33f/u-s-congress-37856.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Maggie Miller</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Maggie Miller</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There’s nothing like the ire of constituents to motivate lawmakers to end a government shutdown. But it could take weeks for the public to start noticing the funding lapse set to hit DHS on Saturday if Congress doesn’t act.</p> 
<p>TSA airport screeners, for instance, wouldn't miss full paychecks until March, and billions of dollars remain in the FEMA coffers used for immediate response to disasters like hurricanes, tornadoes and floods.</p> 
<p>Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem could find creative ways to lessen the pain of a shutdown. That could include bankrolling paychecks for DHS law enforcement personnel and active-duty members of the Coast Guard by tapping money from the tax and spending package Republicans enacted last summer, as the agency did during the shutdown last fall.</p> 
<p>This could decrease pressure on lawmakers to fund DHS amid negotiations over a crackdown on the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement tactics. Congress doesn’t have forever, though, before the pain starts to kick in across the department.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Immigration and border security</h5> 
<p>The Trump administration's immigration and border security operations are at the heart of the partisan dispute that could spark a shutdown. Compared to other parts of the agency, though, the federal government’s three immigration-focused agencies aren’t as affected by funding lapses.</p> 
<p>About 40 percent of funding for Immigration and Customs Enforcement, Customs and Border Protection and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services is untouched by a lapse. That’s because the agencies receive a combination of mandatory funds, revenue from fees and billions of dollars from the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_1" target="_blank">GOP megabill</a> Trump signed into law in 2025.</p> 
<p>Of the three, CBP relies most on the cash Congress provides each year in the regular government funding bills. But the agency received $65 billion from the party-line legislation Republicans cleared last summer, in addition to the $75 billion the law included for ICE.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">TSA</h5> 
<p>When airport security screeners start missing pay, many stop showing up to work, causing TSA lines to grow at hubs throughout the country. In prior shutdowns, that started happening about a month in.</p> 
<p>This time, screeners would begin missing full paychecks in mid-March, likely spurring longer waits during the peak of spring break travel.</p> 
<p>While DHS paid air marshals during the historic government shutdown last fall, that didn’t cover checks for the TSA screeners who keep people and their baggage moving through U.S. airports.</p> 
<p>One factor that could motivate TSA agents to show up to work anyway is the $10,000 bonuses DHS officials gave to screeners who demonstrated “exemplary service” after the funding lapse that ran through October and into November.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">FEMA</h5> 
<p>FEMA has about $7 billion left in its disaster relief fund, a sum likely to buoy the agency for at least a month or two. While most of the agency’s disaster aid work continues during a government shutdown, though, FEMA would have to start restricting its reimbursements to states.</p> 
<p>During past funding lapses, FEMA deemed roughly 85 percent of its 25,000 employees “essential,” meaning they had to continue coming to work without pay, and it continued processing disaster aid applications from individuals.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Coast Guard</h5> 
<p>The Coast Guard’s work alongside the military in missions abroad would continue during a funding lapse. But the service could have to halt some work including family support services and efforts to buy new cutters.</p> 
<p>During the record-setting shutdown late last year, DHS dipped into a $10 billion pot of money from the GOP megabill to pay about 68,000 workers, including some law enforcement personnel and active duty members of the Coast Guard, to the tune of about $1 billion each pay period.</p> 
<p>If DHS shuts down again, department officials could do the same for several months before exhausting the account, which was replenished after the government reopened in mid-November.</p> 
<p>Coast Guard contractors and employees who are not active duty were not paid during the fall shutdown, however. And contractors are not guaranteed back pay, even though all federal employees, whether furloughed or not, are eligible for back pay after a shutdown under a law enacted in the wake of the funding lapse that ended in 2019.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Cybersecurity</h5> 
<p>The Trump administration has previously designated only about a third of federal workers as essential at the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency during a government shutdown.</p> 
<p>That limits the workforce that scans and protects U.S. networks from cyber incursions. It also hinders CISA’s ability to help state and local officials defend against cyber threats and assist other agencies with security patches.</p> 
<p>Even before Congress let any federal funding lapse in recent months, the Trump administration had already considerably downsized the agency. Around a third of its employees were either <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/05/cisa-layoffs-hundreds-deferred-resignation-offers-00346299" target="_blank">laid off</a><a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/05/top-cisa-leaders-to-depart-this-week-as-the-cyber-agency-continues-to-shrink-00371297" target="_blank">or quit</a> over the last year, then dozens were permanently shifted to other DHS agencies during the shutdown that ended in November.</p> 
<h5 class="story-text__heading-medium">Secret Service</h5> 
<p>Most of the Secret Service’s workforce is kept on during a shutdown, sometimes including employees in charge of recruitment, training and communications. But personnel who do jobs in offices like human resources and finance are typically furloughed.</p> 
<p>After Trump was shot at a campaign rally in 2024, the Secret Service significantly elevated the level of security it provides to the more than 40 people the agency is tasked with protecting, among them former presidents. During a government shutdown, the agency is more selective about how it spends money to safeguard those people.</p> 
<p>Like other DHS agencies, the Secret Service also got money from the GOP’s 2025 tax and spending package that can be used during a funding lapse. That included almost $1.2 billion to cover a wide range of expenses such as training facility costs, technology and bonuses.</p> 
<p><i>Thomas Frank, Paroma Soni, Leo Shane III and Andres Picon contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Dems think they have the upper hand at Pam Bondi’s big Hill hearing</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/11/pam-bondi-house-judiciary-tesitmony-00775441</link>
      <description>The attorney general could have to answer for the Trump administration’s handling of immigration enforcement, military action in Venezuela and the Epstein files.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4a9c-d647-addc-ebdfd5b70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0e/ff/a2f449dc487d9d6701f7d71f067d/u-s-congress-88677.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Attorney General Pam Bondi testifies before the Senate Judiciary Committee on Capitol Hill, Oct. 7, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0e/ff/a2f449dc487d9d6701f7d71f067d/u-s-congress-88677.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Attorney General Pam Bondi will testify Wednesday before the House Judiciary Committee amid a barrage of controversies that would ordinarily portend a dicey bipartisan grilling.</p> 
<p>The nation’s top law enforcement officer is being scrutinized for the Justice Department’s handling of the Jeffrey Epstein investigation, with files being released well past the statutory deadline and redactions appearing to defy the law’s requirements.</p> 
<p>Bondi’s department is overseeing the prosecution of former Venezuela President Nicolás Maduro, who was forcibly removed from his country by U.S. troops in an operation that has prompted a flurry of legal questions. Her agency is also being pressured to investigate and bring charges against the federal agents who fatally shot two U.S. citizens in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>“It’s very hard to narrow down all of the lawlessness and gross abuse of power that this Department of Justice has engaged in in just one year,” said Rep. Dan Goldman (D-N.Y.), a member of the committee, in an interview. “She’s been trying to avoid us, but she can't avoid us any longer.”</p> 
<p>But other than Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), who said he plans to pepper Bondi over the Epstein saga, Republicans on the panel don’t appear to be clamoring to challenge Bondi on any of it.</p> 
<p>Asked his priorities for the hearing, House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan in an interview said he wanted to hear about the newly appointed senior DOJ official focused on fraud, the now-defunct investigation into President Donald Trump and “the good work they've done on just regularly prosecuting bad guys.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Glenn Grothman (R-Wis.) said he intends to ask Bondi about efforts to overhaul election law, while Rep. Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.) suggested he would question her about the department’s work to protect what he called “the rights of parents.”</p> 
<p>“It’ll be fun,” Kiley added.</p> 
<p>It’s not unusual for Cabinet officials to confront a hospitable audience when the majority shares the party affiliation of the administration in power, but Democrats think the stack of high-profile dramas encircling Bondi could give them a unique opportunity — namely by drawing out the GOP’s anticipated silence on the hot-button issues and the attorney general’s expected refusal to engage in Democratic questioning.</p> 
<p>“The Department of Justice has been found to be lying by federal courts across the land — they have withheld evidence, they have misled the court, they've shown spectacular disrespect for the rule of law and the integrity of the courts,” said Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, in an interview. “So, I think as little respect as they have for the courts, they probably have less for Congress.”</p> 
<p>But, Raskin said, Democrats plan “to engage in some exchanges that will spotlight some of the worst depredations of the Trump Justice Department, and we hope the mobilization of public opinion will allow us to make some progress in some areas.”</p> 
<p>He told reporters that Democrats will ask about the DOJ’s process for releasing the Epstein files that “produced such flawed results” in its production of the materials.</p> 
<p>Democrats also say they’re ready for Bondi to deflect member questions by personally attacking lawmakers.</p> 
<p>When she appeared before the Senate Judiciary Committee in October, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/07/congress/bondi-goes-after-schiff-00596375" target="_blank">she told Sen. Adam Schiff (D-Calif.)</a> to “apologize” for trying to impeach Trump and accused Sen. Dick Durbin of being unwilling “<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/07/congress/pam-bondi-spars-with-dick-durbin-00596234" target="_blank">to protect your citizens</a>” when the Illinois Democrat asked about National Guard deployment to his state.</p> 
<p>She also punted a question on Epstein back to Sen. Sheldon Whitehouse (D-R.I.) over campaign donations of which there is no record with the Federal Election Commission, then levied a bizarre charge that he had pushed legislation that would subsidize his wife’s company.</p> 
<p>“We've all noticed that at prior hearings, when she's afraid to answer a question, she attacks the members of Congress,” Rep. Ted Lieu of California, a member of House Democratic leadership who also sits on the Judiciary Committee, said in an interview. “So if she starts doing that, you know she's afraid to answer a question, and she's engaged in a cover-up, so the American people will be able to see what she does on Wednesday.”</p> 
<p>Bondi could go after Rep. Eric Swalwell (D-Calif.), a longtime vocal foe of the Trump administration who is now running for governor and has drawn past scrutiny for an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/12/10/pelosi-swalwell-chinese-spy-444308" target="_blank">alleged connection</a> to a suspected Chinese spy. House Republicans removed him from the Intelligence Committee, but the Ethics Committee abandoned its investigation into the matter in 2023.</p> 
<p>It’s possible Republicans on the House Judiciary Committee offer veiled criticism of the Justice Department’s immigration policies following the violent confrontations in Minnesota. House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino (R-N.Y.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/ice-todd-lyons-dhs-funding-hearing-00774309" target="_blank">said at a hearing</a> with some of the Trump administration’s top immigration officials Tuesday that “when officials or elected leaders rush to conclusions about law enforcement or their fellow Americans, public trust suffers.”</p> 
<p>But most of the Republicans who sit on the House Judiciary dais are staunch Trump loyalists unlikely to be out of lockstep with Bondi. Massie, who Trump is now trying to primary out of office after multiple defections, could be the sole exception.</p> 
<p>“It probably wouldn’t surprise you or her that it’s probably going to be Epstein-focused,” Massie said of his plans for questioning Bondi. But he wouldn’t offer any previews: “I don’t want her to know.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filibuster fight comes full circle as GOP faces internal pressure on elections bill</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/10/senate-filibuster-gop-save-act-00775393</link>
      <description>Sen. Mike Lee and other hard-liners want to pursue the “talking filibuster.” Their colleagues are skeptical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-4a38-d0f8-adde-fa7a441b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 20:30:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/54/c1/b62b6dd54b68830aea65790b522e/u-s-congress-31702.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Mike Lee (R-Utah) has been at the front of the push for the SAVE America Act.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/54/c1/b62b6dd54b68830aea65790b522e/u-s-congress-31702.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Republicans are facing a full-circle moment on the filibuster.</p> 
<p>Four years ago, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/01/19/democrats-senate-rules-change-527366" target="_blank">GOP stood united</a> against a failed attempt by Democrats to sidestep the chamber’s 60-vote supermajority requirement and pass a voting-rights bill demanded by their party base. Now — with their own trifecta and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/06/house-save-act-vote-filibuster-00768499?can_id=71597c61003cabad9b09c8444aa14487&amp;email_referrer=email_3092311&amp;email_subject=bumping-this-sign-and-send-a-letter-to-your-members-of-congress-opposing-the-save-act-which-would-impose-significant-new-documentation-requirements-when-registering-to-vote&amp;link_id=1&amp;source=email-sign-and-send-a-letter-to-your-members-of-congress-opposing-the-save-act-which-would-impose-significant-new-documentation-requirements-when-registering-to-vote" target="_blank">their own elections bill</a> at issue — Republicans are under pressure to do much the same.</p> 
<p>The shoe-on-the-other-foot moment is being fueled by a cadre of hard-right senators arguing forcefully for tactics once embraced by Senate progressives. Many Democrats, meanwhile, are keeping silent and watching as the GOP undergoes similar internal turmoil to what they had experienced in the majority.</p> 
<p>Only a few, like Sen. Lisa Murkowski (R-Alaska), have acknowledged the irony of the moment — noting in a statement Tuesday that the push for the <a href="https://x.com/lisamurkowski/status/2021245420303782254?s=20" target="_blank">GOP elections bill</a> looks a lot like what Democrats had previously attempted.</p> 
<p>“Once again, I do not support these efforts,” she said in a statement. “Ensuring public trust in our elections is at the core of our democracy, but federal overreach is not how we achieve this.”</p> 
<p>But the dial on the intraparty pressure cooker is set to ratchet up Wednesday, when House Republicans are expected to pass the SAVE America Act and send it to the Senate. Backed by an Elon Musk-driven public pressure campaign, the conservative hard-liners are working overtime to bend their GOP colleagues toward allowing a “talking filibuster” — a strategy they believe will ultimately allow the Senate to act on a simple-majority basis.</p> 
<p>Much as Democrats said their voting-rights legislation dealt with existential issues of democracy that necessitated an exception to the filibuster, GOP Sen. Mike Lee of Utah and his allies argue SAVE America is essential to securing elections — including the upcoming midterms — from a purported surge of noncitizen voting.</p> 
<p>The bill would mandate voters present proof of citizenship, such as a passport or birth certificate, to register and would require photo ID to vote in every state, among other changes, and has garnered strong backing from President Donald Trump. The push to make Democrats hold the floor indefinitely if they want to block it has picked up support from many of Trump’s GOP allies in the Senate.</p> 
<p>“I’m a fan of the talking filibuster … especially as Democrats have proven more and more obstructionist,” Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said.</p> 
<p>Sen. Ted Cruz (R-Texas) said forcing a talking filibuster is “exactly what we should do” and that he’s “making the case vigorously” for it.</p> 
<p>But many other Senate Republicans are wary of any step that further waters down the 60-vote margin after both parties have already diluted it over the past decade. Once a majority makes an exception for one bill, Republicans argue it will effectively mark the beginning of the end for the legislative filibuster — something many of them see as a bulwark against big-government Democratic policies, not an obstacle to GOP priorities.</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) said he was not eager to rejoin a battle that has resulted in party-line confirmations of presidential nominees after a series of partisan escalations involving the so-called “nuclear option.”</p> 
<p>Tillis said he did not see a substantial difference between those sorts of rules changes and instead by trying to force Democrats into a talking filibuster, which GOP proponents suggest would not require going nuclear. Both, he said, have the “same fundamental message.”</p> 
<p>Lee has been urging his legion of X followers to reach out to his GOP colleagues, seeking to build public pressure on them to support the voting bill even if it means throwing them into a filibuster fight they don’t want.</p> 
<p>He also gave a presentation on his talking filibuster proposal during a closed-door GOP lunch Tuesday, and the topic is expected to come up again Wednesday when Senate Republicans hold a private retreat on Capitol Hill.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, a band of ultraconservatives in the House, led by Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), is trying to focus pressure on Senate Majority Leader John Thune. Luna told reporters last week that she had received “assurances” that the Senate would allow a talking filibuster for the voting bill — something Thune denied.</p> 
<p>The multifront push has sparked frustration among Senate Republicans, according to two people granted anonymity to speak candidly, who warned that trying to put words in Thune and other GOP senators' mouths was only undermining her cause.</p> 
<p>A GOP senator who granted anonymity to disclose private discussions said that while Lee gave a good presentation during Tuesday’s lunch, “a lot of people in the room are sick of Mike Lee fundraising off of it.”</p> 
<p>“It’s a political spectacle,” the senator added. “It’s never going to happen. It doesn’t work.”</p> 
<p>Republican senators have raised concerns that pursuing a talking filibuster strategy would require either eating up potentially weeks of floor time with no guarantee of success or pursuing strategies that would require procedural votes that would essentially require 50 GOP lawmakers to sidestep recent Senate precedent — a hurdle they wouldn’t be able to clear.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Lee did not respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>Republicans have been privately circulating op-eds <a href="https://www.nationalreview.com/bench-memos/the-talking-filibuster-quagmire/" target="_blank">detailing the procedural headaches</a> they could invite upon themselves if they backed Lee’s idea. And they’ve warned that opening up the floor to unlimited amendments could set the stage for Democrats to hijack any bill and turn it into a health care bill or tariff bill or any other proposal they could get a majority to support.</p> 
<p>Many GOP senators aside from Tillis, who is retiring, are starting to speak out against the idea — including Sen. John Curtis of Utah, <a href="https://x.com/SenJohnCurtis/status/2019088376066957731?s=20" target="_blank">who said that</a> “for those concerned in the House, I also oppose skirting around the filibuster.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Kevin Cramer of North Dakota predicted that it wouldn’t go anywhere and summed up his own position as “not interested.”</p> 
<p>One Democrat who has closely studied the issue, Sen. Jeff Merkley of Oregon, said he relished the idea of a “talking filibuster.” During the Biden-era debates over voting legislation, he put forward a <a href="https://www.merkley.senate.gov/jeff-merkley-circulates-talking-filibuster-reform-proposal/" target="_blank">proposal of his own</a> — albeit with rules changes that would ultimately allow debate to end.</p> 
<p>“If they’re operating within the existing rules and looking to have an extended debate where they maintain a quorum and go day and night … I say thumbs up,” Merkley said.</p> 
<p>Thune has vowed to put the SAVE America Act up for a Senate vote at some point after it comes over from the House, and he said he was open to discussions about getting it passed. But he reiterated Tuesday that changing the 60-vote filibuster through a party-line vote is an idea “that doesn’t have a future.”</p> 
<p>Asked later if he knew how a “talking filibuster” could work without a prolonged floor battle — something the South Dakota Republican warned could derail other GOP priorities — Thune started laughing.</p> 
<p>“No, I don’t,” Thune said. “It takes you back over 100 years. So, unlimited debate and unlimited amendments. … Nobody knows.”</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor and Leo Shane III contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-11T21:48:40-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Dan Osborn cancels fundraiser after co-host’s Epstein link surfaces</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/10/congress/dan-osborn-dana-chasin-fundraiser-00775138</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-49c6-d3b5-addf-e9c666030000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 18:04:52 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Daniel Lippman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Daniel Lippman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nebraska Senate candidate Dan Osborn abruptly canceled a <a href="https://www.politico.com/osborn_invite" target="_blank">Tuesday fundraiser</a> that was set to be co-hosted by a Democratic operative who was mentioned in the recently released Jeffrey Epstein files as allegedly transporting young girls for the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>Dana Chasin — a Rockefeller heir who advised Hillary Clinton’s 2016 presidential campaign as well as former Sens. Tim Johnson (D-S.D.) and Jon Tester (D-Mont.) — was listed on an invitation for the Washington event benefiting Osborn, who is running against GOP Sen. Pete Ricketts as an independent.</p> 
<p>His name <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2012/EFTA02731721.pdf" target="_blank">appears in a March 2024 email</a> sent to a Justice Department attorney by Jeanne Christensen, a lawyer representing a young unnamed woman who alleged Chasin flew her on a private plane to Epstein’s Manhattan townhouse for sex with powerful men. The email, which details allegations of sexual abuse, also mentions a second flight with Chasin but does not make a direct accusation against him.</p> 
<p>In a statement sent Wednesday, after publication, Chasin said that “nothing pertaining to me in the March 2024 email” was true.</p> 
<p>He said he had never met Epstein, Ghislaine Maxwell or other prominent men mentioned in the emails or had any relationship with them.</p> 
<p>“Furthermore, I have never owned or rented a prop plane, or any plane for that matter,” he said in an email. “I stand with the victims of Jeffrey Epstein and their pursuit of justice and accountability.”</p> 
<p>Christensen did not respond to an email seeking comment. A spokesperson for her firm, Wigdor, declined to comment.</p> 
<p>POLITICO asked the Osborn campaign Tuesday afternoon whether it was aware of Chasin’s name surfacing in the files. “This event has been cancelled,” a spokesperson replied.</p> 
<p>“Anyone who hurt kids or engaged in other illegal activity needs to be arrested and prosecuted,” the statement continued. The spokesperson did not respond to a question about what vetting had been done of the co-hosts in advance of the event.</p> 
<p>Chasin has donated more than $2 million to Democrats since the 1990s, <a href="https://www.fec.gov/data/receipts/individual-contributions/?contributor_name=chasin+dana&amp;max_date=12%2F31%2F2026" target="_blank">according to federal records</a>. An invitation to the fundraiser listed tickets from $250 to $3,500.</p> 
<p>Chasin donated $3,300 to Osborn’s 2024 failed Senate campaign, the records indicate. The campaign said in an email “a donation has already been made by the Osborn campaign to a nonprofit organization in Nebraska whose mission is to end child abuse and trafficking that is the equivalent to the amount donated by this individual.”</p> 
<p>In recent weeks, Osborn has made numerous posts on X calling for justice to be served for Epstein’s victims.</p> 
<p>“There is a small, powerful group of ELITES who think they can do anything they want on this earth,” he <a href="https://x.com/osbornforne/status/2020873083704230393?s=20" target="_blank">posted Monday</a>. “They think they are deserving. They think they are exceptional.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
