<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 21:20:24 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Thune denies Johnson’s demand for Epstein bill changes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/johnson-thune-epstein-files-gop-00658475</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-99de-df0f-abfa-f9fef55a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 21:20:24 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said he voted for the Jeffrey Epstein disclosure bill Tuesday based on his hope that the Senate would make changes he’s been demanding. Senate Majority Leader John Thune shot that down.</p> 
<p>Thune said Tuesday evening that, while he had talked with the speaker about the bill, he and Senate GOP legal counsel decided the legislation was “sufficient.” The Senate effectively <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764" target="_blank">approved the legislation</a> by unanimous consent mere hours after House passage Tuesday afternoon without provisions sought by Johnson, including additional victim and whistleblower name protections.</p> 
<p>"I talked with the speaker a bit, and we've been in consultation obviously with the White House on this for some time,” Thune told reporters. “The conclusion was when it came out of the House 427-1 that, you know, it was going to pass in the Senate.”</p> 
<p>Thune’s refusal to amend the bill was just the latest setback Johnson has faced in the Epstein saga, where the Louisiana Republican saw a rank-and-file member of his own party, Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), pull off a stunning legislative end-run despite the speaker’s months-long opposition campaign.</p> 
<p>Johnson said after House passage Tuesday that he would “insist upon” changes.</p> 
<p>“I talked to John Thune over the weekend. I just texted him. We’re going to get together. We’ll talk about this,” Johnson told reporters as he left the floor. “There’s an easy way to amend the legislation to make sure that we don’t do permanent damage to the justice system. And I’m going to insist upon that.”</p> 
<p>Asked if he would press Trump to veto the bill if the Senate didn’t amend it, Johnson said he would “cross that bridge” if necessary. He also raised “national security” concerns about the bill Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Thune said Senate Republican lawyers examined the legislation and determined it could go forward without being amended.</p> 
<p>“Our lawyers obviously had looked closely at some of the issues and had concluded that the bill I think was, you know, sufficient to accomplish what needed to be done here, and that is to get the information out there as quickly as possible,” Thune said.</p> 
<p>Earlier this week, Johnson told reporters he had received “some comfort” from the Senate that the chamber would make the changes. But Thune never publicly indicated he expected the Senate to revise the bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/senate-pass-epstein-thune-00657429" target="_blank">and even warned earlier Tuesday</a> that changes were unlikely.</p> 
<p>The only short-lived whiff of resistance that appeared in the Senate Tuesday came from Sen. Markwayne Mullin (R-Okla.), who appeared to raise concerns at the last minute but did not block the effort.</p> 
<p>“We were trying to see if we needed to change language to protect the victims,” Mullin said to reporters.</p> 
<p>Shortly before Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer sought unanimous consent to greenlight the bill, Mullin said that there had been a “conversation” with the administration about what the Oklahoma Republican characterized as “technical changes,” which ultimately didn't get made.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plaskett narrowly escapes censure over her Epstein texts</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-escapes-censure-vote-epstein-texts-00658334</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9993-d51c-a39e-bd9b8c1a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 21:11:09 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House voted 209-214 Tuesday night against formally reprimanding Del. Stacey Plaskett for communicating with the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein during a 2019 Oversight Committee hearing.</p> 
<p>Three House Republicans — Reps. Don Bacon of Nebraska, Lance Gooden of Texas and Dave Joyce of Ohio — voted with all Democrats against the measure. Three Republicans voted present: Reps. Andrew Garbarino of New York, Dan Meuser of Pennsylvania and Jay Obernolte of California.</p> 
<p>Plaskett drew scrutiny after documents released from the Epstein estate revealed her texts with him. She’s denied wrongdoing, saying on the House floor Tuesday that Epstein was a constituent, that her contact was limited to information-gathering and that it was not public information at the time that Epstein had been under federal investigation.</p> 
<p>“I know how to question individuals. I know how to seek information. I have sought information from confidential informants, from murderers, from other individuals because I want the truth,” she said on the House floor.</p> 
<p>Republicans contend Plaskett’s contact with Epstein was more substantive and shaped her questioning during the hearing, which Plaskett denies.</p> 
<p>“Standing against a convicted predator's influence in our proceedings is not partisan. It's basic decency,” said Rep. Ralph Norman (R-S.C.), who brought the measure to the House floor through a fast-track process bypassing committees and Hill leadership.</p> 
<p>But the measure rejected Tuesday by the House would have also removed Plaskett from the House Intelligence Committee, a step too far for some lawmakers. She would have been the latest House Democrats to be removed from a committee position by Hill Republicans after Republicans voted last Congress to remove Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) from the House Foreign Affairs Committee for her past comments on Israel.</p> 
<p>The failed vote to reprimand Plaskett comes on the same day the House voted almost unanimously to force the Department of Justice to release more files about its case against Epstein. The controversy has roiled Congress and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/mtg-speaks-on-epstein-00656279" target="_blank">split the MAGA base</a> for months.</p> 
<p>In retaliation for the move against Plaskett, Democrats introduced a measure to censure Rep. Cory Mills (R-Fla.) and to remove him from the House Armed Services Committee. He’s faced a spate of ethical issues including an since-withdrawn allegation of assault and an ongoing legal dispute over a previous relationship. But that measure is likely to be withdrawn now that the Plaskett effort has failed.</p> 
<p>The failure of the Plaskett measure prompted an outcry from conservative Republicans who had pushed for it, with some accusing leaders of cutting deals to avoid a vote on the Mills resolution. </p> 
<p>"They’re brokering back end deals to avoid bringing forward justice in both Democrat and Republican chambers," said Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.). "So it’s literally covering up public corruption."</p> 
<p><i>Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senators rage against phone data payout measure won by Thune</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/thune-phone-records-payout-jack-smith-00658393</link>
      <description>Senate Republicans are expected to debate the issue during their weekly lunch Wednesday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-99b2-df0f-abfa-f9fa01b20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 20:20:02 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9a/ba/4fdf4fe6447cabc97f629bdde98f/u-s-congress-54663.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) speaks with reporters outside his office at the U.S. Capitol during a vote series on a continuing resolution to end a government shutdown on the 41st day of the shutdown, Nov. 10, 2025. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9a/ba/4fdf4fe6447cabc97f629bdde98f/u-s-congress-54663.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House plans to vote Wednesday to repeal a provision that could award eight GOP senators hundreds of thousands of dollars for having their phone records seized without their knowledge during a Biden-era probe. Senate Majority Leader John Thune, who secured the measure, is standing his ground.</p> 
<p>"The House is going to do what they are going to do with it,” he told reporters Tuesday night. “It doesn't apply to them.”</p> 
<p>But many senators from both parties are eager to roll back the legislative language they didn’t know <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/john-thune-government-funding-phone-records-seizure-00646094" target="_blank">Thune secretly negotiated</a>with Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer in the government funding package that ended the longest shutdown in history last week. Republicans could revolt if leadership doesn’t give them a vote to overturn it.</p> 
<p>In interviews Tuesday with nearly a dozen lawmakers, confusion, frustration and anger ran rampant about what has quickly become branded as a politically toxic, taxpayer-funded windfall for a select few. Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) went so far as to quip there could be “some stabbings” at the Senate GOP’s weekly lunch Wednesday when the topic will inevitably get discussed.</p> 
<p>“Whoever put this in had an obligation to tell us about it, and they didn’t,” said Kennedy. “There's something called trust and good faith around here.”</p> 
<p>Even Schumer conceded the widely unpopular language should ultimately be scrapped.</p> 
<p>“The bottom line is, Thune wanted the provision and we wanted to make sure that at least Democratic senators were protected from [Attorney General Pam] Bondi and others who might go after them,” he said Tuesday. “But I'd be for repealing all of it and I hope that happens,” he told reporters.</p> 
<p>It’s not clear whether it’s too late to reverse course in the Senate.</p> 
<p>The provision at issue, which President Donald Trump signed into law last week, would award senators $500,000 or more if they discover their electronic records were seized without notification.</p> 
<p>In seeking to attach it to the funding bill, Thune was directly responding to furor from several Senate Republicans eager for retribution against former special counsel Jack Smith, who obtained the phone records for at least eight Republican senators during his investigation into Trump’s efforts to overturn the results of the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>Thune in an interview acknowledged that members would indeed discuss the issue at lunch Wednesday but reiterated that he personally was not having second thoughts about including the measure in the funding deal.</p> 
<p>“It’s designed to protect United States senators,” Thune said. “We have a number of people who are interested in making sure that that sort of thing has a consequence if that kind of weaponization of the government along the lines of what Jack Smith did is ever employed again in the future.”</p> 
<p>Senate Commerce Chair Ted Cruz (R-Texas), who claims he was targeted by the Smith probe, praised Thune for including the language. Senate Budget Chair Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.), who is confirmed to have had his records subpoenaed during the Smith investigation, has said he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/senate-republicans-phones-sue-jack-smith-00651463" target="_blank">plans to take advantage</a> of the provision to make it “so painful” for those involved.</p> 
<p>Some Senate Republicans admitted they hope the language is preserved. Sen. Eric Schmitt (R-Mo.) said he wanted the provision expanded to let a broader range of parties sue to show “how corrupt Jack Smith is.”</p> 
<p>It’s far from certain disgruntled lawmakers would make it easy for Thune to move a standalone bill to revoke the provision, even if he decides he wants to — they could insist on controversial amendments or make the voting process drawn-out and disruptive. Nor is it clear Republicans would allow the provision to be stripped in a subsequent government funding bill.</p> 
<p>There's far less hand-wringing in the House, where members were criticizing the language before they even voted on the Senate-passed funding bill last Thursday.</p> 
<p>The House Wednesday evening is expected to easily pass a bill to repeal the payout provision with support from Speaker Mike Johnson and House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan, who is working to get Smith to sit for a transcribed interview before his committee.</p> 
<p>In the Senate, several lawmakers signaled Tuesday night they were anxious to distance themselves from the new policy and wanted to follow the House’s lead.</p> 
<p>"I’m going to support repealing it,” said Sen. Markwayne Mullin (R-Okla.), the chair of the legislative branch appropriations subcommittee.</p> 
<p>He added he was not alerted about the language until after he already voted for the funding package last week and that he later received an “apologetic” call from GOP leadership over how the matter was handled. Thune confirmed that he had spoken to Mullin and that the Oklahoma Republican was not aware of the provision’s drafting.</p> 
<p>Sen. Susan Collins (R-Maine), chair of the Senate Appropriations Committee, said she was likewise in the dark in advance of the vote.</p> 
<p>“That was something that the leaders put into the bill, and I played no role in that whatsoever,” she told reporters.</p> 
<p>Democrats made clear they would continue to pummel Republicans if Thune failed to take action.</p> 
<p>Sen. Martin Heinrich (D-N.M.), the ranking member on the legislative branch appropriations subcommittee, said he was “furious” with leadership and has since introduced a bill to pare back the provision.</p> 
<p>Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.), another senior appropriator, said in an interview his party was “going to make every effort to try to reverse that pretty serious mistake.”</p> 
<p>“I guess there's an argument that it offers some future protection, but that's not what the provision is about,” he said. “The provision is about a cash payout to Republican senators, plain and simple.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House demands Epstein financial records from JPMorgan Chase, Deutsche Bank and US Virgin Islands</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/comer-subpoenas-epsteins-financial-records-00657935</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9911-d51c-a39e-bd1963ef0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:40:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Republicans are pushing ahead with an investigation into the activities of Jeffrey Epstein — even as legislation forcing the release of all Department of Justice files on the late sex offender appears to be heading to President Donald Trump for a signature.</p> 
<p>The House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform issued a series of subpoenas Tuesday for some of Epstein's financial records. </p> 
<p>Rep. James Comer (R-Ky.), chairman of the committee, issued subpoenas to J.P. Morgan Chase and Deutsche Bank and requested additional documents from U.S. Virgin Islands Attorney General Gordon Rhea.</p> 
<p>According to the subpoenas, JPMorgan Chase began an internal investigation into accounts previously held by Epstein, flagging some 4,700 transactions as “suspicious” in the process. Epstein also held accounts at and banked with Deutsche Bank from 2013 until potentially late 2018, the subpoenas state.</p> 
<p>The letter to Rhea comes after documents released last week reveal that Del. Stacey Plaskett <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2025/11/14/epstein-text-messages-cohen-house-hearing/" target="_blank">consulted with Epstein</a>during a 2019 hearing with Trump’s personal lawyer Michael Cohen. Epstein previously owned the islands of Little St. James and Great St. James. The House on Tuesday <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-house-censure-vote-epstein-00657247" target="_blank">will vote to censure Plaskett</a> and remove her from the House Intelligence Committee. </p> 
<p>“The records sought by this subpoena will assist in the Committee’s oversight of the federal government’s enforcement of sex trafficking laws generally and specifically its handling of the investigation and prosecution of Mr. Jeffrey Epstein and Ms. Ghislaine Maxwell,” the subpoenas to the banks read.</p> 
<p>The subpoenas were announced just after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764" target="_blank">the House and Senate voted overwhelmingly</a> to force the Justice Department to release more information about the case it built against Epstein. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Utah congressional map puts Republicans in a bind</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/utah-congressional-map-republicans-00657879</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-98fc-df0f-abfa-f9fef3990000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:06:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The new Utah congressional map, which creates a safe-blue district, will force the four current Republican members of the delegation to compete for three GOP seats.</p> 
<p>The four Republicans have discussed possible configurations, though no final decision has been made, according to two people aware of the conversations who were granted anonymity to discuss the dynamic. The congresspeople have publicly said they will make no decision until the map is finalized, anticipating potential legal appeals.</p> 
<p>“We're still waiting to see if there might be one other change,” said Rep. Burgess Owens (R-Utah). “In the meanwhile, we’re not going to speculate.”</p> 
<p>Leaders of the Republican-controlled Utah legislature vowed to appeal after a district judge tossed out the GOP-leaning map the legislature drew and selected a plaintiff’s map on November 10. But over a week has passed without lawmakers filing the appeal. Utah House Speaker Mike Schultz <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tCejuZn1uzg" target="_blank">told a local TV station</a> the deadline to appeal the 2026 map “has come and gone.”</p> 
<p>"We don't know what's going to happen for 2026,” Schultz said. “We're hoping for some miracle to come in and say, ‘No, this isn't right.’”</p> 
<p>If the map holds, many expect Owens, who has served since 2021, to retire, leaving Rep. Blake Moore (R-Utah) in the northern Utah district and Reps. Celeste Maloy and Mike Kennedy to split the other two.</p> 
<p>“The thing we're good at in politics in Utah that a lot of other states struggle with, is talking to each other and working together and figuring out what's best for the state,” Maloy said. “We're still in the process of doing that, but I'm confident we can figure it out.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clay Higgins explains why he was the lone ’no’ vote on Epstein files release</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/clay-higgins-no-vote-epstein-00657430</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-98b4-df0f-abfa-f9fe675c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:02:59 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Clay Higgins (R-La.), the lone "no" vote on the near-unanimous House legislation to force a release of the Justice Department’s files on the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, said on Tuesday that he opposed it on privacy grounds.</p> 
<p>“It abandons 250 years of criminal justice procedure in America,” <a href="https://x.com/RepClayHiggins/status/1990868089056219267" target="_blank">Higgins wrote</a> on X. “As written, this bill reveals and injures thousands of innocent people — witnesses, people who provided alibis, family members, etc. If enacted in its current form, this type of broad reveal of criminal investigative files, released to a rabid media, will absolutely result in innocent people being hurt.”</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764" target="_blank">Four hundred and twenty-seven House lawmakers</a> — including 216 Republicans — voted in favor of the legislation on Tuesday, two days after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank">President Donald Trump urged his party to support it on Truth Social</a>.</p> 
<p>The White House had spent months lobbying against the effort.</p> 
<p>Higgins, a staunch supporter of the president, nevertheless voted against it. But this isn’t his final word on the matter, he said.</p> 
<p>“If the Senate amends the bill to properly address privacy of victims and other Americans, who are named but not criminally implicated, then I will vote for that bill when it comes back to the House,” he said.</p> 
<p>The Senate could soon clear the bill. Majority Leader John Thune told reporters that the chamber could potentially pass it by unanimous consent <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/senate-pass-epstein-thune-00657429" target="_blank">as soon as later Tuesday</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate may pass Epstein bill today</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/senate-pass-epstein-thune-00657429</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-98b3-d739-a3ba-dcffc4aa0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 15:44:01 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>For the latest</b>, read <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764" target="_blank"><i>Senate approves Epstein files bill, sending it to Trump’s desk</i></a>.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said he expects the Senate will pass the bill to release DOJ files on the late sex offender Jeffrey Epstein as soon as Tuesday, a move that would send it to President Donald Trump for his signature.</p> 
<p>Thune told reporters the Senate could possibly pass it by unanimous consent, a maneuver that requires agreement from all 100 senators. The House <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764" target="_blank">passed it</a> 427-1 with only Rep. Clay Higgins (R-La.) voting in opposition. </p> 
<p>“My assumption is the president sounds like he’s prepared to sign it," Thune said. "So I’d assume it would move fairly quickly over here."</p> 
<p>Senate leadership on Tuesday afternoon began checking the temperature of its members to see if anyone would object.</p> 
<p>The possibility of quick action in the Senate is a shift from just last week when it was expected that the chamber would bury the Epstein bill. But Trump’s insistence that Republicans should pass it, and that he would be willing to sign it, has changed the dynamic within the Senate GOP conference.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson has called on the Senate to add more privacy protections for victims and whistleblowers. But Thune, pointing to the overwhelming vote total in the House, predicted that was “not likely” to happen.</p> 
<p>Democrats have signaled they would oppose any efforts to change the bill. </p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer added that once the House bill gets to the Senate he will try to set up a vote on the bill, which would force Republicans to go on the record instead of letting it pass without a formal vote.</p> 
<p>“We have an opportunity to get this bill done today and have it on the president’s desk to be signed into law tonight. We should seize that opportunity," Schumer said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-18T16:07:23-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House set to vote on Plaskett censure measure</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/stacey-plaskett-house-censure-vote-epstein-00657247</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9871-d51c-a39e-bd79e4bb0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 15:37:11 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House is set to vote Tuesday evening on a measure censuring Democratic Del. Stacey Plaskett for being in contact with the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein. Lawmakers sank a Democratic-led effort to send the measure to the House Ethics Committee by a nearly party-line 214-213 vote. Two Republican lawmakers, Reps. Lance Gooden of Texas and Dave Joyce of Ohio, voted with all Democrats to have the Ethics panel take up the resolution instead. </p> 
<p>Republican Rep. Ralph Norman of South Carolina brought up the measure through a fast-track process bypassing Hill leadership and committees. It would deliver a formal rebuke of Plaskett and remove her from the House Intelligence Committee. </p> 
<p>If the measure is adopted tonight, Plaskett would be the latest House Democrat to be removed from her committee role. Republicans voted last Congress to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/02/02/house-gop-ilhan-omar-00080771" target="_blank">remove</a><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/02/02/house-gop-ilhan-omar-00080771" target="_blank">Rep. Ilhan Omar</a> (D-Minn.) from the House Foreign Affairs Committee for her past comments about Israel. </p> 
<p>Documents released from Epstein’s estate showed the nonvoting delegate from the U.S. Virgin Islands <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2025/11/14/epstein-text-messages-cohen-house-hearing/" target="_blank">texting</a><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2025/11/14/epstein-text-messages-cohen-house-hearing/" target="_blank">with Epstein</a> during a congressional hearing in 2019. </p> 
<p>Tuesday’s votes come on the same day the House <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764" target="_blank">voted nearly unanimously</a> to force the Justice Department to release more information about its case against Epstein. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House votes to rebuke García for election maneuvers</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/house-rebukes-garcia-00657309</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9893-d51c-a39e-bd9bdf400000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 15:22:15 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House voted to rebuke Rep. Chuy García of Illinois for announcing his retirement after the filing deadline — a maneuver that has positioned his chief of staff to be elected his successor in a reliably blue district in the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>The 236-183 vote on the symbolic resolution of disapproval divided Democrats, with 23 members of the minority party ultimately voting with all Republicans to reprimand one of their own.</p> 
<p>Four lawmakers voted “present:” Democratic Reps. Chrissy Houlahan of Pennsylvania, Marcy Kaptur of Ohio and Suhas Subramanyam of Virginia, alongside Republican Rep. Warren Davidson of Ohio.</p> 
<p>Democrats have been hand-wringing over the matter since last week, when Rep. Marie Gluesenkamp Perez introduced the nonbinding resolution against García through a fast-track process that allowed her to bypass leadership — and catch her colleagues off guard.</p> 
<p>Gluesenkamp Perez of Washington is a purple-district moderate who frequently bucks the rest of her party, but her antagonism of García was seen as going a bridge too far by many Democrats who have been trying to project unity coming out of the longest-ever government shutdown.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders whipped against the resolution and urged members to vote against it in their closed-door caucus meeting Tuesday morning. Gluesenkamp Perez attended the meeting but didn’t speak up when leaders spoke against her effort, according to four people granted anonymity to describe the sensitive situation.</p> 
<p>“We disagree with the resolution that’s being offered and we should be talking about issues that affect the American people,” said Rep. Pete Aguilar of California, the third-ranking House Democrat.</p> 
<p>Some Democrats defended García, who has denied accusations of wrongdoing and said his decision to retire <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/03/congress/jesus-chuy-garcia-retirement-watch-00634349" target="_blank"><u>earlier this month</u></a> was based on his personal health and the needs of his family.</p> 
<p>But many others said they had a hard time explaining away the fact that García’s chief of staff, Patty Garcia, filed her papers with Illinois election officials days before her boss announced his decision to retire — timing that appeared designed to clear the primary field.</p> 
<p>Democrats who voted for the disapproval resolution, though, underscored it wasn’t personal. Gluesenkamp Perez also said Monday night she had nothing against García, but “you cannot win the right to represent people through subversion.”</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders unsuccessfully tried Monday evening to kill the measure altogether, but Gluesenkamp Perez and Rep. Jared Golden (D-Maine) sided with all Republicans against doing so, forcing a final vote on the matter Tuesday afternoon.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report included an incorrect vote tally.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-18T17:35:22-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Senate approves Epstein files bill, sending it to Trump’s desk</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-approves-epstein-files-bill-in-near-unanimous-vote-00656764</link>
      <description>The legislation cleared the Senate by unanimous consent, with no debate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9846-df0f-abfa-f96e7dea0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 14:44:43 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/db/14/e9eb351e4441abd0a60b0390a259/u-s-congress-09710.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Reps. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.), and Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) stand alongside Epstein victims during a news conference Tuesday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/db/14/e9eb351e4441abd0a60b0390a259/u-s-congress-09710.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Hailey Fuchs and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Hailey Fuchs and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate moved swiftly to approve legislation Tuesday forcing the Justice Department to release more information about the case it built against the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein — acting hours after an overwhelming House vote to send the bill to the desk of President Donald Trump, who spent months trying to kill it.</p> 
<p>The Senate acted by unanimous consent, which requires signoff from every senator but does not require them to take a roll call vote. Earlier in the day, the House passed the bill on a 427-1 vote.</p> 
<p>“This is about giving the American people the transparency they've been crying for,” Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said before asking for the bill’s approval. “Jeffrey Epstein's victims have waited long enough.”</p> 
<p>Tuesday’s votes caps off a months of drama among congressional Republicans and the White House over how to handle the Epstein files, pitting GOP lawmakers between Trump and their own base.</p> 
<p>That included a long campaign to circumvent House Republican leaders and White House officials who fought tooth and nail to convince members of their party to oppose the measure. As Democrats sought to stoke division in the GOP over the administration’s decision to withhold further information in the Epstein case, the issue proved increasingly toxic for Republicans — and Tuesday’s vote<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank">became inevitable</a>.</p> 
<p>“We have a chance today to make something happen, something that has not happened and should have happened decades ago, and that is to get justice for these victims and survivors and transparency for America,” said Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), who led the effort to force a House vote, later adding that he was “embarrassed for my own party today.”</p> 
<p>Only Rep. Clay Higgins (R-La.), a fervent Trump loyalist, voted against it. Victims of Epstein who had gathered in the House gallery cheered as the vote closed.</p> 
<p>Senate GOP leadership had previously downplayed the odds their chamber would take up the House’s Epstein bill, raising the likelihood that even if Massie and his allies were successful it would just be buried across the Capitol.</p> 
<p>That all changed over the weekend and Monday when Trump reversed course and urged House lawmakers to pass the bill and said that he would sign it. That reflected concerns that the fight was threatening to overshadow the party’s message as Trump tries to focus on the rising cost of living.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson called on the Senate to add more privacy protections for victims and whistleblowers, a concern Higgins cited in<a href="https://x.com/RepClayHiggins/status/1990868089056219267" target="_blank">explaining his vote</a> against the bill. But that would have required the bill to come back to the House for final approval.</p> 
<p>There is a broad desire in the GOP to pass the bill and move on to other legislative business, and Thune predicted that it would move “fairly quickly” through the Senate without changes.</p> 
<p>The political quagmire began for Republicans in July, when the Department of Justice released a memo saying it would not disclose further information in the Epstein case. Quickly, Democrats accused Trump and his allies of reneging on a commitment to transparency.</p> 
<p>The pressure culminated at an otherwise routine House Oversight subcommittee hearing in July, just ahead of the chamber’s summer recess. Democratic lawmakers, joined by a few Republicans, voted to subpoena information from the Justice Department in the Epstein case — launching a wide-ranging Oversight probe into Epstein and the Justice Department’s handling of the case.</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders have repeatedly pointed to that probe to argue that the effort led by Massie and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) to discharge the measure from committee and force an up-or-down vote on the legislation was unnecessary. Their bill would compel only the Justice Department to release information in its possession within 30 days of its enactment.</p> 
<p>The Oversight panel has already subpoenaed Epstein’s estate, which produced a “birthday book” and a number of emails that contained materials damaging to Trump.</p> 
<p>Trump’s relationship with the convicted sex offender has seen intense scrutiny, with Democrats accusing him of supporting a coverup. The president has maintained the two had a falling out years ago, and no evidence has linked Trump to wrongdoing in the Epstein case.</p> 
<p>But recent revelations in emails sent by Epstein suggested Trump “knew about the girls,” and the news has only increased pressure on his administration to release further information in the case.</p> 
<p>The Justice Department has so far released relatively few nonpublic materials to lawmakers as part of the Oversight probe, which was partially held up by the recent 43-day government shutdown. But many GOP lawmakers doubt the bill will trigger the release of much new information from DOJ, including Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.).</p> 
<p>“I think the Department of Justice has turned over what they’re legally allowed to turn over,” Comer said.</p> 
<p>Even before the Massie-Khanna discharge effort had succeeded and the bill passed the House, Senate Democrats were preparing to force Thune and his GOP members to vote quickly on the bill. Schumer warned that Democrats would oppose any efforts to water down the House language before it was sent on to Trump’s desk and relished in the GOP infighting.</p> 
<p>“In trying to hide the truth, Donald Trump has provoked the fiercest rebellion that he has faced among his supporters both in Congress and in the country,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Prior to Trump’s endorsement of the effort, the White House carried out a monthslong pressure campaign to try to prevent the forced vote in the House from happening.</p> 
<p>Trump and White House officials specifically pushed the three Republican women who signed onto the discharge petition — Reps. Marjorie Taylor Greene (Ga.), Lauren Boebert (Colo.) and Nancy Mace (S.C.) — to take their names off the effort, especially once it was clear that the swearing-in of Democratic Rep. Adelita Grijalva would prompt a vote.</p> 
<p>Boebert was even called into the White House Situation Room to try to get her to remove her name.Mace said in an interview that the floor action, after months of drama, is “also a symbolic vote for other survivors who’ve never gotten justice.”“It's a symbolism of justice for all of us. So, I'm emotional about it right now,” she said.</p> 
<p>Trump’s pressure campaign also included a public split with Greene, once one of his most vocal supporters in the House. Greene, who has also split with Trump recently over health care and economic matters, said her fissure with Trump “has all come down to the Epstein files.”</p> 
<p>“This has been one of the most destructive things to MAGA — is watching the man that we supported early on, three elections,” oppose the bill, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/mtg-speaks-on-epstein-00656279" target="_blank">Greene told reporters Tuesday</a>. “Watching this actually turn into a fight has ripped MAGA apart.”</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misreported the home state of Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.).]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CBO chief says ‘no further evidence’ of cyber intrusion of agency systems</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/cbo-chief-says-no-further-evidence-of-cyber-intrusion-of-agency-systems-00657223</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-986c-d49b-af9f-bcec77db0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 14:24:28 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Phillip Swagel, the director of the nonpartisan Congressional Budget Office, told lawmakers at an oversight hearing Tuesday morning before the House Budget Committee that the “sophisticated cyberattack” against his agency two weeks ago has been contained and there is currently no “further evidence of unauthorized access to CBO email.”</p> 
<p>It's the first time he has spoken out publicly about the breach.</p> 
<p>Swagel said the investigation is “extensive and ongoing” as the agency receives assistance from both federal security partners and private sector security specialists.</p> 
<p>He stressed that as more information becomes available about the nature of the attack — including “the threat actor’s activities” and what can be done to strengthen CBO’s systems — he will provide lawmakers updates “in a closed-door setting.”</p> 
<p>He warned that sharing some things during a public hearing “might hinder remediation or investigation” but insisted that CBO is now “operating as normal … without interruption.”</p> 
<p>In advance of the hearing, House Budget Chair Jodey Arrington praised the CBO’s handling of the incident.</p> 
<p>“They notified everybody, and all hands were on deck to address it, remediate it, and make sure that no further information was breached,” the Texas Republican said in an interview Monday night. “I thought they handled that responsibly and there was a great sense of urgency and concern, which is what I would expect.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-18T15:25:10-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Chuy García was the first signer of top aide’s ballot petitions, document shows</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/chuy-garcia-ballot-petitions-00656890</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9857-d49b-af9f-bcf7df7a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 14:04:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Chuy García has denied purposely clearing a path for his chief of staff to take his seat without facing a primary, but a <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-9844-df0f-abfa-f96ed12a0000" target="_blank">document filed with Illinois elections officials</a> shows he was the first to sign her nominating petitions, days before he announced his retirement.</p> 
<p>García said Tuesday in a note to Democratic colleagues obtained by POLITICO that he “did not circulate petitions for any Congressional campaign except my own.” But that obscures his apparent knowledge of the effort by his top aide, Patty Garcia, to get on the ballot.</p> 
<p>A <a href="https://www.politico.com/f/?id=0000019a-9844-df0f-abfa-f96ed12a0000" target="_blank">petition signature page</a> submitted by Patty Garcia to the Illinois Board of Elections shows the representative and his closest allies, whom Chuy García has also helped get elected over the years, signed their names. They include Cook County Commissioner Alma Anaya, Illinois state Sen. Celina Villanueva, state Reps. Aaron Ortiz and Norma Hernandez, and Chicago City Council members Jeylú Gutiérrez and Michael Rodriguez.</p> 
<p>The form is dated Nov. 1, two days before the filing deadline and three days before Chuy García formally announced his retirement. Patty Garcia ultimately filed nearly 3,000 signatures to qualify for the Democratic primary ballot. The two are not related.</p> 
<p>Fabiola Rodriguez-Ciampoli, a spokesperson for Chuy Garcia, said signing a petition is not the same as circulating them. "He did not circulate petitions" for his chief of staff's campaign, she said.</p> 
<p>The House is set to vote Tuesday afternoon on a measure brought by Rep. Marie Gluesenkamp Perez (D-Wash.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/chuy-garcia-house-democrats-split-00655609" target="_blank">rebuking Chuy García’s move</a>, which essentially ensured that Patty Garcia will succeed him as Democratic nominee and likely winner of the 2026 election.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders have signaled they are backing the veteran Chicago lawmaker and are whipping against the measure.</p> 
<p>“We disagree with the resolution that’s being offered, and we should be talking about issues that affect the American people,” said Rep. Pete Aguilar (D-Calif.), the third-ranking House Democrat.</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this story misreported how many petition signatures are necessary to qualify for the ballot in the primary.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-18T11:51:02-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House GOP leaders pitch members on addressing ‘Unaffordable Care Act’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/house-gop-leaders-pitch-members-on-unaffordable-care-act-00656362</link>
      <description>One Republican stood up to share frustrations about the party's health care approach in a closed-door meeting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-97c3-d739-a3ba-dfffb0970000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:22:23 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/bc/69/a692d0364dba9b6dd6f427c55402/u-s-congress-75480.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rather than extend ACA subsidies, Scalise and Johnson want to construct an entirely new health care framework.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/bc/69/a692d0364dba9b6dd6f427c55402/u-s-congress-75480.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Benjamin Guggenheim</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders delivered a presentation to members Tuesday morning slamming the enhanced tax credits for the Affordable Care Act that are due to expire at the end of the year.</p> 
<p>It comes as members of both parties and chambers are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/aca-obamacare-subsidies-extension-00655842" target="_blank">rushing to develop, and pass, legislation</a> to lower health care costs by Dec. 31, when the Obamacare subsidies will expire and premiums are set to go through the roof.</p> 
<p>There are multiple opinions among Republicans about whether the best path forward to keep the price of health care down involves extending the tax credits — possibly with some modifications to appease conservatives — or constructing an entirely new framework, like an overhaul of health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump weighed in Tuesday morning on behalf of the latter approach, saying "THE ONLY HEALTHCARE I WILL SUPPORT OR APPROVE IS SENDING THE MONEY DIRECTLY BACK TO THE PEOPLE, WITH NOTHING GOING TO THE BIG, FAT, RICH INSURANCE COMPANIES."</p> 
<p>"Congress, do not waste your time and energy on anything else," he <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115570813586755288" target="_blank">wrote on Truth Social</a>.</p> 
<p>A slide deck shared by House Majority Leader Steve Scalise in the Tuesday meeting made clear that House GOP leadership also falls in the overhaul camp. One slide viewed by POLITICO was titled “The Unaffordable Care Act,” and highlighted statistics showing that premiums have increased by 80 percent since the ACA’s passage. It also claimed that more than 50 percent of Obamacare enrollees did not file a single claim this year.</p> 
<p>Walking into the meeting, Scalise said in a brief interview that he planned to keep talking with the chairs of three key committees of jurisdiction over health policy — Ways and Means, Energy and Commerce, and Education and the Workforce.</p> 
<p>“A lot of members have called me or texted me during the break about the bills they have, and I've been making sure everybody's directed to the committees and talk to the chairman,” Scalise said. “Ultimately, we're gonna go through regular order on this.”</p> 
<p>But the leadership’s position is making some Republicans nervous — and frustrated. At one point during the meeting, Rep. Nathaniel Moran, a Republican in a deep-red Texas district, challenged GOP leaders on why they were now blasting the enhanced Obamacare tax credits just weeks before their expiration date.</p> 
<p>House Republicans, Moran continued, should have been talking about alternatives months ago, according to four people granted anonymity to share a private exchange inside the meeting room.</p> 
<p>Republican leaders are also facing intense pressure from vulnerable GOP moderates to extend the expiring premium tax credits.</p> 
<p>But other House Republicans were unapologetic Tuesday about their desire to put a conservative imprint on health care policy. Rep. August Pfluger (R-Texas), the chair of the Republican Study Committee, said after the presentation his party should “absolutely” pursue the party-line budget reconciliation process to pass a GOP health care bill.</p> 
<p>“The Democrats are incapable of coming up with a plan that is competitive, transparent and actually reduces costs,” said Pfluger, who has been hosting RSC discussions on policies for a second partisan policy package that can pass with a simple majority in the Senate. “The No. 1 bucket that we are focused on in a reconciliation 2.0 is affordability.”</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders have not given a timeline for any health care package, but are planning to unveil at least several bills on the topic before the end of the year, according to three people granted anonymity to describe internal strategy discussions.</p> 
<p>As House Republicans huddled in the basement of the Capitol building for the first time since September, White House deputy chief of staff James Blair told reporters at a separate event Tuesday morning that while there’s some interest in a bipartisan discussion on health policy, “Dems have not really demonstrated an interest in having constructive conversations.”</p> 
<p>In recent weeks, Blair has been hosting health policy meetings at the White House with providers and representatives from hospitals, along with White House legislative staff, according to one person granted anonymity to share details of the private gatherings. It’s a sign that the administration is taking the political ramifications of the credits’ expirations seriously, with Democrats likely to hammer the GOP on the issue in the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>Democrats are so far continuing to dig their heels in on a “clean” extension of the subsidies. But many moderate Democrats are willing to negotiate modifications as part of an extension.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epstein battle ‘has ripped MAGA apart,’ Marjorie Taylor Greene says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/mtg-speaks-on-epstein-00656279</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-97b5-d739-a3ba-dffd7e460000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:13:28 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene, the once steadfast ally of Donald Trump who has since fallen out with the president, said the saga around convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein has “ripped MAGA apart.”</p> 
<p>Greene made her comments while flanked by some of Epstein’s victims outside the Capitol on Tuesday, just hours before the House is set to vote on a bill that would force the Justice Department to release Epstein case files.</p> 
<p>The White House led an aggressive campaign to pare back Republican support for the effort, but Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank">ultimately gave a nod of approval</a> for the measure after Greene and three other Republicans joined Democrats to force it to the House floor.</p> 
<p>Trump, however, has angrily withdrawn his support for Greene — an early supporter of Trump and his Make America Great Again movement — and called her Marjorie “Traitor” Greene.</p> 
<p>“This has been one of the most destructive things to MAGA — is watching the man that we supported early on, three elections,” oppose the bill, she told reporters. “Watching this actually turn into a fight has ripped MAGA apart.”</p> 
<p>The back-and-forth battle over releasing the files has certainly driven some Republicans into contortions — not least of whom is Speaker Mike Johnson.</p> 
<p>He told reporters Tuesday that he plans to vote for the bill authored by Reps. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) and Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) even as he stood by his longtime claim that it’s “recklessly flawed” because it does not sufficiently protect victims and whistleblowers in his view. He told GOP members in a private conference meeting earlier that morning to vote their “conscience,” according to four people in the room granted anonymity to describe the private meeting.</p> 
<p>“I think it could be a near-unanimous vote,” Johnson said.</p> 
<p>Tuesday’s vote on the Epstein Files Transparency Act is the culmination of a monthslong bipartisan effort. Speaking at the news conference, Massie accused Trump of “trying to protect friends and donors” by opposing the legislation for so long. The victims, meanwhile, shared none of Johnson’s concerns that its passage would threaten their well-being.</p> 
<p>Other members of GOP leadership are also signaling they will vote for the bill. House Majority Leader Steve Scalise confirmed his vote in a brief interview Tuesday morning, and Rep. Lisa McClain (R-Mich.), the GOP conference chair, issued a statement saying she would also support it.</p> 
<p>Both Johnson and Scalise have suggested the Senate might revise the bill later, but there is likely to be little appetite in the other chamber for prolonged consideration of a measure that most Republicans want to put quickly behind them.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune isn't expected to announce what the Senate will do until after the House passes the bill, but there's growing support among Senate Republicans to pass the resolution in the wake of Trump's shift — potentially by unanimous consent this week.</p> 
<p>Johnson and Massie <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/thomas-massie-trump-jeffrey-epstein-00654214" target="_blank">continued to snipe at each other</a>, meanwhile, with the speaker saying Tuesday he got the “middle finger” from the bill sponsors when GOP leaders asked to make revisions, while Massie said in an interview Monday that Johnson’s “concerns were never warranted.”</p> 
<p>“If he actually wanted the Epstein files released, he could have offered his suggestions four months ago and brought it to the floor,” Massie said. “Instead he … spread lies about our legislation he now supports because the president told him to.”</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>White House plans to release health bill and backs reconciliation</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/white-house-health-bill-tariffs-00655917</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9787-d51c-a39e-bf8f7fbd0008</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 10:15:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A senior White House official said the Trump administration intends to put forward a health bill and left open the possibility of using the fast-track legislative process of reconciliation for passage of health or tariff legislation.</p> 
<p>“We’re going to have the health care conversation. We’re going to put some legislation forward,” White House deputy chief of staff James Blair said Tuesday at a Bloomberg Government policy breakfast.</p> 
<p>He expressed interest in a bipartisan health plan but said that “if that path is foreclosed, there is the partisan path of reconciliation as well.”</p> 
<p>Such a move would allow Republicans to advance a health plan with a simple majority, a path they unsuccessfully attempted in Trump’s first term to repeal Obamacare but successfully used earlier this year on <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_1" target="_blank">the megabill</a>.</p> 
<p>“The president probably would like to go bigger than the Hill has the appetite for, so we’ll have to see how that, you know, works out,” Blair added, hinting at potential friction between the White House and congressional Republicans.</p> 
<p>Several GOP lawmakers have said privately that they expect the White House to put forward a framework that revisits long-standing Republican goals — including reducing insurance costs, expanding health savings accounts and unwinding parts of the Affordable Care Act — though it remains unclear how sweeping Trump hopes to go.</p> 
<p>If a reconciliation bill moves soon, Blair indicated that the administration would also want to include "probably the Trump tariff dividends and … interest in locking in tariffs."</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans have been privately discussing a second reconciliation package. Budget Committee Republicans are tentatively looking at early next year for finalizing a budget resolution that would tee up the party-line package, according to senators on the committee.</p> 
<p>Senate Budget Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) previously told POLITICO that the party could use a second bill to tackle health care, spending and tax policy.</p> 
<p>But there’s plenty of skepticism, including within top members of the House and Senate GOP conferences, about doing another party-line bill, which would require near unity from their thin majorities. GOP senators, in a recent closed-door lunch, noted that many of their health care ideas left out of the “big, beautiful bill” wouldn’t comply with the Senate’s strict rules for what can be included under reconciliation, according to one attendee granted anonymity to disclose private discussions.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP tries to rip off the Epstein Band-Aid</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/18/congress/house-republican-vote-epstein-files-chuy-garcia-00655846</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-9546-d51c-a39e-bd4f20e50000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two big votes are hitting the House floor Tuesday afternoon, with each party caught between unity and accountability.</p> 
<p><b>ON THE GOP SIDE —</b> The House is expected to easily pass a resolution calling on the DOJ to release files related to Jeffrey Epstein after a monthslong battle by President Donald Trump and GOP leaders to block the vote.</p> 
<p>Trump said Monday he would sign the bill if it lands on his desk, giving political cover for Republicans to vote for the measure. The House will vote under suspension of the rules Tuesday, limiting debate and requiring a two-thirds majority.</p> 
<p>What we’re really watching is the Senate. Last night, Republicans advanced rule language that effectively forces Speaker Mike Johnson to send the bill across the Rotunda. If he doesn’t, the original discharge petition remains in force, triggering another House vote.</p> 
<p>Senate GOP leaders haven’t committed to putting a vote on the floor, but Trump’s new endorsement has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/epstein-files-bill-congress-00655286" target="_blank">changed the dynamic</a>.</p> 
<p>Johnson said he wants the Senate to amend the measure to include more protections for victims and whistleblowers. But that would require another House vote, further extending a saga most Hill Republicans want to move past as quickly as possible.</p> 
<p><b>ON THE DEM SIDE —</b> The House is also expected to vote at Tuesday's 2 p.m. series on a resolution condemning Rep. Chuy García (D-Ill.) for a move in which he retired and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/03/congress/jesus-chuy-garcia-retirement-watch-00634349" target="_blank">functionally guaranteed</a> his chief of staff would succeed him.</p> 
<p>The resolution, triggered by Rep. Marie Gluesenkamp Perez (D-Wash.), forces Democrats to choose between sticking by a longtime colleague and condemning a hardball move many find difficult to stomach.</p> 
<p>García <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/chuy-garcia-house-democrats-split-00655609" target="_blank">defended himself on the floor</a> Monday night, saying he chose to put family first by retiring and suggesting that what goes around might come around: “One day you might be the one making that choice, and you shouldn’t have to debate it on the House floor.”</p> 
<p>But one House Democrat, granted anonymity to speak candidly, estimated to POLITICO that “a not insignificant number of Democrats” will support the disapproval measure after only Gluesenkamp Perez and Rep. Jared Golden (D-Maine) opposed a motion to table Monday. Keep an eye on more moderate Democrats like Nevada Rep. Susie Lee, who told POLITICO “it was questionable, the timing,” while many others in the caucus hold their nose.</p> 
<p>“It’s an unpleasant one,” said Rep. Jared Huffman (D-Calif.), who said he will vote against it Tuesday. “Chuy García is a friend and a great guy. But I don’t like the optics of this.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p>— <b>ACA latest: </b>House GOP leaders will <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/18/aca-obamacare-subsidies-extension-00655842" target="_blank">lead a high-level discussion</a> in their conference meeting Tuesday morning on how to address rising health care costs. It comes as Senate Republicans are quickly developing their own legislative proposals and some House Republicans fret they could get jammed by the upper chamber. </p> 
<p><b>— CBO hearing:</b> Congressional Budget Office Director Phillip Swagel is set to testify Tuesday morning before the House Budget Committee. The oversight hearing will be the first chance GOP lawmakers have to air their grievances over the agency’s analysis of their party’s megabill since the legislation was enacted in July.</p> 
<p><b>— NDAA crunch time: </b>House and Senate lawmakers have a critical week ahead to reach a compromise on major defense policy legislation if they want to have a deal ready to hit the floor after the Thanksgiving break for an early December vote.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Nicholas Wu, Shia Kapos, Calen Razor, Benjamin Guggenheim, Katherine Tully-McManus and Connor O’Brien contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House set to denounce Illinois Democrat's succession scheme</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/chuy-garcia-house-democrats-split-00655609</link>
      <description>Tensions have flared among Democrats over a potential rebuke for Rep. Chuy García prompted by one of their own.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-944a-df0f-abfa-f56a1dea0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 19:42:34 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/90/e5/26eed2bb4d72931327e1476486ce/u-s-congress-19009.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Jesus “Chuy” Garcia arrives for a Congressional Progressive Caucus press conference on Capitol Hill on Dec. 5, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/90/e5/26eed2bb4d72931327e1476486ce/u-s-congress-19009.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Shia Kapos</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Shia Kapos</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House is on track to rebuke a veteran Illinois lawmaker over a hardball political tactic — a move that has stirred intraparty anger at the fellow Democrat who prompted it.</p> 
<p>The formal admonishment targets Rep. Chuy García, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/03/congress/jesus-chuy-garcia-retirement-watch-00634349" target="_blank">announced his retirement</a> earlier this month only after the candidate qualification period closed — all but assuring his chief of staff would succeed him in the solid blue Chicago district.</p> 
<p>What has roiled Democrats is who forced the issue: Rep. Marie Gluesenkamp Perez of Washington, who introduced the rebuke Wednesday under a fast-track process bypassing House leadership. That she did so as House Democratic leaders moved to focus attention on GOP disarray on health care and the Jeffrey Epstein case has further exacerbated the tensions.</p> 
<p>A vote to kill the disapproval resolution backed by House Democratic leaders failed on a 211-206 vote Monday, with Rep. Jared Golden of Maine being the only other Democrat joining Gluesenkamp Perez to proceed with the symbolic measure. </p> 
<p>That tees up debate and a final vote as soon as Tuesday. Some Democrats granted anonymity to describe private conversations with colleagues said they expected many more defections on that vote.</p> 
<p>“You don't get your cake and eat it, too,” Gluesenkamp Perez said during a debate that followed the vote. “If you are not going to run, you don't choose your successor — no matter the work you have done beforehand.”</p> 
<p>Although some in the party privately disagreed with García's decision to retire after only the filing deadline, many House Democrats bristled at Gluesenkamp Perez’s decision to call it up on a day when the party was attempting to project unity at the end of the record government shutdown.</p> 
<p>Many also cited García’s own response, saying his decision to retire was based on his health and family needs. His office has <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/chuy-garcia-talking-points-00654743" target="_blank">forcefully pushed back</a> against any accusations of wrongdoing, blasting out talking points to Capitol Hill offices Monday.</p> 
<p>“There was absolutely nothing illegal or unethical,” said Rep. Hillary Scholten (D-Mich.). “This is entirely based on an assumption about what one member believes were his intentions, when in fact, he has clearly stated he needed the time to make up his mind, and he was going through a lot of personal difficulties in his life trying to decide if he was going to run again.”</p> 
<p>García spoke out on his own behalf Monday night after the vote, saying that “our job comes second to the people waiting at home.”</p> 
<p>“When a colleague chooses his family, that shouldn’t be a moment for division — it should be a moment for understanding and unity,” he said. “One day you might be the one making that choice, and you shouldn’t have to debate it on the House floor.”</p> 
<p>But many in Democratic circles have spoken up on Gluesenkamp Perez’s behalf for calling out García for essentially hand-picking his successor, including Sen. Andy Kim of New Jersey and veteran Chicago political strategist David Axelrod. Purple-district Rep. Susie Lee (D-Nev.) said Monday she had “a lot of questions about the timing of what he did.”</p> 
<p>Even those who defended García registered some distaste for how he engineered his departure from the House.</p> 
<p>“I have tremendous sympathy for the family situation that Chuy has. I also think we have a long history [in Illinois] of greasing the skids for successors, which is not a good way for democracy to work,” said Rep. Sean Casten (D-Ill.). “But I don’t think that this is something that should really warrant the attention of the House.”</p> 
<p>“I don’t think it was a long decision,” said Rep. Jan Schakowsky (D-Ill.), whose own retirement has kicked off a hotly contested primary, of García’s deliberations. “I don’t know if it was as short as it appears, either."</p> 
<p>Yet Democratic leaders firmly backed García, who remains popular with his Democratic colleagues. The Congressional Hispanic Caucus, of which García and Gluesenkamp Perez are both members, released a statement last week “in solidarity with” García. And House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries gave the 69-year-old his full-throated backing in comments to reporters Monday.</p> 
<p>"He's been a progressive champion in disenfranchised communities for decades, including during his time in Congress, and he's made life better for the American people," Jeffries said, adding that he believed the disapproval measure would be successfully tabled.</p> 
<p>Gluesenkamp Perez, who represents a swing district and belongs to the moderate Blue Dog faction, has a much less cozy relationship with her colleagues. She had a testy confrontation with House Minority Whip Katherine Clark on the House floor after introducing her measure. Clark later told reporters that lawmakers “should be focused on the issue of health care.”</p> 
<p>Gluesenkamp Perez has doubled down on her criticism of her fellow Democrats. In a CNN interview Sunday, she said she understood the desire to have a unified message as a party. But, she added, “When you see things like this … it's not just about having affordable stuff or holding another team accountable, it's that we want leadership. We want a team that calls a spade a spade.”</p> 
<p>It’s not the first time she’s cut against her party. Earlier this year, she unsuccessfully attempted to add congressional <a href="https://gluesenkampperez.house.gov/posts/appropriations-committee-votes-down-gluesenkamp-perezs-cognitive-acuity-amendment" target="_blank">ethics standards relating to cognitive ability</a> to an appropriations bill. And she was one of a half-dozen Democrats who <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/house-votes-to-reopen-government-after-43-day-shutdown-00649927" target="_blank">voted with Republicans</a> to pass the funding bill ending the government shutdown.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-17T18:30:57-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Republicans quickly coalesce behind Epstein bill after Trump backs it</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/epstein-files-bill-congress-00655286</link>
      <description>Two prominent House committee chairs are among the GOP lawmakers now backing the legislation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-93ce-df0f-abfa-f3ee56c30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 17:07:32 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b4/2a/73d02ff24a94899ce719740b1e6e/u-s-congress-22690.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“I think everyone will vote for it,” House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) said Monday.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b4/2a/73d02ff24a94899ce719740b1e6e/u-s-congress-22690.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Capitol Hill Republicans are rapidly falling in line behind a bill that would force the disclosure of Justice Department files concerning Jeffrey Epstein after President Donald Trump signaled Monday he would sign it.</p> 
<p>Two prominent House committee chairs said they planned to support the bill compelling the release of materials related to the late convicted sex offender, and GOP leaders are expected to advance the measure under special fast-track rules Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, Trump’s sudden support for the measure — after a monthslong campaign to kill it — has transformed its prospects in the Senate, where it was long assumed Republicans would simply bottle it up. Now a growing number of GOP senators are open to giving the bill a vote, and some are wondering whether it might simply be sent to Trump’s desk by unanimous consent.</p> 
<p>It’s a remarkable reversal of fortune for the effort to disgorge the “Epstein files,” prompted by a successful bipartisan effort to circumvent Speaker Mike Johnson and force the legislation to the floor.</p> 
<p>Recognizing that House approval of the legislation was all but certain, Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank">abandoned his efforts to derail the bill</a> in a social media post Sunday night. Asked in the Oval Office on Monday if he would sign it, Trump said, “Sure I would.”</p> 
<p>Some of his closest allies in the House said Monday they were ready to follow the president’s lead.</p> 
<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan (R-Ohio) said in an interview Monday afternoon he will vote for the Epstein bill.</p> 
<p>“I think everyone will vote for it,” Jordan said, adding he agreed with Trump that Republicans need “to get this ridiculous thing past us.”</p> 
<p>Asked if he expected any changes to the bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/thomas-massie-trump-jeffrey-epstein-00654214" target="_blank">authored by Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.)</a> before it gets a floor vote, Jordan replied: “No.”</p> 
<p>House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.), whose panel has released thousands of Epstein emails that have heightened scrutiny of Trump’s dealings with the disgraced financier, also said he would vote for the bill. He, too, suggested the vote would not be close.</p> 
<p>“I mean, I think everybody's gonna vote for it,” Comer said in an interview.</p> 
<p>“It’s just a show vote, you know? I mean, we're the ones that have already gotten all the new information from the estate,” he said, touting his own panel’s probe into the matter.</p> 
<p>Comer also questioned the practical impact of the legislation: “I think the Department of Justice has turned over what they're legally allowed to turn over.”</p> 
<p>Trump suggested as much in his Sunday night post telling lawmakers to support the bill, with many Republicans skeptical about how much new information the department would release if the bill passes.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders had been exploring a two-step <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/house-epstein-files-vote-00652964" target="_blank">plan to advance the Epstein bill</a> by first adopting a procedural measure in the Rules Committee Monday night that would incorporate a separate procedural measure from Massie and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.), setting up a final vote Tuesday afternoon.</p> 
<p>But after meeting with fellow Republican leaders, Johnson said they were instead moving toward a plan that would put the bill up for a vote Tuesday under so-called suspension of the rules, a simpler fast-track procedure requiring a two-thirds majority vote for passage. </p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune isn't currently expected to weigh in on whether he will bring up the Epstein measure until after it passes the House, according to a person granted anonymity to disclose internal strategy.</p> 
<p>But Trump's support for passing the Epstein files resolution has changed the dynamic inside the Senate GOP, where top Republicans have previously downplayed the chances of the chamber acting on the House bill, according to two other people granted anonymity to comment on the sensitive matter.</p> 
<p>A growing number of GOP senators are open to giving the resolution a vote — pointing to both Trump's comments and interest from their own constituents in seeing Congress take action on Epstein.</p> 
<p>"I don't have any problems with data coming out. So lots of people ran on this issue in the last election, so I don't have any problems with us voting on it," Sen. John Boozman (R-Ark.) told reporters Monday.</p> 
<p>Johnson said he had "some comfort" that the Senate would amend the bill to provide for "the protection of victims and whistleblowers and all the rest” before passing it. That would require another House vote before it moves to Trump's desk.</p> 
<p>Senate Republicans will not return to Washington until Tuesday evening, when they are expected to discuss next steps. The only way for the resolution to pass the Senate this week would be with buy-in from every senator to either speed up a vote or skip one altogether with a vote by unanimous consent, which would let it clear the chamber without a roll call vote.</p> 
<p>Congressional passage — and a Trump signature — would not be the end of the Epstein saga on Capitol Hill, however.</p> 
<p>Jordan said he plans to have Attorney General Pam Bondi back before his panel for a rescheduled oversight hearing “as soon as possible.” Questions about the Epstein case are sure to take center stage in any hearing, as they did when Bondi recently <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/07/congress/pam-bondi-spars-with-dick-durbin-00596234" target="_blank">appeared before the Senate Judiciary Committee</a>.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers are also bracing for the possibility that Trump might pardon Epstein’s convicted accomplice Ghislaine Maxwell, a possibility Trump has repeatedly declined to rule out .</p> 
<p>Comer responded sharply when asked if he’d support a pardon for Maxwell: “No, I do not,” he said. “I’ve already said that.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘He got tired of me winning’: How Thomas Massie outmaneuvered Trump on Epstein</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/17/thomas-massie-trump-jeffrey-epstein-00654214</link>
      <description>The president’s Sunday capitulation handed his biggest GOP foe in Congress a major victory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-92a6-df0f-abfa-f3ee89bc0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/98/5b/c9f3b0fb43629cb9f50f7ddb9275/u-s-congress-74026.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) speaks with reporters outside the U.S. Capitol Sept. 8, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/98/5b/c9f3b0fb43629cb9f50f7ddb9275/u-s-congress-74026.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump's call for House Republicans to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank">support releasing Jeffrey Epstein-related documents</a> was a stunning capitulation after a months-long campaign to block the vote.</p> 
<p>It was also a specific defeat for Trump at the hands of a despised GOP opponent: Rep. Thomas Massie of Kentucky.</p> 
<p>“He got tired of me winning,” Massie said of Trump’s U-turn in an interview Monday morning.</p> 
<p>Insisting “I DON’T CARE!” in a late-night Truth Social post, Trump was bowing to the inevitable — a broad House Republican mutiny on a vote that was only scheduled because Massie forced it. It was the result of Massie and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) launching a discharge petition aimed at sidestepping senior GOP leaders who desperately wanted to avoid bringing the issue to the House floor.</p> 
<p>The campaign to avoid the vote got remarkably ugly in the days before Trump finally conceded, with the president personally attacking Massie for recently remarrying after the sudden death in June 2024 of his wife of more than 30 years. Just hours before Trump’s reversal, one of his top political advisers called him “garbage” in an X post.</p> 
<p>That adviser, Chris LaCivita, is carrying out a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/07/09/thomas-massie-donald-trump-kentucky-libertarian-conservatism-00441983" target="_blank">Trump-ordered effort to unseat Massie</a> from the rural northern Kentucky seat he has held since 2012. Trump <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/21/congress/massies-challenger-00616290" target="_blank">recently endorsed</a> a challenger, former Navy SEAL Ed Gallrein, in the GOP primary.</p> 
<p>Massie has not flinched from the threats. Politically, he has seen the best fundraising of his congressional career, entering October with more than $2 million in his campaign coffers. As for the personal attacks, Massie said Monday he and his wife were laughing them off.</p> 
<p>“She said, ‘I told you we should have invited him to the wedding!’” Massie said.</p> 
<p>Massie’s efforts around Epstein have been no laughing matter for the White House, with top aides and legislative affairs staff furiously scrambling late last week to head off the completion of the discharge petition.</p> 
<p>That included pulling Rep. Lauren Boebert (R-Colo.) into the White House Situation Room in the final hours to try to persuade her to remove her name from the petition she had signed alongside GOP Reps. Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and Nancy Mace of South Carolina, a survivor of sexual assault. All three have cast their support for the petition as an effort to protect women.</p> 
<p>Trump's pressure campaign failed. The three female House Republicans held firm, and the petition notched its final and 218th signature Wednesday moments after Rep. Adelita Grijalva (D-Ariz.) was sworn in following her September special election win. Despite a final barrage of attacks from the president over the weekend — which included Trump calling his once-close ally Greene a “traitor” and threatening a GOP primary against her — backers of the Massie-Khanna discharge effort knew they had the president beat.</p> 
<p>There were emerging signs that it was Massie, not Trump, who had his fingers closer to the pulse of the MAGA base.</p> 
<p>Rep. Troy Nehls (R-Texas), a top Trump ally in the House, posted online he would be “voting NO on the Epstein Hoax” as he sought to rally Republicans to “stand by” the president’s side. Nehls received an immediate barrage of online pushback, suggesting a position against full transparency on Epstein would not be sustainable.</p> 
<p>Massie in conjunction with the three GOP women who signed the discharge petition have sought to put Epstein’s victims front and center amid the battle. They invited several to Capitol Hill in September to keep the fight in the public eye as members returned from the summer recess. They are tentatively scheduled to appear together again Tuesday ahead of the final House vote.</p> 
<p>“This shouldn’t have been a battle, and unfortunately, it has been one,” Greene said as she left a meeting with Epstein victims in September.</p> 
<p>Yet for months, senior White House officials labored to convince rank-and-file Republicans to keep their names off Massie’s discharge effort. That, according to five people granted anonymity to discuss private conversations, included warnings that any effort to support an Epstein vote would be viewed as a direct and personal move against the president.</p> 
<p>Trump has denied wrongdoing in relation to the Epstein allegations, and no evidence has suggested that Trump took part in Epstein’s trafficking operation. The president also has maintained that he and Epstein had a falling out years ago.</p> 
<p>“President Trump has been consistently calling for transparency related to the Epstein files,” said Abigail Jackson, a deputy White House press secretary, in a statement. “The Democrats knew about Epstein and his victims for years and did nothing to help them until they thought they could weaponize the files against the President.”</p> 
<p>In an effort to undercut Massie's effort, GOP leaders and the Justice Department worked to release 30,000 pages of DOJ documents in early September, right after Massie could begin gathering signatures on his petition. But lawmakers quickly realized most of the materials had been previously released.</p> 
<p>Around that time, the White House’s key legislative affairs liaison to the House, Jeff Freeland, was on the Hill, seeking to head off Massie right after lawmakers returned from recess.</p> 
<p>“Jeff introduced himself to me outside of the Capitol, and he said I was moving too fast for him,” Massie said in the interview. “I told him I made a mistake by getting 12 sponsors [on the Epstein bill], because I had given him his whip list to block the most likely signers” of the discharge petition.</p> 
<p>Over the past week, it became clear to House GOP leaders that they would no longer be able to keep the Epstein measure off the House floor. Shortly after Grijalva signed, Speaker Mike Johnson announced he would expedite the vote, holding it this week rather than next month as required under the discharge petition. Still, with Trump opposing the effort, he maintained Massie’s legislation was reckless and “moot” now that the House Oversight Committee was heading up its own probe.</p> 
<p>Last week, Johnson tried calling one of the three GOP women who had signed on to Massie’s discharge petition. The member looked down at her phone and let the call go to voicemail, according to two people granted anonymity to discuss a sensitive matter who declined to identify the specific lawmaker.</p> 
<p>Trump’s Sunday night edict was directed only at House Republicans, according to Trump officials. The president could order the release of the entire Epstein document trove at any time, vote or no vote. So far, he’s declined to do so.</p> 
<p>Senate GOP leaders have not committed to holding a vote on the Epstein bill if the House passes it as expected this week. While Republicans still widely assume the measure will die in the other chamber, it will be hard to argue to GOP senators that they should take the political heat while their House counterparts get to take a consequence-free vote.</p> 
<p>Massie has been working with Sen. Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.), who authored a Senate version of the bill, to bring the matter to a head across the Rotunda. Senate Democrats are already exploring options to force a vote in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>Massie said last week that the Epstein drama reflects how Republicans are starting to take stock of a post-Trump political world.</p> 
<p>“They need to look past 2028 and wonder if they want this on their record for the rest of their political career,” he said.</p> 
<p>“Right now, it's OK to cover up for pedophiles, because the president will take up for you if you're in the red districts — that's the deal,” Massie told reporters last week. “But that deal only works as long as he's popular or president. … If they're thinking about the right thing to do, that's pretty obvious: You vote for it.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Trump blinks on Epstein as GOP rebels</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/17/congress/trump-epstein-files-house-vote-update-00654109</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-901c-d51c-a39e-bd1d5b900000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is coming to grips with his impending loss on the Jeffrey Epstein files and a rare moment of tenuous control over the House GOP.</p> 
<p>In a late Sunday <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115562626931599548" target="_blank">Truth Social post</a>, Trump said House Republicans should vote to release DOJ records on the late convicted sex offender “because we have nothing to hide.”</p> 
<p>“I DON’T CARE!” he said. “All I do care about is that Republicans get BACK ON POINT.”</p> 
<p>Trump’s reversal after a monthslong pressure campaign came as dozens of Republicans — <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/house-epstein-vote-gop-defections-00649624" target="_blank">perhaps as many as 100</a> — were already poised to break with him in <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/house-epstein-files-vote-00652964" target="_blank">a vote Tuesday</a>. Even close allies of GOP leadership <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460" target="_blank">were weighing whether to defect</a> from the president.</p> 
<p>“I’m a big full disclosure person,” said House Rules Chair Virginia Foxx, a trusted member in Speaker Mike Johnson’s inner circle, who declined to say how she would vote. “I have nothing to hide, and I assume nobody else does, either.”</p> 
<p>Ahead of Trump’s U-turn, Hill Republicans had grown increasingly wary of his fixation on the issue, according to five people granted anonymity to describe internal GOP conversations. Evidence has not linked Trump to wrongdoing in the Epstein case, and the president has maintained that he and the financier had a falling out years ago.</p> 
<p>Trump’s edict is just about the House, two White House officials tell POLITICO. It amounts to a face-saving move ahead of a vote he was going to lose, and at this point it’s still likely the matter dies in the Senate.</p> 
<p>One senior Republican marveled at Trump’s “erratic” and unsettling attempt last week to kill the effort, including pulling Rep. Lauren Boebert (R-Colo.) into the White House Situation Room. That preceded a dramatic break over the weekend when he withdrew his endorsement of Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.). </p> 
<p>The Georgia Republican told CNN Sunday that the animosity between her and Trump “has all come down to the Epstein files.”</p> 
<p>“I have no idea what’s in the files. I can’t even guess,” Greene said. “But that is the question everyone is asking is why fight this so hard?”</p> 
<p>Part of Trump’s obsession over the House vote is Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), who has decisively outmaneuvered the president with the disclosure push. Massie, whom Trump is trying to oust in next year’s primary, said in an interview that the Epstein vote reflects how Republicans are looking ahead to a post-Trump world.</p> 
<p>“They need to look past 2028 and wonder if they want this on their record for the rest of their political career,” he said.</p> 
<p>Once the House passes the bill, Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer and Senate Democrats are expected to launch a blitz to pressure Senate Majority Leader John Thune to bring it to the floor. Democrats may also look at upcoming appropriations bills to try to force an Epstein vote.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Health care talks:</b> House committee chairs will <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/house-gop-committee-leaders-to-hold-health-care-brainstorming-sessions-00649200" target="_blank">begin listening sessions</a> this week with GOP members on the fate of soon-to-expire Affordable Care Act subsidies. It will likely be a big topic of conversation at Tuesday’s conference meeting.</p> 
<p><b>— Undoing the Senate:</b> The House on Wednesday is <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/house-republicans-push-vote-to-reverse-provision-allowing-senators-to-sue-over-phone-records-00648323" target="_blank">fast-tracking a vote</a> to repeal <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/senate-republicans-phones-sue-jack-smith-00651463" target="_blank">the politically toxic</a> records seizure payout provision that Thune secured in the deal to reopen the government.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-17T14:51:00-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump does Epstein U-turn as House Republicans prepare to spurn him</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/jeffrey-epstein-vote-house-republicans-00652460</link>
      <description>Before the reversal, even some House GOP leaders were mulling whether to support the effort to release DOJ files dealing with the late sex offender.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-8427-d739-a3ba-dcff15370000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 22:18:31 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c2/9f/e7f52fb94bdd819c8e30a9e1442c/unlimiteduse-11-12-2025-capitol-hill-anna-rose-layden-0043.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) has managed to outmaneuver the president despite Trump and Speaker Mike Johnson trying to hold him off for months.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c2/9f/e7f52fb94bdd819c8e30a9e1442c/unlimiteduse-11-12-2025-capitol-hill-anna-rose-layden-0043.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump is suddenly reversing his monthslong campaign to bottle up a bipartisan effort to disclose federal records dealing with Jeffrey Epstein — just as scores of House Republicans prepare to defy his demands concerning the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>“House Republicans should vote to release the Epstein files, because we have nothing to hide, and it’s time to move on from this Democrat Hoax,” he wrote Sunday night on Truth Social, adding, “I DON’T CARE! All I do care about is that Republicans get BACK ON POINT” discussing economic issues.</p> 
<p>The U-turn came after months of drama inside the House GOP over a bill that would compel the Justice Department to release its entire Epstein file. An effort by Trump and Speaker Mike Johnson to prevent a floor vote on the measure<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/house-epstein-files-vote-00647392" target="_blank">imploded last week</a> amid an intense White House push to try to keep Republicans in line. The vote is <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/house-epstein-files-vote-00652964" target="_blank">now expected Tuesday</a>.</p> 
<p>At the end of last week, Johnson and senior House leaders appeared powerless to stop<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/house-epstein-vote-gop-defections-00649624" target="_blank">perhaps as many as 100 Republicans</a> from breaking ranks and voting with Democrats to release the files. The situation worsened over the weekend, as Trump lashed out in deeply personal terms at Rep. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.), who is leading the effort to force a House vote on Epstein, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-mtg-aca-epstein-massie-00653412" target="_blank">publicly spurned</a> Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.), a one-time close ally who has recently broken with Trump on Epstein and other matters.</p> 
<p>Even before that, some members closest to House GOP leadership were mulling whether to support Massie’s effort.</p> 
<p>Those include lawmakers like Rep. Virginia Foxx (R-N.C.), who as Rules Committee chair is among the most trusted members of Johnson’s inner circle. She declined to say in an interview last week whether she would support Massie’s measure. But she suggested she favored it coming to a vote, which GOP leaders expect to happen Tuesday.</p> 
<p>“I’m a big full disclosure person,” Foxx said. “I have nothing to hide, and I assume nobody else does, either.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Blake Moore of Utah, the Republican conference vice chair, said in an interview last week he normally doesn’t discuss how he will vote. Rep. Kevin Hern of Oklahoma, the House GOP policy chair, acknowledged “a lot of consternation” inside the party about what to do.</p> 
<p>Asked about his own vote, Hern said, “We'll make that decision at game time.”</p> 
<p>The internal GOP strife underscores how politically toxic Trump’s association with Epstein has become, especially after Democrats on the House Oversight Committee released an email Wednesday in which Epstein suggested that<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/jeffrey-epstein-donald-trump-emails-00647447" target="_blank">Trump “knew about the girls.”</a></p> 
<p>Evidence has not linked Trump to wrongdoing in the Epstein case, and the president has maintained that he and the disgraced financier had a falling out years ago.</p> 
<p>Trump and Johnson had labored to avoid a total GOP jailbreak in the House, knowing a big vote could increase pressure on the Senate to take up the bill and send it to the president’s desk, forcing an embarrassing veto that would prolong the controversy.</p> 
<p>Johnson did not directly answer Monday whether he personally planned to vote for the measure, telling reporters that Trump's new comments "speak for themselves" while also suggesting the bill as written might not <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/21/congress/johnson-wont-block-epstein-vote-00616410" target="_blank">do enough to protect Epstein's victims</a> from invasion of privacy.</p> 
<p>"I'm not sure the discharge does that, and that's part of the problem," Johnson said,</p> 
<p>Senate GOP leaders have not committed to holding a vote, and while Republicans widely expect the measure to die in the chamber, they are in for weeks of fierce pressure to advance it.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer addressed Trump in a <a href="https://x.com/SenSchumer/status/1990263597520556165" target="_blank">late-night X post</a>, pointing out that the president could simply release the files instead of cajoling his allies in Congress.</p> 
<p>"Let’s make this easier," Schumer wrote. "Just release the files now."</p> 
<p>Sen. Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.), who authored a Senate version of the bill, is coordinating with Massie, and Democrats have some options to force the issue, including seeking to force a vote by unanimous consent or to amend unrelated legislation.</p> 
<p>Trump appeared trained on keeping the House defections to a minimum as recently as Friday, when he sent multiple <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115548539359870302" target="_blank">Truth Social posts</a> where he accused Democrats of pushing an “Epstein Hoax … in order to deflect from all of their bad policies and losses” and ordered Attorney General Pam Bondi to<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-epstein-investigation-department-of-justice-00651851" target="_blank">investigate Democrats’ connections to Epstein</a>. The posts, according to three Republicans granted anonymity to discuss the sensitive matter, were part of an effort to limit mass GOP defections on this week’s vote.</p> 
<p>“Some Weak Republicans have fallen into their clutches because they are soft and foolish,” he wrote, telling them, “don’t waste your time with Trump. I have a Country to run!”</p> 
<p>Trump normally enjoys an iron grip over the House, where Republicans are rarely anything but subservient to the president. He’s seen hints of pushback recently on<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/21/trump-pulls-ingrassia-nomination-racist-texts-00617041" target="_blank">key nominees</a> and his demand to<a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/05/congress/gop-senators-filibuster-trump-00637774" target="_blank">eliminate the Senate filibuster</a>.</p> 
<p>But he’s lost all control over the chamber when it comes to the Epstein matter, and Hill Republicans have grown increasingly wary of Trump’s fixation on the issue, according to five other people granted anonymity to describe internal GOP conversations.</p> 
<p>One senior Republican marveled at Trump’s "erratic" and unsettling effort last week to kill the bipartisan end-around led by Massie and Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.). That included pulling Rep. Lauren Boebert (R-Colo.) into the White House Situation Room to try to remove her name from the discharge petition she had signed alongside GOP Reps. Nancy Mace of South Carolina and Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia.</p> 
<p>The effort failed, and Trump administration officials privately warned that Mace’s defiance is likely to cost her an endorsement in the South Carolina governor’s race. One of her Republican opponents in that campaign, Rep. Ralph Norman, suggested he may not vote for the bill in an interview last week: “Oh, I don’t know. We’ll see.”</p> 
<p>A major source of Trump’s obsession over the House vote is Massie, who has opposed a raft of major GOP legislation, including spending bills and the megabill that passed this summer. Trump is now<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/07/09/thomas-massie-donald-trump-kentucky-libertarian-conservatism-00441983" target="_blank">intent on ousting Massie</a> in next year’s primary, but the Kentucky Republican has now managed to outmaneuver the president despite Trump and Johnson trying to hold him off for months.</p> 
<p>Massie said in an interview that the Epstein vote will reflect how Republicans are starting to take stock of a post-Trump world.</p> 
<p>“They need to look past 2028 and wonder if they want this on their record for the rest of their political career,” he said.</p> 
<p>“Right now, it's okay to cover up for pedophiles because the president will take up for you if you're in the red districts — that's the deal,” Massie later told reporters. “But that deal only works as long as he's popular or president. … If they're thinking about the right thing to do, that's pretty obvious: You vote for it.”</p> 
<p>That is reflected in the broad swath of House Republicans who said last week they were ready to back Massie, ranging from conservative hard-liners to moderate dealmakers to endangered swing-seat targets, including Rep. Tom Barrett of Michigan and Reps. Rob Bresnahan and Ryan Mackenzie of Pennsylvania.</p> 
<p>“If it’s on the floor, I’ll be voting for it,” Mackenzie said.</p> 
<p>On the right flank, Reps. Eli Crane of Arizona, Warren Davidson of Ohio, Eric Burlison of Missouri and Tim Burchett of Tennessee said they planned to support the measure. (Burchett sought to pass it on a voice vote last week, but Democrats insisted on a recorded vote.)</p> 
<p>More centrist-leaning Reps. Jeff Van Drew of New Jersey, Kevin Kiley of California and Don Bacon of Nebraska said they would vote for the bill. Bacon, who is retiring, suggested the last-minute pressure campaign from the White House was ill-advised.</p> 
<p>“The train has already left the station, so we should move on,” he said.</p> 
<p>Some key GOP blocs remained split on the matter, including the hard-line House Freedom Caucus and the Republican Study Committee, composed of 189 conservatives. But the legislation is likely to get universal Democratic support in addition to considerable GOP backing, Khanna said before Trump reversed course.</p> 
<p>“While there might be pressure from the White House, there is even more pressure from the public,” he said. “People are sick of our system protecting the Epstein class.”</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu and Hailey Fuchs contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ro Khanna identifies ‘dynamic’ leaders to replace Schumer</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/16/ro-khanna-dynamic-leaders-schumer-00653885</link>
      <description>The California representative said Chuck Schumer is no longer the future of the Democratic Party.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-8d9b-d51c-a39e-ad9bad510000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 12:44:06 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0c/0a/0fbd4ab2449f9193f17e5e06949c/u-s-congress-34434.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>“The question is what is the future of Democratic leadership. Who is going to be effective? And most Democrats around the country just don't think that person is Chuck Schumer,” Rep. Ro Khanna said.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0c/0a/0fbd4ab2449f9193f17e5e06949c/u-s-congress-34434.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. Ro Khanna is buckling down on criticisms of Sen. Minority Leader Chuck Schumer, throwing his support behind bolder Democrats as he calls for a change in Democratic leadership.</p> 
<p>The California Democrat told host Kristen Welker on NBC's "Meet the Press" on Sunday that though Schumer was "terrific" under former President Joe Biden, the New York lawmaker no longer inspires confidence in Democratic voters.</p> 
<p>“The question is what is the future of Democratic leadership. Who is going to be effective? And most Democrats around the country just don't think that person is Chuck Schumer,” Khanna said.</p> 
<p> “I mean, he doesn't inspire confidence. He's not bold. He's out of touch with the grassroots. He's someone who cheer-led us into the war in Iraq. He doesn't have the moral clarity on Gaza. He couldn't say [Zohran] Mamdani's name. And this was the final straw, where he was not strong on fighting for health care.”</p> 
<p>Following the Senate’s vote to advance a variation on the House-passed stopgap last week — which passed only with the help of seven Democrats and one independent who caucuses with the party — Khanna <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/schumer-is-no-longer-effective-dems-outraged-over-shutdown-deal-00644253" target="_blank">accused Schumer of being ineffective</a> and called for his removal.</p> 
<p>On Sunday, Khanna praised some leading Senate Democrats, calling Sen. Chris Murphy (Conn.) a “top leader” and Sens. Cory Booker (N.J.) and Brian Schatz (Hawaii) “dynamic” as well as saying he “appreciates” the ideology of Sen. Elizabeth Warren (Mass.).</p> 
<p>Some Democrats have rushed to Schumer’s defense.</p> 
<p>In a separate interview with Welker on Sunday, Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.) — who voted for the resolution — said Schumer has been an “effective leader." </p> 
<p>Kaine also revealed he told Schumer ahead of the vote that he didn't need a “permission slip” from the minority leader.</p> 
<p>“Being the minority leader is tough,” said Kaine. “We don't control what's on the floor. And you know if you're dealing with senators … it's not exactly like senators just get in line and follow the leader." </p> 
<p>"I don't tell Ro Khanna or AOC or anybody else who you should pick as your House leader because I got a full-time job being a senator," Kaine added. "I don't need to freelance opinions about House leadership. They should focus on their own leadership and let senators do what we need to do to keep this country moving forward.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2025-11-15T12:50:23-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump stews and Dems gloat over feud with Marjorie Taylor Greene</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/15/trump-marjorie-taylor-greene-feud-00653448</link>
      <description>Trump and the Georgia Republican continued their back-and-forth barbs Saturday morning following a very public blowup late Friday.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-8866-d49b-af9f-bce6a5c60001</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 12:10:56 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4c/63/478bf5a943f1b9fb16f723a87f4c/u-s-congress-84520.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.) holds a MAGA hat during a press conference announcing that she will trigger a vote on her motion to remove Rep. Mike Johnson as Speaker of the House outside the U.S. Capitol on May 1, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4c/63/478bf5a943f1b9fb16f723a87f4c/u-s-congress-84520.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Gregory Svirnovskiy and Ben Johansen</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Gregory Svirnovskiy and Ben Johansen</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump escalated his feud with Rep. Marjorie Taylor Greene (R-Ga.) on Saturday, as Democrats delighted over the latest relationship to turn sour in MAGA world.</p> 
<p>“Lightweight Congresswoman Marjorie Taylor Brown (Green grass turns Brown when it begins to ROT!), betrayed the entire Republican Party when she turned Left, performed poorly on the pathetic View, and became the RINO that we all know she always was,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115553994466678093" target="_blank">Trump wrote on Truth Social</a> on Saturday.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-mtg-aca-epstein-massie-00653412?click_x=316&amp;click_y=340&amp;i=6&amp;item_height=500&amp;item_width=328&amp;proximity_active=false&amp;vct=42.167" target="_blank">Trump said he severed ties</a> with Greene on Friday, withdrawing his endorsement of the GOP firebrand and longtime ally in a series of social media posts and reposts in which he accused her of pulling away only after he convinced her not to run for Georgia’s Senate seat.</p> 
<p>Greene — who the president <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115554138689247811" target="_blank">also described</a> as “Marjorie ‘Traitor’ Green,” Saturday morning — has repeatedly bucked the party line in recent months. She’s lambasted the administration’s handling of the investigation into the late convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, criticized Trump’s focus on foreign affairs over domestic policy, lashed out at his tariffs and in July <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/29/maga-is-turning-on-israel-over-gaza-but-trump-is-unmoved-00482891" target="_blank">accused Israel of committing</a> a “genocide” amid its war against Hamas in Gaza.</p> 
<p>Democrats have cheered on the breakup between the two onetime allies, looking to further drive a wedge between the president and his base. Rep. Jasmine Crockett (D-Texas) — who has had several public brawls with Greene — <a href="https://x.com/JasmineForUS/status/1989520641729466618?t=XfWVy94NXtwbUf6Q-kvAZA&amp;s=19" target="_blank">said on Friday that this is a moment</a> where Greene should “phone a friend,” adding that “I’m here for you girl… I told you not to trust him… all he cares about is HIMself.”</p> 
<p>“The GWORLS are fighting!” she added.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jared Moskowitz (D-Fla.) <a href="https://x.com/JaredEMoskowitz/status/1989544466223382860?t=2MXh2ZsnuJnN6REb7rmwJg&amp;s=19" target="_blank">posted a meme</a> in response to one of Greene’s posts, with her face superimposed on the body of X-Men superhero Wolverine, gazing mournfully at a picture of her and Trump sharing a close embrace.<br>Greene was at one time one of Trump’s closest allies in Congress, with the president regularly praising her and promoting her political career. But this weekend’s blowup was preceded by months of simmering tension between the two, with the biggest divergence coming over Epstein.</p> 
<p>Greene was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/09/10/congress/walkinshaw-signs-jeffrey-epstein-discharge-petition-massie-khanna-00556162" target="_blank">one of just four Republicans to sign onto a discharge petition</a> to force a House vote on the full release of the files related to the late financier, who died by suicide in a New York prison in 2019.</p> 
<p>And she’s called on the White House to be more transparent.</p> 
<p>Trump has instead accused Democrats of drumming up drama over the files and fabricating a connection between him and Epstein. Trump has consistently denied any wrongdoing associated with Epstein, his onetime friend, and long said that the pair had a falling out many years before Epstein’s death.</p> 
<p>“The Democrats are doing everything in their withering power to push the Epstein Hoax again, despite the DOJ releasing 50,000 pages of documents, in order to deflect from all of their bad policies and losses, especially the SHUTDOWN EMBARRASSMENT, where their party is in total disarray, and has no idea what to do,” <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115548539359870302" target="_blank">he wrote on Friday</a>. “Some Weak Republicans have fallen into their clutches because they are soft and foolish.”</p> 
<p>Greene was unrepentant in a <a href="https://x.com/RepMTG/status/1989682180503588918" target="_blank">post on X on Saturday</a>, and said the president’s tirade wouldn’t stop her from advocating for Epstein’s victims.</p> 
<p>“I never thought that fighting to release the Epstein files, defending women who were victims of rape, and fighting to expose the web of rich powerful elites would have caused this, but here we are,” she wrote.</p> 
<p>In <a href="https://x.com/mtgreenee/status/1989694152561336688" target="_blank">a separate post</a>, she said she forgave Trump, and “will pray for him to return to his original MAGA promises.”</p> 
<p>Greene <a href="https://x.com/repmtg/status/1989735360524345421?s=46" target="_blank">later wrote that she was</a> "now being contacted by private security firms with warnings for my safety as a hot bed of threats against me are being fueled and egged on by the most powerful man in the world."</p> 
<p>Greene has long been a foil for Democrats, who have regularly lambasted her since her election in 2020 as a pro-Trump MAGA loyalist. But over the last several months they’ve repeatedly sought to elevate her criticism of the president. House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries said Friday night that Greene is “crushing” Trump, adding a go-to line from the president, “Thank you for your attention to this matter.”</p> 
<p>Rep. James Clyburn (D-S.C.) <a href="https://x.com/RepJamesClyburn/status/1989714463944024505" target="_blank">reposted Greene’s text exchange Saturday morning</a>, writing on X, “If Trump is working so hard to keep the Epstein files from coming out, how bad are they?”</p> 
<p>Trump reposted five posts referencing Greene’s break on Friday evening, including one that said Greene “chose” her side when she “joined Democrats,” adding that she “wants to better your political future in 2028 instead of helping President Trump fix this country which is why we voted for him again. Don’t let the door hit you on the way out.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House plans to vote Tuesday on releasing Epstein files</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/house-epstein-files-vote-00652964</link>
      <description>President Donald Trump has made repeated attempts to kill the effort, but a discharge petition has forced Speaker Mike Johnson's hand.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-8470-d51c-a39e-ad796bfa0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 17:47:42 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/ae/7c/acc77baf485b852ab6499fc8f48f/u-s-congress-29295.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Johnson said he plans to vote against the Epstein measure, but scores of fellow Republicans are expected to support it.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ae/7c/acc77baf485b852ab6499fc8f48f/u-s-congress-29295.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders are planning to hold a vote Tuesday on <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/house-epstein-files-vote-00647392" target="_blank">legislation to force the release of federal files</a> related to Jeffrey Epstein, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss internal plans ahead of a public announcement.</p> 
<p>The tentative scheduling decision follows a successful effort by Reps. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) and Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) to sidestep Speaker Mike Johnson and force a floor vote on their bipartisan bill to compel the Justice Department to release all of its records related to the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>President Donald Trump has made repeated attempts to kill the effort, which <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/14/trump-epstein-investigation-department-of-justice-00651851" target="_blank">continued in a series of Truth Social posts Friday</a>. But Johnson said Wednesday he intends to move quickly to hold the vote and put the matter to bed.</p> 
<p>Under the current GOP plan, the House Rules Committee would approve a procedural measure Monday night to advance eight bills for floor consideration, including language to tee up the Epstein legislation. If that measure is approved on the floor, likely early Tuesday afternoon, debate and a final vote on the Epstein bill could immediately follow. GOP leaders are considering whether to postpone the Epstein vote until Tuesday evening.</p> 
<p>Scores of Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/house-epstein-vote-gop-defections-00649624" target="_blank">expected to break ranks and support the bill</a>, which would then have to be approved by the Senate and signed by Trump to take effect. Neither is likely, but the process could drag out for weeks, extending the controversy over Trump's ties to Epstein. </p> 
<p>Epstein said in a 2019 <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/jeffrey-epstein-donald-trump-emails-00647447" target="_blank">email released by the House Oversight Committee</a> this week that Trump "knew about the girls" he was trafficking, but Trump has denied wrongdoing and there is no evidence has suggested that Trump took part in Epstein’s trafficking operation.</p> 
<p>The four Republicans who signed on to the discharge petition forcing the vote — Massie, plus Reps. Lauren Boebert of Colorado, Marjorie Taylor Greene of Georgia and Nancy Mace of South Carolina — are likely to examine Johnson's moves very closely. They could together block any procedural measure that would undercut the Epstein legislation, postpone it or otherwise alter it.</p> 
<p>That would freeze the House floor just as GOP leaders are trying to bring the House back for an aggressive work schedule following a seven-week recess ordered by Johnson amid the record government shutdown.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senators distance themselves from controversial payout provision</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/senate-republicans-phones-sue-jack-smith-00651463</link>
      <description>Only one Republican senator has public plans to sue under new legislative language House Republicans are now seeking to scrap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-7f75-d51c-a39e-ff7d44870000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 18:23:42 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/fd/91/a8bc2d9a410c9281f16dcae16a3f/u-s-congress-57423.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Budget Committee Chair Lindsey Graham (R-S.C.) speaks with reporters as he arrives for a Senate Republican Conference meeting at the U.S. Capitol on the 38th day of a government shutdown, Nov. 7, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/fd/91/a8bc2d9a410c9281f16dcae16a3f/u-s-congress-57423.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> thought he was giving Republicans a gift when he <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/john-thune-government-funding-phone-records-seizure-00646094" target="_blank">secured a provision</a> in the shutdown-ending government funding package that could award hundreds of thousands of dollars to senators subpoenaed as part of former special counsel Jack Smith’s investigation into President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>It turns out, several of them don’t want it.</p> 
<p>Of the eight known Senate Republicans whose phone records were subpoenaed as part of Smith’s probe into Trump’s 2020 election interference, only one so far — Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> of South Carolina — has announced definitive plans to take advantage of the new legislative language that would allow senators to sue the federal government for $500,000 or more if they discover their electronic records were seized without notification.</p> 
<p>“Oh definitely,” Graham said at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6if0modQ6ac" target="_blank">a news conference</a> after the passage of the government funding bill. “And if you think I'm going to settle this thing for a million dollars — no. I want to make it so painful, no one ever does this again … I’m going to pursue through the court system — remedies.”</p> 
<p>The others, however, were less enthusiastic or more opaque about their intentions. In public comments, social media posts or statements to POLITICO over the past few days, the seven remaining Senate Republicans declined to publicly commit to seeking compensation for being singled out by Smith — as the Democrats pummel the GOP for endorsing a taxpayer-funded windfall and fellow Republicans in both chambers decry the provision as poorly conceived.</p> 
<p>“I think the Senate provision is a bad idea,” said Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.) in a statement. “There needs to be accountability for the Biden DOJ’s outrageous abuse of the separation of powers, but the right way to do that is through public hearings, tough oversight, including of the complicit telecomm companies, and prosecution where warranted.”</p> 
<p>It could all soon be moot. Republicans in the House were enraged over the provision's inclusion, and Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> responded by promising to hold a vote for a bill that would repeal the legislative language. The effort is expected to pass overwhelmingly with bipartisan support.</p> 
<p>Johnson told reporters Wednesday that he had spoken with Thune about the issue earlier in the day, and that he communicated his disapproval of his Senate counterpart’s maneuvering.</p> 
<p>It’s not clear what Thune plans to do with the bill, assuming it passes the House. A person familiar with the provision’s introduction into the funding bill, who was granted anonymity to discuss private conversations, said that Senate Republicans requested that Thune include the language in the legislation.</p> 
<p>The person cited a “strong appetite” among the GOP to pursue accountability for the so-called Arctic Frost investigation, a Biden-era probe that Republicans say constituted a weaponization of the Justice Department.</p> 
<p>But as it turns out, the provision in the funding bill related to Smith’s probe is already creating political liability for Senate Republicans. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/306829" data-person-id="306829">John Rose</a> (R-Tenn.), who is running for governor of his state next year, quickly introduced legislation in the House that would reverse the provision. His challenger for the Republican nomination, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51279" data-person-id="51279">Marsha Blackburn</a>, later said she would vote for a bill to undo the language — but expressed a desire to take some legal recourse as a Smith target.</p> 
<p>“Senator Blackburn’s plan has always been to seek a declaratory judgment — not monetary damages — to prevent leftists from violating the constitutional rights of conservatives,” a spokesperson for Blackburn said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Even Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151822" data-person-id="151822">Ron Johnson</a> (R-Wis.), who is co-leading the investigation into Smith’s probe with Senate Judiciary Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51187" data-person-id="51187">Chuck Grassley</a> (R-Iowa), said that while he stood by the provision he wouldn't act on the cash opportunity.</p> 
<p>“I have no plans at this time,” he said in a statement. “If I did sue, it would only be for the purpose of using the courts to expose the corrupt weaponization of federal law enforcement by the Biden and Obama administrations. With the full cooperation in our congressional investigations from the Trump DOJ and FBI, that shouldn’t be necessary.”</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/365070" data-person-id="365070">Bill Hagerty</a> (R-Tenn.) <a href="https://x.com/SenatorHagerty/status/1989000677800947955" target="_blank">said he would not</a> seek damages nor did he want taxpayer money.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/221840" data-person-id="221840">Dan Sullivan</a> (R-Alaska) tried to distance himself from the provision's origin story, with a spokesperson saying he only learned about the payout language while reading the bill. He would support a House measure to repeal it, the spokesperson said.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66891" data-person-id="66891">Cynthia Lummis</a> also emphasized that the Wyoming Republican did not play a role in the provision’s formulation — but added that the lawmaker supported the language.</p> 
<p>“We must not allow the politicization of federal agencies to become routine,” the spokesperson said. “Liquidated damages provisions are commonly used and this provision is the only way to hold Jack Smith and wrongdoers accountable.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/374701" data-person-id="374701">Tommy Tuberville</a> (R-Ala.), another gubernatorial aspirant, pointed to the lawmaker’s statement on social media, noting that he would “sue the living hell out of every Biden official involved” if Smith was not jailed and Judge James Boasberg — who approved the effort to prevent senators from being notified of the subpoena — was not impeached.</p> 
<p>The spokesperson wasn't clear on whether Tuberville intends to sue the federal government under the provision in the funding bill.</p> 
<p>Graham, during his press conference this week, said he believed the language would benefit everyone.</p> 
<p>“This wasn’t about investigating me or other Senators for a crime — it was a fishing expedition,” Graham said. “I’m going to push back really hard … that will protect the Senate in the future.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fetterman hospitalized after sustaining ‘minor injuries’ in fall</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/pennsylvania-senator-john-fetterman-hospitalization-00650867</link>
      <description>A spokesperson said the senator was on an early morning walk near his home in Pennsylvania when he felt lightheaded and fell to the ground.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-7e8b-df0f-abfa-7feb75600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 14:50:22 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/e0/d0/5499d44043d383c32fa29f6657f7/u-s-congress-27032.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. John Fetterman speaks with reporters at the U.S. Capitol, May 2, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/e0/d0/5499d44043d383c32fa29f6657f7/u-s-congress-27032.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Faith Wardwell</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Faith Wardwell</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pennsylvania Sen. John Fetterman was hospitalized Thursday morning after falling and hitting his face, sustaining “minor injuries,” his spokesperson <a href="https://x.com/SenFettermanPA/status/1989026864862507493" target="_blank">said in a statement</a>.</p> 
<p>In a post to the Democrat's account on X, a spokesperson said Fetterman fell to the ground after feeling lightheaded on an early morning walk near his home in Braddock, Pennsylvania. He was transported to a hospital in Pittsburgh “out of an abundance of caution,” where doctors determined the dizzy spell was caused by a “ventricular fibrillation flare-up,” a heartbeat irregularity.</p> 
<p>“Senator Fetterman had this to say: ‘If you thought my face looked bad before, wait until you see it now!’” the spokesperson relayed in the post.</p> 
<p>Fetterman — who returned to his Pennsylvania home after the Senate’s vote to reopen the government on Monday — chose to stay at the hospital so doctors could “fine-tune his medication regimen,” though his team said he’s “doing well” and receiving routine observation. The post did not specify how long the senator is expected to remain at the hospital.</p> 
<p>The incident is the latest in a series of health challenges the Pennsylvania senator has faced since his campaign for the seat. He <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/15/john-fetterman-stroke-pennsylvania-senate-00032588" target="_blank">was hospitalized due to a stroke in 2022</a> just days before winning the state’s Democratic Senate primary. He also spent several nights in the hospital in 2023 for a similar lightheadedness spell, but testing showed no signs of stroke or seizure, his office said at the time.</p> 
<p>The senator <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/02/16/fetterman-hospitalized-clinical-depression-00083286" target="_blank">checked himself into</a> a hospital days later to receive inpatient care for clinical depression — something he’s lived with throughout his life and has since been vocal about in public appearances.</p> 
<p>“It’s a risk that I wanted to take because I wanted to help people and know that I don’t want them to suffer the way — or put any kinds of despair that I’ve been in. And if that conversation helps, then that’s — I’m going to continue to do that,” Fetterman <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/12/31/john-fetterman-mental-health-00133359" target="_blank">told NBC’s Kristen Welker in 2023</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Judge green-lights Rep. LaMonica McIver prosecution, ruling certain to be appealed</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/lamonica-mciver-prosecution-assault-charge-00650229</link>
      <description>The first-term Democrat was charged with assaulting law enforcement officers following a chaotic scrum outside an immigration detention facility in May.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-7de0-d51c-a39e-fde9e30d0001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 11:01:44 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/21/2c/a5e4d1cc4d59b4c4d89ffeb2590d/immigration-protest-mayor-arrested-62619.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Angelina KatsanisAP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. LaMonica McIver (D-N.J.) speaks to the press after Newark Mayor Ras Baraka was arrested while protesting at ICE's Delaney Hall Detention Facility, May 9, 2025, in Newark, New Jersey.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/21/2c/a5e4d1cc4d59b4c4d89ffeb2590d/immigration-protest-mayor-arrested-62619.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Ry Rivard and Matt Friedman</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Ry Rivard and Matt Friedman</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A federal judge on Thursday declined to toss federal assault charges against New Jersey Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/502201" data-person-id="502201">LaMonica McIver</a>.</p> 
<p>The first-term Democrat was charged with assaulting law enforcement officers following a chaotic scrum outside an immigration detention facility in May.</p> 
<p>McIver argued that the prosecution — led by Alina Habba, a former personal attorney to President Donald Trump whom he picked to be the state’s top federal prosecutor — was unfair and that she was shielded from the charges by the Constitution’s “speech or debate” clause, which grants members of Congress a form of immunity that is mostly impenetrable in investigations relating to the official duties of lawmakers.</p> 
<p>U.S. District Judge Jamel Semper, an appointee of former President Joe Biden, disagreed and refused to toss two of the three counts, while reserving judgment on a third until he sees more evidence.</p> 
<p>“Defendant’s active participation in the alleged conduct removes her acts from the safe harbor of mere oversight,” he wrote in a 41-page opinion. “Lawfully or unlawfully, Defendant actively engaged in conduct unrelated to her oversight responsibilities and congressional duties.”</p> 
<p>In a statement, McIver said she was disappointed by the decision and portrayed her prosecution as one in a series of legal attacks by the Trump administration on the president’s foes.</p> 
<p>“I am not in this fight only for myself, and I am concerned that this decision will simply embolden the administration,” she said.</p> 
<p>Her attorney, Paul Fishman, said McIver and her legal team are “evaluating next steps” in response to legal decisions they believe “are wrong.”</p> 
<p>McIver is accused in a three-count indictment of slamming a federal agent with her forearm, “forcibly” grabbing him and using her forearms to strike another agent. Allegations of physical violence by a sitting member of Congress are rare.</p> 
<p>The alleged assaults occurred during a 68-second span in the midst of a three-hour oversight visit to the Delaney Hall Detention Facility in Newark, New Jersey, when McIver and fellow Democratic Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196528" data-person-id="196528">Bonnie Watson Coleman</a> and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/424340" data-person-id="424340">Rob Menendez</a> were part of a chaotic scene as immigration agents moved to arrest city Mayor Ras Baraka on a trespassing charge that was later dropped.<br></p><video id="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/389890d4-401c-4b8a-93c7-92acdd9d4c70/d228086a-c5c8-4fdb-bcb5-e9d378312088/main.mp4" title="Rep. McIver: 'I Will Not Be Intimidated'" data-description="lead image" poster="https://cf-images.us-east-1.prod.boltdns.net/v1/static/1155968404/389890d4-401c-4b8a-93c7-92acdd9d4c70/e6b43d54-82e1-41ec-b7e8-c793ab7abc80/1280x720/match/image.jpg"><source src="http://vod.politico.com/media/v1/pmp4/static/clear/1155968404/389890d4-401c-4b8a-93c7-92acdd9d4c70/d228086a-c5c8-4fdb-bcb5-e9d378312088/main.mp4" type="video/mp4"></source></video><p>McIver’s trial was scheduled to begin earlier this week, but Semper delayed it as he weighed the complex legal issues and perhaps in anticipation of an appeal.</p> 
<p>In his written opinion, Semper seemed to draw a line between alleged contact inside a gated area at Delaney Hall, which the congressional Democrats were allowed to inspect, and actions outside, which is where agents moved to arrest Baraka and where prosecutors allege that McIver committed two crimes: assaulting an agent and impeding that arrest.</p> 
<p>The count Semper did not fully rule on involves alleged contact between McIver and an agent inside the gated area after the scrum outside the gate.</p> 
<p>The ruling — which is likely to be appealed — is a victory for Habba’s office. While she calls herself the “acting U.S. Attorney,” another judge in August ruled she was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/21/alina-habba-new-jersey-us-attorney-ruling-00518559" target="_blank">unlawfully serving</a> in that role. An appeals court is now <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/20/alina-habba-us-attorney-case-arguments-00615489" target="_blank">considering that ruling</a>.</p> 
<p>Semper also rejected a more long-shot attempt by McIver’s attorneys to dismiss the whole case based on selective prosecution. McIver’s team argued for that based on Trump pardoning hundreds of people who attacked police at the Capitol on Jan. 6, 2021, and the Justice Department dropping numerous additional assault cases at Trump’s direction, despite video evidence of the attacks.</p> 
<p>“Irrespective of the pardon, the January 6 defendants are not similarly situated to Defendant because the facts and circumstances surrounding their criminal cases are unambiguously distinct,” Semper wrote.</p> 
<p>While McIver quoted Trump and Habba’s rhetoric to claim vindictive prosecution — including Habba’s wish to “turn New Jersey red” — Semper ruled that McIver failed to demonstrate the case against her is “the result of personal animus harbored by the prosecution.”</p> 
<p>Habba did not immediately comment on the ruling.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The next shutdown threat is around the corner</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/13/shutdown-appropriations-january-30-00649414</link>
      <description>Most of the federal government will continue running on autopilot through Jan. 30, setting up another showdown.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-7a23-d51c-a39e-ff2b92e30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/7d/13/589480e7494d85d7a493bb5962a7/unlimiteduse-11-12-2025-capitol-hill-anna-rose-layden-0055.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A Capitol Police officer walks toward an entrance to the U.S. Capitol building following a vote in Washington, on Nov. 12, 2025. The House passed a short term spending bill after 43 days of a government shutdown, temporarily funding most federal agencies through Jan. 30, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/7d/13/589480e7494d85d7a493bb5962a7/unlimiteduse-11-12-2025-capitol-hill-anna-rose-layden-0055.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The longest shutdown in U.S. history is ending. Yet Congress’ most onerous government funding work remains unfinished — setting up a potential repeat early next year.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_5371" target="_blank">bipartisan deal to end the funding lapse</a> includes a long-term agreement on just three of the dozen bills lawmakers need to finish each year to keep cash flowing to federal programs. And those three measures are some of the easiest to rally around — including money for veterans programs, food aid, assistance for farmers and the operations of Congress itself.</p> 
<p>Together, they represent only about 10 percent of the roughly $1.8 trillion Congress doles out each year to federal agencies. Under the deal, everything else is funded on a temporary basis through Jan. 30 at levels first set by Congress in March 2024, when Joe Biden was president.</p> 
<p>That leaves behind major open decisions about the vast majority of discretionary dollars — including for the military and public health programs — along with the stickiest policy issues. It doesn’t help that House and Senate leaders still haven’t agreed on an overall total for fiscal 2026 spending, amid GOP divisions over how deeply to cut.</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> acknowledged this month that the hardest part of the funding negotiations is ahead after President Donald Trump signs the current deal to end the shutdown.</p> 
<p>“We've got to just find a resolution to get the lights back on,” Scalise said. “But the real negotiation is going to be: Can we get an agreement on how to properly fund the government with individual appropriations bills, packages of appropriations bills?”</p> 
<p>If lawmakers don’t figure it all out by the new January deadline, Congress risks another partial shutdown or running most of the federal government on what are essentially two-year-old budgets. Some Democrats are already hinting they are willing to shut down the government again without a deal on Affordable Care Act insurance subsidies that expire at the end of this year.</p> 
<p>Compounding the challenge are fears that partisan strife during the six-week shutdown will only complicate the already-grueling task of striking a cross-party compromise.</p> 
<p>“If we’re going to function again, we’ve got to be able to trust each other,” senior appropriator Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> (D-N.H.) told reporters this week, after helping broker the deal to end the shutdown.</p> 
<p>The three-bill deal appears to have done little to repair the breach. One of Congress’ top four appropriators, Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a> (D-Conn.), objected to how final negotiations played out over the weekend to close out the funding package.</p> 
<p>“The entire House was marginalized in this process,” she said Tuesday night during a Rules Committee meeting.</p> 
<p>DeLauro accused Senate Republicans of “abruptly” stopping talks in the middle of negotiations, making the bills public before she signed off and secretly <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/10/john-thune-government-funding-phone-records-seizure-00646094" target="_blank">adding controversial language</a> without consulting House lawmakers.</p> 
<p>In the Senate, leaders have committed to quickly advancing more funding measures. Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said senators would be “off to the races” on a second package of spending measures when the chamber gavels back in Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Up to five bills are under consideration for inclusion in that package, covering funding for the military and the departments of Education, Commerce, Labor, Health and Human Services, Justice, Transportation, Interior and Housing and Urban Development.</p> 
<p>Getting that done will be hard enough. All 100 senators would have to consent to quickly assemble the bills on the floor, likely followed by weeks of debate before a vote on passage. Then top Senate appropriators would need to strike a compromise with their House counterparts.</p> 
<p>But the remaining spending bills will be even tougher. Four are so divisive that Senate appropriators didn’t even approve them in committee this summer. Lawmakers in both parties agree it is likely that agencies covered under that slate — among them the departments of Energy, Homeland Security, State and Treasury, including the IRS — will eventually be funded through a stopgap that spans through next September.</p> 
<p>Democrats warn that any partisan demands from Trump or hard-liners in the House could deadlock the effort to reach agreements on the nine bills left.</p> 
<p>“If they want to add poison pills, obviously the whole thing will fall apart,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51658" data-person-id="51658">Chris Van Hollen</a> (D-Md.), a senior appropriator, said in a brief interview.</p> 
<p>But Democrats are also motivated to strike bipartisan deals in light of Trump and White House budget director Russ Vought’s moves this year to shift, freeze and cancel billions of dollars Congress already approved.</p> 
<p>Senators have been careful to be more explicit in the new trio of funding bills about how the Trump administration must spend the money.</p> 
<p>“Obviously, those are not the bills I would have written,” the Senate’s top Democratic appropriator, Washington Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51219" data-person-id="51219">Patty Murray</a>, said in a floor speech this week. But those bills, she added, are “immeasurably better than Trump and Vought holding the pen.”</p> 
<p>“We have a lot of work ahead, and I know we can get there — passing full-year funding bills to ensure Congress, not Trump or Russ Vought, decides how taxpayer dollars are spent,” she continued.</p> 
<p>A couple of the remaining bills, however, are subject to much more profound disputes. An intraparty disagreement over funding levels between Senate Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) and Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260075" data-person-id="260075">John Kennedy</a> (R-La.), for instance, has left the energy bill in limbo.</p> 
<p>“I know that is a new experience for everybody on the committee,” Kennedy said this week. “But I’m not backing down.”</p> 
<p>And then there’s the DHS measure, which hasn’t been unveiled, let alone advanced through committee amid a deep partisan dispute over curbing Trump’s immigration agenda.</p> 
<p>Connecticut Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51493" data-person-id="51493">Chris Murphy</a>, the top Democrat on the panel that funds DHS, said he wants “real constraints” to prevent what he calls the Trump administration’s “clearly illegal” transfers of funding to support border enforcement and mass deportations.</p> 
<p>“It's going to be really hard to get a bipartisan long-term budget,” Murphy said, pointing to $600 million the administration is now using for detaining immigrants despite Congress explicitly approving it for “non-detention” efforts.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/6774" data-person-id="6774">Katie Britt</a> of Alabama, who has clashed with Murphy as his GOP counterpart on the panel, acknowledged appropriators have “a lot of hard work in front of us” when asked this week about the challenge of advancing the next tranche of spending bills.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think anyone is naive,” she said.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Republicans plan legislative response to provision letting senators to sue over phone records</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/12/congress/next-steps-on-data-collection-00650193</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-7b2c-df0f-abfa-7b6e574e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 22:18:08 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said he told Senate Majority Leader John Thune he strongly disagreed with the Senate GOP’s inclusion of a provision in the government funding package allowing senators to sue if their electronic records are obtained without their knowledge.</p> 
<p>“I don’t think that was the smart thing to do,” Johnson told reporters Wednesday night.</p> 
<p>Of Thune, Johnson added, “I think he regretted the way it was done, and we had an honest conversation about that.”</p> 
<p>The House voted late Wednesday on legislation to end the longest government shutdown in history that included a continuing resolution to fund federal operations through Jan. 30 and a “minibus” of three full-year appropriation bills for Department of Agriculture and the FDA, the Department of Veterans Affairs and military construction projects and the legislative branch.</p> 
<p>Thune personally negotiated the inclusion of language in the legislative branch funding measure that would allow senators to receive a $500,000 payment if federal law enforcement obtains their electronic data and doesn’t notify them.</p> 
<p>It was a direct response to recent revelations that eight Republican Senators had their phone records subpoenaed during former special counsel Jack Smith’s probe into President Donald Trump’s efforts to overturn the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>But even though Republicans on both sides of the Capitol are irate over Smith’s actions and want to haul Smith before lawmakers to testify, House Republicans were caught off guard by the provision and are now seeking to have it reversed.</p> 
<p>Johnson announced Wednesday afternoon the House would vote on legislation next week to overturn it; it’s expected to pass with wide bipartisan support.</p> 
<p>Separately, House Judiciary Committee Chair Jim Jordan will hold a vote in his panel on a bill that would create stricter rules for the courts to approve non-disclosure orders often sought by federal law enforcement officials when conducting investigations. It passed the House in the previous Congress.</p> 
<p>Jordan told reporters Wednesday there was no justification for Smith to seek a non-disclosure order when obtaining the senators’ phone data around the date of the Jan. 6, 2021 attacks on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>Still, he did not appear to have an issue with clawing back the related provision in the government funding bill.</p> 
<p>“Frankly, I would just say that we should pass laws for Americans, not for any special category,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The shutdown is ending, and House Democrats are furious</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/angry-house-democrats-shutdown-00650128</link>
      <description>The sour atmosphere stands to linger as another shutdown deadline approaches and the health care fight continues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019a-7ac9-d49b-af9f-feedbd810008</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2025 20:30:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/f1/ec/a4f032654b4d88711302f0caf74d/u-s-congress-29552.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries (D-N.Y.) speaks with reporters as he departs a House Democratic Caucus meeting on the 43rd day of a government shutdown, Nov. 12, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/f1/ec/a4f032654b4d88711302f0caf74d/u-s-congress-29552.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Democrats are back at work — and, boy, are they mad.</p> 
<p>They’re mad at the Senate Democrats who cut them out of negotiations and cut the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_5371" target="_blank">deal to reopen the government</a> after a record 43-day shutdown. They’re mad at Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> for keeping the House out of session all that time for what they’re calling a “seven-week paid vacation.” And they’re mad that, after all that, there’s still no clear path forward on meeting their key demand — an extension of health insurance subsidies that expire next month.</p> 
<p>Their fury was evident across the Capitol in the 24 hours leading up to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/house-votes-to-reopen-government-after-43-day-shutdown-00649927" target="_blank">Wednesday’s decisive vote</a> reopening the government as they took stock of a long, bitter fight that ended without a clear win and left many spoiling for fights and in little mood to compromise with Republicans.</p> 
<p>That sour mood stands to linger with another shutdown deadline approaching in January and members hoping to somehow forge a bipartisan compromise on the insurance subsidies in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>“The Senate says they will have a vote [on the subsidies],” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a> (D-Conn.), the top Democrat on the Appropriations Committee. “Do I trust any of them? Hell no.”</p> 
<p>Speaking to reporters ahead of the final vote Wednesday, House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> vowed to keep up the fight — even as Democrats’ procedural options remain limited. One casualty of the shutdown was Jeffries’ once-cordial relationship with Johnson, which descended into mudslinging as the standoff ground on and frustration mounted.</p> 
<p>“Institutionally, Mike Johnson did great damage to the House of Representatives by castrating his Republican majority and keeping his extremists on a taxpayer-funded vacation for more than seven weeks,” Jeffries said.</p> 
<p>The “vacation” epithet was a popular one for Democrats returning to the Capitol this week, and it grated on the ears of Republicans who blame the other party’s intransigence for the record shutdown.</p> 
<p>During a late-night hearing Tuesday, Rules Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51389" data-person-id="51389">Virginia Foxx</a> (R-N.C.) interrupted Rep. Yassamin Ansari (D-Ariz.) after she sarcastically welcomed Republicans back from the extended recess.</p> 
<p>“I am sick and tired of hearing you say we had an eight-week vacation,” Foxx said. “I worked every day — I don’t know about you — but I don’t want to hear another soul say that.”</p> 
<p>Ansari refused to back off: “I hope you all enjoyed yourselves while American families [were] terrified that their health insurance premiums were going to double or triple,” <a href="https://x.com/Acyn/status/1988459059641806936?s=20" target="_blank">she fired back</a></p> 
<p>Adding to the partisan tension surrounding the shutdown was Johnson’s decision not only to keep the House out of session but to also not swear in Rep. Adelita Grijalva (D-Ariz) until the shutdown ended.</p> 
<p>Democrats packed the House floor for Grijalva’s swearing-in Wednesday. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/304454" data-person-id="304454">Greg Stanton</a> (D-Ariz.), introducing his new colleague, at first joked about how “it has been a minute since we have all been together” before levying more heated attacks on Johnson.</p> 
<p>“At one point, the speaker said, ‘<a href="https://www.msnbc.com/chris-jansing-reports/watch/grijalva-slams-johnson-s-bless-her-heart-dig-condescending-patronizing-misogynistic-250030149843" target="_blank">Bless her heart</a>, she is representative-elect, she doesn't know how it works around here,’” Stanton said. “Bless his heart, because here’s how it should work … When the American people vote, this chamber respects their will and seats them immediately. Politics should never come into play.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/c4/19/58c82247475d8cfc1a8d23ac8b80/unlimiteduse-11-12-2025-capitol-hill-anna-rose-layden-0023.jpg" alt="Rep. Adelita Grijalva (D-Ariz.) poses for a photo with Speaker of the House Mike Johnson (R-La.) during her ceremonial swearing-in at the U.S. Capitol in Washington, on Nov. 12, 2025." data-portal-copyright="Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="Anna Rose Layden for POLITICO" data-title="Rep. Adelita Grijalva (D-Ariz.) poses for a photo with Speaker of the House Mike Johnson (R-La.) during her ceremonial swearing-in at the U.S. Capitol in Washington, on Nov. 12, 2025."/><p>In her own speech, Grijalva criticized Republican leaders for denying her district “access to the basic services that every constituent deserves.”</p> 
<p>“This is an abuse of power,” she said. “One individual should not be able to unilaterally obstruct the swearing in of a duly elected member of congress for political reasons.”</p> 
<p>But Grijalva and Johnson were all smiles when they posed together after she was formally sworn into the House.</p> 
<p>"I really like this lady. I think she's going to be an excellent member of Congress,” Johnson said.</p> 
<p>Republicans displayed some anger of their own Wednesday. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/390300" data-person-id="390300">Mike Lawler</a> (R-N.Y.) used his floor time to decry Democrats for their “extremist” positions and sparking the record shutdown. “You should all be ashamed of yourselves for inflicting this pain on the American people … not paying our troops, our federal employees, our air traffic controllers,” he shouted. “It's a disgrace, and you should all hang your heads in shame.”</p> 
<p>That prompted a warning from Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151739" data-person-id="151739">Steve Womack</a> (R-Ark.), who was presiding over the House at the time, to cool things down: “I fully recognize that there's a lot of pent-up anxiety and emotions have been elevated somewhat, but please.”</p> 
<p>The tensions stand to color the House’s work over the coming weeks. Johnson is promising additional session days and late nights to catch up on the weeks of lost legislative time.</p> 
<p>To jump-start progress on the expiring insurance subsidies, Democrats launched a longshot procedural maneuver known as a discharge petition to force a three-year extension of the credits for a vote, but it is unlikely enough Republicans will sign on to ensure its success. More likely, any compromise will have to be forged in the Senate, something in which House Democrats showed little faith this week.</p> 
<p>And then there’s the next spending deadline, coming on Jan. 30, when many of the factors that led up to the shutdown over the last seven weeks are likely to be unchanged. Leading up to the 43-day shutdown, Democrats pushed for funding guardrails on the Trump administration in addition to the health care provisions — and got neither in the end.</p> 
<p>“I do think at some point it is important for Democrats to have a backbone and really fight for the American people,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/260811" data-person-id="260811">Ilhan Omar</a> (D-Minn.).</p> 
<p>“I'm not going to vote to endorse their cruelty,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512">Jim McGovern</a> (D-Mass.) when asked about the prospect of another shutdown. “And that’s the way I view them not extending the ACA tax credits.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries separately cautioned that a laundry list of other items on the House’s agenda, including passage of the annual defense authorization bill, could be threatened if Republicans cut Democrats out of the process.</p> 
<p>“The business of the American people must continue, but the red line will be if Republicans continue to adopt the my-way-or-the-highway approach,” he said. “At that point, we'll continue to say, ‘Get lost.’”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
