<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 15:20:20 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Rep. Salazar touts Venezuela's Machado before her visit</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/salazar-throws-support-behind-venezuela-machado-00721587</link>
      <description>The Florida Republican said Trump will be ‘highly pleased’ with the opposition leader and winner of the Nobel Peace Prize.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ae86-dca0-ad9b-ff8f70c80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 15:20:20 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="application/octet-stream" url="https://static.politico.com/ff/0b/4134def9479cbb2f3f98fb29abd2/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2250564219">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Odd Andersen/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>President Donald Trump will be "highly, highly pleased” with Maria Corina Machado when she visits Washington this week, said Rep. Maria Elvira Salazar.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/ff/0b/4134def9479cbb2f3f98fb29abd2/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2250564219" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307604" data-person-id="307604">Maria Elvira Salazar</a> on Sunday said Venezuela’s opposition leader Maria Corina Machado has “earned” enough to receive President Donald Trump’s backing as the South American country recovers from the capture of Nicolas Maduro.</p> 
<p>“She proved to the international community that they, the opposition forces, had won the election,” the Florida Republican told CBS’ “Face the Nation.”</p> 
<p>Salazar, who said she was in contact with Machado during the time she was in hiding during Maduro’s rule, added that Trump will be ”highly, highly pleased” with Machado when she visits Washington this week.</p> 
<p>“I am sure that she will have a very good, long, solid conversation with the President,” Salazar said. “I think we are going to welcome her in Congress, and I'm sure that President Trump is going to be highly, highly pleased with that meeting.</p> 
<p>Salazar’s optimism comes as the organization that oversees the Nobel Peace Prize announced Machado cannot give her recent award to Trump.</p> 
<p>Machado won the prestigious prize in October, and quickly dedicated the award to the president. Trump had repeatedly expressed his desire to be awarded the prize, particularly in light of his work to end the Israel-Hamas war and other conflicts.</p> 
<p>Trump declined to endorse Machado as the nation's new leader in the wake of the raid that netted Maduro and left Venezuela at least temporarily leaderless. But Salazar on Sunday said Machado “is part of the transition” in Venezuela now that Maduro is no longer in power — a sharp difference from Trump’s previous statements that the U.S. will run Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Salazar said there are things that the U.S. may not know about what is happening in Venezuela under Maduro’s allies, Delcy Rodríguez and Diosdado Cabello.</p> 
<p>Still, her optimism continued as she said she is confident American prisoners will soon be released.</p> 
<p>“We do not want to make any mistakes and I am sure that the political prisoners will be coming out and that we're not giving them, meaning Diosdado and Delcy, any type of leeway for them to really run the country,” said Salazar. “We will see. I happened two, three weeks ago. Let's give them a little bit more time before we see more results.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rand Paul: Bombing Iran ‘is not the answer’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/rand-paul-bombing-iran-not-the-answer-00721432</link>
      <description>“I don’t think it’s the job of the American government to be involved with every freedom movement around the world,” the Kentucky senator said.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-ae15-d65c-affb-af9761340000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 12:52:48 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8e/bb/9ae9b2134ed28a6db68a873f1ae7/u-s-congress-65498.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Rand Paul speaks during a hearing on Capitol Hill on July 15, 2025.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8e/bb/9ae9b2134ed28a6db68a873f1ae7/u-s-congress-65498.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Cheyanne M. Daniels</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Rand Paul expressed concerns Sunday over President Donald Trump’s threats to bomb Iran as the Middle Eastern country sees widespread protests continue.</p> 
<p>Speaking with ABC’s “This Week,” the Kentucky Republican said he is not sure striking Iran “will have the effects intended.”</p> 
<p>“We wish freedom and liberation the best around the world, but I don’t think it’s the job of the American government to be involved with every freedom movement around the world,” Paul said.</p> 
<p>Paul also expressed concerns over how the administration would distinguish between Iranian protesters and law enforcement if Trump were to approve military action in the region.</p> 
<p>“How do you drop a bomb in the middle of a crowd or a protest and protect the people there?” Paul said. “Plus there's the constitution that we don't let presidents bomb countries when they feel like it. They are supposed to ask the people through the Congress for permission.”</p> 
<p>Protests erupted in the Islamic Republic late last month as Iranians expressed dissatisfaction over the country’s economic free fall. But as demonstrations have continued, many have begun to demand total regime change.</p> 
<p>Reports indicate thousands have been arrested, and agencies have been unable to confirm the total death toll due to an internet blackout as the regime works to quell the dissent. <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/iranian-death-toll-spikes-00721390" target="_blank">The latest Associated Press report</a> put the figure as at least 538.</p> 
<p>Trump on Friday warned Iranian leaders, “You better not start shooting, because we’ll start shooting, too.” And an a post to Truth Social on Saturday, the president wrote that “Iran is looking at FREEDOM, perhaps like never before. The USA stands ready to help!!!”</p> 
<p>But Paul on Sunday said that U.S. involvement may unintentionally rally protesters behind the Ayatollah.</p> 
<p>“If you bomb the government, do you then rally people to their flag who are upset with the Ayatollah but then say, gosh, we can't have a foreign government invading or bombing our country?” Paul said. “It tends to have people rally to the cause.”</p> 
<p>He added that the protests are justifiable.</p> 
<p>“The best way is to encourage them and say, we would recognize a government that is a freedom-loving government, that allows free elections, but bombing is not the answer,” Paul said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How John Thune is trying to save the Senate for Republicans</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/10/john-thune-senate-midterms-campaign-00721008</link>
      <description>The Senate majority leader appeared at the U.S.-Mexico border to rekindle interest in the GOP’s legislative accomplishments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a52e-d65c-affb-afafbbb70000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/d8/0a/b24184f44185abe431eebe5a817f/thune2.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Jordain Carney/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Thune led a campaign delegation at the U.S.-Mexico border to tout provisions in the Republican megabill.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/d8/0a/b24184f44185abe431eebe5a817f/thune2.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>McALLEN, Texas — John Thune is ramping up his sales pitch as he tries to turn the GOP’s attention toward November and keeping the Senate majority.</p> 
<p>But as the majority leader campaigned along the U.S.-Mexico border Friday with a coalition of Republicans up for reelection this year, he acknowledged challenges so far in promoting the legislative centerpiece of the party’s message — not to mention what he called the midterm “headwinds” facing any party in power.</p> 
<p>Thune is betting that an aggressive campaign blitz between now and the fall, and a hopefully burgeoning economy, will help Republicans keep and potentially grow their 53-seat majority — even as voters seem indifferent about the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/house-passes-gop-megabill-00438206" target="_blank">GOP’s “big, beautiful bill”</a> and President Donald Trump struggles in sticking to a kitchen-table script.</p> 
<p>Having Republicans back home touting the party line, Thune said, will help.</p> 
<p>“Last year, our members were in many cases, for obvious reasons, in Washington, trying to get the job done,” Thune said in an interview. “But now that we're in an even-numbered year and people are out running for reelection, I think having us as a body focus very directly on the message that we're delivering to the American people is going to make a big difference.”</p> 
<p>He also acknowledged that Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/03/democrats-megabill-obbba-attacks-00439786" target="_blank">leapt out of the gate</a> last year in hammering the GOP megabill even before it was finished, adding that “they have the advantage of being the opposition party.”</p> 
<p>On Friday, Thune &amp; Co. attempted to turn the tide by highlighting the border security resources that were included in the sprawling policy package that also included tax cuts, defense spending and energy initiatives, among other legislative potpourri.</p> 
<p>Republicans started out the 2026 cycle as <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/10/04/republicans-senate-2026-primaries-thune-trump-00593428" target="_blank">odds-on favorites for keeping control</a> of the Senate. They still have an edge, according to most forecasters. But Democrats have made a dent in the GOP’s advantage by securing big-name recruits in key races as Republicans face some heated and costly intraparty primaries.</p> 
<p>Success will depend in large part on the Republicans who joined Thune Friday in Texas. Michael Whatley, who is running to succeed North Carolina Sen. Thom Tillis, and former Rep. Mike Rogers, who is looking to flip the seat held by retiring Democratic Sen. Gary Peters in Michigan, joined several in-cycle GOP incumbents, including Texas Sen. John Cornyn.<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/8d/aa/0edf59d246ffa279b06d903c9937/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/2161701949" alt="Former RNC chair Michael Whatley is among the Republican candidates Thune is counting on." data-portal-copyright="Angela Weiss/Getty Images" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="" data-licensor-name="AFP via Getty Images" data-title="Former RNC chair Michael Whatley is among the Republican candidates Thune is counting on."/><p>Thune showered particular praise on Cornyn, who is fighting for his political life in a three-way primary. Underscoring the nasty internal fight facing the GOP, rival Ken Paxton — the state attorney general and one of Cornyn’s primary opponents — accused Cornyn of trying to “rewrite history” with the border trip and predicted that his career will end in “national embarrassment.”</p> 
<p>Thune’s effort to use his bully pulpit to focus on the party’s legislative accomplishments comes as Republicans continue to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/21/republicans-trump-vance-megabill-00516964" target="_blank">fret that they haven’t done enough</a> to sell the megabill. Many wonder in hindsight whether their decision to pack so many priorities together into a single piece of legislation — a decision driven in part by the party-line budget reconciliation process — was ill-conceived.</p> 
<p>“We’ve talked about that,” Sen. Mike Rounds (R-S.D.) said in an interview Friday on the sidelines of a news conference at the border wall where it took four placards to display all the highlights from the megabill.</p> 
<p>“Secure Border, More Money, New Opportunities,” read a sign on the podium summarizing the legislation.</p> 
<p>But an overstuffed domestic policy bill is far from the top concern for Republicans who remain nervous about addressing Americans’ anxieties about the steeply rising cost of living.</p> 
<p>While many GOP leaders spent the final months of 2025 vowing to focus on affordability issues — and Thune vowed Friday Republicans would in 2026 — the opening days of the year have been focused abroad after Trump ousted Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro. The military action sparked a fiery debate in Congress about presidential war powers that threaten to blot out other matters.</p> 
<p>“It’s certainly going to consume the news cycle for a while,” said Sen. John Hoeven of North Dakota in an interview in the Capitol this week.</p> 
<p>It certainly has preoccupied Trump, who <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/trump-war-powers-republicans-election-00716332" target="_blank">lashed out at five Senate Republicans</a> who joined with Democrats Thursday to advance a measure constraining his future military moves in Venezuela. One of them, Susan Collins of Maine, is up for reelection, and Trump announced publicly that she and the other four “should never be elected to office again.”</p> 
<p>Thune <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/john-thune-trump-war-powers-00719369" target="_blank">said he had a “very spirited” conversation</a> with Trump before he delivered the attacks and acknowledged his frustrations. But Thune said he was focused on keeping Republicans “united as much as possible and work[ing] with the president.”<br></p><img src="https://static.politico.com/24/86/b934239c498b8fc4bc72d39f4310/white-house-46217.jpg" alt="Trump and Thune had a productive working relationship in 2025." data-portal-copyright="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-has-syndication-rights="0" data-license-id="25199838746217" data-licensor-name="Francis Chung/POLITICO" data-title="Trump and Thune had a productive working relationship in 2025."/><p>The two are viewed as having a good personal relationship, with Trump publicly praising Thune throughout 2025 — a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/03/14/john-thune-south-dakota-profile-00223248" target="_blank">transformation from just a few years before</a>, when Trump threatened to back a primary challenger against the South Dakotan. Thune, in turn, repeatedly praised Trump and his work on the border Friday.</p> 
<p>That doesn’t mean they don’t have their differences. Thune, with the backing of his conference, has rebuffed Trump’s demands to nix the filibuster and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/12/11/congress/b-00686585" target="_blank">other Senate norms</a> that preserve minority power. They have also clashed on policy — most conspicuously on the president’s aggressive use of tariffs which have negatively impacted farmers in Thune’s home state.</p> 
<p>Thune acknowledged they sometimes don’t see eye-to-eye but added he views his job as needing to “protect the institution … maintain it as the founders intended as a check and balance.”</p> 
<p>Thune reiterated Friday that he’s labored to hash out most of those differences behind the scenes, seeking to avoid any public blowups that would suck up political oxygen and potentially force his members to choose sides.</p> 
<p>That said, he added, “there are times, yes, where you have to push back” — pointing back to the conversation on the war powers resolution, which Thune opposed.</p> 
<p>Pushing back could be trickier in an election year, when Republicans need to be in lockstep as they make their case for another two years in power on Capitol Hill while Trump seeks to lock in a presidential legacy and otherwise enforce his will over the party.</p> 
<p>Beyond dealing with Trump’s angry outburst, Thune is trying to keep the party — and the president — singing from the same hymnal heading into November.</p> 
<p>“Obviously, yesterday he was frustrated, but I think there's going to be a lot to point to in terms of a record of accomplishment for him and for him working with us,” Thune said of Trump. “As we get out there and talk about it, I think it’ll start to change the perceptions and the views in the public.”</p> 
<p><i>Alex Gangitano contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>John Thune and Donald Trump had a ‘spirited’ conversation over Senate war powers vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/john-thune-trump-war-powers-00719369</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a442-d15b-abff-fc5e798a0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 14:45:09 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>McALLEN, Texas — Shortly after <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">five Republican senators</a> broke with Donald Trump and voted Thursday to advance a measure constraining his military options in Venezuela, the president lashed out and called for them to lose their seats.</p> 
<p>Before he turned to Truth Social, however, he connected with John Thune and gave him a piece of his mind.</p> 
<p>The Senate majority leader acknowledged the “very spirited” conversation with the angry president in an interview Friday after appearing with several Republican senators and candidates along the U.S.-Mexico border to promote last year’s GOP megabill.</p> 
<p>“There’s a level of frustration at the White House — and with us, too, on a vote like that,” he said.</p> 
<p>A White House spokesperson did not immediately respond to a request for comment.</p> 
<p>The war-powers fight is hardly over — the Senate still needs to debate and pass the resolution that was advanced Thursday, and even if the House passes it, which is unlikely, Trump could still veto it. But the surprising procedural vote contributed to a narrative that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/donald-trump-congress-weak-00718030" target="_blank">Trump is losing his grip</a> on congressional Republicans after running roughshod over potential GOP renegades in 2025.</p> 
<p>Two of the five senators — Rand Paul of Kentucky and Lisa Murkowski of Alaska — supported a previous effort to rein Trump in on Venezuela. Three others — Susan Collins of Maine, Josh Hawley of Missouri and Todd Young of Indiana — were more surprising.</p> 
<p>Thune declined to predict whether he would be able to flip at least two to block the resolution’s passage next week, but he signaled a lobbying effort is underway.</p> 
<p>“Obviously we’d love to have some of our colleagues come back around on that issue,” he said. “The constitutional questions, the legal questions, are being more sufficiently answered as people have probed into it.”</p> 
<p>But he added that, for his part, no grudges would be held — no matter the outcome.</p> 
<p>“The most important vote isn’t the last vote, it’s the next vote,” he said. “At the end of the day, there are going to be a lot more votes coming, and circumstances in which we’re going to have our team united as much as possible and work with the president.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Oversight GOP threatens to hold Clintons in contempt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/clintons-in-contempt-00719084</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a3ca-da56-afff-afdab5460000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 12:34:31 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Republican-led House Oversight and Government Reform Committee is threatening to hold former President Bill Clinton and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton in contempt of Congress if they fail to appear for closed-door depositions next week as part of the panel’s investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>The panel previously issued a subpoena for Bill Clinton, who has been tied to Epstein, to appear before congressional investigators Jan. 13; Hillary Clinton has been provided a subpoena to testify Jan. 14. But a committee spokesperson said Friday that, so far, neither had confirmed they would participate.</p> 
<p>“They are obligated under the law to appear and we expect them to do so,” the spokesperson said in a statement. “If the Clintons do not appear for their depositions, the House Oversight Committee will initiate contempt of Congress proceedings.”</p> 
<p>This seldom-used congressional power can range in implications from a symbolic action to a precursor to forcing jail time.</p> 
<p>In examples of the potential serious consequences to contempt of Congress charges, two Trump associates, Steve Bannon and Peter Navarro, were sentenced to prison time for failing to cooperate with subpoenas from the Democratic-led select committee investigating the Jan. 6, 2021 attacks on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>The GOP-controlled House voted to hold former Attorney General Merrick Garland <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/06/12/congress/house-gop-clears-garland-contempt-00163046" target="_blank">in contempt in 2024</a> over the Justice Department’s decision not to provide the audio of then-President Joe Biden’s interview with former special counsel Robert Hur.</p> 
<p>The Biden-era DOJ did not prosecute the case, and that audio was ultimately released by the Trump-era department.</p> 
<p>A lawyer for the Clintons did not immediately return a request for comment.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Bill Clinton <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/1148357927625023490" target="_blank">has insisted the former president</a> did not know about Epstein’s crimes and that, as of 2019, had not spoken to Epstein in over a decade. In wake of the initial release of materials in the Justice Department's possession in the Epstein case in which Bill Clinton appeared in multiple photos, the same spokesperson has called for the Trump administration to release all materials in its possession related to the former president.</p> 
<p>“We need no such protection,” <a href="https://x.com/angelurena/status/2003166064969154839" target="_blank">the statement read</a>.</p> 
<p>Sara Guerrero, a Democratic spokesperson for the panel, said in a statement Friday, “Oversight Democrats have always said that the Committee is willing to talk to any person who has information about Jeffrey Epstein. We support former President Bill Clinton’s calls on President Trump to direct Attorney General Bondi to immediately release the full Epstein files, including any material including the former President."</p> 
<p>She added, "Compliance with subpoenas from Congress are important and critical to our investigation."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jim Jordan commits to public hearing for Jack Smith</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/jack-smith-will-testify-in-public-00718945</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a392-d15b-abff-ffde6f3b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 11:32:15 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Judiciary Chair Jim Jordan said in an interview Friday he will invite former special counsel Jack Smith to testify in an open hearing as soon as this month in what would be a politically high-stakes event for members of both parties and the White House.</p> 
<p>“He’s coming in,” the Ohio Republican said of Smith, who led the federal criminal cases against President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>Smith <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/17/jack-smith-trump-deposition-congress-00694730" target="_blank">sat for over eight hours</a>, with breaks, before Judiciary Committee members and staff investigators last month behind closed doors while his legal team has repeatedly requested a public forum for their client to argue his case.</p> 
<p>Jordan <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/31/takeaways-jack-smith-congressional-testimony-00708747" target="_blank">released a transcript</a> and video record on New Year’s Eve and said Friday he now wants Smith to stand before the public and defend his claims of misconduct against the president.</p> 
<p>Smith found Trump guilty of working to circumvent the results of the 2020 election, mishandling classified documents and obstruction of justice, but was forced to drop the charges when Trump won reelection in 2024.</p> 
<p>“One of the key takeaways in the transcript is, we said, ‘did you [have] any evidence that President Trump was responsible for the violence that took place at the Capitol?’ He had no evidence of that whatsoever,” Jordan said of the committee’s December interview with Smith.</p> 
<p>Jordan said he is eager for Smith to answer that question, and others, before live cameras.</p> 
<p>When asked during his deposition whether he had evidence that Trump instructed rioters to storm the Capitol on Jan. 6, 2021, Smith responded that "our evidence is that he, in the weeks leading up to January 6th, created a level of distrust ... to get people to believe fraud claims that weren't true. He made false statements to State legislatures, to his supporters in all sorts of contexts."</p> 
<p>Lanny Breuer, one of Smith’s lawyers and a partner at the firm Covington &amp; Burling, said in a statement that “Jack has been clear for months he is ready and willing to answer questions in a public hearing about his investigations into President Trump’s alleged unlawful efforts to overturn the 2020 election and his mishandling of classified documents.”</p> 
<p>Republicans have been going after Smith for years with allegations that he was presiding over a partisan witch hunt with the support of the Biden administration, but they have redoubled their efforts after revelations that Smith’s office secretly obtained phone records for GOP lawmakers in the days around the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the Capitol.</p> 
<p>Smith has maintained he never spoke to Biden or White House staff during his investigation.</p> 
<p>Smith defended his work last month to House Judiciary members and staff, but his testimony was hamstrung, in part, by a federal court order that has kept the second volume of his report surrounding the classified documents case under seal. He has maintained he is interested in sharing the results of this investigation, but the Justice Department has interpreted that the order precludes him from discussing details with Congress.</p> 
<p>These potential restrictions on his testimony back in December will likely be the same for a public hearing in the near future.</p> 
<p>Rep. Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the House Judiciary Committee, is celebrating the opportunity for Smith to discuss his work publicly, believing he has information that will damage the president.</p> 
<p>“After Republicans forced Jack Smith into a backroom interrogation and rejected our calls for an open public hearing, now they decide they want a public hearing with Jack Smith after all," Raskin said in a statement. "Their backroom strategy backfired in historic fashion."</p> 
<p>"Even with many hours of private testimony, Republicans could not lay a glove on Jack Smith, his evidence, or his case. That will not change now that they have finally heeded our call to have him come testify publicly," he added. "This upcoming hearing is a win for truth-seeking Americans and yet another looming humiliation for Donald Trump and Congressional Republicans, who depend on a daily diet of lies to keep their administration afloat.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson says Minneapolis shooting appears to be ‘self-defense’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/mike-johnson-on-minneapolis-shooting-00718731</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a328-d65c-affb-ababb89f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 09:42:20 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson told reporters Friday there needs to be "a full investigation" into the shooting death of a woman in Minneapolis by an ICE agent while asserting that the officer was "operating in self-defense."</p> 
<p>Johnson said he understood many people on social media, including "elected officials," are commenting on the video of the shooting. "But we all understand there has to be a full investigation," he added. "That's the appropriate thing. That will happen."</p> 
<p>Johnson quickly added it "appears to us that the officer involved was operating in self-defense" and "he made a snap judgment, as they do." </p> 
<p>He also mentioned reports that the ICE officer responsible for the shooting had been involved an incident last year where <a href="https://www.startribune.com/ice-agent-who-fatally-shot-woman-in-minneapolis-is-identified/601560214" target="_blank">he had been dragged by a car and injured</a> and thus had reason to think his life "was in danger."</p> 
<p>"We'll have to see," Johnson said, referring to the investigation.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: GOP pushes back on Trump</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/09/congress/gop-pushback-trump-votes-health-care-war-powers-00718544</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-a111-d15b-abff-fd5f85040000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Donald Trump’s grip on congressional Republicans is slipping.</p> 
<p>A series of rebukes on the Hill on Thursday highlighted how rank-and-file Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/donald-trump-congress-weak-00718030" target="_blank">starting to move with less regard</a> for the president heading into the midterms.</p> 
<p>Here’s what comes next on three fronts:</p> 
<p><b>— Bringing back ACA credits:</b> Seventeen House Republicans <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/17-republicans-vote-to-restore-lapsed-obamacare-subsidies-00717497" target="_blank">broke ranks</a> to support a clean three-year restoration of enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies that expired last month. The <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/the-gops-obamacare-defectors-were-more-numerous-than-expected-00718102" target="_blank">bigger-than-anticipated revolt</a> showed how politically dangerous skyrocketing insurance premiums could be.</p> 
<p>The bill is expected to die in the Senate, as Majority Leader John Thune has no plans to bring it up for a vote.</p> 
<p>But the Republican proponents hope the strong bipartisan support pushes the Senate to produce its own ACA solution. Senators are considering a plan that would reestablish the credits for two years with reforms. Text could come as soon as Tuesday, per Sen. Bernie Moreno (R-Ohio), as lawmakers race to get a deal over the finish line before open enrollment ends Jan. 15 in most states.</p> 
<p><b>— Limiting Trump's war powers:&nbsp;</b>The Senate gave one of its strongest admonishments of the president Thursday when five Republicans helped advance a measure to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">constrain Trump’s military action abroad</a>. An outraged president took to social media to say they “should never be elected to office again.”</p> 
<p>The measure now heads to a final Senate vote next week. But it would still need to pass the House, which could prove more challenging. If Thursday’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/trump-vetoes-sustained-00717160" target="_blank">failed veto override votes</a> were any indication, House Republicans are less willing to break with the administration than their Senate counterparts.</p> 
<p>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) told POLITICO he was “inclined” to support the war powers resolution after this week’s briefings on the Venezuela operation, but that Trump’s Thursday attack was a tipping point.</p> 
<p>“Reading the ugly response to those senators sort of convinced me to vote yes,” he said.</p> 
<p>The House may soon vote on its own war powers measure from Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.). </p> 
<p><b>— Installing the Jan. 6 plaque:&nbsp;</b>The Senate voted Thursday to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/senate-unanimous-approves-jan-6-plaque-law-enforcement-00717799" target="_blank">unanimously approve a measure</a>, led by Sens. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) and Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.), to install a plaque in the Capitol honoring the officers who protected it on Jan. 6, 2021.</p> 
<p>The stark moment of bipartisanship was a significant rebuke of Speaker Mike Johnson and the Trump DOJ, which argues the plaque — which has been made but not installed — does not comply with a 2022 law mandating its display because it lists the departments that responded, not individual officers.</p> 
<p>The resolution does not need House approval, but it does put pressure on Johnson. It’s unclear when the Senate will install the plaque, which will remain in the chamber until a permanent location is identified on the west front of the Capitol.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Thune’s border trip: </b>Thune is leading a trip to the border in Texas on Friday with several GOP senators and Senate hopefuls to sell the “big, beautiful bill” Republicans passed last summer. <b>&nbsp;</b></p> 
<p><b>— Funding progress: </b>Appropriators hope to release bill text Sunday night of the next spending package they want to pass before the month-end funding cliff. It’s expected to include the State-Foreign Operations, Financial Services and Homeland Security bills, though the DHS portion is in flux after an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent fatally shot a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney, Nicholas Wu, Lisa Kashinsky, Simon J. Levien, Hailey Fuchs and Katherine Tully-McManus contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Donald Trump can’t count on Congress to have his back any more</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/donald-trump-congress-weak-00718030</link>
      <description>Republicans dealt the president a series of rebukes Thursday that cast fresh doubt about his sway on Capitol Hill.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9ff7-da56-afff-9ff77b320000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 18:48:14 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/6f/0c/3b154a8d4d7a85593d016dfa96e0/u-s-congress-70134.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) voted to constrain Trump's war powers then brushed off a presidential attack. “I love the president," he said. "I understand he’s ticked.”</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/6f/0c/3b154a8d4d7a85593d016dfa96e0/u-s-congress-70134.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill, Jordain Carney and Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A cadre of congressional Republicans dealt President Donald Trump significant defeats Thursday — a series of rebukes that demonstrate <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/06/donald-trump-lame-duck-00639349" target="_blank">how his iron grip</a> on Capitol Hill has weakened at the start of a critical election year.</p> 
<p>The defiance kicked off in the Senate with a stunning vote, backed by <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">five GOP senators</a>, to move ahead with a measure that would constrain Trump on a matter he has presented as a signature triumph — his military intervention in Venezuela. Later in the day, 17 House Republicans joined with Democrats to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/17-gop-defections-on-obamacare-vote-00717883" target="_blank">rescue Obamacare subsidies</a> Trump has repeatedly railed against.</p> 
<p>And in a surprise move, senators of both parties agreed unanimously to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/senate-unanimous-approves-jan-6-plaque-law-enforcement-00717799" target="_blank">erect a plaque</a> honoring the officers who fought the mob at the Capitol on Jan, 6, 2021 — breaking from Trump's false narrative about that day.</p> 
<p>Trump took notice of the disloyalty in the first instance. Almost immediately, he shot off a social media post accusing the five Republicans of “attempting to take away our Powers to fight and defend the United States of America” and declaring that they “should never be elected to office again.”</p> 
<p>None of the Republicans who voted crosswise with the White House Thursday said they intended to deal a personal brushback to Trump. But several said they were determined to assert congressional authority that many on Capitol Hill fear has withered over the past year.</p> 
<p>Sen. Todd Young of Indiana insisted “any future commitment of U.S. forces in Venezuela must be subject to debate and authorization in Congress.”</p> 
<p>“President Trump campaigned against forever wars, and I strongly support him in that position,” Young said in a statement. “A drawn-out campaign in Venezuela involving the American military, even if unintended, would be the opposite of President Trump’s goal of ending foreign entanglements.”</p> 
<p>Speaking at the White House after the Senate vote, Vice President JD Vance rejected the notion that Trump’s grip on Congress was slipping, saying the GOP opposition was “based more on a legal technicality than any disagreement on policy.”</p> 
<p>But the internal GOP dissent came to the delight of Democratic leaders, who are growing jubilant over their ability to highlight the splits and hammer Republicans heading into the midterms.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries told reporters “Republicans need to get their act together in terms of their leadership,” saying the party had been badly distracted from addressing Americans’ cost-of-living concerns.</p> 
<p>After the war powers vote, Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer hailed it as “a critical step” for the chamber in “reasserting its constitutional authority" and pushing back on an imperious president.</p> 
<p>Still, there were signs that Trump’s sway over the GOP had not entirely eroded.</p> 
<p>Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.), while voting to constrain Trump’s war powers, downplayed the break and reiterated multiple times that he supports the president.</p> 
<p>“I don’t take any offense to that,” he said about Trump’s suggestion that he should not be reelected. “I think the president is great. I love the president. … I understand he’s ticked.”</p> 
<p>And in a particularly stark demonstration of Trump’s continued sway over the House GOP, most Republicans in the chamber voted with him Thursday to sustain his veto of two bills they had allowed to pass unanimously just weeks before.</p> 
<p>One bill <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/2025/12/congressional-bill-h-r-504-vetoed/" target="_blank">benefited the Miccosukee Tribe</a> of Florida, which opposed his administration’s attempt to build a vast migrant detention center in the Everglades. Another <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefings-statements/2025/12/congressional-bill-h-r-131-vetoed/" target="_blank">authorized a water project</a> backed by Colorado politicians who have clashed with Trump, including Democratic Gov. Jared Polis and GOP Rep. Lauren Boebert.</p> 
<p>“I am disappointed to see the lack of leadership, the amount of people that will fold, that will cave, that will not take a stand,” Boebert said after the vote. “This had nothing to do with policy. … Folks are afraid of getting a mean tweet or attacked.”</p> 
<p>Some House Republicans who opposed the veto override cited White House officials who circled the chamber as the votes unfolded. It was clear they were taking note of the defectors, one GOP lawmaker said. Trump going nuclear on the five Republican senators who had defied him earlier in the day helped convince others to not stick their neck out.</p> 
<p>“It wasn't worth it,” another House Republican said. “It's not my bill.”</p> 
<p>Still, 35 Republicans broke ranks with Trump on the Colorado project while 24 did so on the tribal bill. Two committee chairs voted to override both vetoes.</p> 
<p>Later in the day, a critical mass of House Republicans sent an incontrovertible message on an issue much more central to the GOP’s midterm prospects than expanding a tribal reservation — addressing health care costs.</p> 
<p>Seventeen GOP members joined with Democrats to pass a bill that would revive lapsed Obamacare tax credits for three years. Trump, with the encouragement of Republican leaders on Capitol Hill, has <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/09/gop-obamacare-subsidies-expire-00684115" target="_blank">refused to engage in bipartisan negotiations</a> — instead slamming the subsidies as wasteful and calling on lawmakers to set up an alternate system where Americans get direct payments to help afford coverage.</p> 
<p>But multiple Republicans, while still blaming Democrats for the morass, said Thursday they were not willing to stand by and do nothing amid the standoff. The expired subsidies were used by more than 20 million Americans, lowering their premiums in many cases by thousands of dollars per year.</p> 
<p>“I have a bunch of my constituents that are depending on these programs, and I'm not going to leave them hanging because the Democrats broke the damn system,” said GOP Rep. Derrick Van Orden, who represents a swing Wisconsin district and referred to the bill as a “bridging mechanism.”</p> 
<p>Asked if his vote could be seen as a rebuke of Trump, Van Orden said he “didn't even think of it like that.”</p> 
<p>Republicans were similarly roundabout when it came to the Senate’s action Thursday to display the contentious Jan. 6 plaque, which was created pursuant to a 2022 law but has remained in storage as Speaker Mike Johnson refuses to install it.</p> 
<p>But the timing spoke volumes, coming two days after the fifth anniversary of the Capitol attack and the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422" target="_blank">White House publication of a website</a> casting the riot as the fault of Democrats and the Capitol Police itself.</p> 
<p>Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.), without mentioning Trump, said the plaque was a commemoration of “what I would consider to be one of the most significant stress tests for this institution since it was founded."</p> 
<p>"It was a great day for democracy because of the law enforcement officers,” he said. “We took a brief recess, we got ourselves together, the Capitol was secured and before we left the compound we came back and completed our constitutional duty" to certify the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>Meanwhile, the fallout of the war powers vote is likely to continue. Thursday’s vote sets up final consideration of the resolution next week, where Trump’s commitment to an “America First” foreign policy will be debated. In addition to the pushback on his plans for Venezuela, many Republicans aired deep misgivings this week about his overt attempts to seize control of Greenland, a Danish territory.</p> 
<p>The House is on track to take up a similar vote later this month after Democrats introduced a companion measure Thursday and expressed cautious optimism that more Republicans might vote to constrain the president.</p> 
<p>Rep. Don Bacon (R-Neb.) said he was already “inclined” to support the war powers resolution after hearing from top administration officials in briefings this week and after hearing about Trump’s threats against Greenland. But he said the president’s attack on the five GOP senators Thursday cemented his position.</p> 
<p>“Reading the ugly response to those senators sort of convinced me to vote yes,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>Mia McCarthy and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate unanimously approves installing Jan. 6, 2021 plaque</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/senate-unanimous-approves-jan-6-plaque-law-enforcement-00717799</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9fac-d65c-affb-bfaf86130000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:50:24 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate unanimously approved a measure Thursday to display an existing plaque honoring the officers who protected the Capitol during the Jan. 6, 2021 riot.</p> 
<p>Congress passed a law in March 2022 mandating the plaque, but years later it has yet to be installed. Speaker Mike Johnson has argued the project is "not implementable," and the Justice Department has maintained in litigation that an existing plaque does not comply with the law because it lists the departments who responded, not the individual officers.</p> 
<p>The measure on Thursday, led by Sen. Thom Tillis (R-N.C.) and Jeff Merkley (D-Ore.), sought to address the long-running political squabble.</p> 
<p>“On January 6, 2021, courageous law enforcement officers from the United States Capitol Police and other agencies risked their lives to defend the United States Capitol and protect Members of Congress and their staff,” Tillis said in a statement. “Prominently displaying this plaque in the United States Senate ensures their heroism and sacrifice are properly recognized.”</p> 
<p>It’s not clear when the Senate will install the plaque, which will remain in the Senate until a permanent location is identified on the west front of the Capitol. The resolution does not need to be approved by the House.</p> 
<p>The stark moment of bipartisanship came just after the 5-year anniversary of the Capitol attack was <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/january-6-anniversary-capitol-riot-00713422" target="_blank">marred by political bickering</a>. The White House published a website to rebut the narrative of the riot filled largely with false information, and Republicans continued to villainize the previous Democratic-led Jan. 6 committee that investigated the attack in its aftermath.</p> 
<p>At the beginning of his second term, President Donald Trump, who has repeatedly downplayed and mischaracterized the attack, pardoned those who took part in the riot, including some convicted of violent offenses.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-08T18:30:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>17 Republicans vote to restore lapsed Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/17-republicans-vote-to-restore-lapsed-obamacare-subsidies-00717497</link>
      <description>Democrats and moderate Republicans hope the bill's passage will put pressure on the Senate to come up a bipartisan compromise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9fb5-d65c-affb-bfb7c2f80001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:24:39 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/0b/c5/72ecd1634b34b7dc6aaa0dfe2e45/u-s-congress-54112.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.) and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries (D-N.Y.) hold a press conference on Capitol Hill Jan. 8, 2026. (Francis Chung/POLITICO via AP Images)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/0b/c5/72ecd1634b34b7dc6aaa0dfe2e45/u-s-congress-54112.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Benjamin Guggenheim and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Seventeen Republicans joined Democrats in passing legislation Thursday that would revive enhanced Affordable Care Act subsidies for three years, rebuffing opposition from GOP leadership.</p> 
<p>The 230-196 vote <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/house-advances-three-year-extension-of-obamacare-subsidies-00714710" target="_blank"><u>follows a procedural vote</u></a> Wednesday to advance the bill, where nine Republicans joined Democrats in favor of moving forward.</p> 
<p>Thursday’s final passage vote had eight additional Republicans supporting the bill, including House Homeland Security Chair Andrew Garbarino of New York and Rep. David Joyce of Ohio, a senior appropriator.</p> 
<p>The vote was met with applause and loud cheering from Democrats, who said it was a vindication of their party’s strategy to pursue a clean extension of the subsidies.</p> 
<p>“This is a tribute to [House Minority Leader] Hakeem Jeffries and our leadership, and to every member of our caucus who stood for him,” said Rep. Jim McGovern (D-Mass.) after the vote.</p> 
<p>While the measure is destined to die in the Senate, Democrats and some Republicans hope it will lay the groundwork for a bipartisan agreement to tame skyrocketing health insurance premiums — the result of Congress allowing the tax credits to lapse Dec. 31.</p> 
<p>“The Senate could put together a product that could ultimately get sent back over to the House that we can then conference on and hopefully move across the finish line,” said Rep. Rob Bresnahan (R-Pa.), who supported the Democratic-led bill.</p> 
<p>A bipartisan group of senators are scrambling to make headway on that framework that could extend the credits while instituting new income caps for eligibility and lengthening the ACA open enrollment period to soften the blow of premium hikes.</p> 
<p>Earlier Thursday, members of the bipartisan House Problem Solvers Caucus met with senators to discuss a potential solution. Rep. Jeff Hurd (R-Colo.) said that the meeting — and senators’ plea to show a strong force on this vote in the House — influenced his decision to vote for the measure after initially being inclined to vote against it.</p> 
<p>“There was a sentiment conveyed that if we could get a bill out of the House that had a meaningful amount of bipartisan support, that that would increase the likelihood that the Senate would take this up, pass a bill that has some reforms in it, and send it back,” Hurd said in an interview about the message communicated during the bicameral meeting.</p> 
<p>The lawmakers continue to project optimism about reaching a deal, though thorny issues remain over how to address the so-called Hyde amendment, which restricts federal funding for abortion. Rep. Nicole Malliotakis, a centrist New York Republican who opposed the Thursday vote, said she continued to be concerned about “how riddled with abuse and fraud” the subsidy program is.</p> 
<p>“We need to do something that actually simultaneously reins in insurance companies,” she said.</p> 
<p>Democrats hope the House vote will pressure Republican leaders in both chambers to compromise on the issue. At a news conference Thursday morning, Jeffries and Chuck Schumer blasted Republicans for repeatedly refusing to back a clean extension before the subsidies expired last year.</p> 
<p>“The American people should ask [Senate Majority Leader John Thune], ‘Are you willing to put this bill that the House now is moving forward on the floor of the Senate?’” Schumer said. “Most of the Republicans in the House and the Senate want to put poison pill riders about abortion on it. They are standing in the way.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries is now especially emboldened, having made the calculation last fall that enough centrist Republicans would join Democrats in supporting a discharge petition to circumvent their own leadership and force a vote on three-year extension legislation.</p> 
<p>And in a sign the pressure campaign might be working, Rep. Derrick Van Orden (R-Wis.) said Thursday night he couldn’t ignore the reality on the ground any longer.</p> 
<p>“I have a bunch of my constituents that are depending on these programs, and I'm not going to leave them hanging because the Democrats broke the damn system,” he said.</p> 
<p>The question of whether to extend the enhanced subsidies, which were established in a 2021 Covid relief package under a Democratic majority, has been one of the most divisive policy issues of the 119th Congress.</p> 
<p>Republican moderates <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/09/15/kiggans-house-gop-aca-00561747" target="_blank"><u>started raising alarms early in the fall that their constituents</u></a> were staring down massive premium spikes in 2026 due to the looming expiration of the subsidies. But they quickly encountered strong headwinds from conservatives who lambasted the credits as rife with fraud and giveaways to insurance companies — a message that has been echoed by Speaker Mike Johnson and House Majority Leader Steve Scalise.</p> 
<p>Johnson’s office, in a last-ditch effort Thursday morning to undermine the effort, blasted out a memo accusing “Democrats [of] want[ing] to expand a COVID subsidy system already flagged for massive fraud and abuse, with absolutely zero reforms.”</p> 
<p>After the vote Thursday evening, Johnson said in an interview of the Republicans who defected, “I think it's a really bad policy, and I wish they hadn't, but everybody had a vote.”</p> 
<p>Last fall, Johnson finally extended GOP moderates the opportunity to have a floor vote on an amendment to a Republican-authored bill intended to lower health care costs, but talks broke down. It led four Republicans to agree to help Democrats get the requisite 218 signatures on their discharge petition to force a vote on the three-year extension bill.</p> 
<p>"I've been asking for a vote on this for at least six months, if not eight, telling leadership it just needs to be resolved,” said Rep. David Valadao (R-Calif.), who voted for the Democratic-led measure, in an interview. “At some point we got to pull the trigger."</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu and Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers request court-appointed official to oversee the Epstein files release</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/massie-khanna-jeffrey-epstein-files-release-00717659</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9f9d-dca0-ad9b-ff9d01650000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 17:04:43 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The bipartisan duo that spearheaded efforts to force the Justice Department to release the Jeffrey Epstein files is now asking a federal judge to appoint an official to oversee the process.</p> 
<p>This new request from Reps. Thomas Massie (R-Ky.) and Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) comes as the DOJ is under criticism from members of both parties for not complying with the law Congress passed late last year, which mandated the department to make materials related to the late convicted sex offender public by Dec. 19.</p> 
<p>The department, instead, has been rolling out documents in tranches, with redactions Massie, Khanna and others say go beyond what they outlined in their legislation.</p> 
<p>“Put simply, the DOJ cannot be trusted with making mandatory disclosures under the Act,” Massie and Khanna wrote to Judge Paul E. Engelmayer of the Southern District of New York, who is overseeing the case against Epstein associate Ghislaine Maxwell. “Absent an independent process, as outlined above, we do not believe the DOJ will produce the records that are required by the Act and what it has represented to this Court.”</p> 
<p>The two lawmakers are asking Engelmayer to appoint a so-called special master, or independent monitor, to preside over the continued release — a court-appointed administrator who would ensure the administration follows the law.</p> 
<p>A judge has wide discretion to appoint a special master, and judges sometimes take such a step in cases where there are a large number of documents and questions of privilege. A special master is often a retired federal judge.</p> 
<p>The judge who oversaw the case against Michael Cohen, Trump's former lawyer, appointed a special master to review the documents seized from Cohen's properties to assess which were subject to attorney-client privilege, for example.</p> 
<p>It's not clear if Engelmayer might be inclined to appoint a special master.</p> 
<p>Massie and Khanna criticized the limited roll-out of materials and the extensive redactions. They also note their bill required Attorney General Pam Bondi to provide details on redactions, which was not submitted to Congress by the statutory deadline.</p> 
<p>“The court can rule fairly quickly,” Massie told reporters Thursday. “Pam Bondi is in communication with this judge about the document production … we are stepping in and offering our opinion on what would be helpful.”</p> 
<p>“We believe they’re over-redacting material,” he continued. “And they’re also releasing it in a manner as to just flood the channel with stuff that doesn’t matter while they withhold the things that do matter.”</p> 
<p>Massie and Khanna have also threatened to hold Bondi in “inherent contempt” — a long-dormant congressional power — over her department’s handling of the case. Massie said Thursday that their effort to pursue that mechanism was still ongoing, but that he is currently focused on the effort to appoint a special master.</p> 
<p>“I think it's the quickest way to produce, to expedite the document production, because these lawyers at the DOJ understand what judges can do in courtrooms,” he added. “And they are already communicating with that judge, even though they're not communicating with us.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House fails to override Trump vetoes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/trump-vetoes-sustained-00717160</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9f5b-da56-afff-9fdb62e10000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 16:05:22 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House voted Thursday not to overturn a pair of vetoes President Donald Trump made to legislation on a Colorado water pipeline and a Florida flood control project — despite Congress passing the bills with no objections last month.</p> 
<p>The votes represented the first attempted veto overrides of the Republican-controlled House, following what were Trump’s first vetoes of his second term in office. And while Trump has acknowledged that his vetoes were for political reasons, most of the House GOP declined to override him.</p> 
<p>The vote to uphold the veto of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_131" target="_blank">water infrastructure project bill in Colorado</a>, which is currently ensnared in the administration’s fight with the state’s Congressional delegation over cuts to a local climate center, got 248 votes, short of the 285 two-thirds majority needed for an override. Just 35 Republicans joined all 213 Democrats in voting for it.</p> 
<p>That project sits in the district of Republican Rep. Lauren Boebert, who also defied Trump and earned the White House’s ire by supporting a discharge petition to force a vote on a bill compelling the Justice Department’s full release of the Jeffrey Epstein files.</p> 
<p>"I will continue to fight for Western water. This was a commitment made by President Trump in 2020 and I will continue to fulfill that commitment," Boebert told reporters after the vote Thursday.</p> 
<p>The House also voted 236-188 to uphold Trump’s veto of <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_504" target="_blank">legislation that would support the local Miccosukee Tribe,</a> which has been at odds with the White House over the administration’s plans to build its “Alligator Alcatraz” immigrant detention center. The bill was endorsed by Florida’s Republican senators and several GOP members of the Florida delegation in the House.</p> 
<p>Twenty-four Republicans and all 212 Democrats voted to overturn the veto, with one Republican, Rep. Nancy Mace of South Carolina, voting "present." That bill needed 284 votes to override.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers in both parties charged that <a href="https://links.us1.defend.egress.com/Warning?crId=6960171f4a78364cdc19f224&amp;Domain=politico.com&amp;Threat=eNpzrShJLcpLzAEADmkDRA%3D%3D&amp;Lang=en&amp;Base64Url=eNoNx1EOg0AIBcATIdRYjb1NXV-UZJUNoF6_nb_ZM1t8mONaorgu8K5Z1dRiza0rdvDX_6tg4MQT3Es_srxY3vxorVTs3BwRZDfcdQWlX0cLupGGIJFJ5mGWHyZYJZ8%3D&amp;@OriginalLink=subscriber.politicopro.com" target="_blank">Trump’s unexpected vetoes</a> shortly after Christmas were political retribution for people who had opposed his agenda.</p> 
<p>Trump justified his veto of the water pipeline bill by calling Colorado Democrat Jared Polis a “bad governor.” State officials have refused to pardon former Republican election official Tina Peters for her convictions last year related to efforts to undermine the results of the 2020 president election, which Trump lost.</p> 
<p>The president accused Florida’s Miccosukee Tribe, which would be allowed under the other bill to carry out construction projects to protect a village from flooding, of trying to obstruct his immigration policies by suing to stop a migrant detention center near their land.</p> 
<p><i>Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House passes three-bill spending package with weeks left to avoid a shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/house-passes-three-bill-spending-package-with-weeks-left-to-avoid-a-shutdown-00716935</link>
      <description>The Senate is expected to take up the so-called “minibus” next week.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9f40-d15b-abff-df5ea53f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 15:16:53 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/4d/42/9a57794e4b85b24b0dccc02ce13a/u-s-congress-32579.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Appropriations Committee Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) is seen at the U.S. Capitol May 14, 2024.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/4d/42/9a57794e4b85b24b0dccc02ce13a/u-s-congress-32579.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House passed three government spending bills Thursday, inching Congress closer to funding federal operations ahead of the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p>The measures would fund the departments of Energy, Commerce, Interior and Justice, as well as water programs, the EPA and federal science initiatives through the end of the current fiscal year. More than 75 percent of government programs still need to be funded.</p> 
<p>The bipartisan vote comes as a relief to Speaker Mike Johnson, who had to mount a real-time whip operation on the floor Wednesday when <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/appropriations-funding-bills-hardliners-chip-roy-00715032" target="_blank"><u>conservatives threatened to tank the procedural rule</u></a> paving the way for consideration of the funding legislation that was originally intended to be brought up in a single package.</p> 
<p>A dozen GOP fiscal hawks were prepared to vote “no” on the rule unless leadership agreed to remove certain earmarks from the underlying package — and promised to revamp the earmarks process surrounding future spending bills.</p> 
<p>To quell the rebellion, a plan was hatched to split up the package and accommodate two separate votes: one on the Commerce-Justice-Science bill, where discontent over certain earmarks couldn’t be resolved, and another on the Interior-Environment and Energy-Water bills coupled together. This maneuver allowed hard-liners to register their opposition to the Commerce-Justice-Science measure but still support the others.</p> 
<p>The House ultimately voted 375-47 on Commerce-Justice-Science, with three dozen Republicans opposing, as compared to the just three Republicans who opposed the Interior-EPA and Energy-Water measures on a 419-6 vote.</p> 
<p>Members of both parties also agreed to nix one particularly controversial, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-earmark-angst-rears-ahead-of-spending-package-votes-00714135" target="_blank"><u>$1 million earmark</u></a> sought by Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn.) for a program in her district.</p> 
<p>A third vote Thursday, 397-28, was on final passage and to approve sending the three measures over to the Senate reconstituted into a package. Majority Leader John Thune is eying consideration of this bundle as soon as next week.</p> 
<p>“Going forward, we're going to be allowed a little more access to the bills and the ability to have an impact on them in the future — this next tranche,” Rep. Andy Harris, a senior appropriator and House Freedom Caucus chair, told reporters.</p> 
<p>But House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) defended the bills against the lamentations of conservatives.</p> 
<p>“These bills are the product of bipartisan, bicameral consensus and are grounded in a member-driven process,” Cole said in a floor speech Thursday. “It wasn’t meant to be easy. In fact, difficulty is what separates serious legislating from political convenience.”</p> 
<p>Appropriators are already working on the next spending package they hope to move in advance of the month-end funding cliff. Legislative text could come this weekend, Cole told reporters Wednesday ahead of a meeting of chairs for the Homeland Security, State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services appropriations subcommittees.</p> 
<p>“All the reports I'm getting are very good,” he added in a Wednesday interview. “We're getting good cooperation from our Democratic friends as well. I mean, people are serious about trying to get this stuff done.”</p> 
<p>But Cole and his colleagues have their work cut out for them in passing the rest of the full-year funding bills for fiscal 2026. There are six measures Congress has not yet advanced, and they include some of the diciest of the bunch — among them, Defense and Labor-HHS-Education, which make up nearly 70 percent of all federal discretionary spending.</p> 
<p>And the DHS portion of the next funding package has likely gotten even more unwieldy following this week’s shooting of a U.S. citizen in Minneapolis by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent.</p> 
<p>The House Republican in charge of that account, Rep. Mark Amodei of Nevada, acknowledged the events in Minnesota “will probably complicate the bill.”</p> 
<p>The appropriations package advanced Thursday largely rejected the dramatic cuts requested by the White House, instead making more <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/eenews/2026/01/06/takeaways-from-congress-latest-spending-package-00712026" target="_blank"><u>tailored spending reductions to energy and environment programs</u></a> and those popular with Democrats.</p> 
<p>The EPA would see a 4 percent, or $320 million, cut, instead of the more than $4 billion reduction President Donald Trump had sought. The National Park Service would face a moderate reduction from current funding levels, much less than the 37 percent cut the White House asked for.</p> 
<p>One area set to <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/congress-looks-to-increase-funding-for-key-trade-agencies-00711038" target="_blank"><u>get a boost are trade agencies</u></a>, including an 18 percent increase for the U.S. Trade Representative’s Office and a 23 percent increase for the Commerce Department office responsible for designing and enforcing export controls used to target China and other countries.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump rages about Republicans backing war powers resolution: ‘Should never be elected to office again’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/trump-war-powers-republicans-election-00716332</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9ed7-dca0-ad9b-ffdfc85c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 13:34:42 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump lashed out at the five Republican senators who voted to advance legislation that would constrain his war powers in Venezuela on Thursday.</p> 
<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245" target="_blank">The GOP lawmakers</a> — Rand Paul of Kentucky, Lisa Murkowski of Alaska, Susan Collins of Maine, Todd Young of Indiana and Josh Hawley of Missouri — joined with the chamber’s entire slate of Democrats to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/senate-votes-to-restrict-trump-on-venezuela-00716127" target="_blank">tee up a vote that could compel Trump</a> to seek the approval of Congress before taking any additional military action in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>The president, who is looking to wield his foreign policy powers to reassert greater U.S. control over the Western Hemisphere, <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115860738010214901" target="_blank">wrote on his social media platform Thursday</a> that Republicans “should be ashamed of the Senators that just voted with Democrats to take our Powers.”</p> 
<p>The senators, he declared, “should never be elected to office again.”</p> 
<p>“This vote greatly hampers American Self Defense and National Security, impeding the President's authority as Commander in Chief,” Trump wrote.</p> 
<p>Collins is the only one of the five Republicans who is up for reelection this year. Her seat has long been a top target for Democrats, although she has continuously won in a state that Democrats typically carry in presidential and other statewide races.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-08T13:01:20-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>The 5 Republicans who voted against Trump on Venezuela</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/the-5-republicans-who-voted-against-trump-on-war-powers-00716245</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9eb8-d15b-abff-defe10c60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 12:53:03 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Five Senate Republicans joined with Democratic lawmakers in a surprise rebuke of President Donald Trump Thursday, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/senate-votes-to-restrict-trump-on-venezuela-00716127" target="_blank">voting to advance legislation</a> that would force the commander in chief to seek Congress’ OK before taking any additional military action in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115860738010214901" target="_blank">attacked the lawmakers</a> in a Truth Social post after the procedural vote, saying they "should never be elected to office again" and that the measure they supported "greatly hampers American Self Defense and National Security."</p> 
<p>Here’s a closer look at each of the GOP lawmakers and how they explained their votes:</p> 
<p><b>Rand Paul of Kentucky:</b> Paul was a co-sponsor of the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_SJRES_98" target="_blank">war powers measure</a> and has been outspoken in his concern across multiple presidencies that the executive branch has overstepped its authority to use military force without congressional consent.</p> 
<p><b>Lisa Murkowski of Alaska:</b> She sided with similar Democratic-led war powers measures in the past, lamenting that White House officials have not provided enough legal justification for attacks on drug traffickers or for the operation to remove Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p><b>Susan Collins of Maine:</b> Collins said <a href="https://x.com/SenatorCollins/status/2009308410836140088?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">in a statement</a> that voting to limit presidential powers was “necessary” because of Trump’s recent comments about potentially using ground troops and a sustained military engagement in Venezuela.</p> 
<p><b>Josh Hawley of Missouri:</b> Hawley similarly said that Trump’s “boots on the ground” comments illustrated the need to reinforce Congress’ role in approving future military actions. The conservative has been a staunch defender of Trump’s policies in the past.</p> 
<p><b>Todd Young of Indiana:</b> Young expressed support for the operation to capture Maduro but <a href="https://x.com/SenToddYoung/status/2009312301296365988?ref_src=twsrc%5Egoogle%7Ctwcamp%5Eserp%7Ctwgr%5Etweet" target="_blank">said in a statement</a> that he is concerned about the potential for a long-term military presence in the country: “I — along with what I believe to be the vast majority of Hoosiers — am not prepared to commit American troops to that mission.”</p>CORRECTION: An earlier version of this report misspelled Nicolás Maduro's name.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insurer CEOs testifying before House health subcommittee Jan. 22</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/insurer-ceos-testifying-before-house-health-subcommittee-jan-22-00716104</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9e7f-d65c-affb-bfff38450004</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 11:49:13 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans are summoning top health insurance executives to testify on Capitol Hill this month as part of a broader effort to examine health care costs, a move that comes weeks after enhanced Affordable Care Act tax credits expired Dec. 31.</p> 
<p>The hearing announcement comes amid Democrat criticism that Republicans allowed the enhanced ACA subsidies to lapse — a decision they argue is burdening Americans who relied on the enhanced tax credits to help them afford Obamacare premiums. It also comes amid pressure from President Donald Trump, who urged House Republicans earlier this week to tackle health care affordability.</p> 
<p>“Alarm bells have been ringing for health care affordability for months,” said House Energy and Commerce health subcommittee ranking member <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51349" data-person-id="51349">Diana DeGette</a> (D-Colo.). “And with the expiration of enhanced premium tax credits at the end of 2025, we knew that premiums would skyrocket in 2026.”</p> 
<p>But House Energy and Commerce Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66855" data-person-id="66855">Brett Guthrie</a> (R-Ky.) said the Jan. 22 health subcommittee meeting with insurer executives will be part of a series of hearings over the next few months focused on health care affordability.</p> 
<p>“While some want to talk solely about a small subset of the population, I believe we have to take a broader look,” Guthrie said.</p> 
<p>UnitedHealth Group, the nation’s largest insurer, said it has received the invitation to the hearings and looks forward “to discussing health care costs as part of their series with hospitals, drug companies, and others,” spokesperson Robert Josephson said in a statement.</p> 
<p>“Keeping health care affordable should be everyone’s top priority, and we will continue to partner with policymakers on solutions,” Josephson said.</p> 
<p>Trump told House Republicans earlier this week that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/trump-health-abortion-restrictions-hyde-00712507" target="_blank">he plans to meet with 14&nbsp; insurance companies</a> in the coming days to pressure them to bring down prices.</p> 
<p>“I am hopeful that we can have a productive discussion about what is truly driving increased healthcare costs and premiums for everyone,” Guthrie said. “From there, we need to look at the entire health care system, why prices and costs are going up.”</p> 
<p><i>Kelly Hooper contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steny Hoyer, announcing his retirement, says he's 'deeply concerned' about the House</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/08/congress/steny-hoyer-speech-deeply-concerned-00716037</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9e52-dca0-ad9b-ffdb97e00000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 11:10:45 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In an emotional nine-minute-long speech, Maryland Rep. Steny Hoyer said goodbye to the institution where he has spent over four decades — and expressed fears for its future.</p> 
<p>The 86-year-old Democratic former majority leader walked through his career and a path to Congress that started in the late 1950s as a University of Maryland undergrad before announcing <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/steny-hoyer-retirement-00715790" target="_blank">his 23rd term would be his last</a>. He then delivered a warning, telling colleagues gathered on the House floor that he was “deeply concerned that this House is not living up to the founders’ goals.”</p> 
<p>“I fear that America is heading not toward greatness, but toward smallness, pettiness, divisiveness, loneliness and disdainfulness,” he said. “We must respect and love one another. We must remember that we are not great or unique because we say we are great, but because we are just generous and fair.”</p> 
<p>Lawmakers from both parties lined up after Hoyer spoke to embrace the former Democratic No. 2, who stepped down from his leadership position after the 2022 midterms but remained a senior member of the Appropriations Committee. </p> 
<p>POLITICO first reported his decision to retire Wednesday.</p> 
<p>As political polarization increased in Congress, he remained a rare leader well-regarded by the opposite side of the aisle — one who paid tribute to the institution for which he has served since 1981 as one "the framers designed to reflect the will of the American people and to serve as the guardian of their liberty and their democracy.”</p> 
<p>Speaking after Hoyer, Rep. G.T. Thompson (R-Pa.), praised him as a “statesman.” And former Speaker Nancy Pelosi, a onetime rival in Democratic leadership, hailed Hoyer as a “leader to us” and a “mentor to many.</p> 
<p>“You have been a really an example of leadership and perhaps can be viewed as one of the most substantial, respected members of Congress in the history of this body,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Marco Rubio is tamping down the Venezuela backlash in Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/08/marco-rubio-venezuela-senate-00715617</link>
      <description>The secretary of State has used his old relationships to help sell the administration’s audacious strategy for the Americas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9aec-dca0-ad9b-fbedee740000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 04:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/09/c4/2a579d484eb5aec87c103bb1c003/u-s-congress-74999.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rubio’s membership in the rarefied club of senators and former senators was on full display Wednesday at the Capitol, where he warmly greeted Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/09/c4/2a579d484eb5aec87c103bb1c003/u-s-congress-74999.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As senators woke up Saturday with questions on President Donald Trump’s audacious decision to order the capture of Venezuelan leader Nicolás Maduro, one of their old colleagues was ready with answers.</p> 
<p>Secretary of State Marco Rubio worked the phones in the wee hours of the morning and, in the days since, has played an outsize role in not only formulating the administration’s strategy in Venezuela but explaining it to skeptical lawmakers wary of a protracted military commitment.</p> 
<p>That outreach has been to his former Republican colleagues as well as Democrats, including those who see him as a rare Trump official with whom they can maintain a trusted and respectful relationship amid profound policy disputes.</p> 
<p>“Although I may disagree with him on a day-to-day or hour-to-hour basis … he has shown extraordinary competence,” Sen. Dick Durbin of Illinois, the No. 2 Democratic leader, said in an interview. “I voted for him in this position; I still have confidence in his abilities.”</p> 
<p>Others said they respected his particular expertise on issues in Latin America while also raising doubts about the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/03/trump-victory-lap-raid-maduro-00709641" target="_blank">strategy for Venezuela he is laying out</a> in public and in private briefings — which for now involves propping up interim president Delcy Rodriguez as a de facto U.S. puppet.</p> 
<p>“You can talk to Marco about — ‘Tell us about Delcy.’ … He knows all of that, and he can give you a sense of who they are and what they're up to,” said Sen. Tim Kaine (D-Va.), a former colleague on the Foreign Relations Committee.</p> 
<p>Kaine complimented Rubio for putting a renewed focus on the Americas, while quickly adding that Trump’s <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/politico-nightly/2026/01/07/the-political-theory-that-explains-trumps-global-power-plays-00715342" target="_blank">self-proclaimed “Donroe doctrine”</a> is the “wrong kind of attention.”</p> 
<p>Rubio returned to his old stomping groups Wednesday as part of a delegation of senior Trump officials who briefed lawmakers on the weekend military operation. There his status as a figure of special consequence who has taken on increasingly significant roles in the administration was on display.</p> 
<p>“He's the one in the center — he's the one that starts it, no notes,” Sen. John Barrasso (R-Wyo.), the No. 2 GOP leader, said in an interview describing the briefing. “To me, he's a mature, experienced, reliable voice as secretary of State, and — specifically for this part of the world — he knows the issues, he knows the people, and that brings a lot.”</p> 
<p>Also on display was Rubio’s membership in the rarefied club of senators and former senators.</p> 
<p>He hugged and briefly huddled with Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer in view of dozens of reporters. A grinning Rubio came up to cameras afterward and joked to reporters, “I’m against everything he said.”</p> 
<p>Schumer, who like most Democrats has been a persistent critic of the administration, offered no praise for Rubio but stopped short this week of disavowing his previous support for Rubio’s nomination as secretary. Asked Tuesday if he regretted his vote, the New York Democrat said he was “deeply, deeply disappointed in Marco Rubio even before Venezuela and even more so now.”</p> 
<p>Rubio took in stride the criticism from Schumer and other Democrats that he and other Trump administration officials have not fully thought through their strategy.</p> 
<p>“I used to be a senator, too — that's what you always say when it's the other party,” he told reporters Wednesday. “The bottom line is, we've gone into great detail with them about the planning.”</p> 
<p>The Senate voted 99-0 hours after Trump’s Jan. 20 swearing-in to confirm Rubio — the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/11/13/congress/marco-rubio-secretary-of-state-00189365" target="_blank">only nominee who got through</a> on Day 1.</p> 
<p>At the time Democrats praised Rubio as a qualified foreign policy hand. They believed he shared some of their views and would work with them on key global matters such as helping Ukraine defeat Russia and strengthening the NATO alliance.</p> 
<p>But since then, Rubio has rankled his former Democratic colleagues at times as he worked with Trump to upend America’s foreign aid infrastructure and back the president’s often erratic policy priorities — ranging from his attempts to force a peace deal in Ukraine to his ongoing push to take over Greenland.</p> 
<p>Those tensions have at times spilled out into the public.</p> 
<p>Sen. Chris Van Hollen (D-Md.) told Rubio during a committee hearing last year, “I have to tell you directly and personally that I regret voting for you for secretary of State." Sen. Jacky Rosen (D-Nev.) said at the same hearing that she found “Senator Rubio to be a bipartisan pragmatic partner” but “I don’t recognize Secretary Rubio.”</p> 
<p>That said, lines of communication have stayed open. Sen. Mark Warner (D-Va.), who worked closely with Rubio on the Intelligence Committee, bristled this week at the administration’s decision not to notify top congressional leaders about the Venezuela operation in advance. But he credited Rubio for reaching out soon after.</p> 
<p>"My phone had been hacked a few months back, and I had a new number,” Warner said. “So he did try to reach me, but it was after the strikes had started.”</p> 
<p>Rubio did manage to reach many of his former Republican colleagues — including Sen. Mike Lee of Utah, with whom he had sometimes clashed over national security issues when they served together.</p> 
<p>As news of the U.S. raid began to trickle out, Lee posted to X shortly after 3 a.m. with a skeptical note: “I look forward to learning what, if anything, might constitutionally justify this action in the absence of a declaration of war or authorization for the use of military force.”</p> 
<p>Less than two hours later, <a href="https://x.com/BasedMikeLee/status/2007395531023352319" target="_blank">Lee posted again</a>, saying he had spoken to Rubio: “This action likely falls within the president’s inherent authority under Article II of the Constitution to protect U.S. personnel from an actual or imminent attack. Thank you, @SecRubio, for keeping me apprised.”</p> 
<p>Rubio also reached out to Senate Majority Leader John Thune and Speaker Mike Johnson soon after the operation launched, as well as chairs and members of key committees.</p> 
<p>“He is a gift to America right now,” Johnson said Wednesday.</p> 
<p>“All members are comfortable with him — certainly those that served with him, which is just about everyone here,” Barrasso said. He added that Rubio was confirmed unanimously “because people knew him and respected him.”</p> 
<p>Democrats who worked with him in the Senate had a more nuanced assessment as they emerged Wednesday from their closed-door briefing with the Trump officials. They raised deep concerns over the administration’s strategy for Venezuela, but they also said they were in no way surprised by Rubio’s role in developing and promoting it given his long opposition to dictatorships in the region.</p> 
<p>“Marco has been evangelical on Latin America for a long time, for a long time — I mean, he’s, you know, a pretty classic neocon who believes that America will generally be greeted as liberators," said Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.), another former Foreign Relations colleague. “I didn’t vote for him because I thought he was going to suddenly agree with me on the importance of military restraint overseas.”</p> 
<p>Added Kaine, “At the end of the day, he’s going to do what Trump tells him to do.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Daniella Cheslow contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-07T22:29:16-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Steny Hoyer set to announce retirement from Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/steny-hoyer-retirement-00715790</link>
      <description>The former second-ranking House Democrat has held his seat since 1981.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9b6b-d65c-affb-bbebf26d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 21:31:22 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/25/68/8c33f4444db39211789bcdb863cc/steny-hoyer-37002.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Majority Leader Steny Hoyer speaks with reporters outside the Capitol on Sept. 21, 2022.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/25/68/8c33f4444db39211789bcdb863cc/steny-hoyer-37002.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Nicholas Wu and Andrew Howard</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Nicholas Wu and Andrew Howard</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Maryland Rep. Steny Hoyer will announce his retirement from Congress Thursday, capping off a decades-long career that culminated in two four-year stints as House majority leader where he played a key part in passing major bills including the Affordable Care Act.</p> 
<p>Hoyer confirmed the news in an <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2026/01/07/steny-hoyer-retire-congress/" target="_blank">interview with the Washington Post</a> that was published shortly after POLITICO's initial report, which cited two people granted anonymity to confirm the news ahead of a public announcement.</p> 
<p>“I did not want to be one of those members who clearly stayed, outstayed his or her ability to do the job," he told the Post. </p> 
<p>Hoyer, who represents a district stretching from the eastern Washington suburbs to southern Maryland, has served in Congress since 1981, rising up through the ranks to become the second-ranking House Democrat under Speaker Nancy Pelosi.</p> 
<p>The two leaders were known for their personal rivalry dating back to their days as congressional interns in the 1960s, but after Pelosi defeated Hoyer in a 2001 leadership race they ultimately formed an effective partnership atop the Democratic Caucus. </p> 
<p>While Pelosi was known for her progressive views and strong fundraising, Hoyer was a master of interpersonal relations — both among fellow Democrats and across the aisle — making him a highly effective floor leader.</p> 
<p>He stepped aside from his senior role after Democrats lost the House in 2022 as part of a broader changing of the guard but remained in Congress, retaking a senior post on the House Appropriations Committee.</p> 
<p>Only two sitting House members — GOP Reps. Hal Rogers of Kentucky and Chris Smith of New Jersey — have served longer than Hoyer, and only by a few months.</p> 
<p>Now 86, Hoyer remained circumspect about his plans to run for re-election. The decision comes as numerous senior Democrats are facing primaries from younger candidates or choosing not to run for reelection. Pelosi <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/10/22/pelosi-to-announce-plans-after-california-election-in-november-00618093" target="_blank">announced in October she plans to retire</a> at the end of her term.</p> 
<p>Hoyer praised Pelosi, whom he lost a leadership contest to in 2001, in the Post interview as "tough-as-nails." </p> 
<p>“Sure, I would have loved to have been speaker. Who wouldn’t love to be speaker? But they’re not deep regrets,” he said.</p> 
<p>His decision to step aside is likely to create a free-for-all for the deep-blue seat. One candidate, Harry Jarin, is already in the race <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/29/hoyer-challenger-age-harry-jarin-00373866" target="_blank">after launching a primary in May</a> that specifically targeted Hoyer’s age.</p> 
<p><i>Jonathan Martin contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Oversight panel to issue more subpoenas in Epstein case</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/more-epstein-subpoenas-00715597</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9ad8-dca0-ad9b-fbd954dd0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:52:26 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The House Oversight and Government Reform Committee will subpoena Les Wexner, the longtime friend and client of Jeffrey Epstein, along with two men who worked for the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>It was the culmination of a flurry of subpoena requests Wednesday from rank-and-file members of the panel, several of which were ultimately approved. The committee also voted to subpoena Darren Indyke and Richard Kahn — Epstein’s lawyer and accountant, respectively.</p> 
<p>It shows how the House Oversight Committee could continue to find itself at the center of efforts to re-investigate the Epstein case as the Justice Department presides over a prolonged and rocky rollout of materials.</p> 
<p>The successful motions, brought by the top Democrat on panel, California Rep. Robert Garcia, appeared to be the result of an agreement between Garcia and Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.), who also successfully moved to subpoena American businessman Neville Singham and journalist Seth Harp.</p> 
<p>“There is probably no one more important as it relates to the financing and the work of this investigation, which both sides of the aisle are interested in,” Garcia said, of Wexner. “Public reporting has documented their longstanding ties. He should answer our questions in a non-partisan way to get the truth.”</p> 
<p>Luna concurred: “I think that this is a sound motion for subpoena because Les Wexner has been named by victims and also, too, is in a number of documentaries,” she said and urged her colleagues to join her in supporting the effort.</p> 
<p>In moving to subpoena Singham, Luna cited a letter signed by then-Sen. Marco Rubio, who now serves as Secretary of State, suggesting the entrepreneur may have been connected to activities that violated the Foreign Agents Registration Act. Luna also claimed Singham was funding groups that were adverse to American interests.</p> 
<p>Rep. Dave Min (D-Calif.) questioned why Luna was making her motion at this time. Still, Garcia recommended lawmakers vote “yes” despite Min’s concerns, explaining “the representative made clear her support for the deposition that we’re going to have with Mr. Wexner.”</p> 
<p>In an interview after the Wexner vote, Garcia said he did not negotiate the matter with Luna before the hearing.</p> 
<p>“[Congress is] about compromise, and I think for us, the Les Wexner subpoena is at the center of this investigation,” he said.</p> 
<p>Garcia also supported Luna’s motion to subpoena Harp, who has been accused of doxxing a Delta Force official involved in the operation to arrest Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>Separately, the committee rejected a bid from Democrats to subpoena the Department of Homeland Security for records related to the Wednesday shooting of a woman in Minneapolis by an ICE agent.</p> 
<p>The panel struck down an attempt from Rep. Ayanna Pressley (D-Mass.) to issue the subpoena at the end of an hours-long hearing around the welfare fraud scandal in Minnesota. Pressley requested “documents and footage” of the fatal incident.</p> 
<p>Garcia said he was hopeful the panel would investigate the episode.</p> 
<p>“We’re talking about Minnesota right now,” he said. “This was a killing by an ICE agent. There are videos that are now online. There’s testimony that’s being brought to light. It’s horrific. I encourage folks to watch those videos and see what’s happened for themselves.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-07T20:24:25-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump has ‘greenlit’ Russia sanctions bill, Lindsey Graham says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/russia-sanctions-lindsey-graham-00715548</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9acf-da56-afff-9edf9aa40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:35:49 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> said Wednesday after meeting with President Donald Trump that the Senate could vote as soon as next week to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/06/07/lindsey-graham-russia-sanctions-bill-trade-embargo-00393297" target="_blank">impose new sanctions aimed at pressuring Russia</a> to end its war with Ukraine.</p> 
<p>“After a very productive meeting today with President Trump on a variety of issues, he greenlit the bipartisan Russia sanctions bill that I have been working on for months with Senator <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151824" data-person-id="151824">[Richard] Blumenthal</a> and many others,” Graham (R-S.C.) said in a statement, referring to the Connecticut Democrat who coauthored the long-stalled legislation.</p> 
<p>Asked about Graham's remarks, a White House official said Trump supports the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_1241" target="_blank">legislation</a>. Graham said a Senate vote would take place “hopefully as early as next week.”</p> 
<p>Graham and Senate Republican leaders have been working with the White House for months to try to reach an agreement on a final version of the legislation — and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/10/23/congress/senators-eye-sanctions-vote-after-trump-targets-russian-oil-00620847" target="_blank">this isn’t the first time</a> Graham has declared that his bill could soon move, for it to only <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/07/14/trump-threatens-tariffs-on-russias-trading-partners-to-pressure-putin-00452131" target="_blank">stall out again</a>.</p> 
<p>The legislation would place secondary sanctions on countries such as China and India that buy oil and gas from Russia in a bid to cut off the cash flow for President Vladimir Putin’s war machine.</p> 
<p>“Ukraine is making concessions for peace and Putin is all talk, continuing to kill the innocent,” Graham said, saying the legislation would be “well-timed.”</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Graham didn’t immediately respond to a question about whether changes will be incorporated at Trump’s request. The president has previously requested absolute flexibility to impose and retract any sanctions at will.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-07T18:23:16-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House 1 step closer to passing 3-bill spending package</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/appropriations-funding-bills-hardliners-chip-roy-00715032</link>
      <description>The minibus is headed toward double-barrel final House votes Thursday before moving to the Senate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9a72-d65c-affb-bbf32f920003</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:34:54 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/dd/33/d4875373414497ce870e4fb70e0a/u-s-congress-78085.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Rep. Chip Roy and other conservatives raised concerns about what they called “outlandish” earmarks in the funding package.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/dd/33/d4875373414497ce870e4fb70e0a/u-s-congress-78085.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republicans pushed a three-bill spending package through a key procedural hurdle Wednesday afternoon after a hard-liner revolt threatened to derail the underlying bill.</p> 
<p>Republicans stayed largely united on a test vote to advance the package with a 214-212 vote that would fund the Departments of Energy, Commerce, Interior and Justice, as well as water programs, the EPA and federal science initiatives through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>But it didn’t come easy. A dozen GOP lawmakers withheld their vote, prompting Speaker Mike Johnson and House Appropriations Committee Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) to launch a real-time whip operation on the House floor. More than a dozen lawmakers and staff huddled for an extended period after everyone else in the chamber had voted, pulling in House Majority Whip Tom Emmer, House Rules Committee Chair Virginia Foxx (R-Va.) and a bevy of staff. </p> 
<p>Reps. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and Scott Perry (R-Pa.) led the hard-liner charge to push their issues with leaders and the chamber’s top appropriator. </p> 
<p>“Members want to participate. So we're requesting that members be allowed to participate fully,” Perry said after the vote.</p> 
<p>The fiscal hawks were laying out their demands for a different approach to earmarks on the next six spending bills that Congress hopes to tackle before the Jan. 30 deadline, which is set to become a major hurdle for finalizing the next bills, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss conversations on the floor Wednesday.</p> 
<p>“Going forward, we're going to be allowed a little more access to the bills and the ability to have an impact on them in the future — this next tranche,” Rep. Andy Harris (R-Md.) told reporters. “We’ll get to take a look at the earmarks too. I mean, that was part of the whole problem here.”</p> 
<p>While the last six spending bills are not yet finalized, earmark requests from both sides of the aisle were submitted months ago.</p> 
<p>Wednesday's planned procedural vote was first thrown into question after a contentious House Rules Committee hearing late Tuesday night where conservatives on the panel raised concerns about “outlandish” earmarks.</p> 
<p>The stalemate forced the committee to recess overnight and reconvene Wednesday morning with the promise of a deal in hand. House Republican leaders <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-earmark-angst-rears-ahead-of-spending-package-votes-00714135" target="_blank"><u>struck a compromise to kill</u></a> what Roy called “the most egregious" earmark for a community organization in the district of Rep. Ilhan Omar (D-Minn).</p> 
<p>Leaders also agreed to pave the way for two separate final passage votes Thursday — one to advance the Commerce-Justice-Science bill and another to approve the Energy-Water and Interior portions.</p> 
<p>This procedural gambit will allow Roy and other hard-liners to vote “no” on the CJS measure, where other earmarks continue to be irksome, while still voting “yes” on the other two appropriations bills.</p> 
<p>If all three bills pass, they will be repackaged into a single bundle before being sent to the Senate for consideration as soon as next week.</p> 
<p>Congress is rushing to approve more spending bills before the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump's State of the Union set for Feb. 24</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/state-of-the-union-on-feb-24-00715125</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9a5b-d651-a1ff-be7b11760000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:28:25 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://x.com/SpeakerJohnson/status/2009008841405727229?s=20" target="_blank">has invited</a> President Donald Trump to deliver his State of the Union address to Congress on Feb. 24.</p> 
<p>The speech comes as Trump is working to address key cost of living issues, leading military intervention in Venezuela and threatening to seize Greenland.</p> 
<p>Trump's last address to Congress in March 2025 devolved into heckling and protests from Democrats. </p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Congress wants oversight of Venezuelan oil revenues</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/congress-venezuelan-oil-revenue-oversight-00714107</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-99cd-d78e-af9f-fdff1f040000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 13:53:30 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congressional lawmakers from both parties are signaling that despite President Donald Trump's assertion that he will control the money gained from selling Venezuelan oil turned over to the United States, they’ll want to check the books.</p> 
<p>Democrats said they were appalled by the Trump administration’s plans to sell Venezuelan oil “indefinitely” and control the revenue, suggesting it would amount to a takeover of the country’s fledgling oil industry.</p> 
<p>“It’s an insane plan,” Sen. Chris Murphy (D-Conn.) told POLITICO coming out of a briefing Wednesday with Trump administration officials on Venezuela. “They are proposing to steal Venezuela's oil at gunpoint forever and use that leverage to run the country.”</p> 
<p>Republicans expressed tepid support for the plan, and though they projected confidence in Energy Secretary Chris Wright’s ability to manage the funds, they demanded some oversight over how the money would be spent.</p> 
<p>“Chris Wright is brilliant when it comes to energy,” said Sen. John Hoeven (R-N.D.) after the briefing. “Nobody's going to do a better job than him in terms of making sure that that oil is properly marketed. Congress will have an oversight role. He'll [Wright] be up here testifying in front of us exactly how they're doing it.”</p> 
<p>Sen. Kevin Cramer (R-N.D.) said the U.S. controlling oil revenues would provide important “leverage” over Venezuela’s government, given the fragile state of its economy.</p> 
<p>“As long as we can control how they spend it, that could be a really important part of rebuilding the country and democracy in the region,” Cramer said after the briefing.</p> 
<p>But he expressed some hesitation around selling the oil in the United States that would compete with crude produced in the United States. Both Cramer and Hoeven represent a state that is one of the largest oil producers in the United States but has recently seen its output plateau amid weak prices. The type of oil it produces wouldn’t compete directly with the lower-quality grades coming from Venezuela, but could be pushed out at the margins.</p> 
<p>“As long as it's not sold at a discount I probably don't have a big problem with it. As long as they aren't going to use that dirty, cheap oil to flood the market,” Cramer said.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson in an interview earlier Wednesday said he didn’t have the full details of the administration's plans to secure oil fields and output in Venezuela, but he said he thought the plan “makes sense.”</p> 
<p>And he said he did not expect the Trump administration would spend taxpayer dollars for the effort. </p> 
<p>“I do not expect that they would,” he said.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report. </i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GOP earmark angst rears ahead of spending package votes</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/gop-earmark-angst-rears-ahead-of-spending-package-votes-00714135</link>
      <description>Plans to kill one Democratic earmark and split the three-bill package up may keep hopes for passage alive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-99b1-df0c-a5bb-bdf786250000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 13:23:15 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/c8/72/a060eb7a495a9ab246e1ccf38ed2/u-s-congress-34956.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>A rebellion from Rep. Chip Roy and other conservatives against earmarks is threatening to tank a key procedural vote Wednesday afternoon on a three-bill spending package.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/c8/72/a060eb7a495a9ab246e1ccf38ed2/u-s-congress-34956.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Katherine Tully-McManus, Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Katherine Tully-McManus, Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A conservative rebellion against earmarks is threatening to tank a key procedural vote Wednesday afternoon on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6938" target="_blank">three-bill spending package</a> as House GOP leaders scramble to avoid another intraparty meltdown on the chamber floor.</p> 
<p>House leaders plan to strip out an earmark from Democratic Rep. Ilhan Omar, which could have major repercussions in a legislative body already plagued by partisan tensions and mistrust. </p> 
<p>The community project funding at the center of hard-liners’ ire is $1 million for an organization in Minneapolis focused on “wraparound services” that include job training, addiction recovery and housing support. The organization describes itself as “youth-led East African recovery organization.”</p> 
<p>The scrutiny over the earmark, which was also backed by Minnesota’s Senate delegation, comes as federal funding for childcare centers in Minnesota’s large Somali community is under fire by the Trump administration due to allegations of fraud. Some Republicans are claiming that this organization is also fraudulent.</p> 
<p>“Earmarks are the currency of corruption, and they're coming back in full force in these products,” Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) told reporters Wednesday morning about the spending package heading to the House floor later in the day. “And I just don't support it.”</p> 
<p>Following a GOP revolt inside the House Rules Committee late Tuesday night, House Republican leaders landed on a compromise to kill the earmark, according to four people granted anonymity to speak candidly about a private plan.</p> 
<p>Leadership also agreed to split up the three-bill package that would fund Energy-Water, Interior-Environment and Commerce-Justice-Science when it comes to the floor for a vote.</p> 
<p>That would give some Republicans the ability to vote against the CJS measure while backing the other two. The procedural gambit would then allow all three bills to be repackaged for the Senate to consider as one bundle.</p> 
<p>House Appropriations Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.), however, warned Wednesday the intense focus on one single earmark is a liability for carefully negotiated full-year funding bills, ahead of the Jan. 30 deadline to avoid a shutdown.</p> 
<p>“I can't afford to have a million dollar project jeopardize a $184 billion package of bills,” Cole told reporters. “If we have an individual project that can pose a political problem, I've had these in the past from our side before, where we had to tell a member, ‘look, there might be a way to do this, but our advice to you is to withdraw this.’”</p> 
<p>Cole said the onus was on Democrats to convince Omar to abandon the request, or risk tanking the whole bipartisan spending package.</p> 
<p>“It is under discussion and it will be resolved. That's the way things go with these community projects. If there's a difficulty, if there's a problem, we try to work it out. Or it comes out,” Rep. Rosa DeLauro of Connecticut, the top Democratic appropriator in the House, said in an interview Wednesday afternoon. </p> 
<p>The underlying language of the bill will not change, but the earmark is expected to be functionally neutered by making a change to report language that accompanies the bill text.</p> 
<p>“It's too late in the process,” for changes to funding levels or the bill text itself, Cole said.</p> 
<p>Omar’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment Wednesday.</p> 
<p>Earmarks were banned under Republican leadership for more than a decade before being revived and rebranded by Democrats as “community project funding” in 2021. The new process has tighter restrictions for eligibility than the old one, which has calmed angst among most Republicans about frivolous hyperlocal projects.</p> 
<p>Lawmakers from both parties request money for initiatives in their districts, and appropriators consider thousands of projects from both sides before narrowing down which will make it into spending bills.</p> 
<p>Roy and Freedom Caucus Chair Andy Harris (R-Md.) each stood up in Wednesday morning’s closed door House GOP Conference meeting to voice their frustration about the earmarks in the CJS funding bill and the lack of opportunity for rank-and-file members to offer amendments to the bill, according to four people in the room granted anonymity to speak candidly.</p> 
<p>With these changes, and if Republicans have perfect attendance Wednesday, House GOP leaders — for now — believe they will have enough votes to narrowly clear the at-risk procedural hurdle on the floor late this afternoon.</p> 
<p>This also would keep Republicans on track for final passage Thursday given strong support from Democrats, according to five people granted anonymity to share internal party dynamics.</p>CORRECTION:  This story has been updated to reflect that Republicans did not submit more earmark requests overall for fiscal 2026.]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate group nears deal to revive Obamacare subsidies</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/senate-deal-obamacare-subsidies-00714048</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9992-d78e-af9f-fdf77e4c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 12:49:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A bipartisan Senate group is nearing an agreement to revive lapsed Obamacare subsidies, with a key negotiator saying the group could release draft legislation early next week.</p> 
<p>The deal being discussed by the senators would reestablish the enhanced tax credits that expired Jan. 1 for two years, with new restrictions including minimum premium payments and income caps. The developing agreement would pair that with new cost-sharing reduction measures and expanding access to health savings accounts.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/398933" data-person-id="398933">Bernie Moreno</a> (R-Ohio), a key negotiator, said Wednesday that legislative text could be finalized “realistically, probably Monday.”</p> 
<p>Two other people granted anonymity to disclose private negotiations characterized the Senate group as close to an agreement. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) added she was “encouraged” by the group’s progress and agreed an agreement is close.</p> 
<p>Even if the fluctuating group of roughly a dozen lawmakers is able to come to a consensus, there’s no guarantee it will get the votes to pass. Senators have been keeping their leadership in the loop on the talks and will meet this week with House lawmakers to update them on their progress.</p> 
<p>The group is eyeing an income restriction for the subsidies that would exclude those earning more than about 700 percent of the federal poverty level, as well as a $5 a month minimum premium. They would also slap steep new fines on any insurance companies that add so-called phantom enrollees, meaning people who are signed up for subsidized coverage without realizing it.</p> 
<p>Under the discussions, according to Moreno, Americans who receive the Obamacare subsidies could choose to have the money go instead into a pre-funded health savings account during the second year of the extension.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a> (D-Ill.), who has been involved in some of the group’s discussions, cautioned that there were “still some major stumbling blocks.”</p> 
<p>Moreno, for instance, did not say how the group was going to resolve concerns that the tax credits could be used to subsidize coverage of abortions. But he said the framework of the agreement, as he had described it, does not change current abortion policy and that the abortion discussion remained a “peripheral” issue.</p> 
<p>“We’re trying to resolve how we ensure compliance with the spirit” of the Hyde Amendment, Moreno said, referring to the longstanding appropriations restriction preventing taxpayer funding of abortions.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Democrats eye Venezuela war powers vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/house-democrats-venezuela-war-powers-00713669</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9915-d78e-af9f-fd77c2950000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 10:33:26 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Democrats are making a fresh attempt to rein in President Donald Trump on Venezuela, plotting to force a vote on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HCONRES_68" target="_blank">war powers resolution</a> in the coming weeks.</p> 
<p>The resolution is likely to be similar to one that was introduced last year as the military began to marshal forces in the Caribbean. That measure was narrowly defeated in the GOP-controlled House. Democrats are hopeful they can garner more support from Republicans following the weekend operation to capture Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512">Jim McGovern</a> of Massachusetts, the top Rules Committee Democrat who co-authored the original measure, said he envisioned "something similar to what we did last time, maybe with a couple of minor adjustments." </p> 
<p>He and other top Democrats privately huddled Tuesday evening as they planned a way forward. Some Democrats are privately concerned that introducing a war powers measure that is broadly worded could fail and give the impression that the House is giving Trump permission to take further action in Venezuela.</p> 
<p>Democratic leaders are involving lawmakers with military backgrounds such as Reps. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227127" data-person-id="227127">Seth Moulton</a> (D-Mass.), <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307328" data-person-id="307328">Jason Crow</a> (D-Colo.) and <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/433952" data-person-id="433952">Pat Ryan</a> (D-N.Y.) as they plan their response, according to Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51521" data-person-id="51521">Gregory Meeks</a> (D-N.Y.), the top Foreign Affairs Committee Democrat. He said he expects “very little” to change from last year’s measure.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Warren cuts checks to state Democratic parties</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/elizabeth-warren-dem-donations-midterms-00713176</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-9543-dba9-addb-b7ff02f30000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:06:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Elizabeth Warren is donating $400,000 to 23 state Democratic parties in an effort to fund Democratic infrastructure ahead of the 2026 midterms.</p> 
<p>In an interview, the Massachusetts Democrat called the “early money” investment “crucial” for state parties. She’s urging fellow Democrats to follow her lead on donating now because “the best time to do it is January, not waiting until next October.”</p> 
<p>The 23 states are ones with competitive congressional or statewide races in the 2026 midterms, and include Maine, North Carolina, Ohio and Texas.</p> 
<p>“They need the resources to build out infrastructure that all of our Democratic candidates will need to win in November,” Warren said. “They need money now to hire staff, recruit volunteers, knock on doors, make calls, do all the things that make Democrats competitive in these elections.”</p> 
<p>She’s also raised more than $1.1 million for candidates this cycle, while weighing in on a handful of contested primaries.</p> 
<p>Warren, a longtime progressive champion, is urging candidates to focus their campaign messaging on “the high costs that families are struggling with every day” and “make it clear that we have solutions and that we will fight to deliver real change.”</p> 
<p>In 2018, Warren also donated $250,000 to state parties, a sign of her early presidential primary preparations ahead of the 2020 campaign. But when asked if the same applied to this year’s investment, Warren said, “no.”</p> 
<p>“Democrats need to win elections everywhere, and I am 100 percent committed to making that happen in November 2026,” she said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: The House GOP’s nerve-wracking return</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/07/congress/what-were-watching-00713615</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019b-96ec-d78e-af9f-feff1dd60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The start of the second session of the 119th Congress isn’t going as planned for House Republicans.</p> 
<p>First, the GOP Conference’s long-planned, day-long policy retreat Tuesday at the Kennedy Center — intended to build unity around a legislative agenda in a midterm election year — was shaken by news of Rep. Doug LaMalfa’s (R-Calif.) <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/doug-lamalfa-dead-00712222" target="_blank">unexpected death</a> and Rep. Jim Baird’s (R-Ind.) hospitalization from a car accident.</p> 
<p>It brought into stark relief the major math challenges House Republicans now face. LaMalfa’s passing brings the balance of the House to 218-213. And as long as Baird is out recovering, Speaker Mike Johnson can afford to lose only a single GOP vote on party-line legislative business on the chamber floor.</p> 
<p>“We keep saying we are one breath away from the minority — that’s more true today than ever,” said one House Republican granted anonymity to speak candidly about the mood.</p> 
<p><b>— The numbers game:&nbsp;</b>Johnson’s margins could be a major problem for Wednesday’s vote to move forward with consideration of a “minibus” funding package covering Commerce-Justice-Science, Energy-Water and Interior-Environment — if the measure makes it to the floor at all.</p> 
<p>Rules ultimately recessed Tuesday night without approving the rule to allow for floor debate on the funding bill after Rep. Chip Roy (R-Texas) and other conservatives revolted over <a href="https://x.com/chiproytx/status/2008691088370942226?s=46" target="_blank">some of the earmarks</a> for projects in Democratic districts and states.</p> 
<p>The panel is expected to reconvene Wednesday morning to discuss a leadership-backed compromise, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the plans — though it wasn’t immediately clear what resolution could satisfy Roy’s demands without alienating Democrats whose support will be key in the Senate. </p> 
<p><b>— Health care:&nbsp;</b>Republicans who hoped a speech from Donald Trump at the Tuesday retreat would bring messaging clarity to their position on health care policy also had their dreams quickly dashed as the president suggested the GOP ought to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/06/conservatives-anti-abortion-trump-health-care-gop-00712565" target="_blank">be “flexible”</a> when it comes to federal funding for abortion.</p> 
<p>It caused an uproar among conservatives who insist any agreement to extend lapsed Affordable Care Act subsidies must include language banning the use of federal funds for abortions — while Democrats say abortion restrictions are a nonstarter.</p> 
<p>Republicans will have to soon decide what compromises they’re willing to make. The House is set to take a procedural vote Wednesday on whether to move forward with legislation that would revive the enhanced ACA subsidies for three years, which Congress let expire in December.</p> 
<p>The bill is expected to pass the House on Thursday with support from all Democrats and a handful of Republicans. Then, senators will have to make the next move.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— More Venezuela briefings: </b>Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth, Attorney General Pam Bondi, CIA Director John Ratcliffe and Joint Chiefs of Staff Chair Gen. Dan Caine will brief all lawmakers on the Venezuela operation Wednesday morning — first in the Senate, then in the House.</p> 
<p><b>— Appropriations movement: </b>Congress has just over three weeks to pass the remaining spending bills needed to avoid another shutdown.</p> 
<p>If lawmakers can pass the Energy-Water, Interior-Environment and Commerce-Justice-Science funding measure by early next week, appropriators are tentatively planning to move two more spending packages. The first, according to Senate Appropriations Chair Susan Collins (R-Maine), would include Homeland, State-Foreign Operations and Financial Services. A final minibus could contain Defense, Labor-HHS-Education and Transportation-HUD.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
