<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Congress</title>
    <link>https://rss.politico.com/congress.xml</link>
    <description>News, Analysis and Opinion from POLITICO</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 17:51:45 EST</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Republican Barry Loudermilk won’t seek reelection</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/barry-loudermilk-georgia-retires-00766319</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2ad9-d3b5-addf-eadd82200000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 17:51:45 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Aaron Pellish</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Aaron Pellish</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Georgia Republican Rep. Barry Loudermilk announced he will not run for reelection this year, the latest Republican to retire amid what’s shaping up to be a tough midterm for Republicans.</p> 
<p>Loudermilk, who was first elected to Congress in 2014, said in a statement he’s retiring to “spend more dedicated time with my family.”</p> 
<p>“Although I continue to have strong support from the people of the Eleventh Congressional District, I believe it is time to contribute to my community, state, and nation in other ways,” he said in the statement.</p> 
<p>Loudermilk’s retirement comes as his select subcommittee reinvestigating the Jan. 6, 2021, attack at the Capitol ramps up its probe. </p> 
<p>The panel — which was launched as a response to the probe helmed by Rep. Bennie Thompson (D-Miss.) and now-former Rep. Liz Cheney (R-Wyo.) in the year after the attack — held its first hearings last month, and <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/jan-6-committee-subpoenas-t-mobile-for-records-relating-to-alleged-pipe-bomb-perpetrator-00764604" target="_blank">subpoenaed for phone records</a> in connection to the suspect accused of placing pipe bombs outside Republican and Democratic headquarters prior to the riot.</p> 
<p>Republicans will expect to retain Loudermilk’s seat in suburban Atlanta in November, which he won by 34 points in 2024. </p> 
<p>But the announcement marks the latest member of the House Republican caucus to leave Congress this cycle. Since the beginning of 2025, <a href="https://pressgallery.house.gov/member-data/casualty-list" target="_blank">33 other House Republicans</a> have resigned, announced their retirements or launched campaigns seeking other elected office.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top Oversight Republican mulls Bill Gates subpoena in Epstein probe</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/house-oversight-mulls-bill-gates-subpoena-00766254</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2ac0-d647-addc-abc7213d0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 17:27:28 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Hailey Fuchs</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Oversight and Government Reform Chair James Comer is considering calling Bill Gates to testify in his ongoing Jeffrey Epstein investigation, saying in an interview Wednesday a bipartisan group of lawmakers on the panel are pressing for a chance to question the billionaire Microsoft founder.</p> 
<p>“We're certainly looking at that, so we'll have more to come on that,” said the Kentucky Republican, adding that he’s been “approached by multiple Republicans and Democrats on the committee that would like to ask Bill Gates questions, so odds are.”</p> 
<p>Comer said he also wants to review an interview from Gates’ ex-wife, Melinda Gates, which will air on NPR Thursday, to see if she divulges any more information about her former husband and the extent of his possible involvement with Epstein, the late convicted sex offender.</p> 
<p>Bill Gates was depicted in the release of Epstein-related materials <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/bill-gates-appears-in-newly-released-photos-from-epstein-estate-00688695" target="_blank">in December</a> but has come under renewed security over his ties to the disgraced financier in the latest set of documents to be made public.</p> 
<p>The newest tranche of files includes allegations that Gates contracted a sexually transmitted disease from women in Epstein’s orbit. A spokesperson for Gates has called the allegations absurd.</p> 
<p>Gates has said he had <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/12/12/bill-gates-appears-in-newly-released-photos-from-epstein-estate-00688695" target="_blank">several dinners</a> with Epstein based on an understanding that Epstein would use his wealthy connections to fundraise for global health causes. When that didn’t happen, Gates told PBS NewsHour in 2021, he cut off the dinners, calling the meetings “a mistake.”</p> 
<p>Comer has already issued subpoenas for other individuals known to have had some ties to Epstein, or mentioned in the Epstein files, including Bill and Hillary Clinton. Negotiations with the former president and secretary of State over the terms of their testimonies dragged on for months, culminating in their final caving to the Oversight committee under threat of being held in contempt of Congress. They will now sit for closed-door depositions at the end of the month.</p> 
<p>It’s not immediately clear if Gates would be willing to share information with the committee.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Democrats plan DHS funding offer as Thune floats long-term punt</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/democrats-dhs-funding-offer-00764643</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-29ea-d647-addc-abefb3bd0007</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 13:30:29 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Democratic and Republican leaders showed no sign of narrowing their <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-funding-deal-shutdown-00763718" target="_blank">differences on Department of Homeland Security funding</a> Wednesday as a Feb. 13 deadline draws nearer.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> and Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> reiterated demands for new restrictions on immigration enforcement agencies at a joint news conference. Flanked by other Democratic leaders, the leaders said they plan to submit draft legislation to Republicans by Thursday.</p> 
<p>“We're going to have tough, strong legislation,” Schumer said. “We want our Republican colleagues to finally get serious about this, because this is turning America inside out.”</p> 
<p>Earlier Wednesday, Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> not only warned that a deal would be next to impossible to consummate before next week’s deadline but threatened a possible long-term stopgap that would effectively exclude changes to immigration enforcement.</p> 
<p>Without quick progress in the talks, he said, “it may be the best way to deal with this particular appropriations bill is, do a year-long CR if that's what it takes,” Thune said, referring to a continuing resolution that would continue existing DHS funding levels through Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>While the two Democratic leaders reiterated in a news conference that they are “on the same page,” Jeffries and Schumer declined to draw the same red lines on a full-year DHS punt.</p> 
<p>Jeffries said after the news conference he is “a hard no” on a full-year CR, while Schumer stopped short of a hard commitment.</p> 
<p>“Republicans shouldn't expect our votes if they're not willing to enact strong, tough reform,” he said when asked if Senate Democrats would oppose another punt.</p> 
<p>The list of demands Jeffries and Schumer laid out Wednesday largely tracks with an earlier list of DHS proposals Senate Democrats put forward after the Jan. 24 killing of a Minneapolis man by federal agents there. They include prohibiting masks for federal agents in most circumstances and requiring a judge to sign off on warrants for DHS immigration apprehensions — proposals that some top Republicans have already rejected.</p> 
<p>In addition to the policy sparring Wednesday, there was some personal squabbling, too — including over who should be involved in notching any agreement.</p> 
<p>Thune suggested any deal needed to be cut primarily between Democrats and the Trump administration. He also warned that he does not view Jeffries as a reliable negotiating partner.</p> 
<p>“He's just not, and I think he and, for that matter, Leader Schumer are afraid of their shadows and they are getting a lot of blowback and pressure from their left,” he said. “I don't think he wants a deal at all. I think he wants the issue.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries, in response to the comments, said it was Thune who is “afraid of his own shadow” in the form of President Donald Trump.</p> 
<p>“We are negotiating in good faith because we want to try to achieve an outcome, but the changes that are enacted with respect to the way in which the Department of Homeland Security is conducting itself need to be bold, meaningful and transformative,” he told reporters.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tim Scott on DOJ probe into Powell: ‘I do not believe that he committed a crime’ in Fed HQ testimony</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/scott-powell-doj-probe-00764230</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2962-d0f8-adde-fb7a8d290000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:02:03 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Victoria Guida</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Victoria Guida</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Banking Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/151800" data-person-id="151800">Tim Scott</a> on Wednesday said he did not believe Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell committed a crime during his congressional testimony last year about the central bank’s headquarter renovations.</p> 
<p>“I was the one asking the questions,” he said on Fox Business. “Jay Powell was responding to me. Obviously, he and I have very, very strong disagreements on many issues, everyone.”</p> 
<p>He said it was time for a new head of the central bank and called Powell “inept” but added: “ineptness or being incompetent is not a criminal act.”</p> 
<p>“I believe what he did was made a gross error in judgment,” Scott said. “He was not prepared for that hearing. I do not believe that he committed a crime during the hearing.”</p> 
<p>The Justice Department issued subpoenas last month to the Fed, probing his statements to Congress, a fact revealed by Powell himself in an unprecedented video message where he accused the administration of using the investigation to pressure him to lower interest rates. Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a> (R-N.C.), saying he fears for the Fed’s independence, has said he will not vote to advance any Fed nominees until the administration has finished its probe.</p> 
<p>Scott said the issue would be “resolved,” adding: “Thom Tillis will be voting for Kevin Warsh as the next chairman of the Federal Reserve.”</p> 
<p>Tillis has spoken positively of Warsh but said his stance regarding the DOJ investigation has not changed.</p> 
<p>Scott’s comments mark the first time that the powerful banking head has substantively weighed in on the administration’s move.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Lawmakers brace for a DHS shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/04/congress/shutdown-dhs-stopgap-funding-bill-ice-cbp-00763914</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-26c3-d42a-afdc-bee75d660000</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress just launched itself onto a nine-day runway to overcome deep partisan divides over the fate of President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda — and conditions are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-funding-deal-shutdown-00763718" target="_blank">trending toward another lengthy shutdown</a> for the Department of Homeland Security.</p> 
<p>According to several senators, DHS funding talks were largely on hold while lawmakers waited for the House to clear the Senate-passed, <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/congress-ends-shutdown-00762482" target="_blank">five-bill spending package</a> Tuesday and end the brief partial government shutdown. Now lawmakers have little time left before the Feb. 13 deadline to reach a bipartisan agreement on major changes to DHS policies and avoid a funding lapse that will also affect TSA, the Coast Guard, FEMA and other agencies — and Democrats are threatening to block any extension of the two-week stopgap measure.</p> 
<p><b>— A stalemate over demands: </b>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer said Tuesday that Democrats plan to formally present Republicans a proposal soon for placing more guardrails around ICE and Customs and Border Protection. The wishlist could include tighter rules on the use of warrants, a ban on masks and mandates for body cameras and IDs on federal agents.</p> 
<p>There’s broad GOP opposition to many of these ideas. Speaker Mike Johnson argued Tuesday that unmasking would be especially dangerous for the agents.</p> 
<p>“I can tell you that we are never going to go along with adding an entirely new layer of judicial warrants,” Johnson added. “It is unimplementable.”</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune believes negotiations will need to be primarily between Democrats and the White House, though Republicans will play a part. He said Alabama Sen. Katie Britt, the top Republican on the Senate Homeland funding panel, will take the lead for the GOP.</p> 
<p>Republicans want to crack down on so-called “sanctuary cities,” localities that don’t comply with federal immigration laws. Some are also mulling whether to try and attach bigger immigration provisions onto the DHS stopgap bill, like increasing penalties for immigrants who cross the border illegally.</p> 
<p>But trying to crack down on “sanctuary cities” has long been a non-starter for Democrats. “We’re not going to make people unsafe, this is about making people safe,” said Washington Sen. Patty Murray, her chamber’s top Democratic appropriator.</p> 
<p><b>— A slippery stopgap slope: </b>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries told reporters Tuesday that “an additional [continuing resolution], from our standpoint, is off the table” despite warnings from Thune and other Republicans that another short-term punt may be necessary to buy more time for talks.</p> 
<p>Some lawmakers are increasingly pessimistic about the prospects for reaching any DHS deal given Congress’ perennial struggle to agree on immigration policy.</p> 
<p>“I’m a little skeptical of the entire project here of trying to lard up an appropriations bill that funds critical agencies with a whole bunch of statutory restrictions,” Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) said.</p> 
<p>Thune warned there’s another possibility: If negotiations drag on too long, lawmakers could eventually be forced to swallow a measure that keeps the status quo at DHS for the remainder of the fiscal year with no policy changes or new funding levels.</p> 
<p>“My assumption would be that even if we don’t have an agreement that we would do a CR for some foreseeable amount of time” to continue discussions, Thune told POLITICO, “or maybe at some point we have to resolve to a full-year CR.”</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Tech hearing: </b>House Judiciary will hold a hearing on Europe’s tech laws at 10 a.m. It’s the latest escalation in the transatlantic fight over regulations that Republicans claim disproportionately silence conservative speech online. European countries view the regulations as crucial guardrails for ensuring online safety and fair market competition, while American tech companies argue such measures target them unfairly.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Gabby Miller contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>With just 10 days to negotiate, a DHS shutdown appears inevitable</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/dhs-funding-deal-shutdown-00763718</link>
      <description>Democrats and Republicans can barely decide on who should be negotiating — let alone how to agree on immigration enforcement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2618-d345-a3bf-273d636b0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:45:29 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/99/db/325d79154798ae47a08a4111f664/2026-0128-congress-francis-6-1-02576.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>John Thune and other Republican leaders are deferring to the White House.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/99/db/325d79154798ae47a08a4111f664/2026-0128-congress-francis-6-1-02576.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill and Mia McCarthy</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress has 10 days to prevent another shutdown — this one exclusively affecting the Department of Homeland Security. There’s not much optimism about a deal.</p> 
<p>At issue is one of the thorniest issues in national politics — federal immigration enforcement, including new guardrails for agencies and repercussions for the local jurisdictions that refuse to cooperate with them.</p> 
<p>Already, Republicans are rejecting central demands from Democrats, including tightening warrant requirements and banning federal agents from wearing masks. Democrats are pouring cold water on a GOP push to target so-called sanctuary cities.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> warned Tuesday that getting an agreement to President Donald Trump’s desk by the new Feb. 13 deadline is an “impossibility.”</p> 
<p>“We’ve got a very short timeframe in which to do this, which I argued against,” he said, referring to his opposition to the two-week DHS punt Democrats insisted on.</p> 
<p>House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a>, meanwhile, said Tuesday that another short-term patch was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/no-more-dhs-crs-jeffries-00762600" target="_blank">“off the table” for Democrats</a>.</p> 
<p>Together those comments portend a potentially lengthy shutdown that would disproportionately impact the DHS functions that don’t involve immigration enforcement, including TSA, FEMA and the Coast Guard. That’s because agencies like ICE and Border Patrol that have been at the center of the Democratic uproar received funding through the domestic policy megabill Republicans enacted in July.</p> 
<p>That reality had a critical mass of Senate Democrats ready to swallow full-year DHS funding last month that held agency budgets flat and passed the House with only seven Democratic votes. But that plan evaporated on Jan. 24, when DHS agents killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti on the streets of Minneapolis and sparked bipartisan calls for new strictures on the Trump administration.</p> 
<p>Thune and other Republicans are already warning that they believe they will need to buy more time after the Feb. 13 deadline. Negotiations over an immigration enforcement deal have largely been on hold, according to several senators, as the House wrestled with the larger <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">spending package</a> that <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/congress-ends-shutdown-00762482" target="_blank">finally passed Tuesday</a>.</p> 
<p>So far, Republicans and Democrats can’t even agree on who will be doing the negotiating. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> is putting the onus on Thune. But Thune and other Republicans believe any viable deal will need to be negotiated primarily by the White House while keeping congressional Republicans “engaged.”</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/201768" data-person-id="201768">Brian Schatz</a> (D-Hawaii) said Tuesday that a deal would be difficult “without Trump deciding to drag Republicans in a direction that is normally uncomfortable for them.”</p> 
<p>“But that's different from John Thune just declaring that he's out,” he added. “The majority leader can't take himself out of the negotiation."</p> 
<p>A lengthy DHS shutdown could be uncomfortable quickly for both parties. While ICE and Customs and Border Protection would largely have a free hand to continue immigration enforcement, the Coast Guard and TSA would lose their appropriations — potentially snarling airports and threatening paychecks for an entire military branch. The Secret Service and Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency would also be affected.</p> 
<p>Plenty of members are skeptical there will be a deal at all, given Congress’ perennial struggle to reach an agreement on anything even <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2024/02/05/congress/deal-nears-collapse-00139779" target="_blank">tangentially related to immigration</a>.</p> 
<p>“I have to say that I’m a little skeptical of this entire enterprise,” Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/307631" data-person-id="307631">Josh Hawley</a> (R-Mo.) said. “I’m a little skeptical of the entire project here of trying to lard up an appropriations bill that funds critical agencies with a whole bunch of statutory restrictions.”</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/134505" data-person-id="134505">Glenn Ivey</a> (D-Md.) said of the incipient negotiation, “I can't say it feels like good faith.”</p> 
<p>Democrats have outlined several key demands for any negotiations and are expected to formally present a proposal “very shortly,” according to Schumer.</p> 
<p>But while Republicans have expressed openness to <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/senators-block-funding-package-amid-dhs-standoff-00754927" target="_blank">some of the Democratic proposals</a>, such as body cameras and deescalation training, there is broad opposition to requiring immigration officers to obtain judicial warrants instead of administrative warrants before seeking apprehensions. Many, including Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>, also oppose requiring federal agents to remove masks, arguing it would be a possible safety threat.</p> 
<p>“I can tell you that we are never going to go along with adding an entirely new layer of judicial warrants,” Johnson said Tuesday. “It is unimplementable. It cannot be done, and it should not be done. It's not necessary.”</p> 
<p>Republicans, meanwhile, are pushing for language cracking down on sanctuary cities that don’t comply with ICE and CBP to be included in any agreement that includes new restrictions on those agencies. Other Republicans are mulling trying to attach bigger immigration provisions, including increasing penalties for immigrants who cross the border illegally or re-enter the country illegally.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.) used an <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/trump-signs-1-2-trillion-funding-bill-to-end-shutdown-and-fund-dhs-for-two-weeks-00763475?utm_medium=twitter&amp;utm_source=dlvr.it" target="_blank">Oval Office bill signing</a> with Trump Tuesday to make his pitch for a sanctuary cities crackdown as part of any negotiation to extend DHS funding.</p> 
<p>“If you want a debate on how to solve this problem, show up next week,” he said.</p> 
<p>Trump encouraged the push: “I hope you’re going to press that very hard,” he told Graham.</p> 
<p>But the policies Graham and other Republicans are proposing — such as imposing criminal penalties on state and local officials who “willfully interfere” with immigration enforcement — have long been a nonstarter for Democrats.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51180" data-person-id="51180">Dick Durbin</a>, the No. 2 Senate Democrat, said it already would be “difficult” to get his caucus to support another funding punt, noting that roughly half of his Democratic colleagues already voted against the last spending package.</p> 
<p>And trying to link sanctuary cities to the debate over immigration enforcement tactics, Durbin added, is “not realistic.”</p> 
<p>“There's so many different versions of sanctuary law in these communities and states,” he said. “What we're talking about is funding this agency, but making sure there are reforms before funding.”</p> 
<p>Other Senate Democrats who voted for the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">spending deal</a> last week — including Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51219" data-person-id="51219">Patty Murray</a> (D-Wash.), the top Democrat on the Appropriations Committee — are already warning that Republicans shouldn’t count on their votes again for another punt.</p> 
<p>Another senior Democratic appropriator, Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/66834" data-person-id="66834">Jeanne Shaheen</a> of New Hampshire, said she believed there was enough time to get a deal if negotiators were “committed.”</p> 
<p>“But it would help if they start negotiating,” Shaheen said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-03T19:58:25-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Mitch McConnell hospitalized with ‘flu-like symptoms’</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/mitch-mcconnell-hospitalized-00763670</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-25e8-d5e0-a1fe-afeec6a80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:51:17 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Mitch McConnell checked himself into a local hospital Monday night "in an abundance of caution" after experiencing "flu-like symptoms," a spokesperson for the Kentucky Republican said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>McConnell missed Senate votes on Monday and Tuesday. A polio survivor, McConnell has had increasingly public mobility challenges, including a series of falls in recent years, and is often seen requiring assistance navigating the Capitol halls.</p> 
<p>He announced last year he <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/02/20/congress/mitch-mcconnell-will-retires-from-senate-00205151" target="_blank">would not seek reelection</a> an eighth time.</p> 
<p>David Popp, the spokesperson, said McConnell's "prognosis is positive" and that he remains in "regular contact with his staff and looks forward to returning to Senate business."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Powell pardon wouldn’t end Fed blockade, Tillis says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/powell-pardon-tillis-blockade-00763054</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2565-d5e0-a1fe-af671d9f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:45:00 EST</pubDate>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A presidential pardon of Federal Reserve Chair Jerome Powell would not end Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/192907" data-person-id="192907">Thom Tillis</a>’ one-man blockade of central bank nominees, the North Carolina Republican said Tuesday.</p> 
<p>Only the Justice Department resolving its investigation into Powell’s Senate testimony on a massive Fed renovation project would suffice, he added, doubling down on his intention to use his vote on the Senate Banking Committee as a <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/11/doj-probe-fed-powell-statements-headquarters-00721679" target="_blank">bulwark against any attempt</a> to dilute the bank’s independence.</p> 
<p>Tillis is the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/kevin-warsh-thom-tillis-federal-reserve-confirmation-00756958" target="_blank">main obstacle to the swift confirmation of Kevin Warsh</a>, President Donald Trump’s nominee to replace Powell as Fed chair. He has vowed to oppose any Fed nominee until the Powell investigation ends.</p> 
<p>A pardon could be a fast and definitive way for Trump to end any legal peril for Powell, but Tillis called the idea “silly” and a “mistake” because it could imply that Powell is guilty of committing perjury during his appearance last year before the Banking Committee.</p> 
<p>“A pardon to me almost validates the whole notion for the investigation,” Tillis said. “If they think they’ve got a valid case, then we’ll just see it through to the end.”</p> 
<p>With Republicans holding a 13-11 majority on the Banking panel, Tillis’ opposition is enough to prevent Warsh from getting advanced out of committee unless he gets support from Democrats on the panel.</p> 
<p>Tillis said Tuesday that he thought Warsh would be a “fine” Fed chair “at some point in the future if not this Congress, then the next Congress, if they don’t get this investigation done.”</p> 
<p>“I’m not budging one inch,” he added. “This is foundational to Fed independence and if you reward this sort of behavior and there’s no compelling evidence that could convince me or a jury that he’s guilty of it then you’ve got to stand on Fed independence.”</p> 
<p>Trump batted down a question Monday about whether he would ask prosecutors to drop the Powell case in order to clear a path for Warsh. He instead told reporters that Jeanine Pirro, the U.S. attorney for D.C., would “take it to the end and see.”</p> 
<p>Responding to Trump’s remarks, Tillis said it showed “an area where we’re in agreement this week — we’re both willing to go all the way.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-03T14:27:29-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Congress ends shutdown, approves $1.2T in funding — and sets up DHS cliff</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/03/congress-ends-shutdown-00762482</link>
      <description>President Donald Trump is expected to swiftly sign the legislation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-24e9-d4f7-a9dd-25ffea1c000d</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:11:16 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b4/5f/6f6bc06c43aeb7d1271a5880c9fc/2026-0202-congress-francis-8-1-03458.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Appropriations Committee Chair Tom Cole (R-Okla.) and Ranking Member Rosa DeLauro (D-Conn.) greet each other as they prepare to testify before the House Rules Committee at the U.S. Capitol, on Feb. 2, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b4/5f/6f6bc06c43aeb7d1271a5880c9fc/2026-0202-congress-francis-8-1-03458.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jennifer Scholtes and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jennifer Scholtes and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Congress approved a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">spending package</a> Tuesday afternoon that secures funding for the vast majority of federal agencies through September, ending the second government shutdown in the span of four months.</p> 
<p>But what’s left unfinished — funding for the Department of Homeland Security — will be a doozy, with partisan tensions over President Donald Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda threatening another lapse for the embattled department that also includes TSA, FEMA and other crucial agencies.</p> 
<p>The package the House passed in a bipartisan 217-214 vote Tuesday afternoon only funds DHS through next week. Democrats are refusing to support months of additional cash until Republicans agree to rein in the actions of ICE and Border Patrol agents following the fatal shootings last month of two U.S. citizens in Minnesota.</p> 
<p>Trump is expected to swiftly sign the legislation, ending the partial government shutdown that began early Saturday morning after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615" target="_blank">the Senate passed</a> the altered package, punting the measure back to the House.</p> 
<p>But if Republicans don’t concede to enacting significant new mandates for DHS by the new Feb. 13 deadline, the department many Democrats have called “rogue” will face another funding lapse or short-term patch.</p> 
<p>“We have a list that we want done, and we aren't settling for half-measures,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/226960" data-person-id="226960">Pete Aguilar</a> (D-Calif.), the No. 3 party leader, told reporters Tuesday. He warned that if Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> and Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> “don't want to come to the table and negotiate real reform, then they're going to have to explain to the American public why they're shutting down agencies.”</p> 
<p>House GOP leaders signaled Tuesday that they will defer to Trump in negotiating a DHS agreement with Democrats.</p> 
<p>“We will keep the wheels of progress turning and let the president do what he does best, and that's negotiate a final deal on his signature issue,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364726" data-person-id="364726">Lisa McClain</a> (R-Mich.), the No. 4 GOP leader, said Tuesday. “If anyone can get this deal done that is going to crack down on illegal criminal aliens to protect our community, that's going to be President Donald J. Trump.”</p> 
<p>By advancing the trillion-dollar package, Congress has approved more than 95 percent of the government funding it approves each year to run federal agencies, after clearing full funding for <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/11/12/house-votes-to-reopen-government-after-43-day-shutdown-00649927" target="_blank">some agencies in November</a> and <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/15/congress-funding-government-shutdown-00732209" target="_blank">another slate in January</a>.</p> 
<p>Under the legislation that now awaits the president’s signature, the Pentagon and all remaining domestic agencies besides DHS will get new funding levels through the end of the fiscal year, which started with the longest government shutdown in U.S. history.</p> 
<p>“We finalized true, bipartisan, bicameral bills to fully fund our government in a member driven, district focused way,” House Appropriations Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51327" data-person-id="51327">Tom Cole</a> (R-Okla.) said on the House floor. “Funding the government is not an optional exercise. It's the most basic duty we have in Congress.”</p> 
<p>Only 21 Democrats voted yes on passage, highlighting the challenge leaders face over the next 10 days in negotiating new immigration enforcement rules that can attract enough Democratic support for funding DHS into the fall.</p> 
<p>“I refuse to send another cent to Stephen Miller or Kristi Noem,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512">Jim McGovern</a> (D-Mass.) said this week. “They are undermining our Constitution, and the department they run is murdering American citizens in the streets.”</p> 
<p>To ensure Democratic leaders on both sides of the Capitol are aligned heading into negotiations with Republicans over changes to DHS immigration operations, House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> is set to meet Tuesday afternoon with Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a>.</p> 
<p>House Democrats are demanding that Jeffries have a seat at the bargaining table after many <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/house-democrats-senate-spending-deal-00761523" target="_blank">groused this week</a> about the altered funding package Senate Democrats brokered with the White House.</p> 
<p>“They need to talk to Hakeem — the House and Senate are equal partners,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/152934" data-person-id="152934">Debbie Dingell</a> (D-Mich.) said in an interview.</p> 
<p>House Democrats contend that they have a better understanding of Trump’s immigration enforcement actions in communities throughout the country, as well as the sentiment of Americans.</p> 
<p>“We are the ones that are closest to the anger and the frustration of our constituents,” Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/239242" data-person-id="239242">Pramila Jayapal</a> (D-Wash.) said in an interview. “We need [Senate Democrats] to start negotiating with us and carrying out our demands instead of constantly caving to Republicans.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-03T12:56:05-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Shutdown end in sight after spending package clears key House hurdle</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/shutdown-ending-house-rule-00762233</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2493-d1ed-a59e-f7df009d0009</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 12:37:23 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">spending package</a> that would fund the vast majority of the federal government cleared a key procedural hurdle Tuesday, setting up votes later in the day to send the measure to the White House for President Donald Trump’s signature.</p> 
<p>Final passage of the measure, which also includes a funding patch for the Department of Homeland Security through Feb. 13, would end the partial government shutdown that began Saturday.</p> 
<p>Republicans stayed mostly united on the 217-215 test vote to advance the package that would fund the Pentagon and departments of Health and Human Services, Labor, Housing and Urban Development, Transportation, and Education through Sept. 30 and less than two weeks of funding for Homeland Security Department.</p> 
<p>The short-term DHS funding is intended to give lawmakers time to negotiate reforms to how ICE and CBP officers execute the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement crackdown, with the hope of tamping down instances where federal officers have killed U.S. citizens. Republicans have their own demands, such as blocking federal funding on “sanctuary cities” that don’t cooperate with federal enforcement agencies.</p> 
<p>The largely unified GOP vote came on the heels of a <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/02/house-gop-moves-to-tee-up-passage-of-shutdown-ending-package-00761481" target="_blank">White House whip operation</a> that headed off a handful of defections from within Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a>’s party. Trump’s call for there to be no changes to the package in the House helped quell an effort from hard-line conservatives to attach a partisan elections bill, known as the SAVE Act, to the rule.</p> 
<p>Johnson, Majority Whip <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227580" data-person-id="227580">Tom Emmer</a> and Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> also did some personal whipping on the House floor during the vote series, circulating between some of the most hard-line members of the Republican Conference in the lead-up to and during the rule vote. It was a nail-biter for the leaders, with the vote held open for nearly an hour as they tried to bring their GOP colleagues in line.</p> 
<p>James Blair, Trump's top political adviser, made calls to the holdouts during the vote, according to two people granted anonymity to describe the private whip effort. Trump urged Republicans to back the spending bill Monday in a Truth Social post.</p> 
<p>Final passage of <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2026/01/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615" target="_blank">the Senate-passed</a> $1.2 trillion funding package is expected Tuesday afternoon on a bipartisan vote.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No filibuster deal with House conservatives, Thune says</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/thune-filibuster-deal-luna-00761867</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2421-dbc5-a7bd-3dbd417c0005</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 10:32:17 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune said in an interview Tuesday he has made no decisions about bypassing Senate filibuster rules to skirt the normal 60-vote margin required to advance legislation in the chamber.</p> 
<p>Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) said Monday she had White House-brokered "assurances" that the Senate would allow for a "standing" or "talking" filibuster that could allow the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_22" target="_blank">SAVE Act</a>, a House-passed elections bill <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/02/congress/mike-johnson-save-act-spending-00760523" target="_blank">pushed by conservative hard-liners</a>, to be enacted into law.</p> 
<p>Thune was not party to Luna's conversation with President Donald Trump, which prompted Luna to indicate she would support a massive spending bill moving through the House on Tuesday. Many GOP senators have long opposed weakening the 60-vote margin, believing it would open the door to far-reaching Democratic policies.</p> 
<p>"Some of our colleagues in the Senate are interested in it," Thune said. "We will have a conversation about it. Nothing decided."</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House GOP leaders set noon deadline for Clintons to reach deal on testifying</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/clintons-on-a-deadline-00761688</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-23d6-df17-afbf-7ff737a20000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 09:17:43 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker Mike Johnson said in an interview Tuesday morning that Republicans have given Bill and Hillary Clinton a noon deadline Tuesday to provide details of how they plan to comply with a pair of subpoenas issued by the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee, which have until this point gone unheeded.</p> 
<p>Otherwise, Johnson said, Republicans will move forward with votes later this week to hold the former president and secretary of state in criminal contempt of Congress.</p> 
<p>“We're holding off until noon,” Johnson said. “They have a deadline until noon to work out the details, and if it's not done satisfactorily, then we'll proceed with the contempt.”</p> 
<p>Majority Leader Steve Scalise also said in an interview that, if the details aren't provided, then Republicans will proceed with a vote Wednesday as leadership had initially intended before the Clintons surprised Capitol Hill by reversing course. They had for months been resisting subpoenas to testify in the House Oversight investigation into the convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein, saying the process was invalid and designed to embarrass and put them in prison.</p> 
<p>According to a person granted anonymity to share internal discussions between the Oversight Committee and the Clintons' legal team, the GOP-led panel is seeking clarification that the Clintons will accept the standard deposition terms for which they were originally subpoenaed. That includes transcribed, filmed depositions to take place in February, with no time limits.</p> 
<p>House Republicans appeared somewhat cautious Tuesday morning about pulling the trigger on the contempt votes, however. House Oversight Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) was still interested in speaking with the former first couple in the service of his ongoing investigation — even after months of them dragging their feet — and Republicans continue to see the threat of contempt as a legitimate persuasion mechanism.</p> 
<p>"What we need is a signature on agreeing to terms," said Rep. Scott Perry (R-Pa.), who brought the initial request in the Oversight subcommittee to subpoena the Clintons, in an interview. “I think we should have the deposition, but the contempt resolution needs to hang there and be available until we’re done."</p> 
<p>Rep. Kevin Kiley (R-Calif.) also emphasized in an interview that the threat of contempt has historically provided an important piece of leverage to compel testimony. The goal was always for the Clintons to cooperate, he added.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Shutdown hinges on razor-thin rule vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/03/congress/shutdown-rule-vote-save-act-deal-filibuster-00761574</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-220d-dbc5-a7bd-3bbde67f0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Republican leaders are facing a white-knuckle vote Tuesday morning as they move to end the partial shutdown after four days.</p> 
<p>Here’s what we’re watching on both sides of the aisle as an unpredictable day shakes out in the House.</p> 
<p><b>— Razor-thin rule vote:&nbsp;</b>Speaker Mike Johnson and President Donald Trump got involved in wrangling hard-liner holdouts Monday who were threatening to oppose the procedural measure setting up final debate of the $1.2 trillion spending package.</p> 
<p>Reps. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) and Tim Burchett (R-Tenn.) started the day threatening to tank the rule if the SAVE Act, a partisan elections bill, wasn’t attached. But a White House meeting left the duo in a better place, with Luna telling reporters Monday night she got “assurances on the standing filibuster” that would allow the bill to pass the Senate.</p> 
<p>One big caveat: There’s been no acknowledgment from Senate Majority Leader John Thune that any such deal is in place.</p> 
<p>Various proposals for a “standing filibuster” or “talking filibuster” have been rattling around for years on both sides of the aisle — most recently from Sen. Mike Lee (R-Utah) — but that hasn’t convinced the vast majority of Senate Republicans who want to keep the 60-vote threshold in place.</p> 
<p>While Luna said she expected “an announcement” on a rules change that would force Democrats to hold the floor in order to block the bill, no such announcement appears imminent. But her remarks — and a big midday <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/116002871169002695" target="_blank">Truth Social nudge</a> from Trump — were enough to buoy GOP leaders.</p> 
<p>Asked Monday night if he was confident he had the votes to move forward and end the shutdown, Johnson said, “I think we do.”</p> 
<p><b>— Dems fume over another Senate jam:</b> While Democrats are expected to unite against the rule, party leaders declined to comment on how they would vote on the overall package ahead of Tuesday morning’s closed-door caucus meeting.</p> 
<p>It appears it will be a vote of conscience: A whip alert circulated Monday night urged a “no” vote on the rule but did not offer any guidance for the underlying bill, which funds most federal agencies but ends Department of Homeland Security funding after Feb. 13.</p> 
<p>Still, many House Democrats <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/house-democrats-senate-spending-deal-00761523" target="_blank">have been left grumbling</a> — again — after being sidelined in negotiations between Senate Democrats and the White House.</p> 
<p>Top leaders Hakeem Jeffries and Chuck Schumer are playing down tensions over the deal, but many in the rank-and-file are miffed at getting jammed with a spending bill they oppose for a third time in less than a year.</p> 
<p>“We end up having to answer for what [the Senate] won’t do, and it can be very frustrating,” Rep. Pramila Jayapal (D-Wash.) said.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— House moves to overturn D.C. tax law: </b>The House Rules Committee teed up floor consideration this week for a bill that would roll back a D.C. law that declines to apply key tax cuts from last summer’s megabill to local income taxes in the city.</p> 
<p>In that measure, the D.C. Council decided not to adopt 13 separate tax provisions from the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, including several key incentives the GOP restored for businesses and the deductions for tipped income, overtime pay, new car loan interest and seniors.</p> 
<p>The Senate Homeland Security Committee is scheduled to consider its version of the resolution Wednesday.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Bernie Becker contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Democrats once again left complaining about a Senate spending deal</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/house-democrats-senate-spending-deal-00761523</link>
      <description>A bipartisan agreement to temporarily extend Homeland Security funding is rekindling tensions between the two chambers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-216e-df8c-a99d-f5fe24bb0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 21:58:52 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/b2/13/c58677304c2b9d92ceede9a9b108/2026-0202-congress-francis-5-1-10148.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries (D-N.Y.) speaks during a press conference on Capitol Hill Feb. 2, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/b2/13/c58677304c2b9d92ceede9a9b108/2026-0202-congress-francis-5-1-10148.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Mia McCarthy and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Mia McCarthy and Meredith Lee Hill</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For the third time in less than a year, a spending deal brokered in the Senate has House Democrats feeling left out — and grumbling about their counterparts across the Capitol.</p> 
<p>This time, the agreement between President Donald Trump and Senate Democratic leaders would spare the vast majority of federal agencies from an extended shutdown. Most would be funded through the end of the fiscal year in September, while Homeland Security funding would extend only through Feb. 13.</p> 
<p>But to Democrats up in arms over Trump’s immigration enforcement agenda, that’s still 10 days of DHS funding too many — assuming the deal passes the House as planned Tuesday — leaving them to vent once again about the other chamber.</p> 
<p>“There are some Senate Democrats who always signal nervousness and are so reluctant to be strong,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/239242" data-person-id="239242">Pramila Jayapal</a> (D-Wash.). “We end up having to answer for what they won't do, and it can be very frustrating.”</p> 
<p>“We are far closer to the people,” said Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/304660" data-person-id="304660">Veronica Escobar</a> (D-Texas), adding that it’s “critically important that House members be brought in” during negotiations over immigration enforcement constraints considering ICE, Border Patrol and other agencies are deployed in their districts.</p> 
<p>The interchamber tensions between Democrats are becoming a regular feature of funding fights in the second Trump term. Lawmakers, strategists and voters alike exploded in anger last March when Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> and a handful of colleagues allowed a spending package to move forward amid the Elon Musk-led DOGE assault on federal agencies. In November, tempers again flared when a handful of Senate Democrats joined with Republicans to end a record 43-day shutdown.</p> 
<p>This time, the situation is more nuanced. At stake is <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">$1.2 trillion in full-year funding</a> that was negotiated on a bipartisan basis; Democrats generally support the vast majority of the agreement. But the inclusion of the DHS money has been a sore spot — especially after the killing last month of two U.S. citizens by federal agents in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>A version of the DHS bill passed in the House before the Jan. 24 killing of Alex Pretti garnered only seven Democratic votes. Senate Democrats immediately declared a no-go on full-year funding for the department after the incident, and Schumer and Trump negotiated a two-week punt to allow for further talks.</p> 
<p>Fewer than half of Senate Democratic Caucus members ultimately ended up voting for the deal, however, and support among House Democrats is considerably more scant.</p> 
<p>Asked if House Democrats were sufficiently read in on the Trump-Schumer deal, Democratic Caucus Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/226960" data-person-id="226960">Pete Aguilar</a> said “no” but added, “I don’t think that that’s surprising.”</p> 
<p>“But I think the split among senators was kind of surprising,” the California lawmaker added. “And so … we'll see what happens.”</p> 
<p>The spending package is headed to the floor Tuesday, where it remains an open question if House Republicans will be able to unite on a key test vote. Late last week — facing dissension in his own ranks over having to pass a bill with only temporary DHS funding — Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> entertained using a bipartisan fast-track process.</p> 
<p>But members of Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries’</a> leadership circle were caught unaware — with some downright livid — at Johnson’s confidence that he could pass the bill under that process — which would require a two-thirds-majority vote, meaning at least 70 Democrats would be needed to get it across the line.</p> 
<p>Such a move generally requires tacit agreement from minority party leaders to supply the votes. But Republicans at that point hadn’t asked their Democratic counterparts for a more formal private count of how many Democrats might support the measure, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the sensitive matter.</p> 
<p>Jeffries told Johnson just hours later on a private call that Democratic leadership would not commit to delivering the required votes for a fast-track vote, forcing Johnson to gather GOP votes to jump through a procedural hurdle first. Johnson has since accused Democrats of “playing games” with the shutdown-ending package.</p> 
<p>Those interparty antics have helped deflect attention from internal Democratic tensions over the Senate-brokered funding deal, with Jeffries playing down any such rift Monday.</p> 
<p>“I speak regularly with Leader Schumer, and I speak regularly with Mike Johnson,” he said when asked if House Democrats were properly consulted in the funding package negotiations. “There's no daylight between House and Senate Democrats on accomplishing the objective, which is dramatic reform of ICE.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries opposed the prior package, with full-year DHS funding, but would not say Monday how he intended to vote on the revised bill with the short-term stopgap.</p> 
<p>Schumer, for his part, said he spoke with Jeffries during the negotiations that erupted in the Senate following Pretti’s killing. He said after the Senate vote Friday night that Jeffries had agreed on limiting DHS funding to Feb. 13.</p> 
<p>“This bill was negotiated by … [Senate Majority LeaderJohn] Thune and me,” Schumer said. “But I’ve talked to Hakeem Jeffries. For instance, we talked about how long a [stopgap] should be, because we wanted to limit it greatly.”</p> 
<p>Asked about Schumer’s comment Monday, Jeffries said, “I think what we made clear to the Senate is that the original three-month proposal was completely and totally unacceptable.”</p> 
<p>Behind the scenes, Schumer told the White House and congressional Republicans last week that they would need to talk to Jeffries because the bill was going back to the House, according to a person granted anonymity to disclose a private conversation.</p> 
<p>If Republicans can get the bill over the procedural hurdle Tuesday, more Democrats are expected to support it than the seven who backed the previous version. But the party remained sharply divided Monday.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a> of Connecticut, the top Appropriations Committee Democrat, said Monday she would support the bill on the floor, while another panel leader, Massachusetts Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512">Jim McGovern</a> of the Rules Committee, said he would oppose it.</p> 
<p>"I will not vote for business as usual while masked agents break into people's homes without a judicial warrant in violation of the Fourth Amendment,” McGovern said.</p> 
<p>Others declined to forecast their plans, including members of the Democratic leadership team. Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/189606" data-person-id="189606">Ted Lieu</a> of California, the caucus vice chair, said he planned to attend Tuesday morning’s caucus meeting before deciding.</p> 
<p>Several Democrats said they do not expect party leaders to formally whip votes for or against the funding package, with some acknowledging that it would not be an easy decision for members who support the vast majority of the funding bill and also don’t want to see noncontroversial DHS agencies such as FEMA and TSA shut down.</p> 
<p>And blaming the Senate for having to take a tough note, one Democrat noted, is hardly new.</p> 
<p>“I've been here long enough that people always complain about the other chamber, so that's always an easy out,” Aguilar said.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>House Republicans eye next week for housing bill vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/02/congress/republicans-housing-bill-vote-00761249</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-20ab-df8c-a99d-f5ff1d300000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 19:27:16 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House leadership is eyeing the week of Feb. 9 for a vote on a bipartisan housing package, according to four people with direct knowledge of the planning.</p> 
<p>Senior lawmakers have also been mulling whether to consider the widely supported bill under suspension of House rules, which would expedite passage of the legislation, said three of the people who were granted anonymity to discuss internal deliberations.</p> 
<p>However, plans for the bill are not locked in and could be subject to change as the House deals with a partial government shutdown.</p> 
<p>The <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6644?activeTabs=overview" target="_blank">Housing in the 21st Century Act</a>, which <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/article/2025/12/house-financial-services-advances-housing-package-community-banking-bills-00695771" target="_blank">overwhelmingly advanced through the House Financial Services Committee in December</a>, is part of a push by Congress to pass legislation that could address a growing housing affordability crisis. The bill includes 25 provisions that aim to increase the housing supply, modernize local development and rural housing programs, expand manufactured and affordable housing, protect borrowers and those utilizing federal housing programs, and enhance oversight of housing providers.</p> 
<p>House Financial Services Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/227472" data-person-id="227472">French Hill</a> (R-Ark.) said Friday that he’s pushing for the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_6644?q=hr+6644" target="_blank">Housing for the 21st Century Act</a> to receive a floor vote expeditiously.</p> 
<p>”I hope that that bill can come to the House floor in just a few days. I really am pushing for that, I think it’s the right decision,” Hill said on Bloomberg Radio.</p> 
<p>The Senate’s housing bill, the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_S_2651?activeTabs=overview" target="_blank">ROAD to Housing Act,</a> passed the upper chamber as an amendment to the National Defense Authorization Act but may be put to a separate floor vote. If the House is able to pass its own version by a wide margin before the Senate, it could have additional leverage for negotiations with the upper chamber for a final bill. Hill and other House Republicans have said the Senate bill, which received overwhelming bipartisan support in the Senate Banking Committee, has a number of provisions that would <a href="https://subscriber.politicopro.com/newsletter/2026/01/the-long-and-winding-road-to-housing-legislation-00736040" target="_blank">not be acceptable among House GOP members</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-02T21:39:43-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Bill and Hillary Clinton now agree to testify before Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/02/bill-and-hillary-clinton-will-now-testify-before-congress-00761325</link>
      <description>It's a stunning change of heart for the former first couple as a contempt vote loomed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-20b0-d1ed-a59e-f3fd66460000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 18:41:42 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/68/05/744897bd42329cfc27807eabde0e/epstein-congress-clintons-35805.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">AP</media:credit>
        <media:title>FILE - Former President Bill Clinton, left, and former Secretary of State Hillary Clinton listen as Vice President Kamala Harris delivers a eulogy for U.S. Rep. Sheila Jackson Lee, Aug. 1, 2024, in Houston. (AP Photo/LM Otero, File)</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/68/05/744897bd42329cfc27807eabde0e/epstein-congress-clintons-35805.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Hailey Fuchs and Calen Razor</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Hailey Fuchs and Calen Razor</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Bill and Hillary Clinton have agreed to testify before the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee as part of the panel's investigation into convicted sex offender Jeffrey Epstein.</p> 
<p>It's a remarkable reversal for the former president and secretary of state, who last month chose to defy committee-issued subpoenas and risk imprisonment by the Trump Justice Department — but changed their minds as the House prepared to vote Wednesday to call their bluff and hold them both in contempt of Congress.</p> 
<p>The House could end up considering the contempt resolutions this week, anyway. GOP leaders were, Monday night, not ruling out moving ahead with the votes if they ultimately decide the Clintons are not making a good-faith effort to expeditiously schedule their depositions with Oversight members and staff.</p> 
<p>After months of refusing to cooperate, the Clintons announced they were now willing to comply with the subpoenas as the House Rules Committee was in the middle of meeting to tee up consideration on the contempt resolutions for later in the week. The unexpected turn of events scrambled the GOP’s plans and it’s not quite clear what comes next.</p> 
<p>"I think we need more time … to clarify with the Clintons what they are actually agreeing to,” said Rules Chair Virginia Foxx (R-N.C.). “Accordingly the committee will postpone further consideration of the contempt. However, should there not be substantial compliance and agreement overnight, the committee will return to continue the hearing on the contempt."</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Bill Clinton said in a statement on social media that the former first couple “look forward[s] to setting a precedent that applies to everyone.”</p> 
<p>The Oversight Committee voted on a bipartisan basis in January to approve a contempt measure for each of the Clintons after both skipped their scheduled depositions earlier this year.</p> 
<p>Although both have said they had no knowledge of Epstein’s crimes, they have maintained that the subpoenas were not tied to a legitimate legislative purpose, rendering them invalid. Bill and Hillary Clinton also argued that the GOP-led exercise was designed to embarrass and put them in jail.</p> 
<p>“The Clintons’ counsel has said they agree to terms, but those terms lack clarity yet again and they have provided no dates for their depositions,” House Oversight Chair James Comer said in a statement Monday. “The only reason they have said they agree to terms is because the House has moved forward with contempt. I will clarify the terms they are agreeing to and then discuss next steps with my committee members.”</p> 
<p>Some Democrats warned House Republicans not to proceed.</p> 
<p>"If you try to move forward, that would be insane," the top Democrat on House Oversight, Rep. Robert Garcia of California, told reporters. "I mean, that would be unprecedented. It would be clearly — it would be clearly a demonstration that [Chair James] Comer is actually not interested in hearing the Clintons, but he's only interested in political games. I think that would be a huge disservice to the survivors and to the investigation.”</p> 
<p>Rep. Suhan Subramanyam (D-Va.), a member of the Oversight panel, also said he feared Republicans would still go through with the House vote for a political end.</p> 
<p>"The Republicans want to give Trump the ability to prosecute and put the Clintons in jail," he said in a brief interview. "That's what this is really about. This isn't about the Epstein investigation.”</p> 
<p>Former Speaker Nancy Pelosi (D-Calif.) suggested to reporters the Clintons were in a lose-lose situation no matter what happens.</p> 
<p>“This is a snake pit. It's a snake pit,” she said. ‘So it's not a question of whether you have to come in. That’s just the way it is.”</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top House Democrats split on funding vote</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/02/congress/top-house-democrats-split-on-funding-vote-00760923</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2071-dbc5-a7bd-39fdbb600000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 17:21:47 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Senior House Democrats are going in different directions on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">massive funding bill</a> headed to the House floor as soon as Tuesday, underscoring the sharp divisions inside the Democratic ranks on the $1.2 trillion spending package.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51351" data-person-id="51351">Rosa DeLauro</a> of Connecticut, the Democrat on the House Appropriations Committee, said Monday she would vote for the funding package when it goes to the floor Tuesday — breaking with a large swath of colleagues who oppose the measure over its extension of Homeland Security funding, including immigration enforcement operations.</p> 
<p>"I will support this package," DeLauro said during Monday meeting of the Rules Committee. She noted it secures funding for the five-full year, bipartisan bills and extends funding at current levels for DHS for 10 days.</p> 
<p>DeLauro said without the DHS stopgap Democrats "won't be able to bring the kinds of pressure" necessary to make changes to the full-year DHS bill they're negotiating with the White House.</p> 
<p>But Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51512" data-person-id="51512">Jim McGovern</a> of Massachusetts, the top Rules Democrat, said he was dead-set against the bill due to the DHS funding.</p> 
<p>"I will not vote for business as usual while masked agents break into people's homes without a judicial warrant, in violation of the Fourth Amendment," he said.</p> 
<p>Neither leader, however, is expected to vote for a key procedural measure setting up a final debate and approval for the massive bill, which passed the Senate on Friday. That measure, known as a rule, is also expected to tee up contempt-of-Congress votes on Bill and Hillary Clinton over their decision not to fully cooperate in a Oversight Committee probe into Jeffrey Epstein. GOP leaders are scrambling to build support for that measure as some in their ranks agitate for amendments, including the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/02/congress/mike-johnson-save-act-spending-00760523" target="_blank">attachment</a> of a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_22" target="_blank">partisan elections bill</a>.</p> 
<p>“Republicans have a responsibility to move the rule, which, by the way, includes a wide variety of other issues that we strongly disagree with," House Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> told reporters Monday.</p> 
<p><i>Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-02-02T16:34:48-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>How Mike Johnson is scrambling to keep the shutdown short</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/02/congress/mike-johnson-save-act-spending-00760523</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-2003-df8c-a99d-f5f786a60000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 15:21:34 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> is pushing forward with a plan to get a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">massive funding package</a> through the House without changes Tuesday, ending a brief partial government shutdown.</p> 
<p>Johnson met with Rules Committee Republicans Monday, shortly before the panel convened to take up a floor plan for the funding bill. The meeting was expected to include discussion of how to handle conservative hard-liners’ demands to attach a partisan elections bill to the $1.2 trillion spending package.</p> 
<p>But any change to the bill could add days more to the three-day partial government shutdown that Johnson is hoping to end Tuesday with House approval of the Senate-passed legislation that combines five full-year funding bills with a two-week extension of Homeland Security spending.</p> 
<p>Rep. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/364729" data-person-id="364729">Anna Paulina Luna</a> (R-Fla.) is vowing to block any move to tee up the Senate-approved package for a final vote unless Johnson moves to attach the elections bill, known as the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_22" target="_blank">SAVE Act</a>. With a razor-thin majority, Johnson can afford no more than one Republican defection on a party-line vote.</p> 
<p>Johnson came out of the Rules meeting Monday playing down the possibility that the elections bill would be added. </p> 
<p>“We all want the SAVE Act. We also look at the reality of the numbers here," he said. "But this is a funding package right now, and I don't think we need to be playing games with government funding. We still have winter storms. We've FEMA and TSA and troop pay and everything else wrapped into this. So we need to get the job done.”</p> 
<p>Johnson got a helping hand Monday from President Donald Trump, who posted on Truth Social that he wanted the funding bill "through the House and to my desk, where I will sign it into Law, IMMEDIATELY!"</p> 
<p>"There can be NO CHANGES at this time," he wrote. "We will work together in good faith to address the issues that have been raised, but we cannot have another long, pointless, and destructive Shutdown."</p> 
<p>House Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/59655" data-person-id="59655">Steve Scalise</a> told reporters Monday that GOP leaders haven’t made any final decisions on how to handle the SAVE Act but Trump emphasized in a recent Oval Office meeting that he wanted the funding legislation quickly passed.</p> 
<p>“The president obviously really wants this,” he said.</p> 
<p>The SAVE Act, which <a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/weekly-score/2025/04/14/the-house-passed-the-save-act-what-comes-next-00288458" target="_blank">passed the House</a> with scant Democratic support last year, would require citizenship documentation to register to vote and several cut back on mail voting. A new version of the bill would also require photo ID to vote.</p> 
<p>Tacking it on to the funding package would essentially guarantee that the government shutdown Johnson and Trump are desperately trying to end as quickly as possible would continue for days — or longer. Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a> warned Monday that the SAVE Act was “dead on arrival” in the other chamber, with Democrats arguing it creates unnecessary barriers to voting.</p> 
<p>“If House Republicans add the SAVE Act to the bipartisan appropriations package it will lead to another prolonged Trump government shutdown,” Schumer said.</p> 
<p>Luna said in an interview Monday that her position has not changed as Johnson faces a growing pressure campaign from both his own members and an army of hard-right online influencers pressing for the election bill’s inclusion.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Mike Johnson’s shutdown gamble</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/02/02/congress/shutdown-vote-timeline-dhs-deal-ice-johnson-00759588</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1c6b-d1ed-a59e-df7f5fea0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House GOP leaders face an uphill battle to pass the revamped government funding package from the Senate, potentially dragging out the shutdown.</p> 
<p>Speaker Mike Johnson hopes to pass the five full-year funding bills and the two-week DHS stopgap Tuesday relying only on Republicans, after Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries told him he wouldn’t help secure the Democrats needed <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/shutdown-tuesday-house-votes-00759001" target="_blank">to expedite the legislation</a>. GOP leaders will have to quell an internal Republican revolt before they get there.</p> 
<p>Here’s how things are shaping up ahead of Tuesday:</p> 
<p><b>— Democrats divided, Republicans seek unity: </b>Most House Democrats who spoke during a private caucus call Sunday evening were against <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615" target="_blank">the package</a>, which was negotiated by Senate Democrats and the White House. House Homeland Security ranking member Bennie Thompson (D-Miss.) was among the Democrats urging members to oppose it in a Dear Colleague email Sunday night.</p> 
<p>But some senior Democrats on the call said they supported the legislation, including Reps. Steny Hoyer of Maryland, Jim Clyburn of South Carolina and New Democrat Coalition Chair Brad Schneider of Illinois, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss the conversation. The disconnect between leadership and other senior members is triggering some hand-wringing among frontline Democrats about what to do next.</p> 
<p>Even though some Democrats are signaling they’d vote for the package in the end, it’s not clear whether Johnson can get past the procedural step of adopting a rule with GOP support still uncertain and Democrats unlikely to bail him out.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders and White House officials are trying to convince key hard-liners to get on board.</p> 
<p>Reps. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) and Tim Burchett (R-Tenn.) are among the Republicans who want to attach legislation aimed at preventing noncitizens from voting in elections. Some ultra-conservatives oppose the Senate agreement overall and would prefer a Homeland stopgap that lasts six weeks or longer.</p> 
<p>Luna said Sunday night that “<a href="https://x.com/RepLuna/status/2018144774662832275?s=20" target="_blank">these appropriations bills will FAIL</a>” if the election citizenship legislation isn’t included.</p> 
<p><b>— Bigger DHS deal looks tougher:</b> Key lawmakers continue to raise red flags about striking a deal on a full-year DHS funding bill by the time the two-week CR expires.</p> 
<p>Johnson on Sunday <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/mike-johnson-government-shutdown-by-tuesday-00759107" target="_blank">panned Democrats’ demands</a> to bar federal immigration enforcement officers from wearing masks and to require them to wear identification. He also signaled unwillingness to negotiate on tightening requirements for judicial warrants for immigration operations. Jeffries is insisting that an agreement on judicial warrants is “a condition of moving forward.”</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader John Thune doesn’t believe Congress can pass a Homeland Security deal in two weeks, telling reporters late last week that “a two-week CR probably means there’s going to be another two-week CR and then maybe another two-week CR after that.”</p> 
<p>“I just think it’s going to be really, really hard to get anything done and then actually execute on the procedures and process we have in the Senate, even if there’s an agreement,” he said.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Johnson to swear in new Dem: </b>Johnson plans to swear in Houston Democrat Christian Menefee before votes Monday night, pending final certification of his special runoff victory to serve out the rest of the late Rep. Sylvester Turner’s term. Once Menefee joins the House, Johnson will have a single-vote buffer with 218 Republicans and 214 Democrats.</p> 
<p><i>Jordain Carney, Meredith Lee Hill, Mia McCarthy and Nicholas Wu contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mike Johnson says House can end government shutdown 'by Tuesday'</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/02/01/mike-johnson-government-shutdown-by-tuesday-00759107</link>
      <description>The House speaker projected confidence about swiftly getting his caucus in line to pass spending for the Department of Homeland Security.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1a02-dbc5-a7bd-1bbed6f40000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 12:19:12 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/03/ca/084d44a34126833cfd97ed3c5d2b/gettyimages-2256854502.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Saul Loeb/AFP via Getty Images</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Speaker Mike Johnson answers questions at a press conference on Capitol Hill on January 21.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/03/ca/084d44a34126833cfd97ed3c5d2b/gettyimages-2256854502.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jacob Wendler</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jacob Wendler</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>House Speaker Mike Johnson said he is confident Congress can end the partial government shutdown "by Tuesday" despite steep opposition from Democrats and turmoil within the GOP conference.</p> 
<p>Johnson is under pressure to unite his caucus, with lawmakers <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/government-shutdown-dhs-minnesota-00748628" target="_blank">raising concerns</a> about funding for the Department of Homeland Security as the Trump administration <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/white-house-reckons-with-gop-backlash-after-federal-agents-kill-a-second-person-in-minneapolis-00746737" target="_blank">faces scrutiny</a> over its nationwide immigration crackdown that has at times turned violent.</p> 
<p>House Republicans are <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/shutdown-tuesday-house-votes-00759001" target="_blank">hoping to take up</a> the $1.2 trillion funding package passed by the Senate on Tuesday following a House Rules Committee meeting Monday. The partial shutdown began early Saturday.</p> 
<p>GOP leadership in the House <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/shutdown-house-spending-suspension-00758522" target="_blank">originally hoped to pass the bill</a> under suspension of the rules, an expedited process that requires a two-thirds-majority vote, but Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries told Johnson on Saturday that Democrats would not help Republicans acquire the necessary support for the spending bill.</p> 
<p>"I'm confident that we'll do it at least by Tuesday,” Johnson said in a Sunday interview on NBC's "Meet the Press.” “We have a logistical challenge of getting everyone in town, and because of the conversation I had with Hakeem Jeffries, I know that we've got to pass a rule and probably do this mostly on our own. I think that's very unfortunate."</p> 
<p>The Senate voted Friday to pass <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615" target="_blank">a compromise spending package</a> after Senate Democrats struck a deal with President Donald Trump to extend DHS funding for two weeks. The move bought Congress more time to work out a compromise on reforms for Immigration and Customs Enforcement after federal officers <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/24/minnesota-tim-walz-shooting-minneapolis-00745570" target="_blank">fatally shot</a> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/07/minneapolis-immigration-crackdown-shooting-00714034" target="_blank">two people</a> in Minnesota last month.</p> 
<p>Speaking to host Kristen Welker on “Meet the Press,” Johnson acknowledged that “there's been tragedies in Minnesota” — but he also blamed Democrats in the state for “inciting violence,” even as the Trump administration attempts to tamp down pressures in the state.</p> 
<p>Johnson praised <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/26/trump-border-czar-minneapolis-00746125" target="_blank">Trump’s decision to send</a> White House border czar Tom Homan to Minneapolis, a step <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/26/congress/tom-homan-gop-support-00746206" target="_blank">widely seen as a deescalation</a> from the aggressive tactics favored by Border Patrol commander Gregory Bovino.</p> 
<p>“[Trump] was right to deputize him over that situation,” he said of Homan on NBC. “He has 40 years of experience in Border Patrol and these issues. So I think that this is going to happen, but we need good faith on both sides. Some of these conditions and requests that they've made are obviously reasonable and should happen. But others are going to require a lot more negotiation.”</p> 
<p>Johnson pushed back in particular on Democratic calls to bar federal immigration enforcement officers from wearing masks and require them to wear identification, telling Fox's Shannon Bream: “Those two things are conditions that would create further danger.” </p> 
<p>He also signaled an unwillingness to negotiate on Democratic demands to tighten requirements for judicial warrants for immigration operations.</p> 
<p>Still, House Democrats remained opposed to passing the funding package as is, with Rep. Ro Khanna (D-Calif.) saying Sunday: “I'm not just a no. I'm a firm no.”</p> 
<p>“I just don't see how in good conscience Democrats can vote for continuing ICE funding when they're killing American citizens, when there's no provision to repeal the tripling of the budget,” Khanna said in a Sunday interview with Welker on NBC. “I hope my colleagues will say no.”</p> 
<p>Jeffries also signaled Sunday that a wide gap remains between his conference and House Republicans, telling ABC’s George Stephanopoulos that the House must reach an agreement on judicial warrants “as a condition of moving forward."</p> 
<p>“The one thing that we've said publicly is that we need a robust path toward dramatic reform,” Jeffries said on ABC’s “This Week.” “The administration can't just talk the talk, they need to walk the walk. That should begin today. Not in two weeks, today.”</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shutdown likely to continue at least into Tuesday</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/31/shutdown-tuesday-house-votes-00759001</link>
      <description>House GOP leaders expect to delay a vote on $1.2T spending package due to Democratic opposition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-171f-d1ed-a59e-d75f4cf80000</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 22:05:00 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/9e/20/1475d5b943d7bded1d005c59dd1a/u-s-congress-67688.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries told Speaker Mike Johnson Saturday that Democrats would not provide scores of votes to pass a massive funding bill by a fast-track process.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/9e/20/1475d5b943d7bded1d005c59dd1a/u-s-congress-67688.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Meredith Lee Hill and Nicholas Wu</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The partial government shutdown that began early Saturday morning is on track to continue at least into Tuesday, which is the earliest the House is now expected to vote on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">$1.2 trillion funding package</a> due to opposition from Democrats and internal GOP strife.</p> 
<p>House Republican leaders have scheduled a Monday meeting of the House Rules Committee to prepare the massive <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615" target="_blank">Senate-passed spending bill</a> for the floor. According to two people granted anonymity to discuss internal deliberations, the procedural measure teeing up a final vote would not happen until Tuesday, with final passage following if that is successful.</p> 
<p>That's one day later than GOP leaders had hoped. Their previous plan was to pass the bill with Democratic help under suspension of the rules, a fast-track process requiring a two-thirds-majority vote.</p> 
<p>But that plan was complicated by Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> telling Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> in a private conversation Saturday that Democratic leadership would not help Johnson secure the 70 or so Democratic votes to get the measure over the line, according to the two people and another person granted anonymity to discuss the matter.</p> 
<p>The Tuesday plan remains tentative as GOP leaders scramble to navigate tensions inside their own conference, which could make passing the procedural measure difficult. Some conservative hard-liners, for instance, want to <a href="https://x.com/repluna/status/2017776647424913616?s=46" target="_blank">attach a sweeping elections bill</a> to the package.</p> 
<p>Jeffries said in a MS NOW interview Saturday that Republicans "cannot simply move forward with legislation taking a my way or the highway approach" while noting that House Democrats are set to have "a discussion about the appropriate way forward" in a Sunday evening caucus call — first reported by POLITICO.</p> 
<p>He did not rule out that Democrats might support the Senate-passed spending package, which funds the majority of federal agencies through Sept. 30 while providing a two-week extension for the Department of Homeland Security — including controversial immigration enforcement agencies.</p> 
<p>Democrats, Jeffries said, want "a robust, ironclad path to bringing about the type of change that the American people are demanding" in immigration enforcement.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Here’s what federal programs are headed for a (possibly brief) shutdown</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/government-shutdown-agencies-list-00758705</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-114c-d1ed-a59e-d35df9330000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 19:16:51 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Government funding is set to lapse at midnight Friday for the military and many domestic programs, but cash will continue to flow at a slew of federal agencies Congress already funded.</p> 
<p>House leaders are aiming to send a funding package to President Donald Trump Monday, days after the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615" target="_blank">Senate passed the legislation</a> just before the deadline to avert a partial shutdown. </p> 
<p>The effect on most federal programs is expected to be minor, and employees who are furloughed would miss just one day of work if the House acts on schedule — <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/shutdown-house-spending-suspension-00758522" target="_blank">which is not assured</a>.</p> 
<p>This time, many of the services that have the greatest public impact when shuttered — like farm loans, SNAP food assistance to low-income households and upkeep at national parks — will continue. That’s because Congress already funded some agencies in November and earlier this month, including the departments of Energy, Commerce, Justice, Agriculture, Interior and Veterans Affairs, as well as military construction projects, the EPA, congressional operations, the FDA and federal science programs.</p> 
<p>Still, the spending package congressional leaders are trying to clear for Trump’s signature next week contains the vast majority of the funding Congress approves each year to run federal programs, including $839 billion for the military.</p> 
<p>Besides the Pentagon, funding will lapse for several major non-defense agencies beginning early Saturday morning. </p> 
<p>That includes federal transportation, labor, housing, education and health programs, along with the IRS, independent trade agencies and foreign aid. The departments of Homeland Security, State and Treasury will also be hit by the shutdown.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-30T19:28:38-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Senate passes $1.2T government funding deal — but a brief shutdown is certain</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615</link>
      <description>With the House not voting until Monday, the Pentagon and most domestic agencies are set to shutter briefly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1149-df8c-a99d-f5ff11cb000a</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 18:42:33 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/8f/9e/8f405a8e4a7a87359309f192f5b1/2026-0128-congress-francis-21-1-19762.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Majority Leader John Thune (R-S.D.) at the Capitol this week.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/8f/9e/8f405a8e4a7a87359309f192f5b1/2026-0128-congress-francis-21-1-19762.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney and Katherine Tully-McManus</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate passed a compromise spending package Friday, clearing a path for Congress to avert a lengthy government shutdown.</p> 
<p>The 71-29 vote came a day after Senate Democrats and President Donald Trump struck a deal to attach two weeks of Homeland Security funding to <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">five spending bills</a> that will fund the Pentagon, State Department and many other agencies until Sept. 30.</p> 
<p>Only five of 53 Republicans voted against it after Trump publicly urged lawmakers Thursday to approve the legislation. Democrats were split, with 24 of 47 caucus members opposing the package.</p> 
<p>The Senate’s vote won’t avert a partial shutdown that will start early Saturday morning since House lawmakers are out of town and not scheduled to return until Monday.</p> 
<p>During a private call with House Republicans Friday, Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> said <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/shutdown-house-spending-suspension-00758522" target="_blank">the likeliest route to House passage</a> would be bringing the package up under a fast-track process Monday evening. That would require a two-thirds majority — and a significant number of Democratic votes.</p> 
<p>The $1.2 trillion package could face challenges in the House, especially from conservative hard-liners who have said they would vote against any Senate changes to what the House already passed. Many House Democrats are also wary of stopgap funding for DHS, which would keep ICE and Border Patrol funded at current levels without immediate new restrictions.</p> 
<p>Senate Majority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51242" data-person-id="51242">John Thune</a> said he had been in constant contact with Johnson “for better or worse” about getting the funding deal through the House, predicting that the Louisiana Republican is “prepared to do everything he can as quickly as possible.”</p> 
<p>“Hopefully things go well over there,” he added.</p> 
<p>If the Trump-blessed deal ultimately gets signed into law, Congress will have approved more than 95 percent of federal funding — leaving only a full-year DHS bill on its to-do list. Congress has already funded several agencies, including the departments of Agriculture, Veterans Affairs and Justice.</p> 
<p>“These are fiscally responsible bills that reflect months of hard work and deliberation from members on both parties and both sides of the Capitol,” Senate Appropriations Committee Chair <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51168" data-person-id="51168">Susan Collins</a> (R-Maine) said before the final vote.</p> 
<p>The Office of Management and Budget has issued shutdown guidance for agencies not already funded, which include furloughs of some personnel.</p> 
<p>Republicans agreeing to strip out the full-year DHS bill and replace it with a two-week patch is a major win for Democrats. They quickly unified behind a demand to split off and renegotiate immigration enforcement funding after federal agents deployed to Minnesota fatally shot 37-year-old U.S. citizen Alex Pretti last week.</p> 
<p>Senate Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51231" data-person-id="51231">Chuck Schumer</a>, who helped negotiate the final deal, took a victory lap after the vote, saying “the agreement we reached today did exactly what Democrats wanted.”</p> 
<p>But Democrats will still need to negotiate with the White House and congressional Republicans about what, if any, policy changes they are willing to codify into law as part of a long-term bill. Republicans are open to some changes, including requiring independent investigations. But they’ve already dismissed some of Democrats’ main demands, including requiring judicial warrants for immigration arrests.</p> 
<p>“I want my Republican colleagues to listen closely: Senate Democrats will not support a DHS bill unless it reins in ICE and ends the violence,” Schumer said. “We will know soon enough if your colleagues understand the stakes.”</p> 
<p>Republicans have demands of their own, and many believe the most likely outcome is that another DHS patch will be needed.</p> 
<p>Sen. <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/51186" data-person-id="51186">Lindsey Graham</a> (R-S.C.), for instance, wants a <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/lindsey-graham-amendments-funding-00757533" target="_blank">future vote on legislation</a> barring federal funding for cities that don’t comply with federal immigration laws. Other Republicans and the White House have pointed to it as a key issue in the upcoming negotiations.</p> 
<p>“I am demanding that my solution to fixing sanctuary cities at least have a vote. You're going to put ideas on the floor to make ICE better? I want to put an idea on the floor to get to the root cause of the problem,” Graham said.</p> 
<p>The Senate vote caps off a days-long sprint to avoid a second lengthy shutdown in the span of four months. Senate Democrats and Trump said Thursday they had a deal, only for it to run into a snag when Graham delayed a quick vote as he fumed over a provision in the bill, <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-poised-to-repeal-payout-provision-00756723" target="_blank">first reported by POLITICO</a>, related to former special counsel Jack Smith’s now-defunct investigation targeting Trump.</p> 
<p>Senate leaders ultimately got the agreement back on track Friday afternoon by offering votes on seven changes to the bill, all of which failed. The Senate defeated proposals to cut refugee assistance, strip out all earmarks from the package and redirect funding for ICE to Medicaid, among others.</p> 
<p>Graham raged against the <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/22/congress/house-votes-to-kill-senate-data-seizure-payouts-00740925" target="_blank">House’s move to overturn</a> a law passed last year allowing senators to sue for up to $500,000 per incident if their data had been used in former special counsel Jack Smith’s investigation into the 2020 election. But he backed off his threats to hold up the bill after announcing that leaders had agreed to support a future vote on the matter.</p> 
<p>“You jammed me,” Graham said on the floor Friday. “Speaker Johnson, I won't forget this.”</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Jennifer Scholtes contributed to this report.&nbsp;</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-30T20:31:19-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>House GOP leaders eye bipartisan path for spending package</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/shutdown-house-spending-suspension-00758522</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-1106-df17-afbf-7d3714a60007</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 17:30:30 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Speaker <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/242539" data-person-id="242539">Mike Johnson</a> told House Republicans on a private call Friday night he intends to hold a vote on a <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">sprawling funding package</a> by Monday evening. Leaders are likely to pursue a bipartisan path for passage, he said, rather than relying on the thin GOP majority to approve it.</p> 
<p>The planned vote would end a partial government shutdown after more than two days. The Senate <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/30/shutdown-senate-passes-funding-deal-00758615" target="_blank">passed the package</a> Friday night, just ahead of a midnight shutdown deadline, but the House has been in recess this week and is not scheduled to reconvene until Monday.</p> 
<p>The vote would happen Monday by 6:30 p.m., Johnson said, according to four people granted anonymity to describe his private remarks. He added he intended to pass it however he could, the people said, but indicated the likeliest route would be bringing it up under suspension of the rules, a fast-track process that requires a two-thirds majority — and hence a significant chunk of Democratic votes.</p> 
<p>The suspension path would avoid a potentially tricky party-line procedural vote, with many conservative hard-liners raising objections to reopening a Homeland Security funding deal — as the Senate bill would do. The House Rules Committee had planned to meet Sunday night and hasn't yet notified members those plans had changed, but Republicans say it is likely.</p> 
<p>House Democrats have been wary of providing any support for the Department of Homeland Security amid President Donald Trump's immigration enforcement surge, and it could be difficult for party leaders to summon the scores of votes needed to pass the deal, which was negotiated between Senate Democrats and the White House.</p> 
<p>The agreement splits off DHS funding from the larger package but still funds the department for two more weeks, allowing time for negotiations on new enforcement restrictions.</p> 
<p>A spokesperson for Minority Leader <a href="https://directory.politicopro.com/member/196306" data-person-id="196306">Hakeem Jeffries</a> indicated there was no agreement between Democratic and Republican leaders about providing votes for the funding bill. The caucus is likely to be sharply divided on the question, many Democrats say privately. Just over half of Senate Democratic Caucus members — 24 of 47 — voted against the package Friday, most over the DHS funding.</p> 
<p>House Democrats are expected to hold a Sunday evening caucus call to discuss the vote, according to a person granted anonymity to discuss the plan ahead of a formal announcement.</p> 
<p>Jeffries has been publicly aligned with Senate Democratic leaders on a push for stronger warrant requirements, banning agents from wearing masks and requiring them to use body cameras. He said in a statement Friday that House Democrats would "evaluate the spending legislation passed by the Senate on its merits and then decide how to proceed legislatively."</p> 
<p>He called on the Trump administration to "set forth an ironclad path that dramatically reforms ICE and other DHS agencies that the American people know have become lawless and heavy-handed" and said it would "in the best interest of the country that this is done before the Congress reconvenes on Monday evening."</p> 
<p>Johnson on the call emphasized that Trump supports the deal, and the House needs to pass it. GOP leaders also pressed members to get into Washington as soon as Sunday night.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deal reached to get spending bill through Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/theyve-got-a-deal-00758107</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-10ac-d1ed-a59e-d3fdeb6c0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 16:03:35 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate reached a deal Friday afternoon to vote on a government funding package.</p> 
<p>As part of that agreement struck among all 100 senators, the chamber will vote on seven amendments to a sweeping appropriations package. </p> 
<p>The Senate will then take a final vote to pass the full package, which would float operations for multiple federal agencies through the remainder of the fiscal year — plus fund the Department of Homeland Security for two weeks to buy lawmakers more time to negotiate guardrails around President Donald Trump's immigration enforcement agenda.</p> 
<p>The House could take up the legislation as soon as Monday to end the partial government shutdown expected to run through the weekend, at least.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-30T14:06:33-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Lindsey Graham signals path to defuse funding threat</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/lindsey-graham-amendments-funding-00757533</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0fe9-d1ed-a59e-dffda3910007</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 12:19:18 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sen. Lindsey Graham laid out a path to <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/shutdown-deal-lindsey-graham-dhs-00756840" target="_blank">pass a funding deal Friday</a>, potentially defusing a standoff that threatens to extend a potential government shutdown set to begin within hours.</p> 
<p>Senate Republican leaders believe they can move forward with approval of the <a href="https://legislation.politicopro.com/bill/US_119_HR_7148" target="_blank">spending agreement</a> notched by President Donald Trump and Senate Democrats by arranging for future votes demanded by the South Carolina Republican — one on legislation addressing cities that don’t comply with federal immigration laws and two others related to the defunct investigation into the 2020 election led by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>Graham signaled during a floor speech Friday that he could settle for the votes at a later date, instead of as part of the pending spending bill. A spokesperson said Graham is not asking for votes today. </p> 
<p>Senate Republican leaders believe they can move forward with approval of the spending agreement notched by President Donald Trump and Senate Democrats by offering votes on amendments demanded by the South Carolina Republican — one related to cities that don’t comply with federal immigration laws and two changes related to the defunct investigation into the 2020 election led by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>Giving Graham those amendment votes would require sign-on from all 99 of his colleagues.</p> 
<p>“I'm asking this body to guarantee me that vote, and we move forward,” Graham said about his sanctuary cities proposal.</p> 
<p>Addressing the Smith language, which would have allowed senators to sue for up to $500,000 per incident in damages, Graham said he wants the Senate to vote on substitute language expanding who can sue if their phone records are seized and requiring notification when senators are impacted.</p> 
<p>"We'll fix the $500,000 — count me in — but you took the notification out,” Graham said. “I am demanding a vote on the floor of the United States Senate.”</p> 
<p>The apparent pathway to Senate passage represents a reversal from Thursday night, when the chamber appeared stuck after Graham railed against the spending bill as a “bad deal” and vowed to block its speedy approval.</p> 
<p>While there were multiple resolved sticking points as of Thursday night, Graham’s objections were widely viewed as the main obstacle.</p> 
<p>Graham’s rebellion is tied to the spending legislation including a House-passed provision undoing a law allowing senators to receive cash payouts if they had their phone records seized by Smith’s investigation.</p> 
<p>The provision’s inclusion in the Senate funding agreement <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-poised-to-repeal-payout-provision-00756723" target="_blank">was first reported by POLITICO</a>.</p> 
<p>Graham, who was among the senators who had records subpoenaed, railed against the provision on Thursday night — though he argued his interest was not personal.</p> 
<p>“It’s not about me — 190 private groups had their phone records messed with. I want notification,” Graham said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gov. Tim Walz and Minnesota AG Keith Ellison will testify before Congress</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/walz-to-testify-00757018</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0f86-d1ed-a59e-dfdfaeaf0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 10:37:26 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Minnesota Gov. Tim Walz and state Attorney General Keith Ellison will testify March 4 before the House Oversight and Government Reform Committee.</p> 
<p>The announcement of their joint appearance by by Chair James Comer (R-Ky.) is the latest development in his panel's investigation into welfare fraud in Minnesota, a scandal that has become a rallying cry for Republicans amid the administration’s highly controversial immigration operation in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>“We look forward to questioning Governor Walz and Attorney General Ellison under oath about this scandal to ensure transparency and accountability for the American people, and to advance solutions to prevent waste, fraud, and abuse and impose stronger penalties on those who defraud taxpayers,” Comer, who threatened to subpoena both men earlier this month, said in a statement.</p> 
<p>Walz, the 2024 Democratic nominee for vice president who recently announced he would not seek reelection to continue serving as his state's chief executive, last testified before Comer’s panel this past June alongside other Democratic governors about their cooperation with federal immigration enforcement activities.</p> 
<p>Ellison is a former Democratic member of Congress.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitol agenda: Senate shutdown deal hits a Lindsey Graham snag</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/30/congress/shutdown-deal-lindsey-graham-dhs-00756840</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0da6-dbc5-a7bd-1dbe9b5e0000</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 08:00:00 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A partial shutdown of multiple federal agencies is just 16 hours away as the Senate deals with a Lindsey Graham-sized snag and House Republicans face pressure from President Donald Trump to expedite whatever the other chamber sends their way.</p> 
<p>Here’s the latest on the stop-start drama around the government funding deal:</p> 
<p><b>— Graham's revenge:</b> It sure seemed like the Senate was ready to vote Thursday night after <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/shutdown-spending-deal-trump-00756372" target="_blank">Trump and Democrats struck a compromise</a> — enactment of five of the full-year appropriations bills and a two-week Homeland Security stopgap — to buy time for both sides to negotiate new guardrails for the administration’s immigration enforcement activities after the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis.</p> 
<p>Then Graham made his move. He refused to go along with the plan <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-poised-to-repeal-payout-provision-00756723" target="_blank">over a House-backed provision</a> that would repeal a law allowing senators to receive cash payouts if they had phone records seized by former special counsel Jack Smith — the South Carolina Republican included.</p> 
<p>The Senate could move ahead as soon as Friday, though there are currently no votes on the schedule as leadership works to resolve holdups. Senate Majority Leader John Thune said there were issues coming from members of both parties, though Graham appears to be the main problem.</p> 
<p>“Hopefully by sometime tomorrow we’ll be in a better spot,” Thune said leaving the Capitol Thursday night. “Tomorrow’s another day, and hopefully people will be in a spirit to try and get this done.”</p> 
<p><b>— What's next in the House:</b> Assuming the Senate can send a funding package across the Capitol in short order, House GOP leaders are planning for a vote in their chamber as soon as Monday. Though if Trump wants a shorter partial shutdown, he could pressure Speaker Mike Johnson to call his members back earlier.</p> 
<p>The full House GOP conference will hold a call at 4:30 p.m., after postponing from 11 a.m. Leaders are expected to try and rally support, according to three people granted anonymity to discuss private plans. </p> 
<p>They’re likely to get an earful from hard-liners, who opposed separating DHS out from the larger funding package from the start and don’t want to negotiate with Democrats on restricting Trump’s deportation agenda.</p> 
<p>Other Republicans could cause problems with their own eleventh-hour wish lists. Rep. Anna Paulina Luna (R-Fla.) is insisting the House amend the appropriations package to tack on the SAVE America Act, which would require proof of citizenship when registering to vote. That would require sending the funding legislation back to the Senate yet again, further prolonging a shutdown.</p> 
<p>GOP leaders were already talking with some House Republican factions Thursday night about the funding deal in an effort to get members on board ahead of what’s expected to be a party-line procedural rule vote — and they’ll soon only have a one-vote margin majority.</p> 
<p>If enough hard-liners hold up the bill during that vote, GOP leaders might look to pass it via suspension, which requires a two-thirds affirmative vote of members present.</p> 
<p><b>— What that means for the DHS bill:</b> Should the DHS stopgap make its way to Trump, two weeks could prove to be a tight window to sort through a host of tough asks from members who want to put their stamp on the full-year funding bill. Graham, for instance, is pushing for his bill to end sanctuary cities to be included in the revamped DHS measure.</p> 
<p>Some Republicans are bracing for the possibility of another weekslong funding patch for DHS if a deal isn’t reached by mid-February, with Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) predicting that “part of the government is just going to stay shut down” indefinitely.</p> 
<p>But Republicans’ biggest fear is it could all end with Democrats jamming the GOP with their demands, which include tighter warrant rules, a ban on masks and a requirement for body cameras and independent investigations.</p> 
<p><b><i>What else we’re watching:&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</i></b></p> 
<p><b>— Johnson’s margin narrows: </b>This Saturday’s special election runoff in Texas between two Democrats vying to fill the seat left vacant by late-Rep. Sylvester Turner will cut further into Johnson’s already-tiny margin — and House Minority Leader Hakeem Jeffries is warning the speaker not to delay the winner's swearing-in.</p> 
<p>Whoever wins the seat — either Amanda Edwards or Christian Menefee — will, once seated, bring the balance of the House to 218-214. When that happens, Johnson will only be able to afford a single defection on party-line votes, which could be especially critical next week assuming government funding legislation heads back to the House.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill and Calen Razor contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senate expected to repeal law allowing lawmakers to sue over data seizures</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-poised-to-repeal-payout-provision-00756723</link>
      <description />
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0ca5-df17-afbf-7db72bc60001</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 21:20:53 EST</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Senate is expected to swallow a House-passed provision that would nix a law that allows senators to receive cash payouts if they had their phone records seized by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>Majority Leader John Thune said in an interview Thursday night he currently anticipates the repeal language to remain a part of the government funding package the Senate hopes to pass in the coming hours, but which has not yet been unveiled.</p> 
<p>A second person granted anonymity to disclose private discussions confirmed that the House provision is likely to be preserved. A third person, a Senate aide, also said the expectation is that the House language stays in.</p> 
<p>It goes back to the spending agreement Congress cleared last November to end the record-breaking government shutdown. At that time, the Senate quietly inserted a new policy into the legislation which would have the effect of allowing certain Republican senators to sue the federal government for hundreds of thousands of dollars if they had their electronic records seized without prior notification during Smith’s 2021 probe of President Donald Trump’s attempts to subvert the results of the 2020 election.</p> 
<p>House members of both parties <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/house-votes-to-overturn-thunes-controversial-subpoena-measure-00661169" target="_blank">were horrified</a> by the language, which they learned about only after the fact, and quickly passed legislation unanimously to undo it. They took steps last week to tuck that repeal into a separate, six-bill government funding package the Senate will need to pass before the end of the day Friday to avoid a partial government shutdown.</p> 
<p>But now the chamber is preparing to strip out the Homeland Security appropriations bill to negotiate new provisions around immigration enforcement activities and pass the other five, and it has been an open question throughout the day Thursday whether the repeal provision would remain intact.</p> 
<p>While the funding agreement hasn’t been announced yet on the Senate floor — meaning it could still change as leaders try to wrangle holdouts, whose blessing they need in order to speed up a passage vote before the shutdown deadline — senators were sending signals that there was <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2025/11/19/congress/senate-gop-split-over-how-to-amend-the-jack-smith-phone-data-measure-00660149" target="_blank">a bipartisan appetite to keep it.</a></p> 
<p>“I think it was politically tone deaf to put a monetary penalty in there,” said Sen. Ron Johnson (R-Wis.), who has been leading the charge to re-investigate the work of Smith’s office.</p> 
<p>Sen. Martin Heinrich (D-N.M.), who had expressed frustration that he was not consulted on the initial measure as ranking member of the relevant appropriations subcommittee, said he would advocate for the repeal provision to be included in any funding bill the Senate considers this week.</p> 
<p>“I think it should be part of anything we vote on,” he said.</p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <dcterms:modified>2026-01-29T23:47:33-05</dcterms:modified>
      <title>Trump-blessed deal to keep government funded gets snagged in Senate</title>
      <link>https://www.politico.com/news/2026/01/29/shutdown-spending-deal-trump-00756372</link>
      <description>The agreement would allow for passage of full-year funding for most federal agencies while extending DHS for two weeks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">0000019c-0c16-df8c-a99d-fdf6e0810000</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 18:29:48 EST</pubDate>
      <media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://static.politico.com/3b/73/7329851f4654a687ed4a7303b78f/2026-0128-congress-francis-7-1-86155.jpg">
        <media:credit scheme="urn:ebu">Francis Chung/POLITICO</media:credit>
        <media:title>Senate Minority Leader Chuck Schumer (D-N.Y.), followed by Sens. Patty Murray (D-Wash.) and Alex Padilla (D-Calif.), arrives for a press conference at the U.S. Capitol, on Jan. 28, 2026.</media:title>
        <media:thumbnail url="https://static.politico.com/3b/73/7329851f4654a687ed4a7303b78f/2026-0128-congress-francis-7-1-86155.jpg" />
      </media:content>
      <dc:creator>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:creator>
      <dc:contributor>By Jordain Carney, Katherine Tully-McManus and Jennifer Scholtes</dc:contributor>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>President Donald Trump and Senate Democrats reached an agreement to fund the federal government as a Friday midnight deadline for a partial shutdown approaches.</p> 
<p>But the Senate’s hopes of quickly passing the deal, text of which is yet to be unveiled, ran into a snag Thursday night, with leadership sending senators home around 11 p.m. Senators hope to pass the deal Friday, but votes aren’t yet scheduled.</p> 
<p>“Hopefully by sometime tomorrow we’ll be in a better spot,” Majority Leader John Thune said as he left the Capitol. “Tomorrow’s another day, and hopefully people will be in a spirit to try and get this done tomorrow.”</p> 
<p>Minority Leader Chuck Schumer was more blunt: “Republicans need to get their act together.”</p> 
<p>Thune said there were unresolved issues on both sides of the aisle. But the main sticking point appears to be Sen. Lindsey Graham’s decision to block a quick vote on the deal because it includes a House-passed provision undoing a law that allows senators to receive cash payouts if they had their phone records seized by former special counsel Jack Smith.</p> 
<p>The provision’s inclusion in the Senate funding agreement <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/29/congress/senate-poised-to-repeal-payout-provision-00756723" target="_blank">was first reported by POLITICO</a>.</p> 
<p>Graham (R-S.C.), who was among the senators who had records subpoenaed, said Thursday night his interest was not personal: “It’s not about me — 190 private groups had their phone records messed with. I want notification.” Graham’s objection comes even after Trump urged support for the agreement.</p> 
<p>"I am working hard with Congress to ensure that we are able to fully fund the Government, without delay," Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115980912926614287" target="_blank">posted on Truth Social</a>. "Hopefully, both Republicans and Democrats will give a very much needed Bipartisan 'YES' Vote."</p> 
<p>Even if the Senate passes the deal Friday, a partial government shutdown could still happen early Saturday morning, since the House is in recess and not scheduled to return until Monday. Speaker Mike Johnson <a href="https://x.com/ZachSchermele/status/2017028033408897052" target="_blank">said at an event Thursday night</a> that is the earliest the House could vote, though House Republicans will hold a conference call Friday morning where leaders could recalibrate.</p> 
<p>Leadership aides reiterated after Trump’s announcement that they still expect the earliest they will be able to hold votes on the agreement is next week, which would guarantee a brief partial shutdown.</p> 
<p>Stripping the full-year DHS bill out of the larger six-bill package is a victory for Senate Democrats, who are unified behind demands for enforcement policy changes after federal agents deployed to Minnesota fatally shot 37-year-old Alex Pretti last week.</p> 
<p>But Democratic leaders are still in negotiations with the White House over exactly what <a href="https://www.politico.com/live-updates/2026/01/28/congress/democrats-dhs-minnesota-shutdown-00753256" target="_blank">policy changes</a> they want signed into law in return for their support for a long-term bill. Though Republicans have signaled they are open to some of the ideas Democrats have proposed, including requiring independent investigations, some in the GOP are raising warning flags about a fight to come.</p> 
<p>Graham told reporters Thursday that while he was “willing to entertain some reforms … the cancer that we're dealing with is sanctuary-city policy.” He wants a vote on legislation cracking down on those jurisdictions that don’t comply with federal immigration laws, an idea Trump also backed this month.</p> 
<p>Republicans are already bracing for the possibility of another weeks-long stopgap for DHS if a deal isn’t reached by mid-February. Sen. John Kennedy (R-La.) went further, predicting that after the two-week stopgap “part of the government is just going to stay shut down.”</p> 
<p>If Thursday’s deal is enacted, Congress will have approved full-year funding for more than 95 percent of the agencies it funds on an annual basis — leaving unfinished only the DHS spending measure.</p> 
<p>If the package isn’t enacted before the Friday night deadline, a shutdown will hit all federal agencies that weren’t covered in the six funding bills Congress already enacted for the current fiscal year.</p> 
<p>Agencies already funded include the departments of Agriculture, Veterans Affairs, Justice, Interior, Commerce and Energy, as well as the EPA, water programs, federal science initiatives, the FDA and the operations of Congress itself.</p> 
<p><i>Meredith Lee Hill contributed to this report.</i></p>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
